<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking Characterization Methods for Noisy Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02243</link>
    <author>Megan L. Dahlhauser, Travis S. Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Effective methods for characterizing the noise in quantum computing devices are essential for programming and debugging circuit performance. Existing approaches vary in the information obtained as well as the amount of quantum and classical resources required, with more information generally requiring more resources. Here we benchmark the characterization methods of gate set tomography, Pauli channel noise reconstruction, and empirical direct characterization for developing models that describe noisy quantum circuit performance on a 27-qubit superconducting transmon device. We evaluate these models by comparing the accuracy of noisy circuit simulations with the corresponding experimental observations. We find that the agreement of noise model to experiment does not correlate with the information gained by characterization and that the underlying circuit strongly influences the best choice of characterization approach. Empirical direct characterization scales best of the methods we tested and produced the most accurate characterizations across our benchmarks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Analytical calculation formulas for capacities of classical and classical-quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02450</link>
    <author>Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive an analytical calculation formula for the channel capacity of a classical channel without any iteration while its existing algorithms require iterations and the number of iteration depends on the required precision level. Hence, our formula is its first analytical formula without any iteration. We apply the obtained formula to examples and see how the obtained formula works in these examples. Then, we extend it to the channel capacity of a classical-quantum (cq-) channel. Many existing studies proposed algorithms for a cq-channel and all of them require iterations. Our extended analytical algorithm have also no iteration and output the exactly optimum values.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scaling Quantum Approximate Optimization on Near-term Hardware</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02247</link>
    <author>Phillip C. Lotshaw, Thien Nguyen, Anthony Santana, Alexander McCaskey, Rebekah Herrman, James Ostrowski, George Siopsis, Travis S. Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) is an approach for near-term quantum computers to potentially demonstrate computational advantage in solving combinatorial optimization problems. However, the viability of the QAOA depends on how its performance and resource requirements scale with problem size and complexity for realistic hardware implementations. Here, we quantify scaling of the expected resource requirements by synthesizing optimized circuits for hardware architectures with varying levels of connectivity. Assuming noisy gate operations, we estimate the number of measurements needed to sample the output of the idealized QAOA circuit with high probability. We show the number of measurements, and hence total time to solution, grows exponentially in problem size and problem graph degree as well as depth of the QAOA ansatz, gate infidelities, and inverse hardware graph degree. These problems may be alleviated by increasing hardware connectivity or by recently proposed modifications to the QAOA that achieve higher performance with fewer circuit layers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction using squeezed Schrödinger cat states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02570</link>
    <author>David S. Schlegel, Fabrizio Minganti, Vincenzo Savona</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bosonic quantum codes redundantly encode quantum information in the states of a quantum harmonic oscillator, making it possible to detect and correct errors. Schrödinger cat codes -- based on the superposition of two coherent states with opposite displacements -- can correct phase-flip errors induced by dephasing, but they are vulnerable to bit-flip errors induced by photon loss. Here, we develop a bosonic quantum code relying on squeezed cat states, i.e. cat states made of a linear superposition of displaced-squeezed states. Squeezed cat states allow to partially correct errors caused by photon loss, while at the same time improving the protection against dephasing. We present a comprehensive analysis of the squeezed cat code, including protocols for code generation and elementary quantum gates. We characterize the effect of both photon loss and dephasing and develop an optimal recovery protocol that is suitable to be implemented on currently available quantum hardware. We show that with moderate squeezing, and using typical parameters of state-of-the-art quantum hardware platforms, the squeezed cat code has a resilience to photon-loss errors that significantly outperforms that of the conventional cat code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Loschmidt echo and Poincaré recurrences of entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02600</link>
    <author>Leonardo Ermann, Klaus M. Frahm, Dima L Shepelyansky</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study numerically the properties of entanglement of two interacting, or noninteracting, particles evolving in a regime of quantum chaos in the quantum Chirikov standard map. Such pairs can be viewed as interacting, on noninteracting, Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen pairs in a regime of quantum chaos. The analysis is done with such tools as the Loschmidt echo of entanglement and the Poincaré recurrences of entanglement in presence of absorption. The obtained results show unusual features of the entropy of entanglement and the spectrum of Schmidt decomposition with their dependence on interactions at different quantum chaos regimes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Pure and indistinguishable single-photon source at telecommunication wavelength</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02465</link>
    <author>Beatrice Da Lio, Carlos Faurby, Xiaoyan Zhou, Ming Lai Chan, Ravitej Uppu, Henri Thyrrestrup, Sven Scholz, Andreas D. Wieck, Arne Ludwig, Peter Lodahl, Leonardo Midolo</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>On-demand single-photon sources emitting pure and indistinguishable photons at the telecommunication wavelength are a critical asset towards the deployment of fiber-based quantum networks. Indeed, single photons may serve as flying qubits, allowing communication of quantum information over long distances. Self-assembled InAs quantum dots embedded in GaAs constitute an excellent nearly deterministic source of high quality single photons, but the vast majority of sources operate in the 900-950 nm wavelength range, precluding their adoption in a quantum network. Here, we present a quantum frequency conversion scheme for converting single photons from quantum dots to the telecommunication C band, around 1550 nm, achieving 40.8% end-to-end efficiency, while maintaining both high purity and a high degree of indistinguishability during conversion with measured values of $g^{(2)}(0)=2.4\%$ and $V^{\text{corr}}=94.8\%$, respectively.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bregman divergence based em algorithm and its application to classical and quantum rate distortion theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02447</link>
    <author>Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We formulate em algorithm in the framework of Bregman divergence, which is a general problem setting of information geometry. That is, we address the minimization problem of the Bregman divergence between an exponential subfamily and a mixture subfamily in a Bregman divergence system. Then, we show the convergence and its speed under several conditions. We apply this algorithm to rate distortion and its variants including the quantum setting, and show the usefulness of our general algorithm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Precision Bootstrap for the $\mathcal{N}=1$ Super-Ising Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02206</link>
    <author>Alexander Atanasov, Aaron Hillman, David Poland, Junchen Rong, Ning Su</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this note we report an improved determination of the scaling dimensions and OPE coefficients of the minimal supersymmetric extension of the 3d Ising model using the conformal bootstrap. We also show how this data can be used as input to the Lorentzian inversion formula, finding good agreement between analytic calculations and numerical extremal spectra once mixing effects are resolved.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Recycled entanglement detection by arbitrarily many sequential and independent pairs of observers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02594</link>
    <author>Mahasweta Pandit, Chirag Srivastava, Ujjwal Sen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the witnessing of two-qubit entangled states by sequential and independent pairs of observers, with both observers of each pair acting independently on their part of the shared state from spatially separated laboratories, and subsequently passing their qubits to the next pair in the sequence. It has previously been conjectured that not more than one pair of observers can detect Clauser-Horne-Shimony-Holt "Bell-nonlocal" correlations in a similar set-up. This is intriguing since it is possible to have an arbitrarily long sequence of Bell-nonlocal correlations when only a single observer is allowed to share a bipartite state with multiple observers at the other end. It is therefore interesting to ask whether such restrictions are also present when entangled correlations are considered in the scenario of multiple pairs of observers. We find that a two-qubit entangled state can be used to witness entanglement arbitrarily many times, by pairs of observers, acting sequentially and independently. We prove the statement to be true when the initial pair of observers in the sequence share any pure entangled state or when they share a state from a class of mixed entangled states. We demonstrate that the phenomenon can also be observed for a certain class of entangled states in which an arbitrarily long sequence of observer pairs witnessing entanglement is reached in the limit of the initial entanglement content tending to a vanishing amount.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Persistence Landscapes of Affine Fractals</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02552</link>
    <author>Michael J. Catanzaro, Lee Przybylski, Eric S. Weber</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop a method for calculating the persistence landscapes of affine fractals using the parameters of the corresponding transformations. Given an iterated function system of affine transformations that satisfies a certain compatibility condition, we prove that there exists an affine transformation acting on the space of persistence landscapes which intertwines the action of the iterated function system. This latter affine transformation is a strict contraction and its unique fixed point is the persistence landscape of the affine fractal. We present several examples of the theory as well as confirm the main results through simulations.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>