<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Alternating Layered Variational Quantum Circuits Can Be Classically Optimized Efficiently Using Classical Shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11623</link>
    <author>Afrad Basheer, Yuan Feng, Christopher Ferrie, Sanjiang Li</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms (VQAs) are the quantum analog of classical neural networks (NNs). A VQA consists of a parameterized quantum circuit (PQC) which is composed of multiple layers of ansatzes (simpler PQCs, which are an analogy of NN layers) that differ only in selections of parameters. Previous work has identified the alternating layered ansatz as potentially a new standard ansatz in near-term quantum computing. Indeed, shallow alternating layered VQAs are easy to implement and have been shown to be both trainable and expressive. In this work, we introduce a training algorithm with an exponential reduction in training cost of such VQAs. Moreover, our algorithm uses classical shadows of quantum input data, and can hence be run on a classical computer with rigorous performance guarantees. We demonstrate 2--3 orders of magnitude improvement in the training cost using our algorithm for the example problems of finding state preparation circuits and the quantum autoencoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Nishimori's cat: stable long-range entanglement from finite-depth unitaries and weak measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11136</link>
    <author>Guo-Yi Zhu, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Ashvin Vishwanath, Simon Trebst, Ruben Verresen</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the field of monitored quantum circuits, it has remained an open question whether finite-time protocols for preparing long-range entangled (LRE) states lead to phases of matter which are stable to gate imperfections. Here we show that such gate imperfections effectively convert projective into weak measurements and that, in certain cases, long-range entanglement persists, even in the presence of weak measurements and gives rise to novel forms of quantum criticality. We demonstrate this explicitly for preparing the two-dimensional (2D) GHZ cat state and the three-dimensional (3D) toric code as minimal instances. In contrast to previous studies on measurement-induced phases and transitions, our circuit of gates and measurements is deterministic; the only randomness is in the measurement outcomes. We show how the randomness in these weak measurements allows us to track the solvable Nishimori line of the random-bond Ising model, rigorously establishing the stability of the glassy LRE states in two and three spatial dimensions. Away from this exactly solvable construction, we use hybrid tensor network and Monte Carlo simulations to obtain a non-zero Edwards-Anderson order parameter as an indicator of long-range entanglement in the 2D scenario. We argue that our protocol admits a natural implementation in existing quantum computing architectures, requiring only a depth-3 circuit on IBM's heavy-hexagon transmon chips.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement-Prepared Quantum Criticality: from Ising model to gauge theory, and beyond</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11699</link>
    <author>Jong Yeon Lee, Wenjie Ji, Zhen Bi, Matthew P. A. Fisher</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Measurements allow efficient preparation of interesting quantum many-body states exhibiting long-range, topological, or fractonic orders. Here, we prove that the so-called conformal quantum critical points (CQCP) can be obtained by performing general single-site measurements in appropriate basis on the cluster states in $d\geq2$. The equal-time correlators of the said states are described by correlation functions of a certain $d$-dimensional classical model at the critical temperature, featuring spatial conformal invariance. This establishes an exact correspondence between the measurement-prepared critical states and conformal field theories of a range of critical spin models, including familiar Ising model and gauge theories among others. Furthermore, by mapping the correlations of the measured quantum state into the statistical mechanics problem, we establish the stability of long-range or topological orders with respect to measurements deviating from the ideal setting, without any post-selection. Therefore, our findings suggest a novel mechanism in which a quantum critical wavefunction emerges, providing new practical ways to study quantum phases and conformal quantum critical points.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Resolving Matrix Spencer Conjecture Up to Poly-logarithmic Rank</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11286</link>
    <author>Nikhil Bansal, Haotian Jiang, Raghu Meka</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a simple proof of the matrix Spencer conjecture up to poly-logarithmic rank: given symmetric $d \times d$ matrices $A_1,\ldots,A_n$ each with $\|A_i\|_{\mathsf{op}} \leq 1$ and rank at most $n/\log^3 n$, one can efficiently find $\pm 1$ signs $x_1,\ldots,x_n$ such that their signed sum has spectral norm $\|\sum_{i=1}^n x_i A_i\|_{\mathsf{op}} = O(\sqrt{n})$. This result also implies a $\log n - \Omega( \log \log n)$ qubit lower bound for quantum random access codes encoding $n$ classical bits with advantage $\gg 1/\sqrt{n}$. Our proof uses the recent refinement of the non-commutative Khintchine inequality in [Bandeira, Boedihardjo, van Handel, 2022] for random matrices with correlated Gaussian entries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A mathematical framework for quantum Hamiltonian simulation and duality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11941</link>
    <author>Harriet Apel, Toby Cubitt</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Analogue Hamiltonian simulation is a promising near-term application of quantum computing and has recently been put on a theoretical footing. In Hamiltonian simulation, a physical Hamiltonian is engineered to have identical physics to another - often very different - Hamiltonian. This is qualitatively similar to the notion of duality in physics, whereby two superficially different theories are mathematically equivalent in some precise sense. However, existing characterisations of Hamiltonian simulations are not sufficiently general to extend to all dualities in physics. In particular, they cannot encompass the important cases of strong/weak and high-temperature/low-temperature dualities. In this work, we give three physically motivated axiomatisations of duality, formulated respectively in terms of observables, partition functions and entropies. We prove that these axiomatisations are equivalent, and characterise the mathematical form that any duality satisfying these axioms must take. A building block in one of our results is a strengthening of earlier results on entropy-preserving maps to maps that are entropy-preserving up to an additive constant, which we prove decompose as a direct sum of unitary and anti-unitary components, which may be of independent mathematical interest.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>