<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>High Dimensional Quantum Learning With Small Quantum Computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13739</link>
    <author>Simon C. Marshall, Casper Gyurik, Vedran Dunjko</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers hold great promise to enhance machine learning, but their current qubit counts restrict the realisation of this promise. In an attempt to placate this limitation techniques can be applied for evaluating a quantum circuit using a machine with fewer qubits than the circuit naively requires. These techniques work by evaluating many smaller circuits on the smaller machine, that are then combined in a polynomial to replicate the output of the larger machine. This scheme requires more circuit evaluations than are practical for general circuits. However, we investigate the possibility that for certain applications many of these subcircuits are superfluous, and that a much smaller sum is sufficient to estimate the full circuit. We construct a machine learning model that may be capable of approximating the outputs of the larger circuit with much fewer circuit evaluations. We successfully apply our model to the task of digit recognition, using simulated quantum computers much smaller than the data dimension. The model is also applied to the task of approximating a random 10 qubit PQC with simulated access to a 5 qubit computer, even with only relatively modest number of circuits our model provides an accurate approximation of the 10 qubit PQCs output, superior to a neural network attempt. The developed method might be useful for implementing quantum models on larger data throughout the NISQ era.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New Quantum Algorithms for Computing Quantum Entropies and Distances</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13522</link>
    <author>Qisheng Wang, Ji Guan, Junyi Liu, Zhicheng Zhang, Mingsheng Ying</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a series of quantum algorithms for computing a wide range of quantum entropies and distances, including the von Neumann entropy, quantum Rényi entropy, trace distance, and fidelity. The proposed algorithms significantly outperform the best known (and even quantum) ones in the low-rank case, some of which achieve exponential speedups. In particular, for $N$-dimensional quantum states of rank $r$, our proposed quantum algorithms for computing the von Neumann entropy, trace distance and fidelity within additive error $\varepsilon$ have time complexity of $\tilde O(r^2/\varepsilon^2)$, $\tilde O(r^5/\varepsilon^6)$ and $\tilde O(r^{6.5}/\varepsilon^{7.5})$, respectively. In contrast, the known algorithms for the von Neumann entropy and trace distance require quantum time complexity of $\Omega(N)$ [AISW19,GL20,GHS21], and the best known one for fidelity requires $\tilde O(r^{21.5}/\varepsilon^{23.5})$ [WZC+21]. The key idea of our quantum algorithms is to extend block-encoding from unitary operators in previous work to quantum states (i.e., density operators). It is realized by developing several convenient techniques to manipulate quantum states and extract information from them. In particular, we introduce a novel technique for eigenvalue transformation of density operators and their (non-integer) positive powers, based on the powerful quantum singular value transformation (QSVT) [GSLW19]. The advantage of our techniques over the existing methods is that no restrictions on density operators are required; in sharp contrast, the previous methods usually require a lower bound of the minimal non-zero eigenvalue of density operators. In addition, we provide some techniques of independent interest for trace estimation, linear combinations, and eigenvalue threshold projectors of (subnormalized) density operators, which will be, we believe, useful in other quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum dynamics is not strictly bidivisible</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13451</link>
    <author>David Davalos, Mario Ziman</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We address the question of the existence of quantum channels that are divisible in two quantum channels but not in three, or more generally channels divisible in $n$ but not in $n+1$ parts. We show that for the qubit, those channels \textitdo not exist, whereas for general finite-dimensional quantum channels the same holds at least for full Kraus rank channels. To prove these results we introduce a novel decomposition of quantum channels which separates them in a boundary and Markovian part, and it holds for any finite dimension. Additionally, the introduced decomposition amounts to the well known connection between divisibility classes and implementation types of quantum dynamical maps.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Information is Physical: Cross-Perspective Links in Relational Quantum Mechanics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13342</link>
    <author>Emily Adlam, Carlo Rovelli</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Relational quantum mechanics (RQM) is an interpretation of quantum mechanics based on the idea that quantum states describe not an absolute property of a system but rather a relationship between systems. In this article, we observe that there is a tension between RQM's naturalistic emphasis on the physicality of information and the inaccessibility of certain sorts of information in current formulations of RQM. Therefore we propose a new postulate for RQM which requires that all of the information possessed by a certain observer is stored in physical variables of that observer and thus accessible by measurement to other observers, so observers can reach intersubjective agreement about quantum events which have occurred in the past. Based on this postulate, we suggest an ontology for RQM which upholds the principle that quantum states are always relational, but which also postulates a set of quantum events which are not strictly relational. We show that the new postulate helps address some existing objections to RQM and finally we address the Frauchiger-Renner experiment in the context of RQM.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive job and resource management for the growing quantum cloud</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13260</link>
    <author>Gokul Subramanian Ravi, Kaitlin N. Smith, Prakash Murali, Frederic T. Chong</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>As the popularity of quantum computing continues to grow, efficient quantum machine access over the cloud is critical to both academic and industry researchers across the globe. And as cloud quantum computing demands increase exponentially, the analysis of resource consumption and execution characteristics are key to efficient management of jobs and resources at both the vendor-end as well as the client-end. While the analysis and optimization of job / resource consumption and management are popular in the classical HPC domain, it is severely lacking for more nascent technology like quantum computing. This paper proposes optimized adaptive job scheduling to the quantum cloud taking note of primary characteristics such as queuing times and fidelity trends across machines, as well as other characteristics such as quality of service guarantees and machine calibration constraints. Key components of the proposal include a) a prediction model which predicts fidelity trends across machine based on compiled circuit features such as circuit depth and different forms of errors, as well as b) queuing time prediction for each machine based on execution time estimations. Overall, this proposal is evaluated on simulated IBM machines across a diverse set of quantum applications and system loading scenarios, and is able to reduce wait times by over 3x and improve fidelity by over 40\% on specific usecases, when compared to traditional job schedulers.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>