<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Non-unitary versus unitary optimization in the control of open quantum systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03114</link>
    <author>Marllos E. Fonseca, Felipe F. Fanchini, Emanuel F. de Lima, Leonardo K. Castelano</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work, we compare the performance of the Krotov method for open quantum systems (non-unitary optimization) with the Krotov method for closed quantum systems (unitary optimization) in finding optimal controls aimed at manipulating qubits and qutrits in the presence of the environment. In the case of unitary optimization, the Krotov method is applied to quantum system neglecting its interaction with the environment, afterwards the resulting controls are used to manipulate the system along with the eviromental noise. We consider two distinct control problems: target-state preparation from a given initial state and quantum gate implementation. For the state preparation, we have found that the performance of the controls obtained from the non-unitary optimization outperform that of the controls obtained from the unitary optimization. However, in the case of the implementation of quantum gates, we have found that the optimal controls obtained from the unitary evolution exhibit a mean fidelity similar to that obtained from the non-unitary evolution. Since unitary optimization does not depend on decay rates nor on specific kinds of noise, besides being less computationally demanding, our results suggest that the best current practice to implement quantum gates in open quantum systems is to employ unitary optimization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multi-Axis Control of a Qubit in the Presence of Unknown Non-Markovian Quantum Noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03058</link>
    <author>Akram Youssry, Hendra I. Nurdin</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we consider the problem of open-loop control of a qubit that is coupled to an unknown fully quantum non-Markovian noise (either bosonic or fermionic). A graybox model that is empirically obtained from measurement data is employed to approximately represent the unknown quantum noise. The estimated model is then used to calculate the open-loop control pulses under constraints on the pulse amplitude and timing. For the control pulse optimization, we explore the use of gradient descent and genetic optimization methods. We consider the effect of finite sampling on estimating expectation values of observables and show results for single- and multi-axis control of a qubit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Tight Analysis of Hutchinson's Diagonal Estimator</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03268</link>
    <author>Prathamesh Dharangutte, Christopher Musco</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Let $\mathbf{A}\in \mathbb{R}^{n\times n}$ be a matrix with diagonal $\text{diag}(\mathbf{A})$ and let $\bar{\mathbf{A}}$ be $\mathbf{A}$ with its diagonal set to all zeros. We show that Hutchinson's estimator run for $m$ iterations returns a diagonal estimate $\tilde{d}\in \mathbb{R}^n$ such that with probability $(1-\delta)$, $$\|\tilded - \textdiag(\mathbfA)\|_2 ≤c\sqrt\frac\log(2/\delta)m\|\bar\mathbfA\|_F,$$ where $c$ is a fixed constant independent of all other parameters. This results improves on a recent result of [Baston and Nakatsukasa, 2022] by a $\log(n)$ factor, yielding a bound that is independent of the matrix dimension $n$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>QUSUM: quickest quantum change-point detection</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03265</link>
    <author>Marco Fanizza, Christoph Hirche, John Calsamiglia</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Online detection of a change in a sequence of events is a fundamental and practically relevant task. In this work we consider the quantum version of the problem, generalizing the well known (classical) CUSUM algorithm to detect a quantum change point. Our algorithm exploits joint measurements to amplify the trade-off between detection delay and false detections, which in the case of a quantum change point is asymptotically characterized by the quantum relative entropy. Furthermore we also show that the relative entropy is indeed asymptotically optimal under arbitrary, potentially adaptive, measurement strategies, hence providing the ultimate bound for the quickest quantum change-point detection. Finally, we discuss online change point detection in quantum channels.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Towards Antisymmetric Neural Ansatz Separation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03264</link>
    <author>Aaron Zweig, Joan Bruna</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study separations between two fundamental models (or \emphAnsätze) of antisymmetric functions, that is, functions $f$ of the form $f(x_{\sigma(1)}, \ldots, x_{\sigma(N)}) = \text{sign}(\sigma)f(x_1, \ldots, x_N)$, where $\sigma$ is any permutation. These arise in the context of quantum chemistry, and are the basic modeling tool for wavefunctions of Fermionic systems. Specifically, we consider two popular antisymmetric Ansätze: the Slater representation, which leverages the alternating structure of determinants, and the Jastrow ansatz, which augments Slater determinants with a product by an arbitrary symmetric function. We construct an antisymmetric function that can be more efficiently expressed in Jastrow form, yet provably cannot be approximated by Slater determinants unless there are exponentially (in $N^2$) many terms. This represents the first explicit quantitative separation between these two Ansätze.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>