<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>An efficient decoder for a linear distance quantum LDPC code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06557</link>
    <author>Shouzhen Gu, Christopher A. Pattison, Eugene Tang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent developments have shown the existence of quantum low-density parity check (qLDPC) codes with constant rate and linear distance. A natural question concerns the efficient decodability of these codes. In this paper, we present a linear time decoder for the recent quantum Tanner codes construction of asymptotically good qLDPC codes, which can correct all errors of weight up to a constant fraction of the blocklength. Our decoder is an iterative algorithm which searches for corrections within constant-sized regions. At each step, the corrections are found by reducing a locally defined and efficiently computable cost function which serves as a proxy for the weight of the remaining error.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Composite Quantum Simulations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06409</link>
    <author>Matthew Hagan, Nathan Wiebe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper we provide a framework for combining multiple quantum simulation methods, such as Trotter-Suzuki formulas and QDrift into a single composite channel that builds upon older coalescing ideas for reducing gate counts. The central idea behind our approach is to use a partitioning scheme that allocates a Hamiltonian term to the Trotter or QDrift part of a channel within the simulation. This allows us to simulate small but numerous terms using QDrift while simulating the larger terms using a high-order Trotter-Suzuki formula. We prove rigorous bounds on the diamond distance between the composite channel and the ideal simulation channel and show under what conditions the cost of implementing the composite channel is asymptotically upper bounded by the methods that comprise it for both probabilistic partitioning of terms and deterministic partitioning. Finally, we discuss strategies for determining partitioning schemes as well as methods for incorporating different simulation methods within the same framework.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On Classical and Hybrid Shadows of Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06616</link>
    <author>Saumya Shivam, C. W. von Keyserlingk, S. L. Sondhi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classical shadows are a computationally efficient approach to storing quantum states on a classical computer for the purposes of estimating expectation values of local observables, obtained by performing repeated random measurements. In this note we offer some comments on this approach. We note that the resources needed to form classical shadows with bounded relative error depend strongly on the target state. We then comment on the advantages and limitations of using classical shadows to simulate many-body dynamics. In addition, we introduce the notion of a hybrid shadow, constructed from measurements on a part of the system instead of the entirety, which provides a framework to gain more insight into the nature of shadow states as one reduces the size of the subsystem measured, and a potential alternative to compressing quantum states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hyper-optimized compressed contraction of tensor networks with arbitrary geometry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07044</link>
    <author>Johnnie Gray, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tensor network contraction is central to problems ranging from many-body physics to computer science. We describe how to approximate tensor network contraction through bond compression on arbitrary graphs. In particular, we introduce a hyper-optimization over the compression and contraction strategy itself to minimize error and cost. We demonstrate that our protocol outperforms both hand-crafted contraction strategies as well as recently proposed general contraction algorithms on a variety of synthetic problems on regular lattices and random regular graphs. We further showcase the power of the approach by demonstrating compressed contraction of tensor networks for frustrated three-dimensional lattice partition functions, dimer counting on random regular graphs, and to access the hardness transition of random tensor network models, in graphs with many thousands of tensors.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Space-efficient Quantization Method for Reversible Markov Chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06886</link>
    <author>Chen-Fu Chiang, Anirban Chowdhury, Pawel Wocjan</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a seminal paper, Szegedy showed how to construct a quantum walk $W(P)$ for any reversible Markov chain $P$ such that its eigenvector with eigenphase $0$ is a quantum sample of the limiting distribution of the random walk and its eigenphase gap is quadratically larger than the spectral gap of $P$. The standard construction of Szegedy's quantum walk requires an ancilla register of Hilbert-space dimension equal to the size of the state space of the Markov chain. We show that it is possible to avoid this doubling of state space for certain Markov chains that employ a symmetric proposal probability and a subsequent accept/reject probability to sample from the Gibbs distribution. For such Markov chains, we give a quantization method which requires an ancilla register of dimension equal to only the number of different energy values, which is often significantly smaller than the size of the state space. To accomplish this, we develop a technique for block encoding Hadamard products of matrices which may be of wider interest.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>