<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Hierarchies of resources for measurement-based quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.09965</link>
    <author>Markus Frembs, Sam Roberts, Earl T. Campbell, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For certain restricted computational tasks, quantum mechanics provides a provable advantage over any possible classical implementation. Several of these results have been proven using the framework of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), where non-locality and more generally contextuality have been identified as necessary resources for certain quantum computations. Here, we consider the computational power of MBQC in more detail by refining its resource requirements, both on the allowed operations and the number of accessible qubits. More precisely, we identify which Boolean functions can be computed in non-adaptive MBQC, with local operations contained within a finite level in the Clifford hierarchy. Moreover, for non-adaptive MBQC restricted to certain subtheories such as stabiliser MBQC, we compute the minimal number of qubits required to compute a given Boolean function. Our results point towards hierarchies of resources that more sharply characterise the power of MBQC beyond the binary of contextuality vs non-contextuality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Algorithms for Testing Hamiltonian Symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.10017</link>
    <author>Margarite L. LaBorde, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Symmetries in a Hamiltonian play an important role in quantum physics because they correspond directly with conserved quantities of the related system. In this paper, we propose quantum algorithms capable of testing whether a Hamiltonian exhibits symmetry with respect to a group. We demonstrate that familiar expressions of Hamiltonian symmetry in quantum mechanics correspond directly with the acceptance probabilities of our algorithms. We execute one of our symmetry-testing algorithms on existing quantum computers for simple examples of both symmetric and asymmetric cases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Shorter quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.10064</link>
    <author>Vadym Kliuchnikov, Kristin Lauter, Romy Minko, Adam Paetznick, Christophe Petit</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a novel procedure for approximating general single-qubit unitaries from a finite universal gate set by reducing the problem to a novel magnitude approximation problem, achieving an immediate improvement in sequence length by a factor of 7/9. Extending the works arXiv:1612.01011 and arXiv:1612.02689, we show that taking probabilistic mixtures of channels to solve fallback (arXiv:1409.3552) and magnitude approximation problems saves factor of two in approximation costs. In particular, over the Clifford+$\sqrt{\mathrm{T}}$ gate set we achieve an average non-Clifford gate count of $0.23\log_2(1/\varepsilon)+2.13$ and T-count $0.56\log_2(1/\varepsilon)+5.3$ with mixed fallback approximations for diamond norm accuracy $\varepsilon$. This paper provides a holistic overview of gate approximation, in addition to these new insights. We give an end-to-end procedure for gate approximation for general gate sets related to some quaternion algebras, providing pedagogical examples using common fault-tolerant gate sets (V, Clifford+T and Clifford+$\sqrt{\mathrm{T}}$). We also provide detailed numerical results for Clifford+T and Clifford+$\sqrt{\mathrm{T}}$ gate sets. In an effort to keep the paper self-contained, we include an overview of the relevant algorithms for integer point enumeration and relative norm equation solving. We provide a number of further applications of the magnitude approximation problems, as well as improved algorithms for exact synthesis, in the Appendices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adiabatic paths of Hamiltonians, symmetries of topological order, and automorphism codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11137</link>
    <author>David Aasen, Zhenghan Wang, Matthew B. Hastings</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recent "honeycomb code" is a fault-tolerant quantum memory defined by a sequence of checks which implements a nontrivial automorphism of the toric code. We argue that a general framework to understand this code is to consider continuous adiabatic paths of gapped Hamiltonians and we give a conjectured description of the fundamental group and second and third homotopy groups of this space in two spatial dimensions. A single cycle of such a path can implement some automorphism of the topological order of that Hamiltonian. We construct such paths for arbitrary automorphisms of two-dimensional doubled topological order. Then, realizing this in the case of the toric code, we turn this path back into a sequence of checks, constructing an automorphism code closely related to the honeycomb code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Third law of thermodynamics and the scaling of quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.09545</link>
    <author>Lorenzo Buffoni, Stefano Gherardini, Emmanuel Zambrini Cruzeiro, Yasser Omar</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The third law of thermodynamics, also known as the Nernst unattainability principle, puts a fundamental bound on how close a system, whether classical or quantum, can be cooled to a temperature near to absolute zero. On the other hand, a fundamental assumption of quantum computing is to start each computation from a register of qubits initialized in a pure state, i.e. at zero temperature. These conflicting aspects, at the interface between quantum computing and thermodynamics, are often overlooked or, at best, addressed only at a single-qubit level. In this work, we argue how the existence of a small, but finite, effective temperature, which makes the initial state a mixed state, poses a real challenge to the fidelity constraints required for the scaling of quantum computers. Our theoretical results, carried out for a generic quantum circuit with $N$-qubit input states, are validated by experiments performed on a real quantum processor.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>