<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Speedups for Zero-Sum Games via Improved Dynamic Gibbs Sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03763</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Yosheb Getachew, Yujia Jin, Aaron Sidford, Kevin Tian</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum algorithm for computing an $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium of a zero-sum game in a $m \times n$ payoff matrix with bounded entries. Given a standard quantum oracle for accessing the payoff matrix our algorithm runs in time $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{m + n}\cdot \epsilon^{-2.5} + \epsilon^{-3})$ and outputs a classical representation of the $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium. This improves upon the best prior quantum runtime of $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{m + n} \cdot \epsilon^{-3})$ obtained by [vAG19] and the classic $\widetilde{O}((m + n) \cdot \epsilon^{-2})$ runtime due to [GK95] whenever $\epsilon = \Omega((m +n)^{-1})$. We obtain this result by designing new quantum data structures for efficiently sampling from a slowly-changing Gibbs distribution.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Drug design on quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.04114</link>
    <author>Raffaele Santagati, Alan Aspuru-Guzik, Ryan Babbush, Matthias Degroote, Leticia Gonzalez, Elica Kyoseva, Nikolaj Moll, Markus Oppel, Robert M. Parrish, Nicholas C. Rubin, Michael Streif, Christofer S. Tautermann, Horst Weiss, Nathan Wiebe, Clemens Utschig-Utschig</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers promise to impact industrial applications, for which quantum chemical calculations are required, by virtue of their high accuracy. This perspective explores the challenges and opportunities of applying quantum computers to drug design, discusses where they could transform industrial research and elaborates on what is needed to reach this goal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Qubit recycling and the path counting problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03725</link>
    <author>Zijian Song, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, it was shown that the qudits used in circuits of a convolutional form (e.g., Matrix Product State sand Multi-scale Entanglement Renormalization Ansatz) can be reset unitarily \hrefhttps://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevA.103.042613[Phys. Rev. A 103, 042613 (2021)], even without measurement. We analyze the fidelity of this protocol for a family of quantum circuits that interpolates between such circuits and local quantum circuits, averaged over Haar-random gates. We establish a connection between this problem and a counting of directed paths on a graph, which is determined by the shape of the quantum circuit. This connection leads to an exact expression for the fidelity of the protocol for the entire family that interpolates between convolutional circuit and random quantum circuit. For convolutional circuits of constant window size, the rate of convergence to unit fidelity is shown to be $\frac{q^2}{q^2+1}$, independent of the window size, where $q$ is the local qudit dimension. Since most applications of convolutional circuits use constant-sized windows, our result suggests that the unitary reset protocol will likely work well in such a regime. We also derive two extra results in the convolutional limit, which may be of an independent interest. First, we derive exact expressions for the correlations between reset qudits and show that it decays exponentially in the distance. Second, we derive an expression for the the fidelity in the presence of noise, expressed in terms of the quantities that define the property of the channel, such as the entanglement fidelity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A universal framework for entanglement detection under group symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03849</link>
    <author>Sang-Jun Park, Yeong-Gwang Jung, Jeongeun Park, Sang-Gyun Youn</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>One of the most fundamental questions in quantum information theory is PPT-entanglement of quantum states, which is an NP-hard problem in general. In this paper, however, we prove that all PPT $(\overline{\pi}_A\otimes \pi_B)$-invariant quantum states are separable if and only if all extremal unital positive $(\pi_A,\pi_B)$-covariant maps are decomposable where $\pi_A,\pi_B$ are unitary representations of a compact group and $\pi_A$ is irreducible. Moreover, an extremal unital positive $(\pi_B,\pi_A)$-covariant map $\mathcal{L}$ is decomposable if and only if $\mathcal{L}$ is completely positive or completely copositive. We apply the results to prove that all PPT quantum channels of the form $$\Phi(\rho)=a\rho+b\rho^T+\fracc\textTr(\rho)d\textId_d+(1-a-b-c)\textdiag(\rho)$$ are entanglement-breaking, and that all A-BC PPT $(U\otimes \overline{U}\otimes U)$-invariant tripartite quantum states are A-BC separable. The former resolves some open questions raised in [DFV08, KMS20] and the latter is a strong contrast to the fact that there exist PPT-entangled $(U\otimes U\otimes U)$-invariant tripartite Werner states [EW01].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Randomized adaptive quantum state preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.04201</link>
    <author>Alicia B. Magann, Sophia E. Economou, Christian Arenz</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We develop an adaptive method for quantum state preparation that utilizes randomness as an essential component and that does not require classical optimization. Instead, a cost function is minimized to prepare a desired quantum state through an adaptively constructed quantum circuit, where each adaptive step is informed by feedback from gradient measurements in which the associated tangent space directions are randomized. We provide theoretical arguments and numerical evidence that convergence to the target state can be achieved for almost all initial states. We investigate different randomization procedures and develop lower bounds on the expected cost function change, which allows for drawing connections to barren plateaus and for assessing the applicability of the algorithm to large-scale problems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>