<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient quantum algorithm for nonlinear reaction-diffusion equations and energy estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01141</link>
    <author>Dong An, Di Fang, Stephen Jordan, Jin-Peng Liu, Guang Hao Low, Jiasu Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Nonlinear differential equations exhibit rich phenomena in many fields but are notoriously challenging to solve. Recently, Liu et al. [1] demonstrated the first efficient quantum algorithm for dissipative quadratic differential equations under the condition $R < 1$, where $R$ measures the ratio of nonlinearity to dissipation using the $\ell_2$ norm. Here we develop an efficient quantum algorithm based on [1] for reaction-diffusion equations, a class of nonlinear partial differential equations (PDEs). To achieve this, we improve upon the Carleman linearization approach introduced in [1] to obtain a faster convergence rate under the condition $R_D < 1$, where $R_D$ measures the ratio of nonlinearity to dissipation using the $\ell_{\infty}$ norm. Since $R_D$ is independent of the number of spatial grid points $n$ while $R$ increases with $n$, the criterion $R_D<1$ is significantly milder than $R<1$ for high-dimensional systems and can stay convergent under grid refinement for approximating PDEs. As applications of our quantum algorithm we consider the Fisher-KPP and Allen-Cahn equations, which have interpretations in classical physics. In particular, we show how to estimate the mean square kinetic energy in the solution by postprocessing the quantum state that encodes it to extract derivative information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A fast quantum algorithm for computing matrix permanent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01328</link>
    <author>Joonsuk Huh</author>
    <pubDate>May 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Computing a matrix permanent is known to be a classically intractable problem. This paper presents the first polynomial time quantum algorithm for computing permanents of arbitrary $N$-dimensional square matrices with multiplicative error and additive error protocols. We transformed the well-known classical algorithm, Ryser's formula, into sums of quantum overlap integrals to develop the quantum algorithm. This requires $\mathcal{O}(N)$ and $\mathcal{O}(N^{3})$ evaluations of the real part of the quantum overlap integrals for real and complex matrices, respectively, with polynomial depth quantum circuits of $\mathcal{O}(N)$ qubits. The existence of the polynomial time multiplicative error estimation of a matrix permanent would strongly imply that quantum computers can access the #P-hard problem. Our quantum algorithm attains the milestone of opening a new direction in quantum computing and computational complexity theory. It could resolve crucial computational complexity issues like locating the bounded error quantum polynomial time (BQP) relative to the polynomial hierarchy, which has been a big complexity question. Depending on the size of a matrix norm of interest, we can also obtain an exponentially small additive error estimation and better estimation against Gurvits' classical sampling algorithm. The additive error protocol is practically implementable in noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices. Moreover, our quantum algorithm directly shows the computational complexity connection between the matrix permanent and the real-time partition function of the quantum Ising Hamiltonian.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive constant-depth circuits for manipulating non-abelian anyons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01933</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Isaac Kim, Alexander Kliesch, Robert Koenig</author>
    <pubDate>May 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider Kitaev's quantum double model based on a finite group $G$ and describe quantum circuits for (a) preparation of the ground state, (b) creation of anyon pairs separated by an arbitrary distance, and (c) non-destructive topological charge measurement. We show that for any solvable group $G$ all above tasks can be realized by constant-depth adaptive circuits with geometrically local unitary gates and mid-circuit measurements. Each gate may be chosen adaptively depending on previous measurement outcomes. Constant-depth circuits are well suited for implementation on a noisy hardware since it may be possible to execute the entire circuit within the qubit coherence time. Thus our results could facilitate an experimental study of exotic phases of matter with a non-abelian particle statistics. We also show that adaptiveness is essential for our circuit construction. Namely, task (b) cannot be realized by non-adaptive constant-depth local circuits for any non-abelian group $G$. This is in a sharp contrast with abelian anyons which can be created and moved over an arbitrary distance by a depth-$1$ circuit composed of generalized Pauli gates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Deep learning of quantum entanglement from incomplete measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01462</link>
    <author>Dominik Koutný, Laia Ginés, Magdalena Moczała-Dusanowska, Sven Höfling, Christian Schneider, Ana Predojević, Miroslav Ježek</author>
    <pubDate>May 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantification of the entanglement present in a physical system is of paramount importance for fundamental research and many cutting-edge applications. Currently, achieving this goal requires very demanding experimental procedures such as full state tomography. Here, we demonstrate that by employing neural networks we can quantify the degree of entanglement without needing to know the full description of the quantum state. Our method allows for direct quantification of the quantum correlations using an incomplete set of local measurements. Despite using under-sampled measurements, we achieve an estimation error of up to an order of magnitude lower than the state-of-the-art quantum tomography. Furthermore, we achieve this result employing networks trained using exclusively simulated data. Finally, we derive a method based on a convolutional network input that can accept data from various measurement scenarios and perform, to some extent, independently of the measurement device.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Use of Quantum Linear System Algorithms in Interior Point Methods for Linear Optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01220</link>
    <author>Mohammadhossein Mohammadisiahroudi, Ramin Fakhimi, Tamás Terlaky</author>
    <pubDate>May 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing has attracted significant interest in the optimization community because it potentially can solve classes of optimization problems faster than conventional supercomputers. Several researchers proposed quantum computing methods, especially Quantum Interior Point Methods (QIPMs), to solve convex optimization problems, such as Linear Optimization, Semidefinite Optimization, and Second-order Cone Optimization problems. Most of them have applied a Quantum Linear System Algorithm at each iteration to compute a Newton step. However, using quantum linear solvers in QIPMs comes with many challenges, such as having ill-conditioned systems and the considerable error of quantum solvers. This paper investigates how one can efficiently use quantum linear solvers in QIPMs. Accordingly, an Inexact Infeasible Quantum Interior Point Method is developed to solve linear optimization problems. We also discuss how can we get an exact solution by Iterative Refinement without excessive time of quantum solvers. Finally, computational results with QISKIT implementation of our QIPM using quantum simulators are analyzed.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>