<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A note on lower bounds to variational problems with guarantees</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06142</link>
    <author>J. Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods play an important role in the study of quantum many body problems, both in the flavour of classical variational principles based on tensor networks as well as of quantum variational principles in near-term quantum computing. This brief pedagogical note stresses that for translationally invariant lattice Hamiltonians, one can easily derive efficiently computable lower bounds to ground state energies that can and should be compared with variational principles providing upper bounds. As small technical results, it is shown that (i) the Anderson bound and a (ii) common hierarchy of semi-definite relaxations both provide approximations with performance guarantees that scale like a constant in the energy density for cubic lattices. (iii) Also, the Anderson bound is systematically improved as a hierarchy of semi-definite relaxations inspired by the marginal problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Block Belief Propagation Algorithm for 2D Tensor Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05844</link>
    <author>Chu Guo, Dario Poletti, Itai Arad</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Belief propagation is a well-studied algorithm for approximating local marginals of multivariate probability distribution over complex networks, while tensor network states are powerful tools for quantum and classical many-body problems. Building on a recent connection between the belief propagation algorithm and the problem of tensor network contraction, we propose a block belief propagation algorithm for contracting two-dimensional tensor networks and approximating the ground state of $2D$ systems. The advantages of our method are three-fold: 1) the same algorithm works for both finite and infinite systems; 2) it allows natural and efficient parallelization; 3) given its flexibility it would allow to deal with different unit cells. As applications, we use our algorithm to study the $2D$ Heisenberg and transverse Ising models, and show that the accuracy of the method is comparable to state-of-the-art results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast Quantum Algorithms for Trace Distance Estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06783</link>
    <author>Qisheng Wang, Zhicheng Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In quantum information processing, trace distance is a basic metric of distinguishability between quantum states. However, there is no known efficient approach to estimate the value of trace distance in general. In this paper, we propose efficient quantum algorithms for estimating the trace distance within additive error $\varepsilon$ between mixed quantum states of rank $r$. Specifically, we first provide a quantum algorithm using $r \cdot \widetilde O(1/\varepsilon^2)$ queries to the quantum circuits that prepare the purifications of quantum states, which achieves a linear time dependence on the rank $r$. Then, we modify this quantum algorithm to obtain another algorithm using $\widetilde O(r^2/\varepsilon^5)$ samples of quantum states, which can be applied to quantum state certification. Both algorithms have the same quantum time complexities as their query/sample complexities up to a logarithmic factor.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Probabilistic unitary synthesis with optimal accuracy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06307</link>
    <author>Seiseki Akibue, Go Kato, Seiichiro Tani</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The purpose of unitary synthesis is to find a gate sequence that optimally approximates a target unitary transformation. A new synthesis approach, called probabilistic synthesis, has been introduced, and its superiority has been demonstrated over traditional deterministic approaches with respect to approximation error and gate length. However, the optimality of current probabilistic synthesis algorithms is unknown. We obtain the tight lower bound on the approximation error obtained by the optimal probabilistic synthesis, which guarantees the sub-optimality of current algorithms. We also show its tight upper bound, which improves and unifies current upper bounds depending on the class of target unitaries. These two bounds reveal the fundamental relationship of approximation error between probabilistic approximation and deterministic approximation of unitary transformations. From a computational point of view, we show that the optimal probability distribution can be computed by the semidefinite program (SDP) we construct. We also construct an efficient probabilistic synthesis algorithm for single-qubit unitaries, rigorously estimate its time complexity, and show that it reduces the approximation error quadratically compared with deterministic algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Unified theory of local quantum many-body dynamics: Eigenoperator thermalization theorems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07091</link>
    <author>Berislav Buča</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Explaining quantum many-body dynamics is a long-held goal of physics. A rigorous operator algebraic theory of dynamics in locally interacting systems in any dimension is provided here in terms of time-dependent Gibbs ensembles. The theory explains dynamics in closed, open and time-dependent systems and time-dependent Gibbs ensembles unify wide classes of quantum non-ergodic and ergodic systems. The theory is applied to quantum many-body scars, continuous, discrete and dissipative time crystals, Hilbert space fragmentation, lattice gauge theories, and disorder-free localization, among other cases. Novel pseudo-local classes of operators are introduced in the process: projected-local, which are local only for some states, crypto-local, whose locality is not manifest in terms of any finite number of local densities and transient ones, that dictate finite-time relaxation dynamics. An immediate corollary is proving saturation of the Mazur bound for the Drude weight. This proven theory is intuitively the rigorous algebraic counterpart of the weak eigenstate thermalization hypothesis and has deep implications for thermodynamics: quantum many-body systems 'out-of-equilibrium' are actually always in a time-dependent equilibrium state for any natural initial state. The work opens the possibility of designing novel out-of-equilibrium phases, with the newly identified scarring phase transition being an example.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>