<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum trapdoor functions from classical one-way functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.12821</link>
    <author>Andrea Coladangelo</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce the notion of a quantum trapdoor function. This is an efficiently computable unitary that takes as input a "public" quantum state and a classical string $x$, and outputs a quantum state. This map is such that (i) it is hard to invert, in the sense that it is hard to recover $x$ given the output state (and many copies of the public state), and (ii) there is a classical trapdoor that allows efficient inversion. We show that a quantum trapdoor function can be constructed from any quantum-secure one-way function. A direct consequence of this result is that, assuming just the existence of quantum-secure one-way functions, there exist: (i) a public-key encryption scheme with a quantum public key, and (ii) a two-message key-exchange protocol, assuming an appropriate notion of a quantum authenticated channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>(Non-)Universality in symmetric quantum circuits: Why Abelian symmetries are special</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.12466</link>
    <author>Iman Marvian</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this work, we develop the theory of symmetric quantum circuits with Abelian symmetries. It has been recently shown that general unitary transformations that respect a global symmetry can not be realized by composing unitaries that respect the same symmetry but do not act on all the subsystems in the system. For a general symmetry group, such as SU(d), the locality of interactions imposes different types of constraints on the realizable unitaries. For instance, the unitary realized in a subspace with one irreducible representation (charge) of the symmetry dictates the realized unitaries in multiple other sectors with inequivalent representations of the symmetry. Furthermore, in certain sectors rather than all unitaries that respect the symmetry, the realizable unitaries are the symplectic, or the orthogonal subgroups of this group. We show that none of the aforementioned restrictions appear in the case of Abelian symmetries: While the locality of interactions still imposes additional constraints on the realizable unitaries, they are of the following two types: (i) constraints on the relative phases between subspaces with different charges, and (ii) constraints due to the presence of multiple invariant subspaces inside a subspace with a given charge, which results in extra conserved observables. The latter type of constraint can be removed by k-local symmetric unitaries with sufficiently large k (independent of the system size), whereas to remove the former constraints, in general, one needs an ancillary qudit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Weak integrability breaking perturbations of integrable models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.12804</link>
    <author>Federica Maria Surace, Olexei Motrunich</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A quantum integrable system slightly perturbed away from integrability is typically expected to thermalize on timescales of order $\tau\sim \lambda^{-2}$, where $\lambda$ is the perturbation strength. We here study classes of perturbations that violate this scaling, and exhibit much longer thermalization times $\tau\sim \lambda^{-2\ell}$ where $\ell>1$ is an integer. Systems with these "weak integrability breaking" perturbations have an extensive number of quasi-conserved quantities that commute with the perturbed Hamiltonian up to corrections of order $\lambda^\ell$. We demonstrate a systematic construction to obtain families of such weak perturbations of a generic integrable model for arbitrary $\ell$. We then apply the construction to various models, including the Heisenberg, XXZ, and XYZ chains, the Hubbard model, models of spinless free fermions, and the quantum Ising chain. Our analytical framework explains the previously observed evidence of weak integrability breaking in the Heisenberg and XXZ chains under certain perturbations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Wigner State and Process Tomography on Near-Term Quantum Devices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.12725</link>
    <author>Amit Devra, Niklas J. Glaser, Dennis Huber, Steffen J. Glaser</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present an experimental scanning-based tomography approach for near-term quantum devices. It is based on a Wigner-type representation of quantum states and operators. These representations provide a rich visualization of quantum operators using shapes assembled from a linear combination of spherical harmonics. These shapes (called droplets in the following) can be experimentally tomographed by measuring the expectation values of rotated axial tensor operators. This study provides a reformulation of the theory of Wigner tomography of arbitrary states and Wigner tomography of known unitary processes for the case of a general-purpose pure-state quantum computer. We present an experimental framework for implementing the scanning-based tomography technique for circuit-based quantum computers and showcase results from IBM quantum experience. We also present a method for estimating the density and process matrices from experimentally tomographed Wigner functions (droplets). This tomography approach can be directly implemented using the Python-based software package $\texttt{DROPStomo}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On Stein's lemma in hypotheses testing in general non-asymptotic case</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.12684</link>
    <author>Marat V. Burnashev</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The problem of testing two simple hypotheses in a general probability space is considered. For a fixed type-I error probability, the best exponential decay rate of the type-II error probability is investigated. In regular asymptotic cases (i.e., when the length of the observation interval grows without limit) the best decay rate is given by Stein's exponent. In the paper, for a general probability space, some non-asymptotic lower and upper bounds for the best rate are derived. These bounds represent pure analytic relations without any limiting operations. In some natural cases, these bounds also give the convergence rate for Stein's exponent. Some illustrating examples are also provided.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>