<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A construction of Combinatorial NLTS</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02741</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of high complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). Here, we prove a weaker version called the combinatorial NLTS, where a quantum circuit lower bound is shown against states that violate a (small) constant fraction of local terms. This generalizes the prior NLETS results (Eldar and Harrow [2017]; Nirkhe, Vazirani and Yuen [2018]). Our construction is obtained by combining tensor networks with expander codes (Sipser and Spielman [1996]). The Hamiltonian is the parent Hamiltonian of a perturbed tensor network, inspired by the `uncle Hamiltonian' of Fernandez-Gonzalez et. al. [2015]. Thus, we deviate from the quantum CSS code Hamiltonians considered in most prior works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Avoiding barren plateaus via transferability of smooth solutions in Hamiltonian Variational Ansatz</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01982</link>
    <author>Antonio Anna Mele, Glen Bigan Mbeng, Giuseppe Ernesto Santoro, Mario Collura, Pietro Torta</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A large ongoing research effort focuses on Variational Quantum Algorithms (VQAs), representing leading candidates to achieve computational speed-ups on current quantum devices. The scalability of VQAs to a large number of qubits, beyond the simulation capabilities of classical computers, is still debated. Two major hurdles are the proliferation of low-quality variational local minima, and the exponential vanishing of gradients in the cost function landscape, a phenomenon referred to as barren plateaus. Here we show that by employing iterative search schemes one can effectively prepare the ground state of paradigmatic quantum many-body models, circumventing also the barren plateau phenomenon. This is accomplished by leveraging the transferability to larger system sizes of iterative solutions, displaying an intrinsic smoothness of the variational parameters, a result that does not extend to other solutions found via random-start local optimization. Our scheme could be directly tested on near-term quantum devices, running a refinement optimization in a favorable local landscape with non-vanishing gradients.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scrambling of Algebras in Open Quantum Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02033</link>
    <author>Faidon Andreadakis, Namit Anand, Paolo Zanardi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many quantitative approaches to the dynamical scrambling of information in quantum systems involve the study of out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs). In this paper, we introduce an algebraic OTOC ($\mathcal{A}$-OTOC) that allows us to study information scrambling of generalized quantum subsystems under quantum channels. For closed quantum systems, this algebraic framework was recently employed to unify quantum information-theoretic notions of operator entanglement, coherence-generating power, and Loschmidt echo. The main focus of this work is to provide a natural generalization of these techniques to open quantum systems. We first show that, for unitary dynamics, the $\mathcal{A}$-OTOC quantifies a generalized notion of information scrambling, namely between a subalgebra of observables and its commutant. For open quantum systems, on the other hand, we find a competition between the global environmental decoherence and the local scrambling of information. We illustrate this interplay by analytically studying various illustrative examples of algebras and quantum channels. To complement our analytical results, we perform numerical simulations of two paradigmatic systems: the PXP model and the Heisenberg XXX model, under dephasing. Our numerical results reveal connections with many-body scars and the stability of decoherence-free subspaces.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Advantages and limitations of quantum routing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01766</link>
    <author>Aniruddha Bapat, Andrew M. Childs, Alexey V. Gorshkov, Eddie Schoute</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Swap gate is a ubiquitous tool for moving information on quantum hardware, yet it can be considered a classical operation because it does not entangle product states. Genuinely quantum operations could outperform Swap for the task of permuting qubits within an architecture, which we call routing. We consider quantum routing in two models: (1) allowing arbitrary two-qubit unitaries, or (2) allowing Hamiltonians with norm-bounded interactions. We lower bound the circuit depth or time of quantum routing in terms of spectral properties of graphs representing the architecture interaction constraints, and give a generalized upper bound for all simple connected $n$-vertex graphs. In particular, we give conditions for a superpolynomial classical-quantum routing separation, which exclude graphs with a small spectral gap and graphs of bounded degree. Finally, we provide examples of a quadratic separation between gate-based and Hamiltonian routing models with a constant number of local ancillas per qubit and of an $\Omega(n)$ speedup if we also allow fast local interactions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Using copies to improve precision in continuous-time quantum computing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02545</link>
    <author>Jemma Bennett, Adam Callison, Tom O'Leary, Mia West, Nicholas Chancellor, Viv Kendon</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the quantum optimisation setting, we build on a scheme introduced by Young et al [PRA 88, 062314, 2013], where physical qubits in multiple copies of a problem encoded into an Ising spin Hamiltonian are linked together to increase the logical system's robustness to error. We introduce several innovations that improve this scheme significantly. First, we note that only one copy needs to be correct by the end of the computation, since solution quality can be checked efficiently. Second, we find that ferromagnetic links do not generally help in this "one correct copy" setting, but anti-ferromagnetic links do help on average, by suppressing the chance of the same error being present on all of the copies. Third, we find that minimum-strength anti-ferromagnetic links perform best, by counteracting the spin-flips induced by the errors. We have numerically tested our innovations on small instances of spin glasses from Callison et al [NJP 21, 123022, 2019], and we find improved error tolerance for three or more copies in configurations that include frustration. Interpreted as an effective precision increase, we obtain several extra bits of precision for three copies connected in a triangle. This provides proof-of-concept of a method for scaling quantum annealing beyond the precision limits of hardware, a step towards fault tolerance in this setting.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>