<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A local-realistic theory for fermions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04553</link>
    <author>Nicetu Tibau Vidal, Vlatko Vedral, Chiara Marletto</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a local model for general fermionic systems, which we express in the Heisenberg picture. To this end, we shall use a recently proposed formalism, the so-called "Raymond-Robichaud" construction, which allows one to construct an explicitly local model for any dynamical theory that satisfies no-signalling, in terms of equivalence classes of transformations that can be attached to each individual subsystem. By following the rigorous use of the parity superselection rule for fermions, we show how this construction removes the usual difficulties that fermionic systems display in regard to the definition of local states and local transformations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Feedback-assisted quantum search by continuous-time quantum walks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04566</link>
    <author>Alessandro Candeloro, Claudia Benedetti, Marco G. Genoni, Matteo G.A. Paris</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We address the quantum search of a target node on a cycle graph by means of a quantum walk assisted by continuous measurement and feedback. Unlike previous spatial search approaches, where the oracle is described as a projector on the target state, we instead consider a dynamical oracle implemented through a feedback Hamiltonian. In particular, our protocol is able to drive the walker to a desired target node. The idea is based on continuously monitoring the position of the quantum walker on the graph and then to apply a unitary feedback operation based on the information obtained from measurement. The feedback changes the couplings between the nodes and it is optimized at each time via a numerical procedure. We numerically simulate the stochastic trajectories describing the evolution for graphs of dimensions up to $N=15$, and quantify the performance of the protocol via the average fidelity between the state of the walker and the target node. We discuss different constraints on the control strategy, in particular on the possible values that the feedback couplings can take. We find that for unbounded controls, the protocol is able to quickly localize the walker on the target node. We then discuss how the performance is lowered by posing an upper bound on the control couplings, but still allowing to stabilize the walker in the desired node. Finally, we show how a digital feedback protocol, where the couplings can take values only from a discrete set, seems in general as efficient as the continuous bounded one.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Statistical Complexity of Sample Amplification</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04315</link>
    <author>Brian Axelrod, Shivam Garg, Yanjun Han, Vatsal Sharan, Gregory Valiant</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given $n$ i.i.d. samples drawn from an unknown distribution $P$, when is it possible to produce a larger set of $n+m$ samples which cannot be distinguished from $n+m$ i.i.d. samples drawn from $P$? (Axelrod et al. 2019) formalized this question as the sample amplification problem, and gave optimal amplification procedures for discrete distributions and Gaussian location models. However, these procedures and associated lower bounds are tailored to the specific distribution classes, and a general statistical understanding of sample amplification is still largely missing. In this work, we place the sample amplification problem on a firm statistical foundation by deriving generally applicable amplification procedures, lower bound techniques and connections to existing statistical notions. Our techniques apply to a large class of distributions including the exponential family, and establish a rigorous connection between sample amplification and distribution learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Splitting indistinguishable photons: Using linear optics to exceed the limit of photon blockade</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04555</link>
    <author>Harjot Singh, Edo Waks</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Photon-photon interactions are an essential requirement of quantum photonic information processing. One way to generate these interactions is to utilize an atom strongly coupled to an optical cavity. This system exhibits the photon blockade effect which enables single photon switching and creation of non-classical light. But the nonlinear effects enabled by this system suffer from a fundamental time-bandwidth constraint. For the the simple case of splitting an input pulse of two indistinguishable photons, this constraint imposes a limit on the efficiency of routing photons to different output ports. We show that this limit can be exceeded by combining the strongly-coupled atom with linear optics. By optimizing the unitary of the linear optical transformation, we achieve improved splitting efficiency for both un-entangled and entangled photons. Our results suggest that it may be possible to improve the efficiency of nonlinear optical processes at the single photon level by making suitable use of linear optics. These results could have implications for quantum information processing with photons.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Overcoming the entanglement barrier in quantum many-body dynamics via space-time duality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04150</link>
    <author>Alessio Lerose, Michael Sonner, Dmitry A. Abanin</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Describing non-equilibrium properties of quantum many-body systems is challenging due to high entanglement in the wavefunction. We take an open-quantum-system viewpoint and describe evolution of local observables in terms of the influence matrix (IM), which encodes the effects of a many-body system as an environment for a local subsystem. Recent works found that in many dynamical regimes the IM of an infinite system has low temporal entanglement and can be efficiently represented as a matrix-product state (MPS). Yet, direct iterative constructions of the IM encounter highly entangled intermediate states - a temporal entanglement barrier (TEB). We argue that TEB is ubiquitous, and elucidate its physical origin via a semiclassical quasiparticle picture that captures the exact behavior of integrable spin chains. Further, we show that a TEB also arises in chaotic spin chains, which lack well-defined quasiparticles. Based on these insights, we formulate an alternative light-cone growth algorithm, which provably avoids TEB, thus providing an efficient construction of the thermodynamic-limit IM as a MPS. This work demonstrates the efficiency of the IM approach to studying thermalization and transport in strongly interacting quantum systems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>