<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Adiabatic paths of Hamiltonians, symmetries of topological order, and automorphism codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11137</link>
    <author>David Aasen, Zhenghan Wang, Matthew B. Hastings</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recent "honeycomb code" is a fault-tolerant quantum memory defined by a sequence of checks which implements a nontrivial automorphism of the toric code. We argue that a general framework to understand this code is to consider continuous adiabatic paths of gapped Hamiltonians and we give a conjectured description of the fundamental group and second and third homotopy groups of this space in two spatial dimensions. A single cycle of such a path can implement some automorphism of the topological order of that Hamiltonian. We construct such paths for arbitrary automorphisms of two-dimensional doubled topological order. Then, realizing this in the case of the toric code, we turn this path back into a sequence of checks, constructing an automorphism code closely related to the honeycomb code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable fast benchmarking for individual quantum gates with local twirling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.10320</link>
    <author>Yihong Zhang, Wenjun Yu, Pei Zeng, Guoding Liu, Xiongfeng Ma</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>With the development of controllable quantum systems, fast and practical characterization for multi-qubit gates is essential for building high-fidelity quantum computing devices. The usual way to fulfill this requirement via randomized benchmarking asks for complicated implementation of numerous multi-qubit twirling gates. How to efficiently and reliably estimate the fidelity of a quantum process remains an open problem. In this work, we propose a character-cycle benchmarking protocol and a fast benchmarking protocol only using local twirling gates to estimate the process fidelity of an individual multi-qubit operation. Our protocols are able to characterize a large class of quantum gates including and beyond the Clifford group via the local gauge transformation, which forms a universal gate set for quantum computing. We numerically demonstrate our protocols for a non-Clifford gate -- controlled-$(TX)$ and a Clifford gate -- five-qubit quantum error-correcting encoding circuit. The numerical results show that our protocols can efficiently and reliably characterize the gate process fidelities. Compared with the cross-entropy benchmarking, the simulation results show that the fast benchmarking achieves three orders of magnitude improvements in terms of sampling complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The randomized measurement toolbox</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11374</link>
    <author>Andreas Elben, Steven T. Flammia, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, John Preskill, Benoît Vermersch, Peter Zoller</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Increasingly sophisticated programmable quantum simulators and quantum computers are opening unprecedented opportunities for exploring and exploiting the properties of highly entangled complex quantum systems. The complexity of large quantum systems is the source of their power, but also makes them difficult to control precisely or characterize accurately using measured classical data. We review recently developed protocols for probing the properties of complex many-qubit systems using measurement schemes that are practical using today's quantum platforms. In all these protocols, a quantum state is repeatedly prepared and measured in a randomly chosen basis; then a classical computer processes the measurement outcomes to estimate the desired property. The randomization of the measurement procedure has distinct advantages; for example, a single data set can be employed multiple times to pursue a variety of applications, and imperfections in the measurements are mapped to a simplified noise model that can more easily be mitigated. We discuss a range of use cases that have already been realized in quantum devices, including Hamiltonian simulation tasks, probes of quantum chaos, measurements of nonlocal order parameters, and comparison of quantum states produced in distantly separated laboratories. By providing a workable method for translating a complex quantum state into a succinct classical representation that preserves a rich variety of relevant physical properties, the randomized measurement toolbox strengthens our ability to grasp and control the quantum world.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-local computation of quantum circuits with small light cones</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.10106</link>
    <author>Kfir Dolev, Sam Cree</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The task of non-local quantum computation requires implementation of a unitary on $n$ qubits between two parties with only one round of communication, ideally with minimal pre-shared entanglement. We introduce a new protocol that makes use of the fact that port-based teleportation costs much less entanglement when done only on a small number of qubits at a time. Whereas previous protocols have entanglement cost independent of the unitary or scaling with its complexity, the cost of the new protocol scales with the \emphnon-locality of the unitary. Specifically, it takes the form $\sim n^{4V}$ with $V$ the maximum volume of a past light cone in a circuit implementing the unitary. Thus we can implement unitary circuits with $V\sim O(1)$ using polynomial entanglement, and those with $V\sim \mathrm{polylog}(n)$ using quasi-polynomial entanglement. For a general unitary circuit with $d$ layers of $k$-qubit gates $V$ is at most $k^d$, but if geometric locality is imposed it is at most polynomial in $d$. We give an explicit class of unitaries for which our protocol's entanglement cost scales better than any known protocol. We also show that several extensions can be made without significantly affecting the entanglement cost - arbitrary local pre- and post-processing; global Clifford pre- and post-processing; and the addition of a polynomial number of auxiliary systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient simulation of Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill states with Gaussian circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11182</link>
    <author>Cameron Calcluth, Alessandro Ferraro, Giulia Ferrini</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the classical simulatability of stabilizer Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill states in combination with arbitrary displacements, a large set of Gaussian operations and homodyne measurements. For these types of circuits, neither continuous-variable theorems based on the non-negativity of quasi-probability distributions nor discrete-variable theorems such as the Gottesman-Knill theorem can be employed to assess the simulatability. We first develop a method to evaluate the probability density function corresponding to measuring a single GKP state in the position basis following squeezing and rotations. This method involves evaluating a transformed Jacobi theta function using techniques from analytic number theory. We then use this result to identify two large classes of multimode circuits which are classically efficiently simulatable and are not contained by the GKP encoded Clifford group. Our results extend the set of circuits previously known to be classically efficiently simulatable.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>