<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Decomposition of Matrix Product States into Shallow Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00595</link>
    <author>Manuel S. Rudolph, Jing Chen, Jacob Miller, Atithi Acharya, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The rapid pace of recent advancements in numerical computation, notably the rise of GPU and TPU hardware accelerators, have allowed tensor network (TN) algorithms to scale to even larger quantum simulation problems, and to be employed more broadly for solving machine learning tasks. The "quantum-inspired" nature of TNs permits them to be mapped to parametrized quantum circuits (PQCs), a fact which has inspired recent proposals for enhancing the performance of TN algorithms using near-term quantum devices, as well as enabling joint quantum-classical training frameworks which benefit from the distinct strengths of TN and PQC models. However, the success of any such methods depends on efficient and accurate methods for approximating TN states using realistic quantum circuits, something which remains an unresolved question. In this work, we compare a range of novel and previously-developed algorithmic protocols for decomposing matrix product states (MPS) of arbitrary bond dimensions into low-depth quantum circuits consisting of stacked linear layers of two-qubit unitaries. These protocols are formed from different combinations of a preexisting analytical decomposition scheme with constrained optimization of circuit unitaries, and all possess efficient classical runtimes. Our experimental results reveal one particular protocol, involving sequential growth and optimization of the quantum circuit, to outperform all other methods, with even greater benefits seen in the setting of limited computational resources. Given these promising results, we expect our proposed decomposition protocol to form a useful ingredient within any joint application of TNs and PQCs, in turn further unlocking the rich and complementary benefits of classical and quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Barren plateaus in quantum tensor network optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00292</link>
    <author>Enrique Cervero Martín, Kirill Plekhanov, Michael Lubasch</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the barren plateau phenomenon in the variational optimization of quantum circuits inspired by matrix product states (qMPS), tree tensor networks (qTTN), and the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (qMERA). We consider as the cost function the expectation value of a Hamiltonian that is a sum of local terms. For randomly chosen variational parameters we show that the variance of the cost function gradient decreases exponentially with the distance of a Hamiltonian term from the canonical centre in the quantum tensor network. Therefore, as a function of qubit count, for qMPS most gradient variances decrease exponentially and for qTTN as well as qMERA they decrease polynomially. We also show that the calculation of these gradients is exponentially more efficient on a classical computer than on a quantum computer.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Some continuity properties of quantum Rényi divergences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00646</link>
    <author>Milán Mosonyi</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the problem of binary quantum channel discrimination with product inputs, the supremum of all type II error exponents for which the optimal type I errors go to zero is equal to the Umegaki channel relative entropy, while the infimum of all type II error exponents for which the optimal type I errors go to one is equal to the infimum of the sandwiched channel Rényi $\alpha$-divergences over all $\alpha>1$. Here we prove that these two threshold values coincide, thus proving, in particular, the strong converse property for this problem. Our proof method uses a minimax argument, which crucially relies on a newly established continuity property of the sandwiched Rényi $\alpha$-divergences for $\alpha\in(1,2]$. Motivated by this, we also prove various other continuity properties for quantum (channel) Rény divergences, which may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cross Entropy Benchmark for Measurement-Induced Phase Transitions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00609</link>
    <author>Yaodong Li, Yijian Zou, Paolo Glorioso, Ehud Altman, Matthew P. A. Fisher</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the prospects of employing the linear cross-entropy to experimentally access measurement-induced phase transitions (MIPT) without requiring any postselection of quantum trajectories. For two random circuits that are identical in the bulk but with different initial states, the linear cross-entropy $\chi$ between the bulk measurement outcome distributions in the two circuits acts as a boundary order parameter, and can be used to distinguish the volume law from area law phases. In the volume law phase (and in the thermodynamic limit) the bulk measurements cannot distinguish between the two different initial states, and $\chi = 1$. In the area law phase $\chi < 1$. For circuits with Clifford gates, we provide numerical evidence that $\chi$ can be sampled to accuracy $\epsilon$ from $O(1/\epsilon^2)$ trajectories, by running the first circuit on a quantum simulator without postselection, aided by a classical simulation of the second. We also find that for weak depolarizing noise the signature of the MIPT is still present for intermediate system sizes. In our protocol we have the freedom of choosing initial states such that the "classical" side can be simulated efficiently, while simulating the "quantum" side is still classically hard.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Mixed State Compiling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00528</link>
    <author>Nic Ezzell, Elliott M. Ball, Aliza U. Siddiqui, Mark M. Wilde, Andrew T. Sornborger, Patrick J. Coles, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The task of learning a quantum circuit to prepare a given mixed state is a fundamental quantum subroutine. We present a variational quantum algorithm (VQA) to learn mixed states which is suitable for near-term hardware. Our algorithm represents a generalization of previous VQAs that aimed at learning preparation circuits for pure states. We consider two different ansätze for compiling the target state; the first is based on learning a purification of the state and the second on representing it as a convex combination of pure states. In both cases, the resources required to store and manipulate the compiled state grow with the rank of the approximation. Thus, by learning a lower rank approximation of the target state, our algorithm provides a means of compressing a state for more efficient processing. As a byproduct of our algorithm, one effectively learns the principal components of the target state, and hence our algorithm further provides a new method for principal component analysis. We investigate the efficacy of our algorithm through extensive numerical implementations, showing that typical random states and thermal states of many body systems may be learnt this way. Additionally, we demonstrate on quantum hardware how our algorithm can be used to study hardware noise-induced states.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>