<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Challenges in Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15844</link>
    <author>Daniel Gottesman</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I will give an overview of what I see as some of the most important future directions in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation. In particular, I will give a brief summary of the major problems that need to be solved in fault tolerance based on low-density parity check codes and in hardware-specific fault tolerance. I will then conclude with a discussion of a possible new paradigm for designing fault-tolerant protocols based on a space-time picture of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Greatly improved higher-order product formulae for quantum simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15817</link>
    <author>Mauro E.S. Morales, Pedro C.S. Costa, Daniel K. Burgarth, Yuval R. Sanders, Dominic W. Berry</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for simulation of Hamiltonian evolution are often based on product formulae like Trotter. The fractal method of Suzuki gives a systematic way to find arbitrarily high-order product formulae, but results in a large number of exponentials. On the other hand, an alternative way, with a minimum number of exponentials, for 6th and 8th order product formulae is given by Yoshida. In this work, we not only extended Yoshida's method to 10th order, but we also found hundreds of new 8th order product formulae. Moreover, we found an 8th order product formula that is over $1000$ times more accurate than the best product formula of Yoshida.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The $2T$-qutrit, a two-mode bosonic qutrit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16188</link>
    <author>Aurélie Denys, Anthony Leverrier</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Building on the observation that bosonic cat codes live in the span of coherent states indexed by a finite subgroup of the complex numbers, we consider a two-mode bosonic code where the coherent states now form a finite subgroup of the quaternions. We focus on the binary tetrahedral group, denoted $2T$, which admits 24 elements forming the vertices of the 24-cell, a regular four-dimensional polytope, and define a bosonic qutrit that appears to be quite robust in the regime of low loss. We initiate a study of the properties of this qutrit and identify stabilisers as well as logical operators for this bosonic code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New magic state distillation factories optimized by temporally encoded lattice surgery</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15814</link>
    <author>Prithviraj Prabhu, Christopher Chamberland</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fault-tolerant quantum computers, with error correction implemented using topological codes, will most likely require lattice surgery protocols in order to implement a universal gate set. Timelike failures during lattice surgery protocols can result in logical failures during the execution of an algorithm. In addition to the spacelike distance of the topological code used to protect the qubits from errors, there is also the timelike distance which is given by the number of syndrome measurement rounds during a lattice surgery protocol. As such, a larger timelike distance requirement will result in the slowdown of an algorithm's runtime. Temporal encoding of lattice surgery (TELS) is a technique which can be used to reduce the number of syndrome measurement rounds that are required during a lattice surgery protocol. This is done by measuring an over-complete set of mutually commuting multi-qubit Pauli operators (referred to as a parallelizable Pauli set) which form codewords of a classical error correcting code. The results of the over-complete set of Pauli measurements can then be used to detect and possibly correct timelike lattice surgery failures. In this work, we introduce an improved TELS protocol and subsequently augment it with the ability to correct low-weight classical errors, resulting in greater speedups in algorithm runtimes. We also explore large families of classical error correcting codes for a wide range of parallelizable Pauli set sizes. We also apply TELS to magic state distillation protocols in the context of biased noise, where logical qubits are encoded in asymmetric surface codes. Using optimized layouts, we show improvements in the space-time cost of our magic state factories compared to previous protocols. Such improvements are achieved using computations performed in the Clifford frame.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>CNOT circuits need little help to implement arbitrary Hadamard-free Clifford transformations they generate</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16195</link>
    <author>Dmitri Maslov, Willers Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A Hadamard-free Clifford transformation is a circuit composed of quantum Phase (P), CZ, and CNOT gates. It is known that such a circuit can be written as a three-stage computation, -P-CZ-CNOT-, where each stage consists only of gates of the specified type. In this paper, we focus on the minimization of circuit depth by entangling gates, corresponding to the important time-to-solution metric and the reduction of noise due to decoherence. We consider two popular connectivity maps: Linear Nearest Neighbor (LNN) and all-to-all. First, we show that a Hadamard-free Clifford operation can be implemented over LNN in depth $5n$, i.e., in the same depth as the -CNOT- stage alone. This implies the ability to implement arbitrary Clifford transformation over LNN in depth no more than $7n{+}2$, improving the best previous upper bound of $9n$. Second, we report heuristic evidence that on average a random uniformly distributed Hadamard-free Clifford transformation over $n{>}6$ qubits can be implemented with only a tiny additive constant overhead over all-to-all connected architecture compared to the best-known depth-optimized implementation of the -CNOT- stage alone. This suggests the reduction of the depth of Clifford circuits from $2n\,{+}\,O(\log^2(n))$ to $1.5n\,{+}\,O(\log^2(n))$ over unrestricted architectures.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>