<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A circuit-level protocol and analysis for twist-based lattice surgery</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05678</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Lattice surgery is a measurement-based technique for performing fault-tolerant quantum computation in two dimensions. When using the surface code, the most general lattice surgery operations require lattice irregularities called twist defects. However, implementing twist-based lattice surgery may require additional resources, such as extra device connectivity, and could lower the threshold and overall performance for the surface code. Here we provide an explicit twist-based lattice surgery protocol and its requisite connectivity layout. We also provide new stabilizer measurement circuits for measuring twist defects which are compatible with our chosen gate scheduling. We undertake the first circuit-level error correction simulations during twist-based lattice surgery using a biased depolarizing noise model. Our results indicate a slight decrease in the threshold for timelike logical failures compared to lattice surgery protocols with no twist defects in the bulk. However, comfortably below threshold (i.e. with CNOT infidelities below $5 \times 10^{-3}$), the performance degradation is mild and in fact preferable over proposed alternative twist-free schemes. Lastly, we provide an efficient scheme for measuring $Y$ operators along boundaries of surface codes which bypasses certain steps that were required in previous schemes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Algorithms for Approximating Quantum Partition Functions at Low Temperature</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06533</link>
    <author>Tyler Helmuth, Ryan L. Mann</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish an efficient approximation algorithm for the partition functions of a class of quantum spin systems at low temperature, which can be viewed as stable quantum perturbations of classical spin systems. Our algorithm is based on combining the contour representation of quantum spin systems of this type due to Borgs, Kotecký, and Ueltschi with the algorithmic framework developed by Helmuth, Perkins, and Regts, and Borgs et al.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cut query algorithms with star contraction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05674</link>
    <author>Simon Apers, Yuval Efron, Paweł Gawrychowski, Troy Lee, Sagnik Mukhopadhyay, Danupon Nanongkai</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the complexity of determining the edge connectivity of a simple graph with cut queries. We show that (i) there is a bounded-error randomized algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $O(n)$ cut queries, and (ii) there is a bounded-error quantum algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $\~O(\sqrt{n})$ cut queries. We prove these results using a new technique called "star contraction" to randomly contract edges of a graph while preserving non-trivial minimum cuts. In star contraction vertices randomly contract an edge incident on a small set of randomly chosen vertices. In contrast to the related 2-out contraction technique of Ghaffari, Nowicki, and Thorup [SODA'20], star contraction only contracts vertex-disjoint star subgraphs, which allows it to be efficiently implemented via cut queries. The $O(n)$ bound from item (i) was not known even for the simpler problem of connectivity, and improves the $O(n\log^3 n)$ bound by Rubinstein, Schramm, and Weinberg [ITCS'18]. The bound is tight under the reasonable conjecture that the randomized communication complexity of connectivity is $\Omega(n\log n)$, an open question since the seminal work of Babai, Frankl, and Simon [FOCS'86]. The bound also excludes using edge connectivity on simple graphs to prove a superlinear randomized query lower bound for minimizing a symmetric submodular function. Item (ii) gives a nearly-quadratic separation with the randomized complexity and addresses an open question of Lee, Santha, and Zhang [SODA'21]. The algorithm can also be viewed as making $\~O(\sqrt{n})$ matrix-vector multiplication queries to the adjacency matrix. Finally, we demonstrate the use of star contraction outside of the cut query setting by designing a one-pass semi-streaming algorithm for computing edge connectivity in the vertex arrival setting. This contrasts with the edge arrival setting where two passes are required.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decoding techniques applied to the compilation of CNOT circuits for NISQ architectures</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06457</link>
    <author>Timothée Goubault de Brugière, Marc Baboulin, Benoît Valiron, Simon Martiel, Cyril Allouche</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Current proposals for quantum compilers require the synthesis and optimization of linear reversible circuits and among them CNOT circuits. Since these circuits represent a significant part of the cost of running an entire quantum circuit, we aim at reducing their size. In this paper we present a new algorithm for the synthesis of CNOT circuits based on the solution of the syndrome decoding problem. Our method addresses the case of ideal hardware with an all-to-all qubit connectivity and the case of near-term quantum devices with restricted connectivity. For both cases, we present benchmarks showing that our algorithm outperforms existing algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum estimation, control and learning: opportunities and challenges</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05835</link>
    <author>Daoyi Dong, Ian R Petersen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The development of estimation and control theories for quantum systems is a fundamental task for practical quantum technology. This vision article presents a brief introduction to challenging problems and potential opportunities in the emerging areas of quantum estimation, control and learning. The topics cover quantum state estimation, quantum parameter identification, quantum filtering, quantum open-loop control, quantum feedback control, machine learning for estimation and control of quantum systems, and quantum machine learning.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>