<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>One-Wayness in Quantum Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03394</link>
    <author>Tomoyuki Morimae, Takashi Yamakawa</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The existence of one-way functions is one of the most fundamental assumptions in classical cryptography. In the quantum world, on the other hand, there are evidences that some cryptographic primitives can exist even if one-way functions do not exist. We therefore have the following important open problem in quantum cryptography: What is the most fundamental element in quantum cryptography? In this direction, Brakerski, Canetti, and Qian recently defined a notion called EFI pairs, which are pairs of efficiently generatable states that are statistically distinguishable but computationally indistinguishable, and showed its equivalence with some cryptographic primitives including commitments, oblivious transfer, and general multi-party computations. However, their work focuses on decision-type primitives and does not cover search-type primitives like quantum money and digital signatures. In this paper, we study properties of one-way state generators (OWSGs), which are a quantum analogue of one-way functions. We first revisit the definition of OWSGs and generalize it by allowing mixed output states. Then we show the following results. (1) We define a weaker version of OWSGs, weak OWSGs, and show that they are equivalent to OWSGs. (2) Quantum digital signatures are equivalent to OWSGs. (3) Private-key quantum money schemes (with pure money states) imply OWSGs. (4) Quantum pseudo one-time pad schemes imply both OWSGs and EFI pairs. (5) We introduce an incomparable variant of OWSGs, which we call secretly-verifiable and statistically-invertible OWSGs, and show that they are equivalent to EFI pairs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal Quantum Speedup for Branch-and-Bound, Branch-and-Cut, and Tree-Search Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03210</link>
    <author>Shouvanik Chakrabarti, Pierre Minssen, Romina Yalovetzky, Marco Pistoia</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Mixed Integer Programs (MIPs) model many optimization problems of interest in Computer Science, Operations Research, and Financial Engineering. Solving MIPs is NP-Hard in general, but several solvers have found success in obtaining near-optimal solutions for problems of intermediate size. Branch-and-Cut algorithms, which combine Branch-and-Bound logic with cutting-plane routines, are at the core of modern MIP solvers. Montanaro proposed a quantum algorithm with a near-quadratic speedup compared to classical Branch-and-Bound algorithms in the worst case, when every optimal solution is desired. In practice, however, a near-optimal solution is satisfactory, and by leveraging tree-search heuristics to search only a portion of the solution tree, classical algorithms can perform much better than the worst-case guarantee. In this paper, we propose a quantum algorithm, Incremental-Quantum-Branch-and-Bound, with universal near-quadratic speedup over classical Branch-and-Bound algorithms for every input, i.e., if classical Branch-and-Bound has complexity $Q$ on an instance that leads to solution depth $d$, Incremental-Quantum-Branch-and-Bound offers the same guarantees with a complexity of $\tilde{O}(\sqrt{Q}d)$. Our results are valid for a wide variety of search heuristics, including depth-based, cost-based, and $A^{\ast}$ heuristics. Universal speedups are also obtained for Branch-and-Cut as well as heuristic tree search. Our algorithms are directly comparable to commercial MIP solvers, and guarantee near quadratic speedup whenever $Q \gg d$. We use numerical simulation to verify that $Q \gg d$ for typical instances of the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model, Maximum Independent Set, and Portfolio Optimization; as well as to extrapolate the dependence of $Q$ on input size parameters. This allows us to project the typical performance of our quantum algorithms for these important problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Investigating the Global Properties of a Resource Theory of Contextuality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03268</link>
    <author>Tiago Santos, Barbara Amaral</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Resource theories constitute a powerful theoretical framework and a tool that captures, in an abstract structure, pragmatic aspects of the most varied theories and processes. For physical theories, while this framework deals directly with questions about the concrete possibilities of carrying out tasks and processes, resource theories also make it possible to recast these already established theories on a new language, providing not only new perspectives on the potential of physical phenomena as valuable resources for technological development, for example, but they also provide insights into the very foundations of these theories. In this work, we will investigate some properties of a resource theory for quantum contextuality, an essential characteristic of quantum phenomena that ensures the impossibility of interpreting the results of quantum measurements as revealing properties that are independent of the set of measurements being made. We will present the resource theory to be studied and investigate certain global properties of this theory using tools and methods that, although already developed and studied by the community in other resource theories, had not yet been used to characterize resource theories of contextuality. In particular, we will use the so called cost and yield monotones, extending the results of reference Quantum 4, 280 (2020) to general contextuality scenarios.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gapped Lineon and Fracton Models on Graphs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03727</link>
    <author>Pranay Gorantla, Ho Tat Lam, Nathan Seiberg, Shu-Heng Shao</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a $\mathbb{Z}_N$ stabilizer code that can be defined on any spatial lattice of the form $\Gamma\times C_{L_z}$, where $\Gamma$ is a general graph. We also present the low-energy limit of this stabilizer code as a Euclidean lattice action, which we refer to as the anisotropic $\mathbb{Z}_N$ Laplacian model. It is gapped, robust (i.e., stable under small deformations), and has lineons. Its ground state degeneracy (GSD) is expressed in terms of a "mod $N$-reduction" of the Jacobian group of the graph $\Gamma$. In the special case when space is an $L\times L\times L_z$ cubic lattice, the logarithm of the GSD depends on $L$ in an erratic way and grows no faster than $O(L)$. We also discuss another gapped model, the $\mathbb{Z}_N$ Laplacian model, which can be defined on any graph. It has fractons and a similarly strange GSD.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Randomized channel-state duality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03723</link>
    <author>Bin Yan, Nikolai A. Sinitsyn</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Channel-state duality is a central result in quantum information science. It refers to the correspondence between a dynamical process (quantum channel) and a static quantum state in an enlarged Hilbert space. Since the corresponding dual state is generally mixed, it is described by a Hermitian matrix. In this article, we present a randomized channel-state duality. In other words, a quantum channel is represented by a collection of $N$ pure quantum states that are produced from a random source. The accuracy of this randomized duality relation is given by $1/N$, with regard to an appropriate distance measure. For large systems, $N$ is much smaller than the dimension of the exact dual matrix of the quantum channel. This provides a highly accurate low-rank approximation of any quantum channel, and, as a consequence of the duality relation, an efficient data compression scheme for mixed quantum states. We demonstrate these two immediate applications of the randomized channel-state duality with a chaotic $1$-dimensional spin system.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>