<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Establishing trust in quantum computations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07568</link>
    <author>Timothy Proctor, Stefan Seritan, Erik Nielsen, Kenneth Rudinger, Kevin Young, Robin Blume-Kohout, Mohan Sarovar</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Real-world quantum computers have grown sufficiently complex that they can no longer be simulated by classical supercomputers, but their computational power remains limited by errors. These errors corrupt the results of quantum algorithms, and it is no longer always feasible to use classical simulations to directly check the correctness of quantum computations. Without practical methods for quantifying the accuracy with which a quantum algorithm has been executed, it is difficult to establish trust in the results of a quantum computation. Here we solve this problem, by introducing a simple and efficient technique for measuring the fidelity with which an as-built quantum computer can execute an algorithm. Our technique converts the algorithm's quantum circuits into a set of closely related circuits whose success rates can be efficiently measured. It enables measuring the fidelity of quantum algorithm executions both in the near-term, with algorithms run on hundreds or thousands of physical qubits, and into the future, with algorithms run on logical qubits protected by quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>ADAPT-VQE is insensitive to rough parameter landscapes and barren plateaus</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07179</link>
    <author>Harper R. Grimsley, George S. Barron, Edwin Barnes, Sophia E. Economou, Nicholas J. Mayhall</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum eigensolvers (VQEs) represent a powerful class of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms for computing molecular energies. Various numerical issues exist for these methods, however, including barren plateaus and large numbers of local minima. In this work, we consider Adaptive, Problem-Tailored (ADAPT)-VQE ansätze, and examine how they are impacted by these local minima. We find that while ADAPT-VQE does not remove local minima, the gradient-informed, one-operator-at-a-time circuit construction seems to accomplish two things: First, it provides an initialization strategy that is dramatically better than random initialization, and which is applicable in situations where chemical intuition cannot help with initialization, i.e., when Hartree-Fock is a poor approximation to the ground state. Second, even if an ADAPT-VQE iteration converges to a local trap at one step, it can still "burrow" toward the exact solution by adding more operators, which preferentially deepens the occupied trap. This same mechanism helps highlight a surprising feature of ADAPT-VQE: It should not suffer optimization problems due to "barren plateaus". Even if barren plateaus appear in the parameter landscape, our analysis and simulations reveal that ADAPT-VQE avoids such regions by design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum many-body systems in thermal equilibrium</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08349</link>
    <author>Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The thermal or equilibrium ensemble is one of the most ubiquitous states of matter. For models comprised of many locally interacting quantum particles, it describes a wide range of physical situations, relevant to condensed matter physics, high energy physics, quantum chemistry and quantum computing, among others. We give a pedagogical overview of some of the most important universal features about the physics and complexity of these states, which have the locality of the Hamiltonian at its core. We focus on mathematically rigorous statements, many of them inspired by ideas and tools from quantum information theory. These include bounds on their correlations, the form of the subsystems, various statistical properties, and the performance of classical and quantum algorithms. We also include a summary of a few of the most important technical tools, as well as some self-contained proofs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Monotonicity of the quantum 2-Wasserstein distance</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07405</link>
    <author>Rafał Bistroń, Michał Eckstein, Karol Życzkowski</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study a quantum analogue of the 2-Wasserstein distance as a measure of proximity on the set $\Omega_N$ of density matrices of dimension $N$. We show that such (semi-)distances do not induce Riemannian metrics on the tangent bundle of $\Omega_N$ and are typically not unitary invariant. Nevertheless, we prove that for $N=2$ dimensional Hilbert space the quantum 2-Wasserstein distance (unique up to rescaling) is monotonous with respect to any single-qubit quantum operation. Furthermore, for any $N \geq 3$ and the quantum cost matrix proportional to a projector we demonstrate the monotonicity under arbitrary mixed unitary channels. Finally, we provide numerical evidence which allows us to conjecture that the unitary invariant quantum 2-Wasserstein semi-distance is monotonous with respect to all CPTP maps in any dimension $N$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Beyond i.i.d. in the Resource Theory of Asymmetry: An Information-Spectrum Approach for Quantum Fisher Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08439</link>
    <author>Koji Yamaguchi, Hiroyasu Tajima</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Energetic coherence is a valuable resource for various operations, including precise measurement of time and acceleration of quantum manipulations. Recently, it has been shown that the theory of energetic coherence, called the resource theory of asymmetry, has a thermodynamic structure, as do entanglement theory and quantum thermodynamics. In the so-called i.i.d. regime, where identical copies of a state are converted into identical copies of another state, the convertibility is entirely determined by the amount of energetic coherence measured by the quantum Fisher information (QFI). This fact means that QFI takes the place of entropy in thermodynamics and entanglement entropy in entanglement theory. So far, such a correspondence between energetic coherence and entropy is known only in the i.i.d. regime. In entanglement theory and quantum thermodynamics in the non-i.i.d. regime, entropy-related quantities based on the information-spectrum method reveal a non-equilibrium thermodynamics structure. Still, it has been an open question whether a similar structure exists for energetic coherence. In this Letter, we solve this problem by constructing an information-spectrum method applicable to the quantum Fisher information content. As a result, we establish a general theory of the pure-state convertibility in the non-i.i.d. regime of the resource theory of asymmetry. The given theory reveals a non-equilibrium thermodynamic structure of energetic coherence in the non-i.i.d. regime, based on QFI rather than entropy.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>