<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08154</link>
    <author>Kerstin Beer</author>
    <pubDate>May 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This PhD thesis combines two of the most exciting research areas of the last decades: quantum computing and machine learning. We introduce dissipative quantum neural networks (DQNNs), which are designed for fully quantum learning tasks, are capable of universal quantum computation and have low memory requirements while training. These networks are optimised with training data pairs in form of input and desired output states and therefore can be used for characterising unknown or untrusted quantum devices. We not only demonstrate the generalisation behaviour of DQNNs using classical simulations, but also implement them successfully on actual quantum computers. To understand the ultimate limits for such quantum machine learning methods, we discuss the quantum no free lunch theorem, which describes a bound on the probability that a quantum device, which can be modelled as a unitary process and is optimised with quantum examples, gives an incorrect output for a random input. Moreover we expand the area of applications of DQNNs in two directions. In the first case, we include additional information beyond just the training data pairs: since quantum devices are always structured, the resulting data is always structured as well. We modify the DQNN's training algorithm such that knowledge about the graph-structure of the training data pairs is included in the training process and show that this can lead to better generalisation behaviour. Both the original DQNN and the DQNN including graph structure are trained with data pairs in order to characterise an underlying relation. However, in the second extension of the algorithm we aim to learn characteristics of a set of quantum states in order to extend it to quantum states which have similar properties. Therefore we build a generative adversarial model where two DQNNs, called the generator and discriminator, are trained in a competitive way.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Work fluctuations and entanglement in quantum batteries</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08447</link>
    <author>Satoya Imai, Otfried Gühne, Stefan Nimmrichter</author>
    <pubDate>May 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider quantum batteries given by composite interacting quantum systems in terms of the thermodynamic work cost of local random unitary processes. We characterize quantum correlations by monitoring the average energy change and its fluctuations in the high-dimensional bipartite systems. We derive a hierarchy of bounds on high-dimensional entanglement (the so-called Schmidt number) from the work fluctuations and thereby show that larger work fluctuations can verify the presence of stronger entanglement in the system. Finally, we develop two-point measurement protocols with noisy detectors that can estimate work fluctuations, showing that the dimensionality of entanglement can be probed in this manner.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimising shadow tomography with generalised measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08990</link>
    <author>H. Chau Nguyen, Jan Lennart Bönsel, Jonathan Steinberg, Otfried Gühne</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Advances in quantum technology require scalable techniques to efficiently extract information from a quantum system, such as expectation values of observables or its entropy. Traditional tomography is limited to a handful of qubits and shadow tomography has been suggested as a scalable replacement for larger systems. Shadow tomography is conventionally analysed based on outcomes of ideal projective measurements on the system upon application of randomised unitaries. Here, we suggest that shadow tomography can be much more straightforwardly formulated for generalised measurements, or positive operator valued measures. Based on the idea of the least-square estimator, shadow tomography with generalised measurements is both more general and simpler than the traditional formulation with randomisation of unitaries. In particular, this formulation allows us to analyse theoretical aspects of shadow tomography in detail. For example, we provide a detailed study of the implication of symmetries in shadow tomography. Shadow tomography with generalised measurements is also indispensable in realistic implementation of quantum mechanical measurements, when noise is unavoidable. Moreover, we also demonstrate how the optimisation of measurements for shadow tomography tailored toward a particular set of observables can be carried out.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Say NO to Optimization: A Non-Orthogonal Quantum Eigensolver</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09039</link>
    <author>Unpil Baek, Diptarka Hait, James Shee, Oskar Leimkuhler, William J. Huggins, Torin F. Stetina, Martin Head-Gordon, K. Birgitta Whaley</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A balanced description of both static and dynamic correlations in electronic systems with nearly degenerate low-lying states presents a challenge for multi-configurational methods on classical computers. We present here a quantum algorithm utilizing the action of correlating cluster operators to provide high-quality wavefunction ansätze employing a non-orthogonal multireference basis that captures a significant portion of the exact wavefunction in a highly compact manner, and that allows computation of the resulting energies and wavefunctions at polynomial cost with a quantum computer. This enables a significant improvement over the corresponding classical non-orthogonal solver, which incurs an exponential cost when evaluating off-diagonal matrix elements between the ansatz states, and is therefore intractable. We implement the non-orthogonal quantum eigensolver (NOQE) here with an efficient ansatz parameterization inspired by classical quantum chemistry methods that succeed in capturing significant amounts of electronic correlation accurately. By taking advantage of classical methods for chemistry, NOQE provides a flexible, compact, and rigorous description of both static and dynamic electronic correlation, making it an attractive method for the calculation of electronic states of a wide range of molecular systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Industry applications of neutral-atom quantum computing solving independent set problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08500</link>
    <author>Jonathan Wurtz, Pedro Lopes, Nathan Gemelke, Alexander Keesling, Shengtao Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Architectures for quantum computing based on neutral atoms have risen to prominence as candidates for both near and long-term applications. These devices are particularly well suited to solve independent set problems, as the combinatorial constraints can be naturally encoded in the low-energy Hilbert space due to the Rydberg blockade mechanism. Here, we approach this connection with a focus on a particular device architecture and explore the ubiquity and utility of independent set problems by providing examples of real-world applications. After a pedagogical introduction of basic graph theory concepts of relevance, we briefly discuss how to encode independent set problems in Rydberg Hamiltonians. We then outline the major classes of independent set problems and include associated example applications with industry and social relevance. We determine a wide range of sectors that could benefit from efficient solutions of independent set problems -- from telecommunications and logistics to finance and strategic planning -- and display some general strategies for efficient problem encoding and implementation on neutral-atom platforms.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>