<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Classification of measurement-based quantum wire in stabilizer PEPS</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00616</link>
    <author>Paul Herringer, Robert Raussendorf</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a class of translation-invariant 2D tensor network states with a stabilizer symmetry, which we call stabilizer PEPS. The cluster state, GHZ state, and states in the toric code belong to this class. We investigate the transmission capacity of stabilizer PEPS for measurement-based quantum wire, and arrive at a complete classification of transmission behaviors. The transmission behaviors fall into 13 classes, one of which corresponds to Clifford quantum cellular automata. In addition, we identify 12 other classes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Clifford Circuit Initialisation for Variational Quantum Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.01539</link>
    <author>M. H. Cheng, K. E. Khosla, C. N. Self, M. Lin, B. X. Li, A. C. Medina, M. S. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an initialisation method for variational quantum algorithms applicable to intermediate scale quantum computers. The method uses simulated annealing of the efficiently simulable Clifford parameter points as a pre-optimisation to find a low energy initial condition. We numerically demonstrate the effectiveness of the technique, and how it depends on Hamiltonian structure, number of qubits and circuit depth. While a range of different problems are considered, we note that the method is particularly useful for quantum chemistry problems. This presented method could help achieve a quantum advantage in noisy or fault-tolerant intermediate scale devices, even though we prove in general that the method is not arbitrarily scalable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lower bounds for adiabatic quantum algorithms by quantum speed limit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.01604</link>
    <author>Jyong-Hao Chen</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a simple framework for estimating lower bounds on the runtime of a broad class of adiabatic quantum algorithms. The central formula is derived by combining a constraint from quantum speed limit and an inequality obeyed by adiabatic fidelity. After examining adiabatic versions of certain keystone circuit-based quantum algorithms, this technique is applied to adiabatic quantum algorithms with undetermined speedup. In particular, we analytically obtain lower bounds on adiabatic algorithms for finding $k$-clique in random graphs. Additionally, for a particular class of Hamiltonian, it is straightforward to prove the equivalence between our framework and the conventional approach based on spectral gap analysis.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Pricing multi-asset derivatives by variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.01277</link>
    <author>Kenji Kubo, Koichi Miyamoto, Kosuke Mitarai, Keisuke Fujii</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Pricing a multi-asset derivative is an important problem in financial engineering, both theoretically and practically. Although it is suitable to numerically solve partial differential equations to calculate the prices of certain types of derivatives, the computational complexity increases exponentially as the number of underlying assets increases in some classical methods, such as the finite difference method. Therefore, there are efforts to reduce the computational complexity by using quantum computation. However, when solving with naive quantum algorithms, the target derivative price is embedded in the amplitude of one basis of the quantum state, and so an exponential complexity is required to obtain the solution. To avoid the bottleneck, the previous study~[Miyamoto and Kubo, IEEE Transactions on Quantum Engineering, \textbf3, 1--25 (2022)] utilizes the fact that the present price of a derivative can be obtained by its discounted expected value at any future point in time and shows that the quantum algorithm can reduce the complexity. In this paper, to make the algorithm feasible to run on a small quantum computer, we use variational quantum simulation to solve the Black-Scholes equation and compute the derivative price from the inner product between the solution and a probability distribution. This avoids the measurement bottleneck of the naive approach and would provide quantum speedup even in noisy quantum computers. We also conduct numerical experiments to validate our method. Our method will be an important breakthrough in derivative pricing using small-scale quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An attempt to understand relational quantum mechanics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.01380</link>
    <author>Pekka Lahti, Juha-Pekka Pellonpää</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We search for a possible mathematical formulation of some of the key ideas of the relational interpretation of quantum mechanics and study their consequences. We also briefly overview some proposals of relational quantum mechanics for an axiomatic reconstruction of the Hilbert space formulation of quantum mechanics.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>