<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement-based quantum computation in finite one-dimensional systems: string order implies computational power</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05089</link>
    <author>Robert Raussendorf, Wang Yang, Arnab Adhikary</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a new framework for assessing the power of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) on short-range entangled symmetric resource states, in spatial dimension one. It requires fewer assumptions than previously known. The formalism can handle finitely extended systems (as opposed to the thermodynamic limit), and does not require translation-invariance. Further, we strengthen the connection between MBQC computational power and string order. Namely, we establish that whenever a suitable set of string order parameters is non-zero, a corresponding set of unitary gates can be realized with fidelity arbitrarily close to unity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Commitments to Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05138</link>
    <author>Sam Gunn, Nathan Ju, Fermi Ma, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>What does it mean to commit to a quantum state? In this work, we propose a simple answer: a commitment to quantum messages is binding if, after the commit phase, the committed state is hidden from the sender's view. We accompany this new definition with several instantiations. We build the first non-interactive succinct quantum state commitments, which can be seen as an analogue of collision-resistant hashing for quantum messages. We also show that hiding quantum state commitments (QSCs) are implied by any commitment scheme for classical messages. All of our constructions can be based on quantum-cryptographic assumptions that are implied by but are potentially weaker than one-way functions. Commitments to quantum states open the door to many new cryptographic possibilities. Our flagship application of a succinct QSC is a quantum-communication version of Kilian's succinct arguments for any language that has quantum PCPs with constant error and polylogarithmic locality. Plugging in the PCP theorem, this yields succinct arguments for NP under significantly weaker assumptions than required classically; moreover, if the quantum PCP conjecture holds, this extends to QMA. At the heart of our security proof is a new rewinding technique for extracting quantum information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing fermionic encodings for both Hamiltonian and hardware</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05652</link>
    <author>Riley W. Chien, Joel Klassen</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work we present a method for generating a fermionic encoding tailored to a set of target fermionic operators and to a target hardware connectivity. Our method uses brute force search, over the space of all encodings which map from Majorana monomials to Pauli operators, to find an encoding which optimizes a target cost function. In contrast to earlier works in this direction, our method searches over an extremely broad class of encodings which subsumes all known second quantized encodings that constitute algebra homomorphisms. In order to search over this class, we give a clear mathematical explanation of how precisely it is characterized, and how to translate this characterization into constructive search criteria. A benefit of searching over this class is that our method is able to supply fairly general optimality guarantees on solutions. A second benefit is that our method is, in principal, capable of finding more efficient representations of fermionic systems when the set of fermionic operators under consideration are faithfully represented by a smaller quotient algebra. Given the high algorithmic cost of performing the search, we adapt our method to handle translationally invariant systems that can be described by a small unit cell that is less costly. We demonstrate our method on various pairings of target fermionic operators and hardware connectivities. We additionally show how our method can be extended to find error detecting fermionic encodings in this class.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum optimization with Instantaneous Quantum Polynomial circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05526</link>
    <author>Sebastian Leontica, David Amaro</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We exploit the ability to embed 1-layer QAOA circuits into the larger class of parameterized IQP circuits to produce an improved variational quantum algorithm for solving combinatorial optimization problems. The 1-layer QAOA was recently shown to approximate low temperature pseudo-Boltzmann states, making it a suitable warm start for exploring the parameter space. We derive analytic expressions that allow us to explore the optimization landscape and find optimal parameters classically. The protocol is robust against barren plateaus and minimizes the necessary quantum resources compared to other traditional variational methods. We show numerically that the average overlap of the final state with the ground state scales like $\sim 2^{-0.31 N}$ with the number of qubits $N$, a polynomial improvement over 1-layer QAOA, for random Sherrington-Kickpatrick Hamiltonians of up to 29 qubits. Additionally, we show that performing variational imaginary time evolution on the manifold approximates low temperature pseudo-Boltzmann states, which may be used for sampling thermal distributions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Long-Range Free Fermions: Lieb-Robinson Bound, Clustering Properties, and Topological Phases</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05389</link>
    <author>Zongping Gong, Tommaso Guaita, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider free fermions living on lattices in arbitrary dimensions, where hopping amplitudes follow a power-law decay with respect to the distance. We focus on the regime where this power is larger than the spatial dimension (i.e., where the single particle energies are guaranteed to be bounded) for which we provide a comprehensive series of fundamental constraints on their equilibrium and nonequilibrium properties. First we derive a Lieb-Robinson bound which is optimal in the spatial tail. This bound then implies a clustering property with essentially the same power law for the Green's function, whenever its variable lies outside the energy spectrum. The widely believed (but yet unproven in this regime) clustering property for the ground-state correlation function follows as a corollary among other implications. Finally, we discuss the impact of these results on topological phases in long-range free-fermion systems: they justify the equivalence between Hamiltonian and state-based definitions and the extension of the short-range phase classification to systems with decay power larger than the spatial dimension. Additionally, we argue that all the short-range topological phases are unified whenever this power is allowed to be smaller.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>