<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Verifiable Quantum Advantage without Structure</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02063</link>
    <author>Takashi Yamakawa, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show the following hold, unconditionally unless otherwise stated, relative to a random oracle with probability 1: - There are NP search problems solvable by BQP machines but not BPP machines. - There exist functions that are one-way, and even collision resistant, against classical adversaries but are easily inverted quantumly. Similar separations hold for digital signatures and CPA-secure public key encryption (the latter requiring the assumption of a classically CPA-secure encryption scheme). Interestingly, the separation does not necessarily extend to the case of other cryptographic objects such as PRGs. - There are unconditional publicly verifiable proofs of quantumness with the minimal rounds of interaction: for uniform adversaries, the proofs are non-interactive, whereas for non-uniform adversaries the proofs are two message public coin. - Our results do not appear to contradict the Aaronson-Ambanis conjecture. Assuming this conjecture, there exist publicly verifiable certifiable randomness, again with the minimal rounds of interaction. By replacing the random oracle with a concrete cryptographic hash function such as SHA2, we obtain plausible Minicrypt instantiations of the above results. Previous analogous results all required substantial structure, either in terms of highly structured oracles and/or algebraic assumptions in Cryptomania and beyond.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental quantum adversarial learning with programmable superconducting qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01738</link>
    <author>Wenhui Ren, Weikang Li, Shibo Xu, Ke Wang, Wenjie Jiang, Feitong Jin, Xuhao Zhu, Jiachen Chen, Zixuan Song, Pengfei Zhang, Hang Dong, Xu Zhang, Jinfeng Deng, Yu Gao, Chuanyu Zhang, Yaozu Wu, Bing Zhang, Qiujiang Guo, Hekang Li, Zhen Wang, et al (4)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing promises to enhance machine learning and artificial intelligence. Different quantum algorithms have been proposed to improve a wide spectrum of machine learning tasks. Yet, recent theoretical works show that, similar to traditional classifiers based on deep classical neural networks, quantum classifiers would suffer from the vulnerability problem: adding tiny carefully-crafted perturbations to the legitimate original data samples would facilitate incorrect predictions at a notably high confidence level. This will pose serious problems for future quantum machine learning applications in safety and security-critical scenarios. Here, we report the first experimental demonstration of quantum adversarial learning with programmable superconducting qubits. We train quantum classifiers, which are built upon variational quantum circuits consisting of ten transmon qubits featuring average lifetimes of 150 $\mu$s, and average fidelities of simultaneous single- and two-qubit gates above 99.94% and 99.4% respectively, with both real-life images (e.g., medical magnetic resonance imaging scans) and quantum data. We demonstrate that these well-trained classifiers (with testing accuracy up to 99%) can be practically deceived by small adversarial perturbations, whereas an adversarial training process would significantly enhance their robustness to such perturbations. Our results reveal experimentally a crucial vulnerability aspect of quantum learning systems under adversarial scenarios and demonstrate an effective defense strategy against adversarial attacks, which provide a valuable guide for quantum artificial intelligence applications with both near-term and future quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Peptide conformational sampling using the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01821</link>
    <author>Sami Boulebnane, Xavier Lucas, Agnes Meyder, Stanislaw Adaszewski, Ashley Montanaro</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Protein folding -- the problem of predicting the spatial structure of a protein given its sequence of amino-acids -- has attracted considerable research effort in biochemistry in recent decades. In this work, we explore the potential of quantum computing to solve a simplified version of protein folding. More precisely, we numerically investigate the performance of a variational quantum algorithm, the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA), in sampling low-energy conformations of short peptides. We start by benchmarking the algorithm on an even simpler problem: sampling self-avoiding walks, which is a necessary condition for a valid protein conformation. Motivated by promising results achieved by QAOA on this problem, we then apply the algorithm to a more complete version of protein folding, including a simplified physical potential. In this case, based on numerical simulations on 20 qubits, we find less promising results: deep quantum circuits are required to achieve accurate results, and the performance of QAOA can be matched by random sampling up to a small overhead. Overall, these results cast serious doubt on the ability of QAOA to address the protein folding problem in the near term, even in an extremely simplified setting. We believe that the approach and conclusions presented in this work could offer valuable methodological insights on how to systematically evaluate variational quantum optimization algorithms on real-world problems beyond protein folding.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>How much classical information is carried by a quantum state? An approach inspired by Kolmogorov complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02370</link>
    <author>Doriano Brogioli</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In quantum mechanics, a state is an element of a Hilbert space whose dimension exponentially grows with the increase of the number of particles (or qubits, in quantum computing). The vague question "is this huge Hilbert space really there?" has been rigorously formalized inside the computational complexity theory, giving rise to interesting questions regarding quantum complexity classes, yet to receive an answer. Here, I give an alternative and quite direct definition of the (classical) information content of a quantum state, taking inspiration from the Kolmogorov complexity. I show that, for some relevant quantum circuits, the information content, evaluated according to my definition, is polynomial in the number of qubits. Finally, I discuss the conjecture that this property holds for any polynomial-sized quantum circuit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generators and relations for 2-qubit Clifford+T operators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02217</link>
    <author>Xiaoning Bian, Peter Selinger</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a presentation by generators and relations of the group of Clifford+T operators on two qubits. The proof relies on an application of the Reidemeister-Schreier theorem to an earlier result of Greylyn, and has been formally verified in the proof assistant Agda.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>