<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Challenges in Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15844</link>
    <author>Daniel Gottesman</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I will give an overview of what I see as some of the most important future directions in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation. In particular, I will give a brief summary of the major problems that need to be solved in fault tolerance based on low-density parity check codes and in hardware-specific fault tolerance. I will then conclude with a discussion of a possible new paradigm for designing fault-tolerant protocols based on a space-time picture of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>CNOT circuits need little help to implement arbitrary Hadamard-free Clifford transformations they generate</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16195</link>
    <author>Dmitri Maslov, Willers Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A Hadamard-free Clifford transformation is a circuit composed of quantum Phase (P), CZ, and CNOT gates. It is known that such a circuit can be written as a three-stage computation, -P-CZ-CNOT-, where each stage consists only of gates of the specified type. In this paper, we focus on the minimization of circuit depth by entangling gates, corresponding to the important time-to-solution metric and the reduction of noise due to decoherence. We consider two popular connectivity maps: Linear Nearest Neighbor (LNN) and all-to-all. First, we show that a Hadamard-free Clifford operation can be implemented over LNN in depth $5n$, i.e., in the same depth as the -CNOT- stage alone. This implies the ability to implement arbitrary Clifford transformation over LNN in depth no more than $7n{+}2$, improving the best previous upper bound of $9n$. Second, we report heuristic evidence that on average a random uniformly distributed Hadamard-free Clifford transformation over $n{>}6$ qubits can be implemented with only a tiny additive constant overhead over all-to-all connected architecture compared to the best-known depth-optimized implementation of the -CNOT- stage alone. This suggests the reduction of the depth of Clifford circuits from $2n\,{+}\,O(\log^2(n))$ to $1.5n\,{+}\,O(\log^2(n))$ over unrestricted architectures.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The $2T$-qutrit, a two-mode bosonic qutrit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16188</link>
    <author>Aurélie Denys, Anthony Leverrier</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Building on the observation that bosonic cat codes live in the span of coherent states indexed by a finite subgroup of the complex numbers, we consider a two-mode bosonic code where the coherent states now form a finite subgroup of the quaternions. We focus on the binary tetrahedral group, denoted $2T$, which admits 24 elements forming the vertices of the 24-cell, a regular four-dimensional polytope, and define a bosonic qutrit that appears to be quite robust in the regime of low loss. We initiate a study of the properties of this qutrit and identify stabilisers as well as logical operators for this bosonic code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Digital Quantum Simulation of the Spin-Boson Model under Open System Dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15922</link>
    <author>Andreas Burger, Leong Chuan Kwek, Dario Poletti</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Digital quantum computers have the potential to simulate complex quantum systems. The spin-boson model is one of such systems, used in disparate physical domains. Importantly, in a number of setups, the spin-boson model is open, i.e. the system is in contact with an external environment which can, for instance, cause the decay of the spin state. Here we study how to simulate such open quantum dynamics in a digital quantum computer, for which we use one of IBM's hardware. We consider in particular how accurate different implementations of the evolution result as a function of the level of noise in the hardware and of the parameters of the open dynamics. For the regimes studied, we show that the key aspect is to simulate the unitary portion of the dynamics, while the dissipative part can lead to a more noise-resistant simulation. We consider both a single spin coupled to a harmonic oscillator, and also two spins coupled to the oscillator. In the latter case, we show that it is possible to simulate the emergence of correlations between the spins via the oscillator.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Real quantum operations and state transformations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15820</link>
    <author>Tulja Varun Kondra, Chandan Datta, Alexander Streltsov</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Resource theory of imaginarity provides a useful framework to understand the role of complex numbers, which are essential in the formulation of quantum mechanics, in a mathematically rigorous way. In this work, we study the properties of "real" (quantum) operations and provide necessary and sufficient conditions for state transformations under real operations. We also study the properties of real operations in spatially separated bipartite settings and show the existence of "real entanglement" monotones which are independent to the "LOCC monotones". This shows that entanglement in real quantum theory is fundamentally different to the entanglement in complex quantum theory. Furthermore, when starting from pure initial states, we completely solve the problem of single copy state transformation, finding an analytical expression for the optimal fidelity of transformation, for a given probability of transformation and vice versa. Moreover, for state transformations involving arbitrary initial states and pure final states, we provide a semidefinite program to compute the optimal achievable fidelity, for a given probability of transformation.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>