<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Exponentially tighter bounds on limitations of quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11505</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Daniel Stilck França, Sumeet Khatri, Johannes Jakob Meyer, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation has been proposed as a means to combat unavoidable errors in near-term quantum computing by classically post-processing outcomes of multiple quantum circuits. It does so in a fashion that requires no or few additional quantum resources, in contrast to fault-tolerant schemes that come along with heavy overheads. Error mitigation leads to noise reduction in small systems. In this work, however, we identify strong limitations to the degree to which quantum noise can be effectively `undone' for larger system sizes. We start out by presenting a formal framework that rigorously encapsulates large classes of meaningful and practically applied schemes for quantum error mitigation, including virtual distillation, Clifford data regression, zero-noise extrapolation and probabilistic error cancellation. With the framework in place, our technical contribution is to construct families of random circuits that are highly sensitive to noise, in the sense that even at log log(n) depth, a whisker beyond constant, quantum noise is seen to super-exponentially rapidly scramble their output into the maximally-mixed state. Our results exponentially tighten known arguments for error mitigation, but they go beyond that: Our arguments can be applied to kernel estimation or to compute the depth at which barren plateaus emerge, implying that the scrambling kicks in at exponentially smaller depths than previously thought. Our results also say that a noisy device must be sampled exponentially many times to estimate expectation values. There are classical algorithms that exhibit the same scaling in complexity. While improvements in quantum hardware will push noise levels down, if error mitigation is used, ultimately this can only lead to an exponential time quantum algorithm with a better exponent, putting up a strong obstruction to the hope for exponential quantum speedups in this setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical simulation of short-time quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11490</link>
    <author>Dominik S. Wild, Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Locality is a key simplifying feature of many physical systems. Cluster expansion techniques provide one particular way of exploiting it. They have historically appeared in statistical physics to prove the uniqueness of Gibbs states and the decay of correlations at high temperature, among many other results. Here, we apply these techniques to quantum many-body systems evolving under local Hamiltonians. We consider the evolution of both local observables and non-local quantities such as the Loschmidt echo. We show that for a product initial state, the cluster expansion enables efficient classical computation of the dynamics up to a fixed evolution time, independent of the system size. The computational cost scales polynomially with the system size and the inverse of the approximation error. In the case of local observables, we can extend the evolution time to any constant value using analytic continuation. In more than one dimension, the resulting algorithm has a better dependence on the approximation error than algorithms based on the Lieb-Robinson bound. Our algorithms rely on the convergence of the cluster expansion, which also has important physical consequences. In particular, we establish a novel quantum speed limit, a bound on dynamical phase transitions, and a concentration bound for product states evolved for short times.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Gauge Networks: A New Kind of Tensor Network</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.12151</link>
    <author>Kevin Slagle</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Although tensor networks are powerful tools for simulating low-dimensional quantum physics, tensor network algorithms are very computationally costly in higher spatial dimensions. We introduce quantum gauge networks: a different kind of tensor network ansatz for which the computation cost of simulations does not explicitly increase for larger spatial dimensions. We take inspiration from the gauge picture of quantum dynamics, which consists of a local wavefunction for each patch of space, with neighboring patches related by unitary connections. A quantum gauge network (QGN) has a similar structure, except the Hilbert space dimensions of the local wavefunctions and connections are truncated. We describe how a QGN can be obtained from a generic wavefunction or matrix product state (MPS). All $2k$-point correlation functions of any wavefunction for $M$ many operators can be encoded exactly by a QGN with bond dimension $O(M^k)$. In comparison, for just $k=1$, an exponentially larger bond dimension of $2^{M/6}$ is generically required for an MPS of qubits. We provide a simple QGN algorithm for approximate simulations of quantum dynamics in any spatial dimension. The approximate dynamics can achieve exact energy conservation for time-independent Hamiltonians, and spatial symmetries can also be maintained exactly. We benchmark the algorithm by simulating the quantum quench of fermionic Hamiltonians in up to three spatial dimensions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Solving quantum dynamics with a Lie algebra decoupling method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11894</link>
    <author>Sofia Qvarfort, Igor Pikovski</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>At the heart of quantum technology development is the control of quantum systems at the level of individual quanta. Mathematically, this is realised through the study of Hamiltonians and the use of methods to solve the dynamics of quantum systems in various regimes. Here, we present a pedagogical introduction to solving the dynamics of quantum systems by the use of a Lie algebra decoupling theorem. As background, we include an overview of Lie groups and Lie algebras aimed at a general physicist audience. We then prove the theorem and apply it to three well-known examples of linear and quadratic Hamiltonian that frequently appear in quantum optics and related fields. The result is a set of differential equations that describe the most Gaussian dynamics for all linear and quadratic single-mode Hamiltonian with generic time-dependent interaction terms. We also discuss the use of the decoupling theorem beyond quadratic Hamiltonians and for solving open-system dynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Efficient Quantum Decoder for Prime-Power Fields</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11552</link>
    <author>Lior Eldar</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a version of the nearest-codeword problem on finite fields $\mathbb{F}_q$ using the Manhattan distance, an analog of the Hamming metric for non-binary alphabets. Similarly to other lattice related problems, this problem is NP-hard even up to constant factor approximation. We show, however, that for $q = p^m$ where $p$ is small relative to the code block-size $n$, there is a quantum algorithm that solves the problem in time ${\rm poly}(n)$, for approximation factor $1/n$, for any $p$. On the other hand, to the best of our knowledge, classical algorithms can efficiently solve the problem only for much smaller inverse polynomial factors. Hence, the decoder provides an exponential improvement over classical algorithms, and places limitations on the cryptographic security of large-alphabet extensions of code-based cryptosystems like Classic McEliece.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>