<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Learning quantum graph states with product measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06432</link>
    <author>Yingkai Ouyang, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>May 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of learning $N$ identical copies of an unknown $n$-qubit quantum graph state with product measurements. These graph states have corresponding graphs where every vertex has exactly $d$ neighboring vertices. Here, we detail an explicit algorithm that uses product measurements on multiple identical copies of such graph states to learn them. When $n \gg d$ and $N = O(d \log(1/\epsilon) + d^2 \log n ),$ this algorithm correctly learns the graph state with probability at least $1- \epsilon$. From channel coding theory, we find that for arbitrary joint measurements on graph states, any learning algorithm achieving this accuracy requires at least $\Omega(\log (1/\epsilon) + d \log n)$ copies when $d=o(\sqrt n)$. We also supply bounds on $N$ when every graph state encounters identical and independent depolarizing errors on each qubit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Barren plateaus from learning scramblers with local cost functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06679</link>
    <author>Roy J. Garcia, Chen Zhao, Kaifeng Bu, Arthur Jaffe</author>
    <pubDate>May 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The existence of barren plateaus has recently revealed new training challenges in quantum machine learning (QML). Uncovering the mechanisms behind barren plateaus is essential in understanding the scope of problems that QML can efficiently tackle. Barren plateaus have recently been shown to exist when learning global properties of random unitaries. Establishing whether local cost functions can circumvent these barren plateaus is pertinent if we hope to apply QML to quantum many-body systems. We prove a no-go theorem showing that local cost functions encounter barren plateaus in learning random unitary properties.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The QAOA with Slow Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06845</link>
    <author>Anthony Polloreno, Graeme Smith</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) was originally developed to solve combinatorial optimization problems, but has become a standard for assessing the performance of quantum computers. Fully descriptive benchmarking techniques are often prohibitively expensive for large numbers of qubits ($n \gtrsim 10$), so the QAOA often serves in practice as a computational benchmark. The QAOA involves a classical optimization subroutine that attempts to find optimal parameters for a quantum subroutine. Unfortunately, many optimizers used for the QAOA require many shots ($N \gtrsim 1000$) per point in parameter space to get a reliable estimate of the energy being minimized. However, some experimental quantum computing platforms such as neutral atom quantum computers have slow repetition rates, placing unique requirements on the classical optimization subroutine used in the QAOA in these systems. In this paper we investigate the performance of a gradient free classical optimizer for the QAOA - dual annealing - and demonstrate that optimization is possible even with $N=1$ and $n=16$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Black Holes Decohere Quantum Superpositions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06279</link>
    <author>Daine L. Danielson, Gautam Satishchandran, Robert M. Wald</author>
    <pubDate>May 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that if a massive body is put in a quantum superposition of spatially separated states, the mere presence of a black hole in the vicinity of the body will eventually destroy the coherence of the superposition. This occurs because, in effect, the gravitational field of the body radiates soft gravitons into the black hole, allowing the black hole to acquire "which path" information about the superposition. A similar effect occurs for quantum superpositions of electrically charged bodies. We provide estimates of the decoherence time for such quantum superpositions. We believe that the fact that a black hole will eventually decohere any quantum superposition may be of fundamental significance for our understanding of the nature of black holes in a quantum theory of gravity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement distillation towards minimal bond cut surface in tensor networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06633</link>
    <author>Takato Mori, Hidetaka Manabe, Hiroaki Matsueda</author>
    <pubDate>May 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose that a minimal bond cut surface is characterized by entanglement distillation in tensor networks. Our proposal is not only consistent with the holographic models of perfect or tree tensor networks, but also can be applied for several different classes of tensor networks including matrix product states and multi-scale entanglement renormalization ansatz. We confirmed our proposal by a numerical simulation based on the random tensor network. The result sheds new light on a deeper understanding of the Ryu-Takayanagi formula for entanglement entropy in holography.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>