<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Real-time quantum error correction beyond break-even</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09116</link>
    <author>V. V. Sivak, A. Eickbusch, B. Royer, S. Singh, I. Tsioutsios, S. Ganjam, A. Miano, B. L. Brock, A. Z. Ding, L. Frunzio, S. M. Girvin, R. J. Schoelkopf, M. H. Devoret</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ambition of harnessing the quantum for computation is at odds with the fundamental phenomenon of decoherence. The purpose of quantum error correction (QEC) is to counteract the natural tendency of a complex system to decohere. This cooperative process, which requires participation of multiple quantum and classical components, creates a special type of dissipation that removes the entropy caused by the errors faster than the rate at which these errors corrupt the stored quantum information. Previous experimental attempts to engineer such a process faced an excessive generation of errors that overwhelmed the error-correcting capability of the process itself. Whether it is practically possible to utilize QEC for extending quantum coherence thus remains an open question. We answer it by demonstrating a fully stabilized and error-corrected logical qubit whose quantum coherence is significantly longer than that of all the imperfect quantum components involved in the QEC process, beating the best of them with a coherence gain of $G = 2.27 \pm 0.07$. We achieve this performance by combining innovations in several domains including the fabrication of superconducting quantum circuits and model-free reinforcement learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive surface code for quantum error correction in the presence of temporary or permanent defects</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08468</link>
    <author>Adam Siegel, Armands Strikis, Thomas Flatters, Simon Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Whether it is at the fabrication stage or during the course of the quantum computation, e.g. because of high-energy events like cosmic rays, the qubits constituting an error correcting code may be rendered inoperable. Such defects may correspond to individual qubits or to clusters and could potentially disrupt the code sufficiently to generate logical errors. In this paper, we explore a novel adaptive approach for surface code quantum error correction on a defective lattice. We show that combining an appropriate defect detection algorithm and a quarantine of the identified zone allows one to preserve the advantage of quantum error correction at finite code sizes, at the cost of a qubit overhead that scales with the size of the defect. Our numerics indicate that the code's threshold need not be significantly affected; for example, for a certain scenario where small defects repeatedly arise in each logical qubit, the noise threshold is $2.7\%$ (versus the defect-free case of $2.9\%$). These results pave the way to the experimental implementation of large-scale quantum computers where defects will be inevitable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error bounds for Lie Group representations in quantum mechanics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08582</link>
    <author>Lauritz van Luijk, Niklas Galke, Alexander Hahn, Daniel Burgarth</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide state-dependent error bounds for strongly continuous unitary representations of connected Lie groups. That is, we bound the difference of two unitaries applied to a state in terms of the energy with respect to a reference Hamiltonian associated to the representation and a left-invariant metric distance on the group. Our method works for any connected Lie group and the metric is independent of the chosen representation. The approach also applies to projective representations and allows us to provide bounds on the energy constrained diamond norm distance of any suitably continuous channel representation of the group.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise-robust ground state energy estimates from deep quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08780</link>
    <author>Harish J. Vallury, Michael A. Jones, Gregory A. L. White, Floyd M. Creevey, Charles D. Hill, Lloyd C. L. Hollenberg</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the lead up to fault tolerance, the utility of quantum computing will be determined by how adequately the effects of noise can be circumvented in quantum algorithms. Hybrid quantum-classical algorithms such as the variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) have been designed for the short-term regime. However, as problems scale, VQE results are generally scrambled by noise on present-day hardware. While error mitigation techniques alleviate these issues to some extent, there is a pressing need to develop algorithmic approaches with higher robustness to noise. Here, we explore the robustness properties of the recently introduced quantum computed moments (QCM) approach to ground state energy problems, and show through an analytic example how the underlying energy estimate explicitly filters out incoherent noise. Motivated by this observation, we implement QCM for a model of quantum magnetism on IBM Quantum hardware to examine the noise-filtering effect with increasing circuit depth. We find that QCM maintains a remarkably high degree of error robustness where VQE completely fails. On instances of the quantum magnetism model up to 20 qubits for ultra-deep trial state circuits of up to ~500 CNOTs, QCM is still able to extract accurate energy estimates. The observation is bolstered by an extensive set of experimental results. To match this accuracy, VQE would need hardware improvement by some 2 orders of magnitude on error rates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Large $N$ Matrix Quantum Mechanics as a Quantum Memory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08448</link>
    <author>ChunJun Cao, Gong Cheng, Brian Swingle</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we explore the possibility of building a quantum memory that is robust to thermal noise using large $N$ matrix quantum mechanics models. First, we investigate the gauged $SU(N)$ matrix harmonic oscillator and different ways to encode quantum information in it. By calculating the mutual information between the system and a reference which purifies the encoded information, we identify a transition temperature, $T_c$, below which the encoded quantum information is protected from thermal noise for a memory time scaling as $N^2$. Conversely, for temperatures higher than $T_c$, the information is quickly destroyed by thermal noise. Second, we relax the requirement of gauge invariance and study a matrix harmonic oscillator model with only global symmetry. Finally, we further relax even the symmetry requirement and propose a model that consists of a large number $N^2$ of qubits, with interactions derived from an approximate $SU(N)$ symmetry. In both ungauged models, we find that the effects of gauging can be mimicked using an energy penalty to give a similar result for the memory time. The final qubit model also has the potential to be realized in the laboratory.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>