<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Fold-Transversal Clifford Gates for Quantum Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06647</link>
    <author>Nikolas P. Breuckmann, Simon Burton</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We generalize the concept of folding from surface codes to CSS codes by considering certain dualities within them. In particular, this gives a general method to implement logical operations in suitable LDPC quantum codes using transversal gates and qubit permutations only. To demonstrate our approach, we specifically consider a [[30, 8, 3]] hyperbolic quantum code called Bring's code. Further, we show that by restricting the logical subspace of Bring's code to four qubits, we can obtain the full Clifford group on that subspace.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Comparison of 2D topological codes and their decoding performances</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06612</link>
    <author>Kao-Yueh Kuo, Ching-Yi Lai</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Topological quantum codes are favored because they allow qubit layouts that are suitable for practical implementation. An $N$-qubit topological code can be decoded by minimum-weight perfect matching (MWPM) with complexity $O(\text{poly}(N))$ if it is of CSS-type. Recently it is shown that various quantum codes, including non-CSS codes, can be decoded by an adapted belief propagation with memory effects (denoted MBP) with complexity almost linear in $N$. In this paper, we show that various two-dimensional topological codes, CSS or non-CSS, regardless of the layout, can be decoded by MBP, including color codes and twisted XZZX codes. We will comprehensively compare these codes in terms of code efficiency and decoding performance, assuming perfect error syndromes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An elegant proof of self-testing for multipartite Bell inequalities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06908</link>
    <author>Ekta Panwar, Palash Pandya, Marcin Wieśniak</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The predictions of quantum theory are incompatible with local-causal explanations. This phenomenon is called Bell non-locality and is witnessed by violation of Bell-inequalities. The maximal violation of certain Bell-inequalities can only be attained in an essentially unique manner. This feature is referred to as self-testing and constitutes the most accurate form of certification of quantum devices. While self-testing in bipartite Bell scenarios has been thoroughly studied, self-testing in the more complex multipartite Bell scenarios remains largely unexplored. This work presents a simple and broadly applicable self-testing argument for N-partite correlation Bell inequalities with two binary outcome observables per party. Our proof technique forms a generalization of the Mayer-Yao formulation and is not restricted to linear Bell-inequalities, unlike the usual sum of squares method. To showcase the versatility of our proof technique, we obtain self-testing statements for N party Mermin-Ardehali-Belinskii-Klyshko (MABK) and Werner-Wolf-Weinfurter-Żukowski-Brukner (WWWŻB) family of linear Bell inequalities, and Uffink's family of N party quadratic Bell-inequalities.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matrix quantum groups as matrix product operator representations of Lie groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06937</link>
    <author>Romain Couvreur, Laurens Lootens, Frank Verstraete</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We demonstrate that the matrix quantum group $SL_q(2)$ gives rise to nontrivial matrix product operator representations of the Lie group $SL(2)$, providing an explicit characterization of the nontrivial global $SU(2)$ symmetry of the XXZ model with periodic boundary conditions. The matrix product operators are non-injective and their set is closed under multiplication. This allows to calculate the fusion tensors acting on the virtual or quantum degrees of freedom and to obtain the recoupling coefficients, which satisfy a type of pentagon relation. We argue that the combination of this data with the well known $q$-deformed Clebsch-Gordan coefficients and 6j-symbols is consistent with a description of this quantum group in terms of bimodule categories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Grid-based methods for chemistry modelling on a quantum computer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05864</link>
    <author>Hans Hon Sang Chan, Richard Meister, Tyson Jones, David P. Tew, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We explore grid-based techniques for simulating multi-electron dynamics using a quantum computer, an approach sometimes called first quantized chemistry. Using a split-operator Fourier transform (SO-FT) method on exactly-emulated quantum computers with up to 36 qubits, we model the dynamics of 2D and 3D atoms with single and paired particles interacting via the Coulomb potential. The grid-based method enables direct visualisation of quantum dynamics, including the behaviour of bound states, electron ionization by an applied electric field, and electron-electron scattering. We exploit ancilla-qubit measurements for iterative phase estimation, state preparation and for implementing complex (absorbing) potentials. Ancilla-based methods for obtaining observables such as binding energies are found to be far more efficient and robust than direct sampling. We also introduce an augmented split-operator (ASO) method where the usual kinetic and potential operators are supplemented by a core-stabilisation operator that dramatically improves wavepacket propagation near a Coulomb singularity. Overall, the grid-based method scales well in terms of the quantum processor's size and execution time; we extrapolate the resource requirements for accurate modelling of classically-intractable systems from our numerical results, and we describe suitable quantum architectures. We conclude by noting that the approach should be successful in far broader settings, from high energy physics to financial portfolio modelling.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>