<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A single $T$-gate makes distribution learning hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03140</link>
    <author>Marcel Hinsche, Marios Ioannou, Alexander Nietner, Jonas Haferkamp, Yihui Quek, Dominik Hangleiter, Jean-Pierre Seifert, Jens Eisert, Ryan Sweke</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The task of learning a probability distribution from samples is ubiquitous across the natural sciences. The output distributions of local quantum circuits form a particularly interesting class of distributions, of key importance both to quantum advantage proposals and a variety of quantum machine learning algorithms. In this work, we provide an extensive characterization of the learnability of the output distributions of local quantum circuits. Our first result yields insight into the relationship between the efficient learnability and the efficient simulatability of these distributions. Specifically, we prove that the density modelling problem associated with Clifford circuits can be efficiently solved, while for depth $d=n^{\Omega(1)}$ circuits the injection of a single $T$-gate into the circuit renders this problem hard. This result shows that efficient simulatability does not imply efficient learnability. Our second set of results provides insight into the potential and limitations of quantum generative modelling algorithms. We first show that the generative modelling problem associated with depth $d=n^{\Omega(1)}$ local quantum circuits is hard for any learning algorithm, classical or quantum. As a consequence, one cannot use a quantum algorithm to gain a practical advantage for this task. We then show that, for a wide variety of the most practically relevant learning algorithms -- including hybrid-quantum classical algorithms -- even the generative modelling problem associated with depth $d=\omega(\log(n))$ Clifford circuits is hard. This result places limitations on the applicability of near-term hybrid quantum-classical generative modelling algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The classical cost of transmitting a qubit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02244</link>
    <author>Martin J. Renner, Armin Tavakoli, Marco Túlio Quintino</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider general prepare-and-measure scenarios in which Alice can transmit qubit states to Bob, who can perform general measurements in the form of positive operator-valued measures (POVMs). We show that the statistics obtained in any such quantum protocol can be simulated by the purely classical means of shared randomness and two bits of communication. Furthermore, we prove that two bits of communication is the minimal cost of a perfect classical simulation. In addition, we apply our methods to Bell scenarios, which extends the well-known Toner and Bacon protocol. In particular, two bits of communication are enough to simulate all quantum correlations associated to arbitrary local POVMs applied to any entangled two-qubit state.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the design and analysis of near-term quantum network protocols using Markov decision processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03403</link>
    <author>Sumeet Khatri</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum internet is one of the frontiers of quantum information science research. It will revolutionize the way we communicate and do other tasks, and it will allow for tasks that are not possible using the current, classical internet. The backbone of a quantum internet is entanglement distributed globally in order to allow for such novel applications to be performed over long distances. Experimental progress is currently being made to realize quantum networks on a small scale, but much theoretical work is still needed in order to understand how best to distribute entanglement, especially with the limitations of near-term quantum technologies taken into account. This work provides an initial step towards this goal. In this work, we lay out a theory of near-term quantum networks based on Markov decision processes (MDPs), and we show that MDPs provide a precise and systematic mathematical framework to model protocols for near-term quantum networks that is agnostic to the specific implementation platform. We start by simplifying the MDP for elementary links introduced in prior work, and by providing new results on policies for elementary links in the steady-state (infinite-time) limit. In particular, we show that the well-known memory-cutoff policy is optimal in the steady-state limit. Then we show how the elementary link MDP can be used to analyze a quantum network protocol in which we wait for all elementary links to be active before creating end-to-end links. We then provide an extension of the MDP formalism to two elementary links, which is useful for analyzing more sophisticated quantum network protocols. Here, as new results, we derive linear programming relaxations that allow us to obtain optimal steady-state policies with respect to the expected fidelity and waiting time of the end-to-end link.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Positive maps and entanglement in real Hilbert spaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02510</link>
    <author>Giulio Chiribella, Kenneth R. Davidson, Vern I. Paulsen, Mizanur Rahaman</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The theory of positive maps plays a central role in operator algebras and functional analysis, and has countless applications in quantum information science. The theory was originally developed for operators acting on complex Hilbert spaces, and little is known about its variant on real Hilbert spaces. In this article we study positive maps acting on a full matrix algebra over the reals, pointing out a number of fundamental differences with the complex case and discussing their implications in quantum information. We provide a necessary and sufficient condition for a real map to admit a positive complexification, and connect the existence of positive maps with non-positive complexification with the existence of mixed states that are entangled in real Hilbert space quantum mechanics, but separable in the complex version, providing explicit examples both for the maps and for the states. Finally, we discuss entanglement breaking and PPT maps, and we show that a straightforward real version of the PPT-squared conjecture is false even in dimension 2. Nevertheless, we show that the original PPT-squared conjecture implies a different conjecture for real maps, in which the PPT property is replaced by a stronger property of invariance under partial transposition (IPT). When the IPT property is assumed, we prove an asymptotic version of the conjecture.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Geometric structure of thermal cones</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02237</link>
    <author>A. de Oliveira Junior, Jakub Czartowski, Karol Życzkowski, Kamil Korzekwa</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The second law of thermodynamics imposes a fundamental asymmetry in the flow of events. The so-called thermodynamic arrow of time introduces an ordering that divides the system's state space into past, future and incomparable regions. In this work, we analyse the structure of the resulting thermal cones, i.e., sets of states that a given state can thermodynamically evolve to (the future thermal cone) or evolve from (the past thermal cone). Specifically, for a $d$-dimensional classical state of a system interacting with a heat bath, we find explicit construction of the past thermal cone and the incomparable region. Moreover, we provide a detailed analysis of their behaviour based on newly introduced thermodynamic monotones given by the volumes of thermal cones. Finally, we point out that our results also apply to other majorisation-based resource theories (such as that of entanglement and coherence), since the partial ordering describing allowed state transformations is then the opposite of the thermodynamic order in the infinite temperature limit.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>