<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>QUSUM: quickest quantum change-point detection</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03265</link>
    <author>Marco Fanizza, Christoph Hirche, John Calsamiglia</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Online detection of a change in a sequence of events is a fundamental and practically relevant task. In this work we consider the quantum version of the problem, generalizing the well known (classical) CUSUM algorithm to detect a quantum change point. Our algorithm exploits joint measurements to amplify the trade-off between detection delay and false detections, which in the case of a quantum change point is asymptotically characterized by the quantum relative entropy. Furthermore we also show that the relative entropy is indeed asymptotically optimal under arbitrary, potentially adaptive, measurement strategies, hence providing the ultimate bound for the quickest quantum change-point detection. Finally, we discuss online change point detection in quantum channels.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Indefinite causal order is not always a resource for thermodynamic processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03205</link>
    <author>Matheus Capela, Harshit Verma, Fabio Costa, Lucas Chibebe Céleri</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Indefinite causal order is a key feature involved in the study of quantum higher order transformations. Recently, intense research has been focused on possible advantages related to the lack of definite causal order of quantum processes. Quite often the quantum switch is claimed to provide advantages in information-theoretic and thermodynamic tasks. We address here the question whether indefinite causal order is a resource for quantum thermodynamics. Inspired by previous results in the literature taking free energy and ergotropy as the figures of merit, we propose a framework for properly comparing the thermodynamic value of processes by comparing higher order transformations of the same type, and show that for the tasks considered here indefinite causal order is not necessary for thermodynamic advantages. More specifically, we show that there is a non-Markovian process, a causally ordered higher-order transformation, outperforming the results obtained for the quantum switch. We also discuss a possible way to study the advantages that may arise from indefinite causal order in a general scenario.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Beyond the Worst Case: Structured Convergence of High Dimensional Random Walks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03241</link>
    <author>Roy Gotlib, Tali Kaufman</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One of the most important properties of high dimensional expanders is that high dimensional random walks converge rapidly. This property has proven to be extremely useful in variety of fields in the theory of computer science from agreement testing to sampling, coding theory and more. In this paper we improve upon the result of Kaufman-Oppenheim and Alev-Lau regarding the convergence of random walks by presenting a structured version of their result. While previous works examined the expansion in the viewpoint of the worst possible eigenvalue, in this work we relate the expansion of a function to the entire spectrum of the random walk operator using the structure of the function. In some cases this finer result can be much better than the worst case. In order to prove our structured version of the convergence of random walks, we present a general framework that allows us to relate the convergence of random walks to the trickling down theorem for the first time. Concretely, we show that both the state of the art results for convergence of random walks and the tricking down theorem can be derived using the same argument that we present here. This new, unified, way of looking at the convergence of high dimensional random walks and the trickling down theorem gives us a new understanding of pseudorandom functions that allows us to consider pseudorandom functions in one-sided local spectral expanders for the first time.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise-resilient phase estimation with randomized compiling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04100</link>
    <author>Yanwu Gu, Yunheng Ma, Nicolo Forcellini, Dong E. Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop an error mitigation method for the control-free phase estimation. We prove a theorem that under the first-order correction, the noise channels with only Hermitian Kraus operators do not change the phases of a unitary operator, and therefore, the benign types of noise for phase estimation are identified. By using the randomized compiling protocol, we can convert the generic noise in the phase estimation circuits into stochastic Pauli noise, which satisfies the condition of our theorem. Thus we achieve a noise-resilient phase estimation without any quantum resource overhead. The simulated experiments show that our method can significantly reduce the estimation error of the phases by up to two orders of magnitude. Our method paves the way for the utilization of quantum phase estimation before the advent of fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multi-Axis Control of a Qubit in the Presence of Unknown Non-Markovian Quantum Noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03058</link>
    <author>Akram Youssry, Hendra I. Nurdin</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we consider the problem of open-loop control of a qubit that is coupled to an unknown fully quantum non-Markovian noise (either bosonic or fermionic). A graybox model that is empirically obtained from measurement data is employed to approximately represent the unknown quantum noise. The estimated model is then used to calculate the open-loop control pulses under constraints on the pulse amplitude and timing. For the control pulse optimization, we explore the use of gradient descent and genetic optimization methods. We consider the effect of finite sampling on estimating expectation values of observables and show results for single- and multi-axis control of a qubit.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>