<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Biological error correction codes generate fault-tolerant neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12887</link>
    <author>Alexander Zlokapa, Andrew K. Tan, John M. Martyn, Max Tegmark, Isaac L. Chuang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It has been an open question in deep learning if fault-tolerant computation is possible: can arbitrarily reliable computation be achieved using only unreliable neurons? In the mammalian cortex, analog error correction codes known as grid codes have been observed to protect states against neural spiking noise, but their role in information processing is unclear. Here, we use these biological codes to show that a universal fault-tolerant neural network can be achieved if the faultiness of each neuron lies below a sharp threshold, which we find coincides in order of magnitude with noise observed in biological neurons. The discovery of a sharp phase transition from faulty to fault-tolerant neural computation opens a path towards understanding noisy analog systems in artificial intelligence and neuroscience.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>One-dimensional SPT phases protected by frieze symmetries</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12880</link>
    <author>Bram Vancraeynest-De Cuiper, Nicolas Dewolf, Jutho Haegeman, Frank Verstraete</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We undertake a systematic study of symmetry-protected topological gapped phases of quantum spin chains in the presence of the quasi-one-dimensional frieze space groups. Here, the spatial symmetries of the one-dimensional lattice are considered together with an additional 'vertical reflection', which we take to be an on-site $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry. We identify seventeen distinct non-trivial phases and define canonical forms. If time-reversal is combined with a shift over one site, then no new topological phases arise. We furthermore construct explicit renormalization-group fixed point wavefunctions for symmetry-protected topological phases with global on-site symmetries, and demonstrate how group cohomology can be computed using the Smith normal form</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning Dynamic Mechanisms in Unknown Environments: A Reinforcement Learning Approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12797</link>
    <author>Boxiang Lyu, Qinglin Meng, Shuang Qiu, Zhaoran Wang, Zhuoran Yang, Michael I. Jordan</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Dynamic mechanism design studies how mechanism designers should allocate resources among agents in a time-varying environment. We consider the problem where the agents interact with the mechanism designer according to an unknown Markov Decision Process (MDP), where agent rewards and the mechanism designer's state evolve according to an episodic MDP with unknown reward functions and transition kernels. We focus on the online setting with linear function approximation and attempt to recover the dynamic Vickrey-Clarke-Grove (VCG) mechanism over multiple rounds of interaction. A key contribution of our work is incorporating reward-free online Reinforcement Learning (RL) to aid exploration over a rich policy space to estimate prices in the dynamic VCG mechanism. We show that the regret of our proposed method is upper bounded by $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(T^{2/3})$ and further devise a lower bound to show that our algorithm is efficient, incurring the same $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(T^{2 / 3})$ regret as the lower bound, where $T$ is the total number of rounds. Our work establishes the regret guarantee for online RL in solving dynamic mechanism design problems without prior knowledge of the underlying model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Towards Optimal Lower Bounds for k-median and k-means Coresets</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12793</link>
    <author>Vincent Cohen-Addad, Kasper Green Larsen, David Saulpic, Chris Schwiegelshohn</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a set of points in a metric space, the $(k,z)$-clustering problem consists of finding a set of $k$ points called centers, such that the sum of distances raised to the power of $z$ of every data point to its closest center is minimized. Special cases include the famous k-median problem ($z = 1$) and k-means problem ($z = 2$). The $k$-median and $k$-means problems are at the heart of modern data analysis and massive data applications have given raise to the notion of coreset: a small (weighted) subset of the input point set preserving the cost of any solution to the problem up to a multiplicative $(1 \pm \varepsilon)$ factor, hence reducing from large to small scale the input to the problem. In this paper, we present improved lower bounds for coresets in various metric spaces. In finite metrics consisting of $n$ points and doubling metrics with doubling constant $D$, we show that any coreset for $(k,z)$ clustering must consist of at least $\Omega(k \varepsilon^{-2} \log n)$ and $\Omega(k \varepsilon^{-2} D)$ points, respectively. Both bounds match previous upper bounds up to polylog factors. In Euclidean spaces, we show that any coreset for $(k,z)$ clustering must consists of at least $\Omega(k\varepsilon^{-2})$ points. We complement these lower bounds with a coreset construction consisting of at most $\tilde{O}(k\varepsilon^{-2}\cdot \min(\varepsilon^{-z},k))$ points.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Relation between Quantum Coherence and Quantum Entanglement in Quantum Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12656</link>
    <author>Ho-Joon Kim, Soojoon Lee</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum measurement is a class of quantum channels that sends quantum states to classical states. We set up resource theories of quantum coherence and quantum entanglement for quantum measurements and find relations between them. For this, we conceive a relative entropy type quantity to account for the quantum resources of quantum measurements. The quantum coherence of a quantum measurement can be converted into the entanglement in a bipartite quantum measurement through coherence-non generating transformations. Conversely, a quantum entanglement monotone of quantum measurements induces a quantum coherence monotone of quantum measurement. Our results confirm that the intuition on the link between quantum coherence and quantum entanglement is valid even for quantum measurements which do not generate any quantum resource.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>