<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Fragile boundaries of tailored surface codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04948</link>
    <author>Oscar Higgott, Thomas C. Bohdanowicz, Aleksander Kubica, Steven T. Flammia, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Biased noise is common in physical qubits, and tailoring a quantum code to the bias by locally modifying stabilizers or changing boundary conditions has been shown to greatly increase error correction thresholds. In this work, we explore the challenges of using a specific tailored code, the XY surface code, for fault-tolerant quantum computation. We introduce an efficient and fault-tolerant decoder, belief-matching, which we show has good performance for biased circuit-level noise. Using this decoder, we find that for moderately biased noise, the XY surface code has a higher threshold and lower overhead than the square CSS surface code, however it performs worse when below threshold than the rectangular CSS surface code. We identify a contributor to the reduced performance that we call fragile boundary errors. These are string-like errors that can occur along spatial or temporal boundaries in planar architectures or during logical state preparation and measurement. While we make partial progress towards mitigating these errors by deforming the boundaries of the XY surface code, our work suggests that fragility could remain a significant obstacle, even for other tailored codes. We expect belief-matching will have other uses, and find that it increases the threshold of the surface code to 0.940(3)% in the presence of circuit-level depolarising noise, compared to 0.817(5)% for a minimum-weight perfect matching decoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Limitations in Broadband Sensing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.05520</link>
    <author>Anthony M. Polloreno, Jacob L. Beckey, Joshua Levin, Ariel Shlosberg, James K. Thompson, Michael Foss-Feig, David Hayes, Graeme Smith</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider estimating the magnitude of a monochromatic AC signal that couples to a two-level sensor. For any detection protocol, the precision achieved depends on the signal's frequency and can be quantified by the quantum Fisher information. To study limitations in broadband sensing, we introduce the integrated quantum Fisher information and derive inequality bounds that embody fundamental tradeoffs in any sensing protocol. These inequalities show that sensitivity in one frequency range must come at a cost of reduced sensitivity elsewhere. For many protocols, including those with small phase accumulation and those consisting of $\pi$-pulses, we find the integrated Fisher information scales linearly with $T$. We also find protocols with substantial phase accumulation can have integrated QFI that grows quadratically with $T$, which is optimal. These protocols may allow the very rapid detection of a signal with unknown frequency over a very wide bandwidth.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying Grover speed-ups beyond asymptotic analysis</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04975</link>
    <author>Chris Cade, Marten Folkertsma, Ido Niesen, Jordi Weggemans</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The usual method for studying run-times of quantum algorithms is via an asymptotic, worst-case analysis. Whilst useful, such a comparison can often fall short: it is not uncommon for algorithms with a large worst-case run-time to end up performing well on instances of practical interest. To remedy this it is necessary to resort to run-time analyses of a more empirical nature, which for sufficiently small input sizes can be performed on a quantum device or a simulation thereof. For larger input sizes, alternative approaches are required. In this paper we consider an approach that combines classical emulation with rigorous complexity bounds: simulating quantum algorithms by running classical versions of the sub-routines, whilst simultaneously collecting information about what the run-time of the quantum routine would have been if it were run instead. To do this accurately and efficiently for very large input sizes, we describe an estimation procedure that provides provable guarantees on the estimates that it obtains. A nice feature of this approach is that it allows one to compare the performance of quantum and classical algorithms on particular inputs of interest, rather than only on those that allow for an easier mathematical analysis. We apply our method to some simple quantum speedups of classical heuristic algorithms for solving the well-studied MAX-k-SAT optimization problem. To do this we first obtain some rigorous bounds (including all constants) on the expected- and worst-case complexities of two important quantum sub-routines, which improve upon existing results and might be of broader interest: Grover search with an unknown number of marked items, and quantum maximum-finding. Our results suggest that such an approach can provide insightful and meaningful information, in particular when the speedup is of a small polynomial nature.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Information recoverability of noisy quantum states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04862</link>
    <author>Xuanqiang Zhao, Benchi Zhao, Zihan Xia, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classical information, also known as shadow information, carried by quantum states could be corrupted as they undergo undesirable noises modelled by quantum channels. Due to quantum channels' destructive nature, a fundamental problem in quantum information theory is how well we can retrieve information from noisy quantum states. In this work, we introduce a systematic framework to quantitatively study this problem. First, we prove that classical information can be retrieved if and only if the querying observable is in the image of the whole observable space under the channel's adjoint. Second, we further define the dimension of the evolved observable space as the quantum channel's effective shadow dimension that quantifies the information recoverability of the channel. This quantity can be computed as the rank of a matrix derived from the channel's Kraus operators, and it induces the shadow destructivity as a measure with meaningful properties. Third, we resolve the minimum cost of retrieving a piece of shadow information from the required number of copies of a noisy state. We in particular show that the optimal cost and the corresponding protocol are efficiently computable by semidefinite programming. As applications, we derive the ultimate limits on shadow retrieving costs for generalized amplitude damping channels and mixed Pauli channels and employ the corresponding protocol to mitigate errors in tasks of ground state energy estimation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Individual qubit addressing of rotating ion crystals in a Penning trap</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.05196</link>
    <author>Anthony M. Polloreno, Ana Maria Rey, John J. Bollinger</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Trapped ions boast long coherence times and excellent gate fidelities, making them a useful platform for quantum information processing. Scaling to larger numbers of ion qubits in RF Paul traps demands great effort. Another technique for trapping ions is via a Penning trap where a 2D crystal of hundreds of ions is formed by controlling the rotation of the ions in the presence of a strong magnetic field. However, the rotation of the ion crystal makes single ion addressability a significant challenge. We propose a protocol that takes advantage of a deformable mirror to introduce AC Stark shift patterns that are static in the rotating frame of the crystal. Through numerical simulations we validate the potential of this protocol to perform high-fidelity single-ion gates in crystalline arrays of hundreds of ions.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>