<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction with fractal topological codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03568</link>
    <author>Arpit Dua, Tomas Jochym-O'Connor, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, a class of fractal surface codes (FSCs), has been constructed on fractal lattices with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$, which admits a fault-tolerant non-Clifford CCZ gate. We investigate the performance of such FSCs as fault-tolerant quantum memories. We prove that there exist decoding strategies with non-zero thresholds for bit-flip and phase-flip errors in the FSCs with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$. For the bit-flip errors, we adapt the sweep decoder, developed for string-like syndromes in the regular 3D surface code, to the FSCs by designing suitable modifications on the boundaries of the holes in the fractal lattice. Moreover, our adaptation of the sweep decoder for the FSCs maintains its self-correcting and single-shot nature. For the phase-flip errors, we employ the minimum-weight-perfect-matching (MWPM) decoder for the point-like syndromes. We report a sustainable fault-tolerant threshold ($\sim 1.7\%$) under phenomenological noise for the sweep decoder and the code capacity threshold (lower bounded by $2.95\%$) for the MWPM decoder for a particular FSC with Hausdorff dimension $D_H\approx2.966$. The latter can be mapped to the critical point of a zero-temperature confinement-Higgs transition on the fractal lattice, which is tunable via the Hausdorff dimension.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Systematic Literature Review: Quantum Machine Learning and its applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04093</link>
    <author>David Peral García, Juan Cruz-Benito, Francisco José García-Peñalvo</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing is the process of performing calculations using quantum mechanics. This field studies the quantum behavior of certain subatomic particles for subsequent use in performing calculations, as well as for large-scale information processing. These capabilities can give quantum computers an advantage in terms of computational time and cost over classical computers. Nowadays, there are scientific challenges that are impossible to perform by classical computation due to computational complexity or the time the calculation would take, and quantum computation is one of the possible answers. However, current quantum devices have not yet the necessary qubits and are not fault-tolerant enough to achieve these goals. Nonetheless, there are other fields like machine learning or chemistry where quantum computation could be useful with current quantum devices. This manuscript aims to present a Systematic Literature Review of the papers published between 2017 and 2021 to identify, analyze and classify the different algorithms used in quantum machine learning and their applications. Consequently, this study identified 52 articles that used quantum machine learning techniques and algorithms. The main types of found algorithms are quantum implementations of classical machine learning algorithms, such as support vector machines or the k-nearest neighbor model, and classical deep learning algorithms, like quantum neural networks. Many articles try to solve problems currently answered by classical machine learning but using quantum devices and algorithms. Even though results are promising, quantum machine learning is far from achieving its full potential. An improvement in the quantum hardware is required since the existing quantum computers lack enough quality, speed, and scale to allow quantum computing to achieve its full potential.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dynamical preparation of quantum spin liquids in Rydberg atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04034</link>
    <author>Giuliano Giudici, Mikhail D. Lukin, Hannes Pichler</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We theoretically analyze recent experiments [G. Semeghini et al., Science 374, 1242 (2021)] demonstrating the onset of a topological spin liquid using a programmable quantum simulator based on Rydberg atom arrays. In the experiment, robust signatures of topological order emerge in out-of-equilibrium states that are prepared using a quasi-adiabatic state preparation protocol. We show theoretically that the state preparation protocol can be optimized to target the fixed point of the topological phase -- the resonating valence bond (RVB) state of hard dimers -- in a time that scales linearly with the number of atoms. Moreover, we provide a two-parameter variational manifold of tensor network (TN) states that accurately describe the many-body dynamics of the preparation process. Using this approach we analyze the nature of the non-equilibrium state, establishing the emergence of topological order.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The dipolar Bose-Hubbard model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04132</link>
    <author>Ethan Lake, Michael Hermele, T. Senthil</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study a simple model of interacting bosons on a d-dimensional cubic lattice whose dynamics conserves both total boson number and total boson dipole moment. This model provides a simple framework in which several remarkable consequences of dipole conservation can be explored. As a function of chemical potential and hopping strength, the model can be tuned between gapped Mott insulating phases and various types of gapless condensates. The condensed phase realized at large hopping strengths, which we dub a Bose-Einstein insulator, is particularly interesting: despite having a Bose condensate, it is insulating, and despite being an insulator, it is compressible.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Computing the group of minimal non-degenerate extensions of a super-Tannakian category</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04076</link>
    <author>Dmitri Nikshych</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove an analog of the Künneth formula for the groups of minimal non-degenerate extensions arXiv:1602.05936 of symmetric fusion categories. We describe in detail the structure of the group of minimal extensions of a pointed super-Tannakian fusion category. This description resembles that of the third cohomology group of a finite abelian group. We explicitly compute this group in several concrete examples.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>