<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A Theory of Direct Randomized Benchmarking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.13853</link>
    <author>Anthony M. Polloreno, Arnaud Carignan-Dugas, Jordan Hines, Robin Blume-Kohout, Kevin Young, Timothy Proctor</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Randomized benchmarking (RB) protocols are widely used to measure an average error rate for a set of quantum logic gates. However, the standard version of RB is limited because it only benchmarks a processor's native gates indirectly, by using them in composite $n$-qubit Clifford gates. Standard RB's reliance on $n$-qubit Clifford gates restricts it to the few-qubit regime, because the fidelity of a typical composite $n$-qubit Clifford gate decreases rapidly with increasing $n$. Furthermore, although standard RB is often used to infer the error rate of native gates, by rescaling standard RB's error per Clifford to an error per native gate, this is an unreliable extrapolation. Direct RB is a method that addresses these limitations of standard RB, by directly benchmarking a customizable gate set, such as a processor's native gates. Here we provide a detailed introduction to direct RB, we discuss how to design direct RB experiments, and we present two complementary theories for direct RB. The first of these theories uses the concept of error propagation or scrambling in random circuits to show that direct RB is reliable for gates that experience stochastic Pauli errors. We prove that the direct RB decay is a single exponential, and that the decay rate is equal to the average infidelity of the benchmarked gates, under broad circumstances. This theory shows that group twirling is not required for reliable RB. Our second theory proves that direct RB is reliable for gates that experience general gate-dependent Markovian errors, using similar techniques to contemporary theories for standard RB. Our two theories for direct RB have complementary regimes of applicability, and they provide complementary perspectives on why direct RB works. Together these theories provide comprehensive guarantees on the reliability of direct RB.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Field Theory and The Sum-of-Squares for Quantum Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.14006</link>
    <author>M. B. Hastings</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>This is a collection of various result and notes, addressing the sum-of-squares hierarchy for spin and fermion systems using some ideas from quantum field theory, including higher order perturbation theory, critical phenomena, nonlocal coupling in time, and auxiliary field Monte Carlo. This paper should be seen as a sequel to Refs. 1,2. Additionally in this paper, we consider the difficulty of approximating the ground state energy of the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model using other methods. We provide limitations on the power of the Lanczos method, starting with a Gausian wavefunction, and on the power of a sum of Gaussian wavefunctions (in this case under an assumption).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Implementing Linear Combination of Unitaries on Intermediate-term Quantum Computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.13555</link>
    <author>Shantanav Chakraborty</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Over the years, the framework of Linear combination of unitaries (LCU) has been extremely useful for designing a plethora of quantum algorithms. In this work, we explore whether this widely applicable paradigm can be implemented on quantum computers that will be available immediately after the current NISQ stage. To this end, we develop three variants of LCU and apply each, to quantum algorithms of practical interest. First, we develop a physically motivated, continuous-time analogue of LCU (``Analog LCU''). This technique, implementable on hybrid qubit-qumode systems, is simpler than its discrete-time counterpart. We use this method to develop analog quantum algorithms for ground state preparation and quantum linear systems. We also develop a randomized quantum algorithm to sample from functions of Hamiltonians applied to quantum states (``Single-Ancilla LCU''). This approach repeatedly samples from a short-depth quantum circuit and uses only a single ancilla qubit. We use this to estimate expectation values of observables in the ground states of a Hamiltonian, and in the solution of quantum linear systems. This method is suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum computers. Our third approach stems from the observation that for several applications, it suffices to replace LCU with randomized sampling of unitaries according to the distribution of the LCU coefficients (``Ancilla-free LCU''). This is particularly useful when one is interested in the projection of a quantum state implemented by an LCU procedure in some subspace of interest. We demonstrate that this technique applies to the spatial search problem and helps establish a relationship between discrete and continuous-time quantum walks with their classical counterparts. Our work demonstrates that generic quantum algorithmic paradigms, such as LCU, can potentially be implemented on intermediate-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From Classical to Quantum Information Geometry, an Introductory Guide</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.13515</link>
    <author>J. Lambert, E. S. Sørensen</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, geometrical aspects of quantum information have attracted considerable attention due to their applicability in promising new quantum technologies. In particular, the quantum Fisher information has gained prominence for its utility within the field of quantum sensing through the Cramér-Rao bound. Closely related concepts, such as quantum variance and co-variance, fidelity susceptibility, entanglement entropy and Berry curvature have also been extensively studied. While classical information geometry has been developed as a sub-field of mathematical statistics since the late 1950s, it has had a more limited impact within the field of condensed matter physics. Despite this, the generalization of information geometry to incorporate quantum mechanics provides a natural framework for understanding all the above concepts in a unified manner. Starting from an introduction to classical information geometry and Shannon information, we discuss the difficulties in generalizing the classical results to the quantum case and present a pedagogical guide to quantum information geometry. Rather than a thorough review of the by now extensive literature, the intention is to emphasize the unifying framework relating the different concepts and to discuss their applicability to quantum sensing, as well as to the detection of quantum criticality via fidelity susceptibility, and to the understanding of topological properties of ground state manifolds. General relations between the quantum Fisher information and response functions are derived, and scaling relations are discussed, along with bounds relevant to quantum enhanced metrology. Several examples are given for simple one and two qubit systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum dynamics is linear because quantum states are epistemic</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.13421</link>
    <author>Jacques L. Pienaar</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>According to quantum theory, a scientist in a sealed laboratory cannot tell whether they are inside a superposition or not. Consequently, so long as they remain isolated, they can assume without inconsistency that their measurements result in definite outcomes. We elevate this feature to a postulate, which we call Local Definiteness. If quantum states are ontic, this postulate must be derived by assuming the dynamical law is linear. On the other hand, if quantum states are epistemic then the postulate comes for free. We can then use it to prove that the dynamics must be linear. Therefore the simplest explanation for why experiments keep failing to find evidence of non-linear dynamics is that quantum states are epistemic.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>