<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Representation Theory for Geometric Quantum Machine Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07980</link>
    <author>Michael Ragone, Paolo Braccia, Quynh T. Nguyen, Louis Schatzki, Patrick J. Coles, Frederic Sauvage, Martin Larocca, M. Cerezo</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent advances in classical machine learning have shown that creating models with inductive biases encoding the symmetries of a problem can greatly improve performance. Importation of these ideas, combined with an existing rich body of work at the nexus of quantum theory and symmetry, has given rise to the field of Geometric Quantum Machine Learning (GQML). Following the success of its classical counterpart, it is reasonable to expect that GQML will play a crucial role in developing problem-specific and quantum-aware models capable of achieving a computational advantage. Despite the simplicity of the main idea of GQML -- create architectures respecting the symmetries of the data -- its practical implementation requires a significant amount of knowledge of group representation theory. We present an introduction to representation theory tools from the optics of quantum learning, driven by key examples involving discrete and continuous groups. These examples are sewn together by an exposition outlining the formal capture of GQML symmetries via "label invariance under the action of a group representation", a brief (but rigorous) tour through finite and compact Lie group representation theory, a reexamination of ubiquitous tools like Haar integration and twirling, and an overview of some successful strategies for detecting symmetries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A random matrix model for random approximate $t$-designs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07872</link>
    <author>Piotr Dulian, Adam Sawicki</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For a Haar random set $\mathcal{S}\subset U(d)$ of quantum gates we consider the uniform measure $\nu_\mathcal{S}$ whose support is given by $\mathcal{S}$. The measure $\nu_\mathcal{S}$ can be regarded as a $\delta(\nu_\mathcal{S},t)$-approximate $t$-design, $t\in\mathbb{Z}_+$. We propose a random matrix model that aims to describe the probability distribution of $\delta(\nu_\mathcal{S},t)$ for any $t$. Our model is given by a block diagonal matrix whose blocks are independent, given by Gaussian or Ginibre ensembles, and their number, size and type is determined by $t$. We prove that, the operator norm of this matrix, $\delta({t})$, is the random variable to which $\sqrt{|\mathcal{S}|}\delta(\nu_\mathcal{S},t)$ converges in distribution when the number of elements in $\mathcal{S}$ grows to infinity. Moreover, we characterize our model giving explicit bounds on the tail probabilities $\mathbb{P}(\delta(t)>2+\epsilon)$, for any $\epsilon>0$. We also show that our model satisfies the so-called spectral gap conjecture, i.e. we prove that with the probability $1$ there is $t\in\mathbb{Z}_+$ such that $\sup_{k\in\mathbb{Z}_{+}}\delta(k)=\delta(t)$. Numerical simulations give convincing evidence that the proposed model is actually almost exact for any cardinality of $\mathcal{S}$. The heuristic explanation of this phenomenon, that we provide, leads us to conjecture that the tail probabilities $\mathbb{P}(\sqrt{\mathcal{S}}\delta(\nu_\mathcal{S},t)>2+\epsilon)$ are bounded from above by the tail probabilities $\mathbb{P}(\delta(t)>2+\epsilon)$ of our random matrix model. In particular our conjecture implies that a Haar random set $\mathcal{S}\subset U(d)$ satisfies the spectral gap conjecture with the probability $1$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental nonclassicality in a causal network without assuming freedom of choice</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07263</link>
    <author>Emanuele Polino, Davide Poderini, Giovanni Rodari, Iris Agresti, Alessia Suprano, Gonzalo Carvacho, Elie Wolfe, Askery Canabarro, George Moreno, Giorgio Milani, Robert W. Spekkens, Rafael Chaves, Fabio Sciarrino</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a Bell experiment, it is natural to seek a causal account of correlations wherein only a common cause acts on the outcomes. For this causal structure, Bell inequality violations can be explained only if causal dependencies are modelled as intrinsically quantum. There also exists a vast landscape of causal structures beyond Bell that can witness nonclassicality, in some cases without even requiring free external inputs. Here, we undertake a photonic experiment realizing one such example: the triangle causal network, consisting of three measurement stations pairwise connected by common causes and no external inputs. To demonstrate the nonclassicality of the data, we adapt and improve three known techniques: (i) a machine-learning-based heuristic test, (ii) a data-seeded inflation technique generating polynomial Bell-type inequalities and (iii) entropic inequalities. The demonstrated experimental and data analysis tools are broadly applicable paving the way for future networks of growing complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Compensating for non-linear distortions in controlled quantum systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07833</link>
    <author>Juhi Singh, Robert Zeier, Tommaso Calarco, Felix Motzoi</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Predictive design and optimization methods for controlled quantum systems depend on the accuracy of the system model. Any distortion of the input fields in an experimental platform alters the model accuracy and eventually disturbs the predicted dynamics. These distortions can be non-linear with a strong frequency dependence so that the field interacting with the microscopic quantum system has limited resemblance to the input signal. We present an effective method for estimating these distortions which is suitable for non-linear transfer functions of arbitrary lengths and magnitudes provided the available training data has enough spectral components. Using a quadratic estimation, we have successfully tested our approach for a numerical example of a single Rydberg atom system. The transfer function estimated from the presented method is incorporated into an open-loop control optimization algorithm allowing for high-fidelity operations in quantum experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement-induced phase transitions on dynamical quantum trees</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07264</link>
    <author>Xiaozhou Feng, Brian Skinner, Adam Nahum</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Monitored many-body systems fall broadly into two dynamical phases, ``entangling'' or ``disentangling'', separated by a transition as a function of the rate at which measurements are made on the system. Producing an analytical theory of this measurement-induced transition is an outstanding challenge. Recent work made progress in the context of tree tensor networks, which can be related to all-to-all quantum circuit dynamics with forced (postselected) measurement outcomes. So far, however, there are no exact solutions for dynamics of spin-1/2 degrees of freedom (qubits) with ``real'' measurements, whose outcome probabilities are sampled according to the Born rule. Here we define dynamical processes for qubits, with real measurements, that have a tree-like spacetime interaction graph, either collapsing or expanding the system as a function of time. The former case yields an exactly solvable measurement transition. We explore these processes analytically and numerically, exploiting the recursive structure of the tree. We compare the case of ``real'' measurements with the case of ``forced'' measurements. Both cases show a transition at a nontrivial value of the measurement strength, with the real measurement case exhibiting a smaller entangling phase. Both exhibit exponential scaling of the entanglement near the transition, but they differ in the value of a critical exponent. An intriguing difference between the two cases is that the real measurement case lies at the boundary between two distinct types of critical scaling. On the basis of our results we propose a protocol for realizing a measurement phase transition experimentally via an expansion process.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>