<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Copula-based Risk Aggregation with Trapped Ion Quantum Computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11937</link>
    <author>Daiwei Zhu, Weiwei Shen, Annarita Giani, Saikat Ray Majumder, Bogdan Neculaes, Sonika Johri</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Copulas are mathematical tools for modeling joint probability distributions. Since copulas enable one to conveniently treat the marginal distribution of each variable and the interdependencies among variables separately, in the past 60 years they have become an essential analysis tool on classical computers in various fields ranging from quantitative finance and civil engineering to signal processing and medicine. The recent finding that copulas can be expressed as maximally entangled quantum states has revealed a promising approach to practical quantum advantages: performing tasks faster, requiring less memory, or, as we show, yielding better predictions. Studying the scalability of this quantum approach as both the precision and the number of modeled variables increase is crucial for its adoption in real-world applications. In this paper, we successfully apply a Quantum Circuit Born Machine (QCBM) based approach to modeling 3- and 4-variable copulas on trapped ion quantum computers. We study the training of QCBMs with different levels of precision and circuit design on a simulator and a state-of-the-art trapped ion quantum computer. We observe decreased training efficacy due to the increased complexity in parameter optimization as the models scale up. To address this challenge, we introduce an annealing-inspired strategy that dramatically improves the training results. In our end-to-end tests, various configurations of the quantum models make a comparable or better prediction in risk aggregation tasks than the standard classical models. Our detailed study of the copula paradigm using quantum computing opens opportunities for its deployment in various industries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From Tensor Network Quantum States to Tensorial Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12363</link>
    <author>Dian Wu, Riccardo Rossi, Filippo Vicentini, Giuseppe Carleo</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that any matrix product state (MPS) can be exactly represented by a recurrent neural network (RNN) with a linear memory update. We generalize this RNN architecture to 2D lattices using a multilinear memory update. It supports perfect sampling and wave function evaluation in polynomial time, and can represent an area law of entanglement entropy. Numerical evidence shows that it can encode the wave function using a bond dimension lower by orders of magnitude when compared to MPS, with an accuracy that can be systematically improved by increasing the bond dimension.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental Demonstration of Quantum Pseudotelepathy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12042</link>
    <author>Jia-Min Xu, Yi-Zheng Zhen, Yu-Xiang Yang, Zi-Mo Cheng, Zhi-Cheng Ren, Kai Chen, Xi-Lin Wang, Hui-Tian Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum pseudotelepathy is a strong form of nonlocality. Different from the conventional nonlocal games where quantum strategies win statistically, e.g., the CHSH game, quantum pseudotelepathy in principle allows quantum players to with probability one. In this work, we report a faithful experimental demonstration of quantum pseudotelepathy via playing the nonlocal version of Mermin-Peres magic square game, where Alice and Bob cooperatively fill in a 3*3 magic square. We adopt the hyperentanglement scheme and prepare photon pairs entangled in both the polarization and the orbital angular momentum degrees of freedom, such that the experiment is carried out in a resource-efficient manner. Under the locality and fair-sampling assumption, our results show that quantum players can simultaneously win all the queries over any classical strategy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Spatially programmable spin interactions in neutral atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12385</link>
    <author>Lea-Marina Steinert, Philip Osterholz, Robin Eberhard, Lorenzo Festa, Nikolaus Lorenz, Zaijun Chen, Arno Trautmann, Christian Gross</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum simulators based on arrays of neutral atoms have proven to be among the most promising platforms to explore and solve non-trivial problems of complex strongly correlated many-body phenomena. This success is based on the optimally hardware-efficient analog implementation of the Hamiltonian under study. The drawback of this approach is the narrow range of problems addressable with any chosen architecture, which motivates the development of flexible programming techniques for analog simulators. We report on the realization of spatially programmable interactions for XYZ models implemented with neutral atoms in optical tweezers. We use multi-color near-resonant coupling to highly excited electronic states to induce spin-dependent interactions between atoms in atomic ground states. Van-der-Waals interactions between these Rydberg states lead to mixing between usually well-separated $m_j$-sublevels. This opens up distance and angular-dependent programmable interaction channels, which we use to design spin-exchange and pairwise spin flips. Our results pave the way toward universally programmable spin arrays for analog quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Relative Survivable Network Design</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12245</link>
    <author>Michael Dinitz, Ama Koranteng, Guy Kortsarz</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One of the most important and well-studied settings for network design is edge-connectivity requirements. This encompasses uniform demands such as the Minimum $k$-Edge-Connected Spanning Subgraph problem ($k$-ECSS), as well as nonuniform demands such as the Survivable Network Design problem. A weakness of these formulations, though, is that we are not able to ask for fault-tolerance larger than the connectivity. We introduce and study new variants of these problems under a notion of relative fault-tolerance. Informally, we require not that two nodes are connected if there are a bounded number of faults (as in the classical setting), but that two nodes are connected if there are a bounded number of faults and the two nodes are connected in the underlying graph post-faults. That is, the subgraph we build must "behave" identically to the underlying graph with respect to connectivity after bounded faults. We define and introduce these problems, and provide the first approximation algorithms: a $(1+4/k)$-approximation for the unweighted relative version of $k$-ECSS, a $2$-approximation for the weighted relative version of $k$-ECSS, and a $27/4$-approximation for the special case of Relative Survivable Network Design with only a single demand with a connectivity requirement of $3$. To obtain these results, we introduce a number of technical ideas that may of independent interest. First, we give a generalization of Jain's iterative rounding analysis that works even when the cut-requirement function is not weakly supermodular, but instead satisfies a weaker definition we introduce and term local weak supermodularity. Second, we prove a structure theorem and design an approximation algorithm utilizing a new decomposition based on important separators, which are structures commonly used in fixed-parameter algorithms that have not commonly been used in approximation algorithms.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>