<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13228</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas Breuckmann, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of non-trivial complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). We prove this conjecture by showing that the recently discovered families of constant-rate and linear-distance QLDPC codes correspond to NLTS local Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Pair Measurement Surface Code on Pentagons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12780</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, I present a way to compile the surface code into two-body parity measurements ("pair measurements"), where the pair measurements run along the edges of a Cairo pentagonal tiling. The resulting circuit improves on prior work by Chao et al. by using fewer pair measurements per four-body stabilizer measurement (5 instead of 6) and fewer time steps per round of stabilizer measurement (6 instead of 10). Using Monte Carlo sampling, I show that these improvements increase the threshold of the surface code when compiling into pair measurements from $\approx 0.2\%$ to $\approx 0.4\%$, and also that they improve the teraquop footprint at a $0.1\%$ physical gate error rate from $\approx6000$ qubits to $\approx3000$ qubits. However, I also show that Chao et al's construction will have a smaller teraquop footprint for physical gate error rates below $\approx 0.03\%$ (due to bidirectional hook errors in my construction). I also compare to the planar honeycomb code, showing that although this work does noticeably reduce the gap between the surface code and the honeycomb code (when compiling into pair measurements), the honeycomb code is still more efficient (threshold $\approx 0.8\%$, teraquop footprint at $0.1\%$ of $\approx 1000$).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Positive-definite parametrization of mixed quantum states with deep neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13488</link>
    <author>Filippo Vicentini, Riccardo Rossi, Giuseppe Carleo</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce the Gram-Hadamard Density Operator (GHDO), a new deep neural-network architecture that can encode positive semi-definite density operators of exponential rank with polynomial resources. We then show how to embed an autoregressive structure in the GHDO to allow direct sampling of the probability distribution. These properties are especially important when representing and variationally optimizing the mixed quantum state of a system interacting with an environment. Finally, we benchmark this architecture by simulating the steady state of the dissipative transverse-field Ising model. Estimating local observables and the Rényi entropy, we show significant improvements over previous state-of-the-art variational approaches.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Regularized Least Squares</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13143</link>
    <author>Shantanav Chakraborty, Aditya Morolia, Anurudh Peduri</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Linear regression is a widely used technique to fit linear models and finds widespread applications across different areas such as machine learning and statistics. In most real-world scenarios, however, linear regression problems are often ill-posed or the underlying model suffers from overfitting, leading to erroneous or trivial solutions. This is often dealt with by adding extra constraints, known as regularization. In this paper, we use the frameworks of block-encoding and quantum singular value transformation to design new quantum algorithms for quantum least squares with general $\ell_2$-regularization. These include regularized versions of quantum ordinary least squares, quantum weighted least squares, and quantum generalized least squares. Our quantum algorithms substantially improve upon prior results on quantum ridge regression (the regularization term is proportional to the $\ell_2$-norm of the least squares solution), which is a particular case of our result. To this end, we assume approximate block-encodings of the underlying matrices as input and use robust QSVT algorithms for various linear algebra operations. In particular, we develop a variable-time quantum algorithm for matrix inversion using QSVT, where we use quantum eigenvalue discrimination as a subroutine instead of gapped phase estimation. This ensures that fewer additional qubits are required for this procedure than prior results. Owing to the generality of the block-encoding framework, our algorithms can be implemented on a variety of input models and can also be seen as improved and generalized versions of the standard (non-regularized) quantum least squares algorithms of Chakraborty et al. [ICALP 2019].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-Convex Optimization by Hamiltonian Alternation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14072</link>
    <author>Anuj Apte, Kunal Marwaha, Arvind Murugan</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A major obstacle to non-convex optimization is the problem of getting stuck in local minima. We introduce a novel metaheuristic to handle this issue, creating an alternate Hamiltonian that shares minima with the original Hamiltonian only within a chosen energy range. We find that repeatedly minimizing each Hamiltonian in sequence allows an algorithm to escape local minima. This technique is particularly straightforward when the ground state energy is known, and one obtains an improvement even without this knowledge. We demonstrate this technique by using it to find the ground state for instances of a Sherrington-Kirkpatrick spin glass.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>