<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13228</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas Breuckmann, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of non-trivial complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). We prove this conjecture by showing that the recently discovered families of constant-rate and linear-distance QLDPC codes correspond to NLTS local Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From Tensor Network Quantum States to Tensorial Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12363</link>
    <author>Dian Wu, Riccardo Rossi, Filippo Vicentini, Giuseppe Carleo</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that any matrix product state (MPS) can be exactly represented by a recurrent neural network (RNN) with a linear memory update. We generalize this RNN architecture to 2D lattices using a multilinear memory update. It supports perfect sampling and wave function evaluation in polynomial time, and can represent an area law of entanglement entropy. Numerical evidence shows that it can encode the wave function using a bond dimension lower by orders of magnitude when compared to MPS, with an accuracy that can be systematically improved by increasing the bond dimension.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Pair Measurement Surface Code on Pentagons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12780</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, I present a way to compile the surface code into two-body parity measurements ("pair measurements"), where the pair measurements run along the edges of a Cairo pentagonal tiling. The resulting circuit improves on prior work by Chao et al. by using fewer pair measurements per four-body stabilizer measurement (5 instead of 6) and fewer time steps per round of stabilizer measurement (6 instead of 10). Using Monte Carlo sampling, I show that these improvements increase the threshold of the surface code when compiling into pair measurements from $\approx 0.2\%$ to $\approx 0.4\%$, and also that they improve the teraquop footprint at a $0.1\%$ physical gate error rate from $\approx6000$ qubits to $\approx3000$ qubits. However, I also show that Chao et al's construction will have a smaller teraquop footprint for physical gate error rates below $\approx 0.03\%$ (due to bidirectional hook errors in my construction). I also compare to the planar honeycomb code, showing that although this work does noticeably reduce the gap between the surface code and the honeycomb code (when compiling into pair measurements), the honeycomb code is still more efficient (threshold $\approx 0.8\%$, teraquop footprint at $0.1\%$ of $\approx 1000$).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Spatially programmable spin interactions in neutral atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12385</link>
    <author>Lea-Marina Steinert, Philip Osterholz, Robin Eberhard, Lorenzo Festa, Nikolaus Lorenz, Zaijun Chen, Arno Trautmann, Christian Gross</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum simulators based on arrays of neutral atoms have proven to be among the most promising platforms to explore and solve non-trivial problems of complex strongly correlated many-body phenomena. This success is based on the optimally hardware-efficient analog implementation of the Hamiltonian under study. The drawback of this approach is the narrow range of problems addressable with any chosen architecture, which motivates the development of flexible programming techniques for analog simulators. We report on the realization of spatially programmable interactions for XYZ models implemented with neutral atoms in optical tweezers. We use multi-color near-resonant coupling to highly excited electronic states to induce spin-dependent interactions between atoms in atomic ground states. Van-der-Waals interactions between these Rydberg states lead to mixing between usually well-separated $m_j$-sublevels. This opens up distance and angular-dependent programmable interaction channels, which we use to design spin-exchange and pairwise spin flips. Our results pave the way toward universally programmable spin arrays for analog quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental graybox quantum control</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12201</link>
    <author>Akram Youssry, Yang Yang, Robert J. Chapman, Ben Haylock, Mirko Lobino, Alberto Peruzzo</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding and controlling engineered quantum systems is key to developing practical quantum technology. However, given the current technological limitations, such as fabrication imperfections and environmental noise, this is not always possible. To address these issues, a great deal of theoretical and numerical methods for quantum system identification and control have been developed. These methods range from traditional curve fittings, which are limited by the accuracy of the model that describes the system, to machine learning methods, including neural networks, which provide efficient control solutions but do not provide control beyond the output of the model, nor insights into the underlying physical process. Here we experimentally demonstrate a "graybox" approach for characterizing and controlling quantum devices. We report superior performance over model fitting, while generating unitaries and Hamiltonians which are inaccessible with machine learning techniques. Our approach combines prior physics knowledge with high accuracy machine learning and is effective with any problem where the required controlled quantities are not directly accessible from the training set. This method naturally extends to time-dependent and open quantum systems, with applications in quantum noise spectroscopy and cancellation.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>