<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Asymptotic and catalytic matrix majorization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07353</link>
    <author>Muhammad Usman Farooq, Tobias Fritz, Erkka Haapasalo, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The matrix majorization problem asks, given two tuples of probability vectors, whether there exists a single stochastic matrix transforming one tuple into the other. Solving an open problem due to Mu et al, we show that if certain monotones - namely multivariate extensions of Renyi divergences - are strictly ordered between the two tuples, then for sufficiently large $n$, there exists a stochastic matrix taking $n$ copies of each input distribution to $n$ copies of the corresponding output distribution. The same conditions, with non-strict ordering for the monotones, are also necessary for such asymptotic matrix majorization. Our result also yields a map that approximately converts a single copy of each input distribution to the corresponding output distribution with the help of a catalyst that is returned unchanged. Allowing for transformation with arbitrarily small error, we find conditions that are both necessary and sufficient for such catalytic matrix majorization. We derive our results by building on a general algebraic theory of preordered semirings recently developed by one of the authors. This also allows us to recover various existing results on asymptotic and catalytic majorization as well as relative majorization in a unified manner.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New constructive counterexamples to additivity of minimum output Rényi entropy of quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07428</link>
    <author>Krzysztof Szczygielski, Michał Studziński</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper we present new families of quantum channels for which corresponding minimum output Rényi entropy is not additive. In the first part of the manuscript, motivated by work of Grudka et. al. (J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 43, 425304 (2010)), we focus on extensions of the antisymmetric space and its subspaces. Later on we analyze a special case of completely entangled subspace proposed by Parthasarathy in Proc. Math. Sci. 114, 365-374 (2004). Our construction works for every $p>2$ and dimension high enough.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Remote detectability from entanglement bootstrap I: Kirby's torus trick</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07119</link>
    <author>Bowen Shi, Jin-Long Huang, John McGreevy</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Remote detectability is often taken as a physical assumption in the study of topologically ordered systems, and it is a central axiom of mathematical frameworks of topological quantum field theories. We show under the entanglement bootstrap approach that remote detectability is a necessary property; that is, we derive it as a theorem. Starting from a single wave function on a topologically-trivial region satisfying the entanglement bootstrap axioms, we can construct states on closed manifolds. The crucial technique is to immerse the punctured manifold into the topologically trivial region and then heal the puncture. This is analogous to Kirby's torus trick. We then analyze a special class of such manifolds, which we call pairing manifolds. For each pairing manifold, which pairs two classes of excitations, we identify an analog of the topological S-matrix. This pairing matrix is unitary, which implies remote detectability between two classes of excitations. These matrices are in general not associated with the mapping class group of the manifold. As a by-product, we can count excitation types (e.g., graph excitations in 3+1d). The pairing phenomenon occurs in many physical contexts, including systems in different dimensions, with or without gapped boundaries. We provide a variety of examples to illustrate its scope.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Enhancing quantum computer performance via symmetrization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07233</link>
    <author>Andrii Maksymov, Jason Nguyen, Yunseong Nam, Igor Markov</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Large quantum computers promise to solve some critical problems not solvable otherwise. However, modern quantum technologies suffer various imperfections such as control errors and qubit decoherence, inhibiting their potential utility. The overheads of quantum error correction are too great for near-term quantum computers, whereas error-mitigation strategies that address specific device imperfections may lose relevance as devices improve. To enhance the performance of quantum computers with high-quality qubits, we introduce a strategy based on symmetrization and nonlinear aggregation. On a commercial trapped-ion quantum computer, it improves performance of multiple practical algorithms by 100x with no qubit or gate overhead.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>stateQIP = statePSPACE</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07730</link>
    <author>Tony Metger, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Complexity theory traditionally studies the hardness of solving classical computational problems. In the quantum setting, it is also natural to consider a different notion of complexity, namely the complexity of physically preparing a certain quantum state. We study the relation between two such state complexity classes: statePSPACE, which contains states that can be generated by space-uniform polynomial-space quantum circuits, and stateQIP, which contains states that a polynomial-time quantum verifier can generate by interacting with an all-powerful untrusted quantum prover. The latter class was recently introduced by Rosenthal and Yuen (ITCS 2022), who proved that statePSPACE $\subseteq$ stateQIP. Our main result is the reverse inclusion, stateQIP $\subseteq$ statePSPACE, thereby establishing equality of the two classes and providing a natural state-complexity analogue to the celebrated QIP = PSPACE theorem of Jain, et al. (J. ACM 2011). To prove this, we develop a polynomial-space quantum algorithm for solving exponentially large "PSPACE-computable" semidefinite programs (SDPs), which also prepares an optimiser encoded in a quantum state. Our SDP solver relies on recent block-encoding techniques from quantum algorithms, demonstrating that these techniques are also useful for complexity theory. Using similar techniques, we also show that optimal prover strategies for general quantum interactive protocols can be implemented in quantum polynomial space. We prove this by studying an algorithmic version of Uhlmann's theorem and establishing an upper bound on the complexity of implementing Uhlmann transformations.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>