<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>On the Role of Quantum Coherence in Thermodynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.13612</link>
    <author>Gilad Gour</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We find necessary and sufficient conditions to determine the inter-convertibility of quantum systems under time-translation covariant evolution, and use it to solve several problems in quantum thermodynamics both in the single-shot and asymptotic regimes. It is well known that the resource theory of quantum athermality is not reversible, but in PRL 111, 250404 (2013) it was claimed that the theory becomes reversible "provided a sublinear amount of coherent superposition over energy levels is available". Here we show that the original proof of this claim is incorrect, and then provide a completely new rigorous proof for the pure-state case. A proof of the same claim for the mixed-state case is still lacking.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Only Classical Parametrised States have Optimal Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.14142</link>
    <author>Wilfred Salmon, Sergii Strelchuk, David Arvidsson-Shukur</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Measurements of quantum states form a key component in quantum-information processing. It is therefore an important task to compare measurements and furthermore decide if a measurement strategy is optimal. We introduce a framework that allows one to conclusively establish if a measurement is optimal. Our method relies on the fundamental property of expected errors of estimators, known as risk, and it does not involve optimisation over entropic quantities. The framework applies to finite sample sizes and lack of prior knowledge, as well as to the asymptotic and Bayesian settings. We prove a no-go theorem that shows that only classical states admit optimal measurements. We further consider the less restrictive notion of an approximately optimal measurement and give sufficient conditions for such measurements to exist. Finally, we generalise the notion of when an estimator is inadmissible (i.e. strictly worse than an alternative), and provide two sufficient conditions for a measurement to be inadmissible.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Mitigation via Quantum-Noise-Effect Circuit Groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.13907</link>
    <author>Yusuke Hama, Hirofumi Nishi</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Our near-term quantum computers have been built as intermediate-scale quantum devices and are fragile against quantum noise effects, namely, NISQ devices. Traditional quantum-error-correcting (QEC) codes are not implemented on such devices and to perform quantum computation in good accuracy with these machines we need to develop alternative approaches for mitigating quantum computational errors. In this work, we propose quantum error mitigation (QEM) scheme for quantum computational errors which occur due to couplings with environments during gate operations, i.e., decoherence. To establish our QEM scheme, first we estimate the quantum noise effects on single-qubit states and represent them as groups of quantum circuits, namely, quantum-noise-effect circuit groups. Then our QEM scheme is conducted by subtracting expectation values generated by the quantum-noise-effect circuit groups from that obtained by the quantum circuit for the quantum algorithm under consideration. As a result, the quantum noise effect is reduced, and we obtain approximately the ideal expectation values via the quantum-noise-effect circuit group and the number of elementary quantum circuits composing it scales polynomial with respect to the product of the depth of quantum algorithm and the number of register bits. To numerically demonstrate the validity of our QEM scheme, we run noisy quantum simulations of qubits under the amplitude damping (AD) effects for four types of quantum algorithms. Our QEM scheme is solely composed of quantum-computational operations (quantum gates and measurements), and thus, it can be conducted by any type of quantum device without having limitations on the number of register bits and error rates of quantum gates. In addition, it can be applied to error mitigation for many other types of quantum noise effects as well as noisy quantum computing of long-depth quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Towards near-term quantum simulation of materials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15256</link>
    <author>Laura Clinton, Toby Cubitt, Brian Flynn, Filippo Maria Gambetta, Joel Klassen, Ashley Montanaro, Stephen Piddock, Raul A. Santos, Evan Sheridan</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulation of materials is one of the most promising applications of quantum computers. On near-term hardware the crucial constraint on these simulations is circuit depth. Many quantum simulation algorithms rely on a layer of unitary evolutions generated by each term in a Hamiltonian. This appears in time-dynamics as a single Trotter step, and in variational quantum eigensolvers under the Hamiltonian variational ansatz as a single ansatz layer. We present a new quantum algorithm design for materials modelling where the depth of a layer is independent of the system size. This design takes advantage of the locality of materials in the Wannier basis and employs a tailored fermionic encoding that preserves locality. We analyse the circuit costs of this approach and present a compiler that transforms density functional theory data into quantum circuit instructions -- connecting the physics of the material to the simulation circuit. The compiler automatically optimises circuits at multiple levels, from the base gate level to optimisations derived from the physics of the specific target material. We present numerical results for materials spanning a wide structural and technological range. Our results demonstrate a reduction of many orders of magnitude in circuit depth over standard prior methods that do not consider the structure of the Hamiltonian. For example our results improve resource requirements for Strontium Vanadate (SrVO$_3$) from 864 to 180 qubits for a $3\times3\times3$ lattice, and the circuit depth of a single Trotter or variational layer from $7.5\times 10^8$ to depth $730$. Although this is still beyond current hardware, our results show that materials simulation may be feasible on quantum computers without necessarily requiring scalable, fault-tolerant quantum computers, provided quantum algorithm design incorporates understanding of the materials and applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Finding many Collisions via Reusable Quantum Walks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.14023</link>
    <author>Xavier Bonnetain, André Chailloux, André Schrottenloher, Yixin Shen</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a random function $f$ with domain $[2^n]$ and codomain $[2^m]$, with $m \geq n$, a collision of $f$ is a pair of distinct inputs with the same image. Collision finding is an ubiquitous problem in cryptanalysis, and it has been well studied using both classical and quantum algorithms. Indeed, the quantum query complexity of the problem is well known to be $\Theta(2^{m/3})$, and matching algorithms are known for any value of $m$. The situation becomes different when one is looking for multiple collision pairs. Here, for $2^k$ collisions, a query lower bound of $\Theta(2^{(2k+m)/3})$ was shown by Liu and Zhandry (EUROCRYPT~2019). A matching algorithm is known, but only for relatively small values of $m$, when many collisions exist. In this paper, we improve the algorithms for this problem and, in particular, extend the range of admissible parameters where the lower bound is met. Our new method relies on a chained quantum walk algorithm, which might be of independent interest. It allows to extract multiple solutions of an MNRS-style quantum walk, without having to recompute it entirely: after finding and outputting a solution, the current state is reused as the initial state of another walk. As an application, we improve the quantum sieving algorithms for the shortest vector problem (SVP), with a complexity of $2^{0.2563d + o(d)}$ instead of the previous $2^{0.2570d + o(d)}$.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>