<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The learnability of Pauli noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06362</link>
    <author>Senrui Chen, Yunchao Liu, Matthew Otten, Alireza Seif, Bill Fefferman, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, several noise benchmarking algorithms have been developed to characterize noisy quantum gates on today's quantum devices. A well-known issue in benchmarking is that not everything about quantum noise is learnable due to the existence of gauge freedom, leaving open the question of what information about noise is learnable and what is not, which has been unclear even for a single CNOT gate. Here we give a precise characterization of the learnability of Pauli noise channels attached to Clifford gates, showing that learnable information corresponds to the cycle space of the pattern transfer graph of the gate set, while unlearnable information corresponds to the cut space. This implies the optimality of cycle benchmarking, in the sense that it can learn all learnable information about Pauli noise. We experimentally demonstrate noise characterization of IBM's CNOT gate up to 2 unlearnable degrees of freedom, for which we obtain bounds using physical constraints. In addition, we give an attempt to characterize the unlearnable information by assuming perfect initial state preparation. However, based on the experimental data, we conclude that this assumption is inaccurate as it yields unphysical estimates, and we obtain a lower bound on state preparation noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Average-case hardness of estimating probabilities of random quantum circuits with a linear scaling in the error exponent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05642</link>
    <author>Hari Krovi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the hardness of computing additive approximations to output probabilities of random quantum circuits. We consider three random circuit families, namely, Haar random, $p=1$ QAOA, and random IQP circuits. Our results are as follows. For Haar random circuits with $m$ gates, we improve on prior results by showing $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hardness of average-case additive approximations to an imprecision of $2^{-O(m)}$. Efficient classical simulation of such problems would imply the collapse of the polynomial hierarchy. For constant depth circuits i.e., when $m=O(n)$, this linear scaling in the exponent is within a constant of the scaling required to show hardness of sampling. Prior to our work, such a result was shown only for Boson Sampling in Bouland et al (2021). We also use recent results in polynomial interpolation to show $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hardness under $\mathsf{BPP}$ reductions rather than $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{NP}}$ reductions. This improves the results of prior work for Haar random circuits both in terms of the error scaling and the power of reductions. Next, we consider random $p=1$ QAOA and IQP circuits and show that in the average-case, it is $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hard to approximate the output probability to within an additive error of $2^{-O(n)}$. For $p=1$ QAOA circuits, this work constitutes the first average-case hardness result for the problem of approximating output probabilities for random QAOA circuits, which include Sherrington-Kirkpatrick and Erdös-Renyi graphs. For IQP circuits, a consequence of our results is that approximating the Ising partition function with imaginary couplings to an additive error of $2^{-O(n)}$ is hard even in the average-case, which extends prior work on worst-case hardness of multiplicative approximation to Ising partition functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Predicting Gibbs State Expectation Values with Pure Thermal Shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05302</link>
    <author>Luuk Coopmans, Yuta Kikuchi, Marcello Benedetti</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The preparation and computation of many properties of quantum Gibbs states are essential for algorithms such as quantum semi-definite programming and quantum Boltzmann machines. We propose a quantum algorithm that can predict $M$ linear functions of an arbitrary Gibbs state with only $\mathcal{O}(\log{M})$ experimental measurements. Our main insight is that for sufficiently large systems we do not need to prepare the $n$-qubit mixed Gibbs state explicitly, but instead we can evolve a random $n$-qubit pure state in imaginary time. The result then follows by constructing classical shadows of these random pure states. We propose a quantum circuit that implements this algorithm by using quantum signal processing for the imaginary time evolution. We verify the algorithm numerically by simulating the circuit for a 10 spin-1/2 XXZ-Heisenberg model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Microwave-activated gates between a fluxonium and a transmon qubit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06203</link>
    <author>Alessandro Ciani, Boris M. Varbanov, Nicolas Jolly, Christian K. Andersen, Barbara M. Terhal</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose and analyze two types of microwave-activated gates between a fluxonium and a transmon qubit, namely a cross-resonance (CR) and a CPHASE gate. The large frequency difference between a transmon and a fluxonium makes the realization of a two-qubit gate challenging. For a medium-frequency fluxonium qubit, the transmon-fluxonium system allows for a cross-resonance effect mediated by the higher levels of the fluxonium over a wide range of transmon frequencies. This allows one to realize the cross-resonance gate by driving the fluxonium at the transmon frequency, mitigating typical problems of the cross-resonance gate in transmon-transmon chips related to frequency targeting and residual ZZ coupling. However, when the fundamental frequency of the fluxonium enters the low-frequency regime below 100 MHz, the cross-resonance effect decreases leading to long gate times. For this range of parameters, a fast microwave CPHASE gate can be implemented using the higher levels of the fluxonium. In both cases, we perform numerical simulations of the gate showing that a gate fidelity above 99% can be obtained with gate times between 100 and 300 ns. Next to a detailed gate analysis, we perform a study of chip yield for a surface code lattice of fluxonia and transmons interacting via the proposed cross-resonance gate. We find a much better yield as compared to a transmon-only architecture with the cross-resonance gate as native two-qubit gate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Rewindable Quantum Computation and Its Equivalence to Cloning and Adaptive Postselection</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05434</link>
    <author>Ryo Hiromasa, Akihiro Mizutani, Yuki Takeuchi, Seiichiro Tani</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We define rewinding operators that invert quantum measurements. Then, we define complexity classes ${\sf RwBQP}$, ${\sf CBQP}$, and ${\sf AdPostBQP}$ as sets of decision problems solvable by polynomial-size quantum circuits with a polynomial number of rewinding operators, cloning operators, and (adaptive) postselections, respectively. Our main result is that ${\sf BPP}^{\sf PP}\subseteq{\sf RwBQP}={\sf CBQP}={\sf AdPostBQP}\subseteq{\sf PSPACE}$. As a byproduct of this result, we show that any problem in ${\sf PostBQP}$ can be solved with only postselections of outputs whose probabilities are at least some constant. Under the strongly believed assumption that the shortest independent vectors problem cannot be efficiently solved with quantum computers, we also show that a single rewinding operator is sufficient to achieve a task that is intractable for quantum computation. In addition, we consider rewindable Clifford and instantaneous quantum polynomial time circuits.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>