<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Learning Distributions over Quantum Measurement Outcomes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03007</link>
    <author>Weiyuan Gong, Scott Aaronson</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shadow tomography for quantum states provides a sample efficient approach for predicting the properties of quantum systems when the properties are restricted to expectation values of $2$-outcome POVMs. However, these shadow tomography procedures yield poor bounds if there are more than 2 outcomes per measurement. In this paper, we consider a general problem of learning properties from unknown quantum states: given an unknown $d$-dimensional quantum state $\rho$ and $M$ unknown quantum measurements $\mathcal{M}_1,...,\mathcal{M}_M$ with $K\geq 2$ outcomes, estimating the probability distribution for applying $\mathcal{M}_i$ on $\rho$ to within total variation distance $\epsilon$. Compared to the special case when $K=2$, we need to learn unknown distributions instead of values. We develop an online shadow tomography procedure that solves this problem with high success probability requiring $\tilde{O}(K\log^2M\log d/\epsilon^4)$ copies of $\rho$. We further prove an information-theoretic lower bound that at least $\Omega(\min\{d^2,K+\log M\}/\epsilon^2)$ copies of $\rho$ are required to solve this problem with high success probability. Our shadow tomography procedure requires sample complexity with only logarithmic dependence on $M$ and $d$ and is sample-optimal for the dependence on $K$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Concentration bounds for quantum states and limitations on the QAOA from polynomial approximations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02715</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Tony Metger</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove concentration bounds for the following classes of quantum states: (i) output states of shallow quantum circuits, answering an open question from [DPMRF22]; (ii) injective matrix product states; (iii) output states of dense Hamiltonian evolution, i.e. states of the form $e^{\iota H^{(p)}} \cdots e^{\iota H^{(1)}} |\psi_0\rangle$ for any $n$-qubit product state $|\psi_0\rangle$, where each $H^{(i)}$ can be any local commuting Hamiltonian satisfying a norm constraint, including dense Hamiltonians with interactions between any qubits. Our proofs use polynomial approximations to show that these states are close to local operators. This implies that the distribution of the Hamming weight of a computational basis measurement (and of other related observables) concentrates. An example of (iii) are the states produced by the quantum approximate optimisation algorithm (QAOA). Using our concentration results for these states, we show that for a random spin model, the QAOA can only succeed with negligible probability even at super-constant level $p = o(\log \log n)$. This gives the first limitations on the QAOA on dense instances at super-constant level, improving upon the recent result [BGMZ22].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved maximum-likelihood quantum amplitude estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03321</link>
    <author>Adam Callison, Dan Browne</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum amplitude estimation is a key subroutine in a number of powerful quantum algorithms, including quantum-enhanced Monte Carlo simulation and quantum machine learning. Maximum-likelihood quantum amplitude estimation (MLQAE) is one of a number of recent approaches that employ much simpler quantum circuits than the original algorithm based on quantum phase estimation. In this article, we deepen the analysis of MLQAE to put the algorithm in a more prescriptive form, including scenarios where quantum circuit depth is limited. In the process, we observe and explain particular ranges of `exceptional' values of the target amplitude for which the algorithm fails to achieve the desired precision. We then propose and numerically validate a heuristic modification to the algorithm to overcome this problem, bringing the algorithm even closer to being useful as a practical subroutine on near- and mid-term quantum hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Simulation on Noisy Superconducting Quantum Computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02795</link>
    <author>Kaelyn J. Ferris, A. J. Rasmusson, Nicholas T. Bronn, Olivia Lanes</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum simulation is a potentially powerful application of quantum computing, holding the promise to be able to emulate interesting quantum systems beyond the reach of classical computing methods. Despite such promising applications, and the increase in active research, there is little introductory literature or demonstrations of the topic at a graduate or undergraduate student level. This artificially raises the barrier to entry into the field which already has a limited workforce, both in academia and industry. Here we present an introduction to simulating quantum systems, starting with a chosen Hamiltonian, overviewing state preparation and evolution, and discussing measurement methods. We provide an example simulation by measuring the state dynamics of a tight-binding model with disorder by time evolution using the Suzuki-Trotter decomposition. Furthermore, error mitigation and noise reduction are essential to executing quantum algorithms on currently available noisy quantum computers. We discuss and demonstrate various error mitigation and circuit optimization techniques that significantly improve performance. All source code is freely available, and we encourage the reader to build upon it.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reversing unknown qubit-unitary operation, deterministically and exactly</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02907</link>
    <author>Satoshi Yoshida, Akihito Soeda, Mio Murao</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this Letter, we report a deterministic and exact protocol to reverse any unknown qubit-unitary operation. We derive the Choi matrix representing a quantum circuit transforming four copies of a qubit-unitary operation to its inverse operation by imposing the $\mathrm{SU}(2) \times \mathrm{SU}(2)$ symmetry on the Choi matrix. We also present the semidefinite programming to search deterministic exact unitary inversion for an arbitrary dimension. The large search space including all possible protocols is reduced to the space of the Choi matrices with the $\mathrm{SU}(d)\times \mathrm{SU}(d)$ symmetry.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>