<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Detecting entanglement in quantum many-body systems via permutation moments</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08391</link>
    <author>Zhenhuan Liu, Yifan Tang, Hao Dai, Pengyu Liu, Shu Chen, Xiongfeng Ma</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Multipartite entanglement plays an essential role in both quantum information science and many-body physics. Due to the exponentially large dimension and complex geometric structure of the state space, the detection of entanglement in many-body systems is extremely challenging in reality. Conventional means, like entanglement witness and entropy criterion, either highly depend on the prior knowledge of the studied systems or the detection capability is relatively weak. In this work, we propose a framework for designing multipartite entanglement criteria based on permutation moments, which have an effective implementation with either the generalized control-SWAP quantum circuits or the random unitary techniques. These criteria show strong detection capability in the multi-qubit Ising model with a long-range $XY$ Hamiltonian. The quantities associated with these criteria have clear physical meaning and can be used as entanglement quantifiers, with which we show the entanglement scaling transition in a quantum dynamical phase transition. Furthermore, our framework can also be generalized to detect the much more complicated entanglement structure in quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Intrinsic randomness under general quantum measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08624</link>
    <author>Hao Dai, Boyang Chen, Xingjian Zhang, Xiongfeng Ma</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum measurements can produce randomness arising from the uncertainty principle. When measuring a state with von Neumann measurements, the intrinsic randomness can be quantified by the quantum coherence of the state on the measurement basis. Unlike projection measurements, there are additional and possibly hidden degrees of freedom in apparatus for generic measurements. We propose an adversary scenario for general measurements with arbitrary input states, based on which, we characterize the intrinsic randomness. Interestingly, we discover that under certain measurements, such as the symmetric and information-complete measurement, all states have nonzero randomness, inspiring a new design of source-independent random number generators without state characterization. Furthermore, our results show that intrinsic randomness can quantify coherence under general measurements, which generalizes the result in the standard resource theory of state coherence.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A constant lower bound for any quantum protocol for secure function evaluation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08268</link>
    <author>Sarah Osborn, Jamie Sikora</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Secure function evaluation is a two-party cryptographic primitive where Bob computes a function of Alice's and his respective inputs, and both hope to keep their inputs private from the other party. It has been proven that perfect (or near perfect) security is impossible, even for quantum protocols. We generalize this no-go result by exhibiting a constant lower bound on the cheating probabilities for any quantum protocol for secure function evaluation, and present many applications from oblivious transfer to the millionaire's problem. Constant lower bounds are of practical interest since they imply the impossibility to arbitrarily amplify the security of quantum protocols by any means.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error-Mitigated Simulation of Quantum Many-Body Scars on Quantum Computers with Pulse-Level Control</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08291</link>
    <author>I-Chi Chen, Benjamin Burdick, Yongxin Yao, Peter P. Orth, Thomas Iadecola</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum many-body scars are an intriguing dynamical regime in which quantum systems exhibit coherent dynamics and long-range correlations when prepared in certain initial states. We use this combination of coherence and many-body correlations to benchmark the performance of present-day quantum computing devices by using them to simulate the dynamics of an antiferromagnetic initial state in mixed-field Ising chains of up to 19 sites. In addition to calculating the dynamics of local observables, we also calculate the Loschmidt echo and a nontrivial connected correlation function that witnesses long-range many-body correlations in the scarred dynamics. We find coherent dynamics to persist over up to 40 Trotter steps even in the presence of various sources of error. To obtain these results, we leverage a variety of error mitigation techniques including noise tailoring, zero-noise extrapolation, dynamical decoupling, and physically motivated postselection of measurement results. Crucially, we also find that using pulse-level control to implement the Ising interaction yields a substantial improvement over the standard CNOT-based compilation of this interaction. Our results demonstrate the power of error mitigation techniques and pulse-level control to probe many-body coherence and correlation effects on present-day quantum hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms from fluctuation theorems: Thermal-state preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08882</link>
    <author>Zoe Holmes, Gopikrishnan Muraleedharan, Rolando D. Somma, Yigit Subasi, Burak Şahinoğlu</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fluctuation theorems provide a correspondence between properties of quantum systems in thermal equilibrium and a work distribution arising in a non-equilibrium process that connects two quantum systems with Hamiltonians $H_0$ and $H_1=H_0+V$. Building upon these theorems, we present a quantum algorithm to prepare a purification of the thermal state of $H_1$ at inverse temperature $\beta \ge 0$ starting from a purification of the thermal state of $H_0$. The complexity of the quantum algorithm, given by the number of uses of certain unitaries, is $\tilde {\cal O}(e^{\beta (\Delta \! A- w_l)/2})$, where $\Delta \! A$ is the free-energy difference between $H_1$ and $H_0,$ and $w_l$ is a work cutoff that depends on the properties of the work distribution and the approximation error $\epsilon>0$. If the non-equilibrium process is trivial, this complexity is exponential in $\beta \|V\|$, where $\|V\|$ is the spectral norm of $V$. This represents a significant improvement of prior quantum algorithms that have complexity exponential in $\beta \|H_1\|$ in the regime where $\|V\|\ll \|H_1\|$. The dependence of the complexity in $\epsilon$ varies according to the structure of the quantum systems. It can be exponential in $1/\epsilon$ in general, but we show it to be sublinear in $1/\epsilon$ if $H_0$ and $H_1$ commute, or polynomial in $1/\epsilon$ if $H_0$ and $H_1$ are local spin systems. The possibility of applying a unitary that drives the system out of equilibrium allows one to increase the value of $w_l$ and improve the complexity even further. To this end, we analyze the complexity for preparing the thermal state of the transverse field Ising model using different non-equilibrium unitary processes and see significant complexity improvements.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>