<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The quantum low-rank approximation problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00811</link>
    <author>Nic Ezzell, Zoë Holmes, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a quantum version of the famous low-rank approximation problem. Specifically, we consider the distance $D(\rho,\sigma)$ between two normalized quantum states, $\rho$ and $\sigma$, where the rank of $\sigma$ is constrained to be at most $R$. For both the trace distance and Hilbert-Schmidt distance, we analytically solve for the optimal state $\sigma$ that minimizes this distance. For the Hilbert-Schmidt distance, the unique optimal state is $\sigma = \tau_R +N_R$, where $\tau_R = \Pi_R \rho \Pi_R$ is given by projecting $\rho$ onto its $R$ principal components with projector $\Pi_R$, and $N_R$ is a normalization factor given by $N_R = \frac{1- \text{Tr}(\tau_R)}{R}\Pi_R$. For the trace distance, this state is also optimal but not uniquely optimal, and we provide the full set of states that are optimal. We briefly discuss how our results have application for performing principal component analysis (PCA) via variational optimization on quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Boson bunching is not maximized by indistinguishable particles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01306</link>
    <author>Benoît Seron, Leonardo Novo, Nicolas J. Cerf</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Boson bunching is amongst the most remarkable features of quantum physics. A celebrated example in optics is the Hong-Ou-Mandel effect, where the bunching of two photons arises from a destructive quantum interference between the trajectories where they both either cross a beam splitter or are reflected. This effect takes its roots in the indistinguishability of identical photons. Hence, it is generally admitted -- and experimentally verified -- that bunching vanishes as soon as photons can be distinguished, e.g., when they occupy distinct time bins or have different polarizations. Here we disproof this alleged straightforward link between indistinguishability and bunching by exploiting a recent finding in the theory of matrix permanents. We exhibit a family of optical circuits where the bunching of photons into two modes can be significantly boosted by making them partially distinguishable via an appropriate polarization pattern. This boosting effect is already visible in a 7-photon interferometric process, making the observation of this phenomenon within reach of current photonic technology. This unexpected behavior questions our understanding of multiparticle interference in the grey zone between indistinguishable bosons and classical particles.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time-frequency as quantum continuous variables</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01220</link>
    <author>Nicolas Fabre, Camille Nous, Arne Keller, Pérola Milman</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a second quantization description of frequency-based continuous variables quantum computation in the subspace of single photons. For this, we define frequency and time operators using the free field Hamiltonian and its Fourier transform, and show that these observables, when restricted to the one photon per mode subspace, reproduce the canonical position-momentum commutation relations. As a consequence, frequency and time operators can be used to define a universal set of gates in this particular subspace. We discuss the physical implementation of these gates as well as their effect on single photon states, and show that frequency and time variables can also be used to implement continuous variables quantum information protocols, in the same way than polarization is currently used as a two-dimensional quantum variable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Holographic quantum simulation of entanglement renormalization circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00886</link>
    <author>Sajant Anand, Johannes Hauschild, Yuxuan Zhang, Andrew C. Potter, Michael P. Zaletel</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While standard approaches to quantum simulation require a number of qubits proportional to the number of simulated particles, current noisy quantum computers are limited to tens of qubits. With the technique of holographic quantum simulation, a $D$-dimensional system can be simulated with a $D{\rm -}1$-dimensional subset of qubits, enabling the study of systems significantly larger than current quantum computers. Using circuits derived from the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (MERA), we accurately prepare the ground state of an $L=32$ critical, non-integrable perturbed Ising model and measure long-range correlations on the 10 qubit Quantinuum trapped ion computer. We introduce generalized MERA (gMERA) networks that interpolate between MERA and matrix product state networks and demonstrate that gMERA can capture far longer correlations than a MERA with the same number of qubits, at the expense of greater circuit depth. Finally, we perform noisy simulations of these two network ansätze and find that the optimal choice of network depends on noise level, available qubits, and the state to be represented.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Achieving Heisenberg Scaling on Measurement of A Three-Qubit System via Quantum Error Correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01179</link>
    <author>Le Hu, Shengshi Pang, Andrew Jordan</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In many-body quantum systems, the quantum Fisher information an observer can obtain is susceptible to decoherence. Consequently, quantum enhanced metrology, such as Heisenberg scaling, cannot usually be achieved. We show, via two distinct methods, that by applying periodic quantum error corrections, we can achieve the Heisenberg scaling for an extended period of time on a three-qubit Tavis-Cumming Model, where three two-level atoms interact with a single cavity mode, under certain approximations. The generalization to arbitrary number of atoms case is also discussed.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>