<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A lower bound on the space overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00119</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Alexander Müller-Hermes, Ala Shayeghi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The threshold theorem is a fundamental result in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation stating that arbitrarily long quantum computations can be performed with a polylogarithmic overhead provided the noise level is below a constant level. A recent work by Fawzi, Grospellier and Leverrier (FOCS 2018) building on a result by Gottesman (QIC 2013) has shown that the space overhead can be asymptotically reduced to a constant independent of the circuit provided we only consider circuits with a length bounded by a polynomial in the width. In this work, using a minimal model for quantum fault tolerance, we establish a general lower bound on the space overhead required to achieve fault tolerance. For any non-unitary qubit channel $\mathcal{N}$ and any quantum fault tolerance schemes against $\mathrm{i.i.d.}$ noise modeled by $\mathcal{N}$, we prove a lower bound of $\max\left\{\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})^{-1}n,\alpha_\mathcal{N} \log T\right\}$ on the number of physical qubits, for circuits of length $T$ and width $n$. Here, $\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})$ denotes the quantum capacity of $\mathcal{N}$ and $\alpha_\mathcal{N}>0$ is a constant only depending on the channel $\mathcal{N}$. In our model, we allow for qubits to be replaced by fresh ones during the execution of the circuit and we allow classical computation to be free and perfect. This improves upon results that assumed classical computations to be also affected by noise, and that sometimes did not allow for fresh qubits to be added. Along the way, we prove an exponential upper bound on the maximal length of fault-tolerant quantum computation with amplitude damping noise resolving a conjecture by Ben-Or, Gottesman, and Hassidim (2013).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum machine learning with subspace states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00054</link>
    <author>Iordanis Kerenidis, Anupam Prakash</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new approach for quantum linear algebra based on quantum subspace states and present three new quantum machine learning algorithms. The first is a quantum determinant sampling algorithm that samples from the distribution $\Pr[S]= det(X_{S}X_{S}^{T})$ for $|S|=d$ using $O(nd)$ gates and with circuit depth $O(d\log n)$. The state of art classical algorithm for the task requires $O(d^{3})$ operations \citederezinski2019minimax. The second is a quantum singular value estimation algorithm for compound matrices $\mathcal{A}^{k}$, the speedup for this algorithm is potentially exponential. It decomposes a $\binom{n}{k}$ dimensional vector of order-$k$ correlations into a linear combination of subspace states corresponding to $k$-tuples of singular vectors of $A$. The third algorithm reduces exponentially the depth of circuits used in quantum topological data analysis from $O(n)$ to $O(\log n)$. Our basic tool are quantum subspace states, defined as $|Col(X)\rangle = \sum_{S\subset [n], |S|=d} det(X_{S}) |S\rangle$ for matrices $X \in \mathbb{R}^{n \times d}$ such that $X^{T} X = I_{d}$, that encode $d$-dimensional subspaces of $\mathbb{R}^{n}$. We develop two efficient state preparation techniques, the first using Givens circuits uses the representation of a subspace as a sequence of Givens rotations, while the second uses efficient implementations of unitaries $\Gamma(x) = \sum_{i} x_{i} Z^{\otimes (i-1)} \otimes X \otimes I^{n-i}$ with $O(\log n)$ depth circuits that we term Clifford loaders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Correction with Quantum Autoencoders</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00555</link>
    <author>David F. Locher, Lorenzo Cardarelli, Markus Müller</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Active quantum error correction is a central ingredient to achieve robust quantum processors. In this paper we investigate the potential of quantum machine learning for quantum error correction. Specifically, we demonstrate how quantum neural networks, in the form of quantum autoencoders, can be trained to learn optimal strategies for active detection and correction of errors, including spatially correlated computational errors as well as qubit losses. We highlight that the denoising capabilities of quantum autoencoders are not limited to the protection of specific states but extend to the entire logical codespace. We also show that quantum neural networks can be used to discover new logical encodings that are optimally adapted to the underlying noise. Moreover, we find that, even in the presence of moderate noise in the quantum autoencoders themselves, they may still be successfully used to perform beneficial quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dimension towers of SICs. II. Some constructions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00600</link>
    <author>Ingemar Bengtsson, Basudha Srivastava</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A SIC is a maximal equiangular tight frame in a finite dimensional Hilbert space. Given a SIC in dimension $d$, there is good evidence that there always exists an aligned SIC in dimension $d(d-2)$, having predictable symmetries and smaller equiangular tight frames embedded in them. We provide a recipe for how to calculate sets of vectors in dimension $d(d-2)$ that share these properties. They consist of maximally entangled vectors in certain subspaces defined by the numbers entering the $d$ dimensional SIC. However, the construction contains free parameters and we have not proven that they can always be chosen so that one of these sets of vectors is a SIC. We give some worked examples that, we hope, may suggest to the reader how our construction can be improved. For simplicity we restrict ourselves to the case of odd dimensions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>How quantum nonlocality without entanglement witnesses classical communication without causal order</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00440</link>
    <author>Ravi Kunjwal, Ämin Baumeler</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show a correspondence between quantum nonlocality without entanglement and logically consistent classical processes without causal order. Three parties with access to a noncausal classical process -- the AF/BW process -- can perfectly discriminate the states in an ensemble -- the SHIFT ensemble -- exhibiting quantum nonlocality without entanglement, something impossible with local operations and classical communication (LOCC): The LOCC restriction implicitly assumes causal classical communication. This provides an operational interpretation of the AF/BW process as a noncausal information-theoretic resource. From a foundational perspective, this means that the ability to perfectly discriminate quantum states in the SHIFT ensemble via local operations and classical communication would serve as an operational witness of noncausality. We then generalize our result to show how any Boolean classical process that maximally violates causal order can be transformed to an ensemble of states that exhibits quantum nonlocality without entanglement. Since multipartite generalizations of the AF/BW process are known, this yields novel multiqubit ensembles of quantum nonlocality without entanglement, which is of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>