<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Surviving The Barren Plateau in Variational Quantum Circuits with Bayesian Learning Initialization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.02464</link>
    <author>Ali Rad, Alireza Seif, Norbert M. Linke</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum-classical hybrid algorithms are seen as a promising strategy for solving practical problems on quantum computers in the near term. While this approach reduces the number of qubits and operations required from the quantum machine, it places a heavy load on a classical optimizer. While often under-appreciated, the latter is a computationally hard task due to the barren plateau phenomenon in parameterized quantum circuits. The absence of guiding features like gradients renders conventional optimization strategies ineffective as the number of qubits increases. Here, we introduce the fast-and-slow algorithm, which uses Bayesian Learning to identify a promising region in parameter space. This is used to initialize a fast local optimizer to find the global optimum point efficiently. We illustrate the effectiveness of this method on the Bars-and-Stripes (BAS) quantum generative model, which has been studied on several quantum hardware platforms. Our results move variational quantum algorithms closer to their envisioned applications in quantum chemistry, combinatorial optimization, and quantum simulation problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms for estimating quantum entropies</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.02386</link>
    <author>Youle Wang, Benchi Zhao, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The von Neumann and quantum Rényi entropies characterize fundamental properties of quantum systems and lead to theoretical and practical applications in many fields. Quantum algorithms for estimating quantum entropies, using a quantum query model that prepares the purification of the input state, have been established in the literature. However, constructing such a model is almost as hard as state tomography. In this paper, we propose quantum algorithms to estimate the von Neumann and quantum $\alpha$-Rényi entropies of an $n$-qubit quantum state $\rho$ using independent copies of the input state. We also show how to efficiently construct the quantum circuits for quantum entropy estimation using primitive single/two-qubit gates. We prove that the number of required copies scales polynomially in $1/\epsilon$ and $1/\Lambda$, where $\epsilon$ denotes the additive precision and $\Lambda$ denotes the lower bound on all non-zero eigenvalues. Notably, our method outperforms previous methods in the aspect of practicality since it does not require any quantum query oracles, which are usually necessary for previous methods. Furthermore, we conduct experiments to show the efficacy of our algorithms to single-qubit states and study the noise robustness. We also discuss the applications to some quantum states of practical interest as well as some meaningful tasks such as quantum Gibbs state preparation and entanglement estimation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gluon Digitization via Character Expansion for Quantum Computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.02330</link>
    <author>Yao Ji, Henry Lamm, Shuchen Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Efficient digitization is required for quantum simulations of gauge theories. Schemes based on discrete subgroups use a smaller, fixed number of qubits at the cost of systematic errors. We systematize this approach by deriving the single plaquette action through matching the continuous group action to that of a discrete one via group character expansions modulo the field fluctuation contributions. We accompany this scheme by simulations of pure gauge over the largest discrete crystal-like subgroup of $SU(3)$ up to the fifth-order in the coupling constant.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The SEDIGISM survey: Molecular cloud morphology. I. Classification and star formation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.02504</link>
    <author>K. R. Neralwar, D. Colombo, A. Duarte-Cabral, J. S. Urquhart, M. Mattern, F. Wyrowski, K. M. Menten, P. Barnes, A. Sanchez-Monge, H. Beuther, A. J. Rigby, P. Mazumdar, D. Eden, T. Csengeri, C.L. Dobbs, V. S. Veena, S. Neupane, T. Henning, F. Schuller, S. Leurini, et al (5)</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present one of the very first extensive classifications of a large sample of molecular clouds based on their morphology. This is achieved using a recently published catalogue of 10663 clouds obtained from the first data release of the SEDIGISM survey. The clouds are classified into four different morphologies by visual inspection and using an automated algorithm -- J plots. The visual inspection also serves as a test for the J plots algorithm, as this is the first time it has been used on molecular gas. Generally, it has been found that the structure of molecular clouds is highly filamentary and our observations indeed verify that most of our molecular clouds are elongated structures. Based on our visual classification of the 10663 SEDIGISM clouds, 15% are ring-like, 57% are elongated, 15% are concentrated and 10% are clumpy clouds. The remaining clouds do not belong to any of these morphology classes and are termed unclassified. We compare the SEDIGISM molecular clouds with structures identified through other surveys, i.e. ATLASGAL elongated structures and the bubbles from Milky Way Project (MWP). We find that many of the ATLASGAL and MWP structures are velocity coherent. ATLASGAL elongated structures overlap with ~ 21% of the SEDIGISM elongated structures (elongated and clumpy clouds) and MWP bubbles overlap with ~ 25% of the SEDIGISM ring-like clouds. We also analyse the star-formation associated with different cloud morphologies using two different techniques. The first technique examines star formation efficiency (SFE) and the dense gas fraction (DGF), based on SEDIGISM clouds and ATLASGAL clumps data. The second technique uses the high-mass star formation (HMSF) threshold for molecular clouds. The results indicate that clouds with ring-like and clumpy morphologies show a higher degree of star formation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>HyperTransformer: A Textural and Spectral Feature Fusion Transformer for Pansharpening</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.02503</link>
    <author>Wele Gedara Chaminda Bandara, Vishal M. Patel</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Pansharpening aims to fuse a registered high-resolution panchromatic image (PAN) with a low-resolution hyperspectral image (LR-HSI) to generate an enhanced HSI with high spectral and spatial resolution. Existing pansharpening approaches neglect using an attention mechanism to transfer HR texture features from PAN to LR-HSI features, resulting in spatial and spectral distortions. In this paper, we present a novel attention mechanism for pansharpening called HyperTransformer, in which features of LR-HSI and PAN are formulated as queries and keys in a transformer, respectively. HyperTransformer consists of three main modules, namely two separate feature extractors for PAN and HSI, a multi-head feature soft attention module, and a spatial-spectral feature fusion module. Such a network improves both spatial and spectral quality measures of the pansharpened HSI by learning cross-feature space dependencies and long-range details of PAN and LR-HSI. Furthermore, HyperTransformer can be utilized across multiple spatial scales at the backbone for obtaining improved performance. Extensive experiments conducted on three widely used datasets demonstrate that HyperTransformer achieves significant improvement over the state-of-the-art methods on both spatial and spectral quality measures. Implementation code and pre-trained weights can be accessed at https://github.com/wgcban/HyperTransformer.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>