<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Fragile boundaries of tailored surface codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04948</link>
    <author>Oscar Higgott, Thomas C. Bohdanowicz, Aleksander Kubica, Steven T. Flammia, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Biased noise is common in physical qubits, and tailoring a quantum code to the bias by locally modifying stabilizers or changing boundary conditions has been shown to greatly increase error correction thresholds. In this work, we explore the challenges of using a specific tailored code, the XY surface code, for fault-tolerant quantum computation. We introduce an efficient and fault-tolerant decoder, belief-matching, which we show has good performance for biased circuit-level noise. Using this decoder, we find that for moderately biased noise, the XY surface code has a higher threshold and lower overhead than the square CSS surface code, however it performs worse when below threshold than the rectangular CSS surface code. We identify a contributor to the reduced performance that we call fragile boundary errors. These are string-like errors that can occur along spatial or temporal boundaries in planar architectures or during logical state preparation and measurement. While we make partial progress towards mitigating these errors by deforming the boundaries of the XY surface code, our work suggests that fragility could remain a significant obstacle, even for other tailored codes. We expect belief-matching will have other uses, and find that it increases the threshold of the surface code to 0.940(3)% in the presence of circuit-level depolarising noise, compared to 0.817(5)% for a minimum-weight perfect matching decoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Information recoverability of noisy quantum states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04862</link>
    <author>Xuanqiang Zhao, Benchi Zhao, Zihan Xia, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classical information, also known as shadow information, carried by quantum states could be corrupted as they undergo undesirable noises modelled by quantum channels. Due to quantum channels' destructive nature, a fundamental problem in quantum information theory is how well we can retrieve information from noisy quantum states. In this work, we introduce a systematic framework to quantitatively study this problem. First, we prove that classical information can be retrieved if and only if the querying observable is in the image of the whole observable space under the channel's adjoint. Second, we further define the dimension of the evolved observable space as the quantum channel's effective shadow dimension that quantifies the information recoverability of the channel. This quantity can be computed as the rank of a matrix derived from the channel's Kraus operators, and it induces the shadow destructivity as a measure with meaningful properties. Third, we resolve the minimum cost of retrieving a piece of shadow information from the required number of copies of a noisy state. We in particular show that the optimal cost and the corresponding protocol are efficiently computable by semidefinite programming. As applications, we derive the ultimate limits on shadow retrieving costs for generalized amplitude damping channels and mixed Pauli channels and employ the corresponding protocol to mitigate errors in tasks of ground state energy estimation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient quantum gate decomposition via adaptive circuit compression</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04426</link>
    <author>Péter Rakyta, Zoltán Zimborás</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work, we report on a novel quantum gate approximation algorithm based on the application of parametric two-qubit gates in the synthesis process. The utilization of these parametric two-qubit gates in the circuit design allows us to transform the discrete combinatorial problem of circuit synthesis into an optimization problem over continuous variables. The circuit is then compressed by a sequential removal of two-qubit gates from the design, while the remaining building blocks are continuously adapted to the reduced gate structure by iterated learning cycles. We implemented the developed algorithm in the SQUANDER software package and benchmarked it against several state-of-the-art quantum gate synthesis tools. Our numerical experiments revealed outstanding circuit compression capabilities of our compilation algorithm providing the most optimal gate count in the majority of the addressed quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Snowmass White Paper: New ideas for many-body quantum systems from string theory and black holes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04718</link>
    <author>Mike Blake, Yingfei Gu, Sean A. Hartnoll, Hong Liu, Andrew Lucas, Krishna Rajagopal, Brian Swingle, Beni Yoshida</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>During the last two decades many new insights into the dynamics of strongly coupled quantum many-body systems have been obtained using gauge/gravity duality, with black holes often playing a universal role. In this white paper we summarize the results obtained and offer some outlook for future developments, including the ongoing mutually beneficial feedback loop with the study of more general, not necessarily holographic, quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Detecting topological order from modular transformations of ground states on the torus</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04329</link>
    <author>Zhuan Li, Roger S.K. Mong</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ground states encode the information of the topological phases of a 2-dimensional system, which makes them crucial in determining the associated topological quantum field theory (TQFT). Most numerical methods for detecting the TQFT relied on the use of minimum entanglement states (MESs), extracting the anyon mutual statistics and self statistics via overlaps and/or the entanglement spectra. The MESs are the eigenstates of the Wilson loop operators, and are labeled by the anyons corresponding to their eigenvalues. Here we revisit the definition of the Wilson loop operators and MESs. We derive the modular transformation of the ground states purely from the Wilson loop algebra, and as a result, the modular $S$- and $T$-matrices naturally show up in the overlap of MESs. Importantly, we show that due to the phase degree of freedom of the Wilson loop operators, the MES-anyon assignment is not unique. This ambiguity obstructs our attempt to detect the topological order, that is, there exist different TQFTs that cannot be distinguished solely by the overlap of MESs. In this paper, we provide the upper limit of the information one may obtain from the overlap of MESs without other additional structure. Finally, we show that if the phase is enriched by rotational symmetry, there may be additional TQFT information that can be extracted from overlap of MESs.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>