<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum supremacy in mechanical tasks: projectiles, rockets and quantum backflow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00725</link>
    <author>David Trillo, Thinh P. Le, Miguel Navascues</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a scenario where a non-relativistic one-dimensional quantum particle is prepared in some bounded region of space and left to propagate freely. After a certain amount of time, we check if the particle has reached some distant target region. We find that there exist "ultrafast" ("ultraslow") quantum states, whose probability of arrival is greater (smaller) than that of any classical system prepared in the same region with the same momentum distribution. We prove that the maximum possible difference between quantum and optimal classical arrival probabilities for projectiles, as well as for self-propelling particles or rockets, is limited by the Bracken-Melloy constant $c_{bm}$, introduced in $1969$ to characterize the maximum expression of the phenomenon known as quantum backflow. This mathematical correspondence extends to other examples of mechanical effects with a quantum advantage, whose study we advance by deriving the first rigorous upper bound $c_{bm} \leq 0.0725$. We also prove that the hard limit given by $c_{bm}$ can be overcome in a variant of the original projectile scenario: if the classical particle is required to possess, not just the same momentum distribution as the quantum particle, but also the same position distribution, then the difference between arrival probabilities can reach $0.1228$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Software Tools for Decoding Quantum Low-Density Parity Check Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01180</link>
    <author>Lucas Berent, Lukas Burgholzer, Robert Wille</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Error Correction (QEC) is an essential field of research towards the realization of large-scale quantum computers. On the theoretical side, a lot of effort is put into designing error-correcting codes that protect quantum data from errors, which inevitably happen due to the noisy nature of quantum hardware and quantum bits (qubits). Protecting data with an error-correcting code necessitates means to recover the original data, given a potentially corrupted data set-a task referred to as decoding. It is vital that decoding algorithms can recover error-free states in an efficient manner. While theoretical properties of recent QEC methods have been extensively studied, good techniques to analyze their performance in practically more relevant settings is still a widely unexplored area. In this work, we propose a set of software tools that allows to numerically experiment with so-called Quantum Low-Density Parity Check codes (QLDPC codes)-a broad class of codes, some of which have recently been shown to be asymptotically good. Based on that, we provide an implementation of a general decoder for QLDPC codes. On top of that, we propose an efficient heuristic decoder that tackles the runtime bottlenecks of the general QLDPC decoder while still maintaining comparable decoding performance. These tools eventually allow to confirm theoretical results around QLDPC codes in a more practical setting and showcase the value of software tools (in addition to theoretical considerations) for investigating codes for practical applications. The resulting tool, which is publicly available at https://github.com/lucasberent/qecc under the MIT license, is meant to provide a playground for the search for "practically good" quantum codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Transition states and greedy exploration of the QAOA optimization landscape</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01159</link>
    <author>Stefan H. Sack, Raimel A. Medina, Richard Kueng, Maksym Serbyn</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The QAOA is a variational quantum algorithm, where a quantum computer implements a variational ansatz consisting of p layers of alternating unitary operators and a classical computer is used to optimize the variational parameters. For a random initialization the optimization typically leads to local minima with poor performance, motivating the search for initialization strategies of QAOA variational parameters. Although numerous heuristic intializations were shown to have a good numerical performance, an analytical understanding remains evasive. Inspired by the study of energy landscapes, in this work we focus on so-called transition states (TS) that are saddle points with a unique negative curvature direction that connects to local minima. Starting from a local minimum of QAOA with p layers, we analytically construct 2p + 1 TS for QAOA with p + 1 layers. These TS connect to new local minima, all of which are guaranteed to lower the energy compared to the minimum found for p layers. We introduce a Greedy procedure to effectively maneuver the exponentially increasing number of TS and corresponding local minima. The performance of our procedure matches the best available initialization strategy, and in addition provides a guarantee for the minimal energy to decrease with an increasing number of layers p. Generalization of analytic TS and the Greedy approach to other ansätze may provide a universal framework for initialization of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing quantum circuit parameters via SDP</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00789</link>
    <author>Eunou Lee</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In recent years, parameterized quantum circuits have become a major tool to design quantum algorithms for optimization problems. The challenge in fully taking advantage of a given family of parameterized circuits lies in finding a good set of parameters in a non-convex landscape that can grow exponentially to the number of parameters. We introduce a new framework for optimizing parameterized quantum circuits: round SDP solutions to circuit parameters. Within this framework, we propose an algorithm that produces approximate solutions for a quantum optimization problem called Quantum Max Cut. The rounding algorithm runs in polynomial time to the number of parameters regardless of the underlying interaction graph. The resulting 0.562-approximation algorithm for generic instances of Quantum Max Cut improves on the previously known best algorithms, which give approximation ratios of less than 0.54.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decohering Tensor Network Quantum Machine Learning Models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01195</link>
    <author>Haoran Liao, Ian Convy, Zhibo Yang, K. Birgitta Whaley</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tensor network quantum machine learning (QML) models are promising applications on near-term quantum hardware. While decoherence of qubits is expected to decrease the performance of QML models, it is unclear to what extent the diminished performance can be compensated for by adding ancillas to the models and accordingly increasing the virtual bond dimension of the models. We investigate here the competition between decoherence and adding ancillas on the classification performance of two models, with an analysis of the decoherence effect from the perspective of regression. We present numerical evidence that the fully-decohered unitary tree tensor network (TTN) with two ancillas performs at least as well as the non-decohered unitary TTN, suggesting that it is beneficial to add at least two ancillas to the unitary TTN regardless of the amount of decoherence may be consequently introduced.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>