<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Lower bounds for learning quantum states with single-copy measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14438</link>
    <author>Angus Lowe, Ashwin Nayak</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problems of quantum tomography and shadow tomography using measurements performed on individual, identical copies of an unknown $d$-dimensional state. We first revisit a known lower bound due to Haah et al. (2017) on quantum tomography with accuracy $\epsilon$ in trace distance, when the measurements choices are independent of previously observed outcomes (i.e., they are nonadaptive). We give a succinct proof of this result. This leads to stronger lower bounds when the learner uses measurements with a constant number of outcomes. In particular, this rigorously establishes the optimality of the folklore ``Pauli tomography" algorithm in terms of its sample complexity. We also derive novel bounds of $\Omega(r^2 d/\epsilon^2)$ and $\Omega(r^2 d^2/\epsilon^2)$ for learning rank $r$ states using arbitrary and constant-outcome measurements, respectively, in the nonadaptive case. In addition to the sample complexity, a resource of practical significance for learning quantum states is the number of different measurements used by an algorithm. We extend our lower bounds to the case where the learner performs possibly adaptive measurements from a fixed set of $\exp(O(d))$ measurements. This implies in particular that adaptivity does not give us any advantage using single-copy measurements that are efficiently implementable. We also obtain a similar bound in the case where the goal is to predict the expectation values of a given sequence of observables, a task known as shadow tomography. Finally, in the case of adaptive, single-copy measurements implementable with polynomial-size circuits, we prove that a straightforward strategy based on computing sample means of the given observables is optimal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Data Center: Theories and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14336</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Connor T. Hann, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we propose the Quantum Data Center (QDC), an architecture combining Quantum Random Access Memory (QRAM) and quantum networks. We give a precise definition of QDC, and discuss its possible realizations and extensions. We discuss applications of QDC in quantum computation, quantum communication, and quantum sensing, with a primary focus on QDC for $T$-gate resources, QDC for multi-party private quantum communication, and QDC for distributed sensing through data compression. We show that QDC will provide efficient, private, and fast services as a future version of data centers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fermionic tomography and learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14787</link>
    <author>Bryan O'Gorman</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shadow tomography via classical shadows is a state-of-the-art approach for estimating properties of a quantum state. We present a simplified, combinatorial analysis of a recently proposed instantiation of this approach based on the ensemble of unitaries that are both fermionic Gaussian and Clifford. Using this analysis, we derive a corrected expression for the variance of the estimator. We then show how this leads to efficient estimation protocols for the fidelity with a pure fermionic Gaussian state (provably) and for an $X$-like operator of the form ($|\mathbf 0\rangle\langle\psi|$ + h.c.) (via numerical evidence). We also construct much smaller ensembles of measurement bases that yield the exact same quantum channel, which may help with compilation. We use these tools to show that an $n$-electron, $m$-mode Slater determinant can be learned to within $\epsilon$ fidelity given $O(n^2 m^7 \log(m / \delta) / \epsilon^2)$ samples of the Slater determinant.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast quantum circuit cutting with randomized measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14734</link>
    <author>Angus Lowe, Matija Medvidović, Anthony Hayes, Lee J. O'Riordan, Thomas R. Bromley, Juan Miguel Arrazola, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a new method to extend the size of a quantum computation beyond the number of physical qubits available on a single device. This is accomplished by randomly inserting measure-and-prepare channels to express the output state of a large circuit as a separable state across distinct devices. Our method employs randomized measurements, resulting in a sample overhead that is $\widetilde{O}(4^k / \varepsilon ^2)$, where $\varepsilon $ is the accuracy of the computation and $k$ the number of parallel wires that are "cut" to obtain smaller sub-circuits. We also show an information-theoretic lower bound of $\Omega(2^k / \varepsilon ^2)$ for any comparable procedure. We use our techniques to show that circuits in the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) with $p$ entangling layers can be simulated by circuits on a fraction of the original number of qubits with an overhead that is roughly $2^{O(p\kappa)}$, where $\kappa$ is the size of a known balanced vertex separator of the graph which encodes the optimization problem. We obtain numerical evidence of practical speedups using our method applied to the QAOA, compared to prior work. Finally, we investigate the practical feasibility of applying the circuit cutting procedure to large-scale QAOA problems on clustered graphs by using a $30$-qubit simulator to evaluate the variational energy of a $129$-qubit problem as well as carry out a $62$-qubit optimization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast erasure decoder for a class of quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01002</link>
    <author>Nicholas Connolly, Vivien Londe, Anthony Leverrier, Nicolas Delfosse</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a decoder for the correction of erasures with hypergraph product codes, which form one of the most popular families of quantum LDPC codes. Our numerical simulations show that this decoder provides a close approximation of the maximum likelihood decoder that can be implemented in O(N^2) bit operations where N is the length of the quantum code. A probabilistic version of this decoder can be implemented in O(N^1.5) bit operations.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>