<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Sample optimal tomography of quantum Markov chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02240</link>
    <author>Li Gao, Nengkun Yu</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A state on a tripartite quantum system $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C} $ forms a Markov chain, i.e., quantum conditional independence, if it can be reconstructed from its marginal on $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}$ by a quantum operation from $\mathcal{H}_{B}$ to $\mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C}$ via the famous Petz map: a quantum Markov chain $\rho_{ABC}$ satisfies $\rho_{ABC}=\rho_{BC}^{1/2}(\rho_B^{-1/2}\rho_{AB}\rho_B^{-1/2}\otimes id_C)\rho_{BC}^{1/2}$. In this paper, we study the robustness of the Petz map for different metrics, i.e., the closeness of marginals implies the closeness of the Petz map outcomes. The robustness results are dimension-independent for infidelity $\delta$ and trace distance $\epsilon$. The applications of robustness results are The sample complexity of quantum Markov chain tomography, i.e., how many copies of an unknown quantum Markov chain are necessary and sufficient to determine the state, is $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\delta})$, and $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\epsilon^2}) $. The sample complexity of quantum Markov Chain certification, i.e., to certify whether a tripartite state equals a fixed given quantum Markov Chain $\sigma_{ABC}$ or at least $\delta$-far from $\sigma_{ABC}$, is ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\delta})$, and ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\epsilon^2})$. $\tilde{O}(\frac{\min\{d_Ad_B^3d_C^3,d_A^3d_B^3d_C\}}{\epsilon^2})$ copies to test whether $\rho_{ABC}$ is a quantum Markov Chain or $\epsilon$-far from its Petz recovery state. We generalized the tomography results into multipartite quantum system by showing $\tilde{O}(\frac{n^2\max_{i} \{d_i^2d_{i+1}^2\}}{\delta})$ copies for infidelity $\delta$ are enough for $n$-partite quantum Markov chain tomography with $d_i$ being the dimension of the $i$-th subsystem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Concentration of polynomial random matrices via Efron-Stein inequalities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02655</link>
    <author>Goutham Rajendran, Madhur Tulsiani</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Analyzing concentration of large random matrices is a common task in a wide variety of fields. Given independent random variables, many tools are available to analyze random matrices whose entries are linear in the variables, e.g. the matrix-Bernstein inequality. However, in many applications, we need to analyze random matrices whose entries are polynomials in the variables. These arise naturally in the analysis of spectral algorithms, e.g., Hopkins et al. [STOC 2016], Moitra-Wein [STOC 2019]; and in lower bounds for semidefinite programs based on the Sum of Squares hierarchy, e.g. Barak et al. [FOCS 2016], Jones et al. [FOCS 2021]. In this work, we present a general framework to obtain such bounds, based on the matrix Efron-Stein inequalities developed by Paulin-Mackey-Tropp [Annals of Probability 2016]. The Efron-Stein inequality bounds the norm of a random matrix by the norm of another simpler (but still random) matrix, which we view as arising by "differentiating" the starting matrix. By recursively differentiating, our framework reduces the main task to analyzing far simpler matrices. For Rademacher variables, these simpler matrices are in fact deterministic and hence, analyzing them is far easier. For general non-Rademacher variables, the task reduces to scalar concentration, which is much easier. Moreover, in the setting of polynomial matrices, our results generalize the work of Paulin-Mackey-Tropp. Using our basic framework, we recover known bounds in the literature for simple "tensor networks" and "dense graph matrices". Using our general framework, we derive bounds for "sparse graph matrices", which were obtained only recently by Jones et al. [FOCS 2021] using a nontrivial application of the trace power method, and was a core component in their work. We expect our framework to be helpful for other applications involving concentration phenomena for nonlinear random matrices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable and Flexible Classical Shadow Tomography with Tensor Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02093</link>
    <author>Ahmed A. Akhtar, Hong-Ye Hu, Yi-Zhuang You</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classical shadow tomography is a powerful randomized measurement protocol for predicting many properties of a quantum state with few measurements. Two classical shadow protocols have been extensively studied in the literature: the single-qubit (local) Pauli measurement, which is well suited for predicting local operators but inefficient for large operators; and the global Clifford measurement, which is efficient for low-rank operators but infeasible on near-term quantum devices due to the extensive gate overhead. In this work, we demonstrate a scalable classical shadow tomography approach for generic randomized measurements implemented with finite-depth local Clifford random unitary circuits, which interpolates between the limits of Pauli and Clifford measurements. The method combines the recently proposed locally-scrambled classical shadow tomography framework with tensor network techniques to achieve scalability for computing the classical shadow reconstruction map and evaluating various physical properties. The method enables classical shadow tomography to be performed on shallow quantum circuits with superior sample efficiency and minimal gate overhead and is friendly to noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. We show that the shallow-circuit measurement protocol provides immediate, exponential advantages over the Pauli measurement protocol for predicting quasi-local operators. It also enables a more efficient fidelity estimation compared to the Pauli measurement.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Characterizing and quantifying the incompatibility of quantum instruments</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02621</link>
    <author>Arindam Mitra, Máté Farkas</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Incompatibility of quantum devices is one of the cornerstones of quantum theory, and the incompatibility of quantum measurements and channels has been linked to quantum advantage in certain information theoretic tasks. In this work, we focus on the less well-explored question of the incompatibility of quantum instruments, that is, devices that describe the measurement process in its entirety, accounting for both the classical measurement outcome and the quantum post-measurement state. In particular, we focus on the recently introduced notion of parallel compatibility of instruments, which has been argued to be a natural notion of instrument compatibility. We introduce -- similarly to the case of measurements and channels -- the incompatibility robustness of quantum instruments and derive universal bounds on it. We then prove that post-processing of quantum instruments is a free operation for parallel compatibility. Last, we provide families of instruments for which our bounds are tight, and families of compatible indecomposable instruments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Approximate Degree of DNF and CNF Formulas</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01584</link>
    <author>Alexander A. Sherstov</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The approximate degree of a Boolean function $f\colon\{0,1\}^n\to\{0,1\}$ is the minimum degree of a real polynomial $p$ that approximates $f$ pointwise: $|f(x)-p(x)|\leq1/3$ for all $x\in\{0,1\}^n.$ For every $\delta>0,$ we construct CNF and DNF formulas of polynomial size with approximate degree $\Omega(n^{1-\delta}),$ essentially matching the trivial upper bound of $n.$ This improves polynomially on previous lower bounds and fully resolves the approximate degree of constant-depth circuits ($\text{AC}^0$), a question that has seen extensive research over the past 10 years. Previously, an $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$ lower bound was known only for $\text{AC}^0$ circuits of depth that grows with $1/\delta$ (Bun and Thaler, FOCS 2017). Moreover, our CNF and DNF formulas are the simplest possible in that they have constant width. Our result holds even for one-sided approximation, and has the following further consequences. (i) We essentially settle the communication complexity of $\text{AC}^0$ circuits in the bounded-error quantum model, $k$-party number-on-the-forehead randomized model, and $k$-party number-on-the-forehead nondeterministic model: we prove that for every $\delta>0$, these models require $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$, $\Omega(n/4^kk^2)^{1-\delta}$, and $\Omega(n/4^kk^2)^{1-\delta}$, respectively, bits of communication even for polynomial-size constant-width CNF formulas. (ii) In particular, we show that the multiparty communication class $\text{coNP}_k$ can be separated essentially optimally from $\text{NP}_k$ and $\text{BPP}_k$ by a particularly simple function, a polynomial-size constant-width CNF. (iii) We give an essentially tight separation, of $O(1)$ versus $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$, for the one-sided versus two-sided approximate degree of a function; and $O(1)$ versus $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$ for the one-sided approximate degree of a function $f$ versus its negation $\neg f$.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>