<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Parameterized Complexity of Quantum Verification</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08119</link>
    <author>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Sergey Bravyi, Chinmay Nirkhe, Bryan O'Gorman</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We initiate the study of parameterized complexity of $\textsf{QMA}$ problems in terms of the number of non-Clifford gates in the problem description. We show that for the problem of parameterized quantum circuit satisfiability, there exists a classical algorithm solving the problem with a runtime scaling exponentially in the number of non-Clifford gates but only polynomially with the system size. This result follows from our main result, that for any Clifford + $t$ $T$-gate quantum circuit satisfiability problem, the search space of optimal witnesses can be reduced to a stabilizer subspace isomorphic to at most $t$ qubits (independent of the system size). Furthermore, we derive new lower bounds on the $T$-count of circuit satisfiability instances and the $T$-count of the $W$-state assuming the classical exponential time hypothesis ($\textsf{ETH}$). Lastly, we explore the parameterized complexity of the quantum non-identity check problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying dynamical magic with completely stabilizer preserving operations as free</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.07867</link>
    <author>Gaurav Saxena, Gilad Gour</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we extend the resource theory of magic to the channel case by considering completely stabilizer preserving operations (CSPOs) as free. We introduce and characterize the set of CSPO preserving and completely CSPO preserving superchannels. We quantify the magic of quantum channels by extending the generalized robustness and the min relative entropy of magic from the state to the channel domain and show that they bound the single-shot dynamical magic cost and distillation. We also provide analytical conditions for qubit interconversion under CSPOs and show that it is a linear programming feasibility problem and hence can be efficiently solved. Lastly, we give a classical simulation algorithm whose runtime is related to the generalized robustness of magic for channels. Our algorithm depends on some pre-defined precision, and if there is no bound on the desired precision then it achieves a constant runtime.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum speedups for treewidth</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08186</link>
    <author>Vladislavs Kļevickis, Krišjānis Prūsis, Jevgēnijs Vihrovs</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we study quantum algorithms for computing the exact value of the treewidth of a graph. Our algorithms are based on the classical algorithm by Fomin and Villanger (Combinatorica 32, 2012) that uses $O(2.616^n)$ time and polynomial space. We show three quantum algorithms with the following complexity, using QRAM in both exponential space algorithms: $\bullet$ $O(1.618^n)$ time and polynomial space; $\bullet$ $O(1.554^n)$ time and $O(1.452^n)$ space; $\bullet$ $O(1.538^n)$ time and space. In contrast, the fastest known classical algorithm for treewidth uses $O(1.755^n)$ time and space. The first two speed-ups are obtained in a fairly straightforward way. The first version uses additionally only Grover's search and provides a quadratic speedup. The second speedup is more time-efficient and uses both Grover's search and the quantum exponential dynamic programming by Ambainis et al. (SODA '19). The third version uses the specific properties of the classical algorithm and treewidth, with a modified version of the quantum dynamic programming on the hypercube. Lastly, as a small side result, we also give a new classical time-space tradeoff for computing treewidth in $O^*(2^n)$ time and $O^*(\sqrt{2^n})$ space.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generative modeling with projected entangled-pair states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08177</link>
    <author>Tom Vieijra, Laurens Vanderstraeten, Frank Verstraete</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We argue and demonstrate that projected entangled-pair states (PEPS) outperform matrix product states significantly for the task of generative modeling of datasets with an intrinsic two-dimensional structure such as images. Our approach builds on a recently introduced algorithm for sampling PEPS, which allows for the efficient optimization and sampling of the distributions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The platypus of the quantum channel zoo</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08380</link>
    <author>Felix Leditzky, Debbie Leung, Vikesh Siddhu, Graeme Smith, John A. Smolin</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding quantum channels and the strange behavior of their capacities is a key objective of quantum information theory. Here we study a remarkably simple, low-dimensional, single-parameter family of quantum channels with exotic quantum information-theoretic features. As the simplest example from this family, we focus on a qutrit-to-qutrit channel that is intuitively obtained by hybridizing together a simple degradable channel and a completely useless qubit channel. Such hybridizing makes this channel's capacities behave in a variety of interesting ways. For instance, the private and classical capacity of this channel coincide and can be explicitly calculated, even though the channel does not belong to any class for which the underlying information quantities are known to be additive. Moreover, the quantum capacity of the channel can be computed explicitly, given a clear and compelling conjecture is true. This "spin alignment conjecture", which may be of independent interest, is proved in certain special cases and additional numerical evidence for its validity is provided. Finally, we generalize the qutrit channel in two ways, and the resulting channels and their capacities display similarly rich behavior. In a companion paper, we further show that the qutrit channel demonstrates superadditivity when transmitting quantum information jointly with a variety of assisting channels, in a manner unknown before.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>