<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Chain rules for quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11153</link>
    <author>Mario Berta, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Divergence chain rules for channels relate the divergence of a pair of channel inputs and to the divergence of the corresponding channel outputs. An important special case of such a rule is the data-processing inequality, which tells us that if the same channel is applied to both inputs then the divergence cannot increase. Based on direct matrix analysis methods, we derive several Rényi divergence chain rules for channels in the quantum setting. Our results simplify and in some cases generalise previous derivations in the literature.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Certifiable Randomness from a Single Quantum Device</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11353</link>
    <author>Urmila Mahadev, Umesh Vazirani, Thomas Vidick</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Brakerski et. al [BCM+18] introduced the model of cryptographic testing of a single untrusted quantum device and gave a protocol for certifiable randomness generation. We use the leakage resilience properties of the Learning With Errors problem to address a key issue left open in previous work - the rate of generation of randomness. Our new protocol can certify $\Omega(n)$ fresh bits of randomness in constant rounds, where $n$ is a parameter of the protocol and the total communication is $O(n)$, thus achieving a nearly optimal rate. The proof that the output is statistically random is conceptually simple and technically elementary.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise-resilient Majorana Edge Modes on a Chain of Superconducting Qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11372</link>
    <author>Xiao Mi, Michael Sonner, Murphy Yuezhen Niu, Kenneth W. Lee, Brooks Foxen, Rajeev Acharya, Igor Aleiner, Trond I. Andersen, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Joao Basso, Andreas Bengtsson, Gina Bortoli, Alexandre Bourassa, Leon Brill, et al (108)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Inherent symmetry of a quantum system may protect its otherwise fragile states. Leveraging such protection requires testing its robustness against uncontrolled environmental interactions. Using 47 superconducting qubits, we implement the kicked Ising model which exhibits Majorana edge modes (MEMs) protected by $\mathbb{Z}_2$ parity symmetry. Remarkably, we find that any multi-qubit Pauli operator overlapping with the MEMs exhibits a uniform decay rate comparable to single-qubit relaxation rates, irrespective of its size or composition. This finding allows us to accurately reconstruct the exponentially localized spatial profiles of the MEMs. Spectroscopic measurements further indicate exponentially suppressed hybridization between the MEMs at larger system sizes, which manifests as a strong resilience against low-frequency noise. Our work elucidates the noise sensitivity of symmetry-protected edge modes in a solid-state environment.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simulation and performance analysis of quantum error correction with a rotated surface code under a realistic noise model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11404</link>
    <author>Mitsuki Katsuda, Kosuke Mitarai, Keisuke Fujii</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The demonstration of quantum error correction (QEC) is one of the most important milestones in the realization of fully-fledged quantum computers. Toward this, QEC experiments using the surface codes have recently been actively conducted. However, it has not yet been realized to protect logical quantum information beyond the physical coherence time. In this work, we performed a full simulation of QEC for the rotated surface codes with a code distance 5, which employs 49 qubits and is within reach of the current state-of-the-art quantum computers. In particular, we evaluate the logical error probability in a realistic noise model that incorporates not only stochastic Pauli errors but also coherent errors due to a systematic control error or unintended interactions. While a straightforward simulation of 49 qubits is not tractable within a reasonable computational time, we reduced the number of qubits required to 26 qubits by delaying the syndrome measurement in simulation. This and a fast quantum computer simulator, Qulacs, implemented on GPU allows us to simulate full QEC with an arbitrary local noise within reasonable simulation time. Based on the numerical results, we also construct and verify an effective model to incorporate the effect of the coherent error into a stochastic noise model. This allows us to understand what the effect coherent error has on the logical error probability on a large scale without full simulation based on the detailed full simulation of a small scale. The present simulation framework and effective model, which can handle arbitrary local noise, will play a vital role in clarifying the physical parameters that future experimental QEC should target.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Incompatibility of local measurements provide advantage in local quantum state discrimination</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10948</link>
    <author>Kornikar Sen, Ujjwal Sen</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A pack of quantum measurements that cannot be measured simultaneously is said to form a set of incompatible measurements. Every set of incompatible measurements have advantage over the compatible ones in a quantum state discrimination task where one prepares a state from an ensemble and sends it to another party, and the latter tries to detect the state using available measurements. We consider the local quantum state discrimination task where a sender prepares a bipartite state and sends the subsystems to two receivers. The receivers try to detect the sent state using locally incompatible measurements. We analyze the ratio of the probability of successfully guessing the state using incompatible measurements and the maximum probability of successfully guessing the state using compatible measurements. We find that this ratio is upper bounded by a simple function of robustnesses of incompatibilities of the local measurements. Interestingly, corresponding to every pair of sets of incompatible measurements, there exists at least one local state discrimination task where this bound can be achieved. We argue that the optimal local quantum state discrimination task does not present any "nonlocality", where the term is used in the sense of a difference between the ratios, of probabilities of successful detection via incompatible and compatible measurements, in global and local state discriminations. The results can be generalized to the regime of multipartite local quantum state distinguishing tasks.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>