<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Long-distance transmon coupler with CZ gate fidelity above $99.8\%$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09460</link>
    <author>Fabian Marxer, Antti Vepsäläinen, Shan W. Jolin, Jani Tuorila, Alessandro Landra, Caspar Ockeloen-Korppi, Wei Liu, Olli Ahonen, Adrian Auer, Lucien Belzane, Ville Bergholm, Chun Fai Chan, Kok Wai Chan, Tuukka Hiltunen, Juho Hotari, Eric Hyyppä, Joni Ikonen, David Janzso, Miikka Koistinen, Janne Kotilahti, et al (19)</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tunable coupling of superconducting qubits has been widely studied due to its importance for isolated gate operations in scalable quantum processor architectures. Here, we demonstrate a tunable qubit-qubit coupler based on a floating transmon device which allows us to place qubits at least 2 mm apart from each other while maintaining over 50 MHz coupling between the coupler and the qubits. In the introduced tunable-coupler design, both the qubit-qubit and the qubit-coupler couplings are mediated by two waveguides instead of relying on direct capacitive couplings between the components, reducing the impact of the qubit-qubit distance on the couplings. This leaves space for each qubit to have an individual readout resonator and a Purcell filter needed for fast high-fidelity readout. In addition, the large qubit-qubit distance reduces unwanted non-nearest neighbor coupling and allows multiple control lines to cross over the structure with minimal crosstalk. Using the proposed flexible and scalable architecture, we demonstrate a controlled-$Z$ gate with $(99.81 \pm 0.02)\%$ fidelity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal cost bound of quantum error mitigation based on quantum estimation theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09385</link>
    <author>Kento Tsubouchi, Takahiro Sagawa, Nobuyuki Yoshioka</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation is an art to combat noise in quantum computers that are not fully fault tolerant. While a wide variety of techniques has been proposed with surging number of experimental applications, little is known concerning the unified understanding on their fundamental aspects. In this paper, we perform a theoretical analysis on the cost of quantum error mitigation using the quantum estimation theory. The applicability of quantum estimation theory is extended so that we can analyze the quantum Fisher information of layered noisy quantum circuits equipped with a wide range of quantum error mitigation methods. By showing that the quantum Fisher information decays exponentially with the circuit depth, we derive for a general class of Markovian noise that unbiased estimation of an observable encounters an exponential growth in the lower bound on the measurement cost, or more precisely the required number of copies of noisy quantum state. As two practical and illustrative examples, we discuss the case when the noise channel is solely the global or local depolarizing noise. We explicitly express the lower bound in terms of their noise rates, and further find that we can asymptotically saturate the bound by a simple mitigation technique for the global depolarizing noise. Our results not only reveal the physical limitations of quantum error mitigation, but may also provide a new criteria for performance evaluation of quantum error mitigation techniques.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal sample lower bounds for quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09178</link>
    <author>Ryuji Takagi, Hiroyasu Tajima, Mile Gu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Although numerous quantum error-mitigation protocols have been proposed as means to suppress noise effects on intermediate-scale quantum devices, their general potential and limitations have still been elusive. In particular, to understand the ultimate feasibility of quantum error mitigation, it is crucial to characterize the fundamental sampling cost -- how many times an arbitrary mitigation protocol must run a noisy quantum device. Here, we establish universal lower bounds on the sampling cost for quantum error mitigation to achieve the desired accuracy with high probability. Our bounds apply to general mitigation protocols, including the ones involving nonlinear postprocessing. We further show that the number of samples required for a wide class of protocols to mitigate errors in layered circuits must grow exponentially with the circuit depth for various noise models, revealing the fundamental obstacles in showing useful applications of noisy near-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum metrology of noisy spreading channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09386</link>
    <author>Wojciech Górecki, Alberto Riccardi, Lorenzo Maccone</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide the optimal measurement strategy for a class of noisy channels that reduce to the identity channel for a specific value of a parameter (spreading channels). We provide an example that is physically relevant: the estimation of the absolute value of the displacement in the presence of phase randomizing noise. Surprisingly, this noise does not affect the effectiveness of the optimal measurement. We show that, for small displacement, a squeezed vacuum probe field is optimal among strategies with same average energy. A squeezer followed by photodetection is the optimal detection strategy that attains the quantum Fisher information, whereas the customarily used homodyne detection becomes useless in the limit of small displacements, due to the same effect that gives Rayleigh's curse in optical superresolution. There is a quantum advantage: a squeezed or a Fock state with $N$ average photons allow to asymptotically estimate the parameter with a $\sqrt{N}$ better precision than classical states with same energy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A hierarchy of semidefinite programs for generalised Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen scenarios</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09236</link>
    <author>Matty J. Hoban, Tom Drescher, Ana Belén Sainz</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Correlations in Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen (EPR) scenarios, captured by \textitassemblages of unnormalised quantum states, have recently caught the attention of the community, both from a foundational and an information-theoretic perspective. The set of quantum-realisable assemblages, or abbreviated to quantum assemblages, are those that arise from multiple parties performing local measurements on a shared quantum system. In general, deciding whether or not a given assemblage is a quantum assemblage, i.e. membership of the set of quantum assemblages, is a hard problem, and not always solvable. In this paper we introduce a hierarchy of tests where each level either determines non-membership of the set of quantum assemblages or is inconclusive. The higher the level of the hierarchy the better one can determine non-membership, and this hierarchy converges to a particular set of assemblages. Furthermore, this set to which it converges contains the quantum assemblages. Each test in the hierarchy is formulated as a semidefinite program. This hierarchy allows one to upper bound the quantum violation of a steering inequality and the quantum advantage provided by quantum EPR assemblages in a communication or information-processing task.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>