<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Tight Bounds for State Tomography with Incoherent Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05265</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Brice Huang, Jerry Li, Allen Liu, Mark Sellke</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the classic question of state tomography: given copies of an unknown quantum state $\rho\in\mathbb{C}^{d\times d}$, output $\widehat{\rho}$ for which $\|\rho - \widehat{\rho}\|_{\mathsf{tr}} \le \varepsilon$. When one is allowed to make coherent measurements entangled across all copies, $\Theta(d^2/\varepsilon^2)$ copies are necessary and sufficient [Haah et al. '17, O'Donnell-Wright '16]. Unfortunately, the protocols achieving this rate incur large quantum memory overheads that preclude implementation on current or near-term devices. On the other hand, the best known protocol using incoherent (single-copy) measurements uses $O(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17], and multiple papers have posed it as an open question to understand whether or not this rate is tight. In this work, we fully resolve this question, by showing that any protocol using incoherent measurements, even if they are chosen adaptively, requires $\Omega(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies, matching the upper bound of [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17]. We do so by a new proof technique which directly bounds the "tilt" of the posterior distribution after measurements, which yields a surprisingly short proof of our lower bound, and which we believe may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Connections between graphs and matrix spaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04815</link>
    <author>Yinan Li, Youming Qiao, Avi Wigderson, Yuval Wigderson, Chuanqi Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a bipartite graph $G$, the graphical matrix space $\mathcal{S}_G$ consists of matrices whose non-zero entries can only be at those positions corresponding to edges in $G$. Tutte (J. London Math. Soc., 1947), Edmonds (J. Res. Nat. Bur. Standards Sect. B, 1967) and Lovász (FCT, 1979) observed connections between perfect matchings in $G$ and full-rank matrices in $\mathcal{S}_G$. Dieudonné (Arch. Math., 1948) proved a tight upper bound on the dimensions of those matrix spaces containing only singular matrices. The starting point of this paper is a simultaneous generalization of these two classical results: we show that the largest dimension over subspaces of $\mathcal{S}_G$ containing only singular matrices is equal to the maximum size over subgraphs of $G$ without perfect matchings, based on Meshulam's proof of Dieudonné's result (Quart. J. Math., 1985). Starting from this result, we go on to establish more connections between properties of graphs and matrix spaces. For example, we establish connections between acyclicity and nilpotency, between strong connectivity and irreducibility, and between isomorphism and conjugacy/congruence. For each connection, we study three types of correspondences, namely the basic correspondence, the inherited correspondence (for subgraphs and subspaces), and the induced correspondence (for induced subgraphs and restrictions). Some correspondences lead to intriguing generalizations of classical results, such as for Dieudonné's result mentioned above, and for a celebrated theorem of Gerstenhaber regarding the largest dimension of nil matrix spaces (Amer. J. Math., 1958). Finally, we show some implications of our results to quantum information and present open problems in computational complexity motivated by these results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum space, ground space traversal, and how to embed multi-prover interactive proofs into unentanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05243</link>
    <author>Sevag Gharibian, Dorian Rudolph</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Savitch's theorem states that NPSPACE computations can be simulated in PSPACE. We initiate the study of a quantum analogue of NPSPACE, denoted Streaming-QCMASPACE (SQCMASPACE), where an exponentially long classical proof is streamed to a poly-space quantum verifier. Besides two main results, we also show that a quantum analogue of Savitch's theorem is unlikely to hold, as SQCMASPACE=NEXP. For completeness, we introduce Streaming-QMASPACE (SQMASPACE) with an exponentially long streamed quantum proof, and show SQMASPACE=QMA_EXP (quantum analogue of NEXP). Our first main result shows, in contrast to the classical setting, the solution space of a quantum constraint satisfaction problem (i.e. a local Hamiltonian) is always connected when exponentially long proofs are permitted. For this, we show how to simulate any Lipschitz continuous path on the unit hypersphere via a sequence of local unitary gates, at the expense of blowing up the circuit size. This shows quantum error-correcting codes can be unable to detect one codeword erroneously evolving to another if the evolution happens sufficiently slowly, and answers an open question of [Gharibian, Sikora, ICALP 2015] regarding the Ground State Connectivity problem. Our second main result is that any SQCMASPACE computation can be embedded into "unentanglement", i.e. into a quantum constraint satisfaction problem with unentangled provers. Formally, we show how to embed SQCMASPACE into the Sparse Separable Hamiltonian problem of [Chailloux, Sattath, CCC 2012] (QMA(2)-complete for 1/poly promise gap), at the expense of scaling the promise gap with the streamed proof size. As a corollary, we obtain the first systematic construction for obtaining QMA(2)-type upper bounds on arbitrary multi-prover interactive proof systems, where the QMA(2) promise gap scales exponentially with the number of bits of communication in the interactive proof.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Accelerated Algorithms for Monotone Inclusions and Constrained Nonconvex-Nonconcave Min-Max Optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05248</link>
    <author>Yang Cai, Argyris Oikonomou, Weiqiang Zheng</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study monotone inclusions and monotone variational inequalities, as well as their generalizations to non-monotone settings. We first show that the Extra Anchored Gradient (EAG) algorithm, originally proposed by Yoon and Ryu [2021] for unconstrained convex-concave min-max optimization, can be applied to solve the more general problem of Lipschitz monotone inclusion. More specifically, we prove that the EAG solves Lipschitz monotone inclusion problems with an \emphaccelerated convergence rate of $O(\frac{1}{T})$, which is \emphoptimal among all first-order methods [Diakonikolas, 2020, Yoon and Ryu, 2021]. Our second result is a new algorithm, called Extra Anchored Gradient Plus (EAG+), which not only achieves the accelerated $O(\frac{1}{T})$ convergence rate for all monotone inclusion problems, but also exhibits the same accelerated rate for a family of general (non-monotone) inclusion problems that concern negative comonotone operators. As a special case of our second result, EAG+ enjoys the $O(\frac{1}{T})$ convergence rate for solving a non-trivial class of nonconvex-nonconcave min-max optimization problems. Our analyses are based on simple potential function arguments, which might be useful for analysing other accelerated algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>List-Decodable Sparse Mean Estimation via Difference-of-Pairs Filtering</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05245</link>
    <author>Ilias Diakonikolas, Daniel M. Kane, Sushrut Karmalkar, Ankit Pensia, Thanasis Pittas</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of list-decodable sparse mean estimation. Specifically, for a parameter $\alpha \in (0, 1/2)$, we are given $m$ points in $\mathbb{R}^n$, $\lfloor \alpha m \rfloor$ of which are i.i.d. samples from a distribution $D$ with unknown $k$-sparse mean $\mu$. No assumptions are made on the remaining points, which form the majority of the dataset. The goal is to return a small list of candidates containing a vector $\widehat \mu$ such that $\| \widehat \mu - \mu \|_2$ is small. Prior work had studied the problem of list-decodable mean estimation in the dense setting. In this work, we develop a novel, conceptually simpler technique for list-decodable mean estimation. As the main application of our approach, we provide the first sample and computationally efficient algorithm for list-decodable sparse mean estimation. In particular, for distributions with ``certifiably bounded'' $t$-th moments in $k$-sparse directions and sufficiently light tails, our algorithm achieves error of $(1/\alpha)^{O(1/t)}$ with sample complexity $m = (k\log(n))^{O(t)}/\alpha$ and running time $\mathrm{poly}(mn^t)$. For the special case of Gaussian inliers, our algorithm achieves the optimal error guarantee of $\Theta (\sqrt{\log(1/\alpha)})$ with quasi-polynomial sample and computational complexity. We complement our upper bounds with nearly-matching statistical query and low-degree polynomial testing lower bounds.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>