<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Memory Compression with Quantum Random-Access Gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.05599</link>
    <author>Harry Buhrman, Bruno Loff, Subhasree Patro, Florian Speelman</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the classical RAM, we have the following useful property. If we have an algorithm that uses $M$ memory cells throughout its execution, and in addition is sparse, in the sense that, at any point in time, only $m$ out of $M$ cells will be non-zero, then we may "compress" it into another algorithm which uses only $m \log M$ memory and runs in almost the same time. We may do so by simulating the memory using either a hash table, or a self-balancing tree. We show an analogous result for quantum algorithms equipped with quantum random-access gates. If we have a quantum algorithm that runs in time $T$ and uses $M$ qubits, such that the state of the memory, at any time step, is supported on computational-basis vectors of Hamming weight at most $m$, then it can be simulated by another algorithm which uses only $O(m \log M)$ memory, and runs in time $\tilde O(T)$. We show how this theorem can be used, in a black-box way, to simplify the presentation in several papers. Broadly speaking, when there exists a need for a space-efficient history-independent quantum data-structure, it is often possible to construct a space-inefficient, yet sparse, quantum data structure, and then appeal to our main theorem. This results in simpler and shorter arguments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying the barren plateau phenomenon for a model of unstructured variational ansätze</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.06174</link>
    <author>John Napp</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantifying the flatness of the objective-function landscape associated with unstructured parameterized quantum circuits is important for understanding the performance of variational algorithms utilizing a "hardware-efficient ansatz", particularly for ensuring that a prohibitively flat landscape -- a so-called "barren plateau" -- is avoided. For a model of such ansätze, we relate the typical landscape flatness to a certain family of random walks, enabling us to derive a Monte Carlo algorithm for efficiently, classically estimating the landscape flatness for any architecture. The statistical picture additionally allows us to prove new analytic bounds on the barren plateau phenomenon, and more generally provides novel insights into the phenomenon's dependence on the ansatz depth, architecture, qudit dimension, and Hamiltonian combinatorial and spatial locality. Our analysis utilizes techniques originally developed by Dalzell et al. to study anti-concentration in random circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fundamental resolution limit of quantum imaging with undetected photons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.06106</link>
    <author>Andres Vega, Elkin A. Santos, Jorge Fuenzalida, Marta Gilaberte Basset, Thomas Pertsch, Markus Grafe, Sina Saravi, Frank Setzpfandt</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum imaging with undetected photons relies on the principle of induced coherence without induced emission and uses two sources of photon-pairs with a signal- and an idler photon of wavelengths $\lambda_S$ and $\lambda_I$, respectively. Each pair shares strong quantum correlations in both position and momentum, which allows to image an object illuminated with idler photons by just measuring signal photons that never interact with the object. In this work, we theoretically investigate the transverse resolution of this non-local imaging scheme through a general formalism that treats propagating photons beyond the commonly used paraxial approximation. We hereby prove that the resolution of quantum imaging with undetected photons is diffraction limited to the longer wavelength of the signal and idler pairs, with a minimum resolvable resolution of $ \mathrm{max}(\lambda_S,\lambda_I)/2$. Moreover, we conclude that this result is also valid for other non-local two-photon imaging schemes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Thermodynamic principle for quantum metrology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.05688</link>
    <author>Yaoming Chu, Jianming Cai</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The heat dissipation in quantum metrology represents not only an unavoidable problem towards practical applications of quantum sensing devices but also a fundamental relationship between thermodynamics and quantum metrology. However, a general thermodynamic principle which governs the rule of energy consumption in quantum metrology, similar to Landauer's principle for heat dissipation in computations, has remained elusive. Here, we establish such a physical principle for energy consumption in order to achieve a certain level of measurement precision in quantum metrology, and show that it is intrinsically determined by the erasure of quantum Fisher information. The principle provides a powerful tool to investigate the advantage of quantum resources, not only in measurement precision but also in energy efficiency. It also serves as a bridge between thermodynamics and various fundamental physical concepts related in quantum physics and quantum information theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Modeling of Solids</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.06178</link>
    <author>Paolo Vannucci</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This text is the support for the course of Modeling of Solids, of the Master of Mechanics of the University Paris-Saclay - Curriculum MMM: Mathematical Methods for Mechanics, held at Versailles. The course is the continuation of the course Continuum Mechanics - Solids, and as such it is an introduction, for graduate students, to some typical topics of the theory of solid bodies. The different arguments are dealt with in a simple, succinct way, the objective being to give to students the fundamentals of each argument. Only static problems are considered, being the dynamic of structures dealt with in other courses.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>