<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement as a shortcut to long-range entangled quantum matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13527</link>
    <author>Tsung-Cheng Lu, Leonardo A. Lessa, Isaac H. Kim, Timothy H. Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The preparation of long-range entangled states using unitary circuits is limited by Lieb-Robinson bounds, but circuits with projective measurements and feedback (``adaptive circuits'') can evade such restrictions. We introduce four classes of local adaptive circuits that enable low-depth preparation of long-range entangled quantum matter characterized by gapped topological orders and conformal field theories (CFTs). The four classes are inspired by distinct physical insights, including tensor-network constructions, short-range entangled states with non-trivial braiding structures, multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (MERA), and parton constructions. A large class of topological orders, including chiral and symmetry-enriched topological orders, can be prepared in constant depth or time, and one-dimensional CFT states and non-abelian topological orders with both solvable and non-solvable groups can be prepared in depth scaling logarithmically with system size. Our work illustrates the practical and conceptual versatility of measurement for state preparation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Detecting and Eliminating Quantum Noise of Quantum Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13743</link>
    <author>Shuanghong Tang, Congcong Zheng, Kun Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work, we propose a two-stage procedure to systematically address quantum noise inherent in quantum measurements. The idea behind it is intuitive: we first detect and then eliminate quantum noise so that the classical noise assumption is satisfied and measurement error mitigation works. In the first stage, inspired by coherence witness in the resource theory of quantum coherence, we design an efficient method to detect quantum noise. It works by fitting the difference between two measurement statistics to the Fourier series, where the statistics are obtained using maximally coherent states with relative phase and maximally mixed states as inputs. The fitting coefficients quantitatively benchmark quantum noise. In the second stage, we design various methods to eliminate quantum noise, inspired by the Pauli twirling technique. They work by executing randomly sampled Pauli gates before the measurement device and conditionally flipping the measurement outcomes in such a way that the effective measurement device contains only classical noise. We demonstrate the feasibility of the two-stage procedure numerically on Baidu Quantum Platform. Remarkably, the results show that quantum noise in measurement devices is significantly suppressed, and the quantum computation accuracy is substantially improved. We highlight that the two-stage procedure complements existing measurement error mitigation techniques, and they together form a standard toolbox for manipulating measurement errors in near-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-Convex Optimization by Hamiltonian Alternation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14072</link>
    <author>Anuj Apte, Kunal Marwaha, Arvind Murugan</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A major obstacle to non-convex optimization is the problem of getting stuck in local minima. We introduce a novel metaheuristic to handle this issue, creating an alternate Hamiltonian that shares minima with the original Hamiltonian only within a chosen energy range. We find that repeatedly minimizing each Hamiltonian in sequence allows an algorithm to escape local minima. This technique is particularly straightforward when the ground state energy is known, and one obtains an improvement even without this knowledge. We demonstrate this technique by using it to find the ground state for instances of a Sherrington-Kirkpatrick spin glass.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time and Query Complexity Tradeoff for the Dihedral Coset Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14408</link>
    <author>Maxime Remaud, jean-Pierre Tillich</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Dihedral Coset Problem (DCP) in $Z_N$ is an important quantumly defined problem to which for instance the learning with errors problem reduces.There are several algorithms for solving it. On one hand, we have algorithms \textità la Ettinger-Høyer running in $\OO{2^{c_{\SS}\log{N}}}$ time but using $\OO{\log{N}}$ queries, for some constant $c_{\SS}$. On the other hand, algorithms \textità la Kuperberg need $\OOt{2^{\sqrt{c_{\DCP}\log{N}}}}$ time and queries, for some constant $c_{\DCP}$. Despite being the subject of a lot of studies, no algorithm using an intermediate number of queries was known up till now. It means that an attacker who has, for cost or time reasons, limited queries, will be forced to use a linear query algorithm running in exponential time. We propose an algorithm taking as a parameter the number $Q$ of queries we are allowed to do, therefore interpolating between existing algorithms. We thus explicitly show that it takes $\OOt{2^{c_{\SS}\left(\log{N}-\frac{1}{c_{\DCP}}\log^2{Q}\right)}}$ time. Our algorithm improves over algorithms \textità la Ettinger-Høyer when $Q$ is minimal and matches algorithms \textità la Kuperberg when $Q$ is maximal, while offering new possibilities in between. The key point of our algorithm is to give a degree of freedom in the way coset states are preprocessed, that we then link to the parameter $Q$ to obtain an optimal algorithm with respect to $Q$. We also introduce a new sieving procedure to assemble the constructed coset states, allowing us to retrieve the secret $s$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entropy Inequalities and Gaussian Comparisons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14182</link>
    <author>Efe Aras, Thomas A. Courtade</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish a general class of entropy inequalities that take the concise form of Gaussian comparisons. The main result unifies many classical and recent results, including the Shannon-Stam inequality, the Brunn-Minkowski inequality, the Zamir-Feder inequality, the Brascamp-Lieb and Barthe inequalities, the Anantharam-Jog-Nair inequality, and others.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>