<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Solvent distribution effects on quantum chemical calculations with quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12487</link>
    <author>Yuichiro Yoshida, Wataru Mizukami, Norio Yoshida</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a combination of three-dimensional reference interaction site model self-consistent field (3D-RISM-SCF) theory and the variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) to consider the solvent distribution effects within the framework of quantum-classical hybrid computing. The present method, 3D-RISM-VQE, does not include any statistical errors from the solvent configuration sampling owing to the analytical treatment of the statistical solvent distribution. We apply 3D-RISM-VQE to compute the spatial distribution functions of solvent water around a water molecule, the potential and Helmholtz energy curves of NaCl, and to conduct Helmholtz energy component analysis of H$_2$O and NH$_4^+$. Moreover, we utilize 3D-RISM-VQE to analyze the extent to which solvent effects alter the efficiency of quantum calculations compared with calculations in the gas phase using the $L^1$-norms of molecular electronic Hamiltonians. Our results demonstrate that the efficiency of quantum chemical calculations on a quantum computer in solution is virtually the same as in the gas phase.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ab-initio quantum chemistry with neural-network wavefunctions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12590</link>
    <author>Jan Hermann, James Spencer, Kenny Choo, Antonio Mezzacapo, W. M. C. Foulkes, David Pfau, Giuseppe Carleo, Frank Noé</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Machine learning and specifically deep-learning methods have outperformed human capabilities in many pattern recognition and data processing problems, in game playing, and now also play an increasingly important role in scientific discovery. A key application of machine learning in the molecular sciences is to learn potential energy surfaces or force fields from ab-initio solutions of the electronic Schrödinger equation using datasets obtained with density functional theory, coupled cluster, or other quantum chemistry methods. Here we review a recent and complementary approach: using machine learning to aid the direct solution of quantum chemistry problems from first principles. Specifically, we focus on quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) methods that use neural network ansatz functions in order to solve the electronic Schrödinger equation, both in first and second quantization, computing ground and excited states, and generalizing over multiple nuclear configurations. Compared to existing quantum chemistry methods, these new deep QMC methods have the potential to generate highly accurate solutions of the Schrödinger equation at relatively modest computational cost.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Proofs of Quantumness from Trapdoor Permutations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12390</link>
    <author>Tomoyuki Morimae, Takashi Yamakawa</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Assume that Alice can do only classical probabilistic polynomial-time computing while Bob can do quantum polynomial-time computing. Alice and Bob communicate over only classical channels, and finally Bob gets a state $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$ with some bit strings $x_0$ and $x_1$. Is it possible that Alice can know $\{x_0,x_1\}$ but Bob cannot? Such a task, called \it remote state preparations, is indeed possible under some complexity assumptions, and is bases of many quantum cryptographic primitives such as proofs of quantumness, (classical-client) blind quantum computing, (classical) verifications of quantum computing, and quantum money. A typical technique to realize remote state preparations is to use 2-to-1 trapdoor collision resistant hash functions: Alice sends a 2-to-1 trapdoor collision resistant hash function $f$ to Bob, and Bob evaluates it on superposition and measures the image. Bob's post-measurement state is $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$, where $f(x_0)=f(x_1)=y$. With the trapdoor, Alice can learn $\{x_0,x_1\}$, but due to the collision resistance, Bob cannot. This Alice's advantage can be leveraged to realize the quantum cryptographic primitives listed above. It seems that the collision resistance is essential here. In this paper, surprisingly, we show that the collision resistance is not necessary for a restricted case: we show that (non-verifiable) remote state preparations of $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$ secure against \it classical probabilistic polynomial-time Bob can be constructed from classically-secure (full-domain) trapdoor permutations. Trapdoor permutations are not likely to imply the collision resistance, because black-box reductions from collision-resistant hash functions to trapdoor permutations are known to be impossible. As an application of our result, we construct proofs of quantumness from classically-secure (full-domain) trapdoor permutations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Parameterized Complexity Binary CSP for Graphs with a Small Vertex Cover and Related Results</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12543</link>
    <author>Hans L. Bodlaender</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we show that \textscBinary CSP with the size of a vertex cover as parameter is complete for the class W[3]. This is one of the firstexamples of a natural W[3]-complete problem that is not a variant of\textscSatisfiability. We obtain a number of related results with variations of the proof techniques, that include: \textscBinary CSP is complete for W[$2d+1$] with as parameter the size of a vertex modulator to graphs of treedepth $c$, or forests of depth $d$, for constant $c\geq 1$, W[$t$]-hard for all $t\in \mathbb{N}$ with treewidth as parameter, and hard for W[SAT] with feedback vertex set as parameter. As corollaries, we give some hardness and membership problems for classes in the W-hierarchy for \textscList Colouring under different parameterizations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Comparison of unknown unitary channels with multiple uses</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12519</link>
    <author>Yutaka Hashimoto, Akihito Soeda, Mio Murao</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Comparison of quantum objects is a task to determine whether two unknown quantum objects are the same or different. It is one of the most basic information processing tasks for learning property of quantum objects, and comparison of quantum states, quantum channels, and quantum measurements have been investigated. In general, repeated uses of quantum objects improve the success probability of comparison. The optimal strategy of pure-state comparison, the comparison of quantum states for the case of multiple copies of each unknown pure state, is known, but the optimal strategy of unitary comparison, the comparison of quantum channels for the case of multiple uses of each unknown unitary channel, was not known due to the complication of the varieties of causal order structures among the uses of each unitary channel. In this paper, we investigate unitary comparison with multiple uses of unitary channels based on the quantum tester formalism. We obtain the optimal minimum-error and the optimal unambiguous strategies of unitary comparison of two unknown $d$-dimensional unitary channels $U_1$ and $U_2$ when $U_1$ can be used $N_1$ times and $U_2$ can be used $N_2$ times for $N_2 \ge (d-1)N_1$. These optimal strategies are implemented by parallel uses of the unitary channels, even though all sequential and adaptive strategies implementable by the quantum circuit model are considered. When the number of the smaller uses of the unitary channels $N_1$ is fixed, the optimal averaged success probability cannot be improved by adding more uses of $U_2$ than $N_2 = (d-1) N_1$. This feature is in contrast to the case of pure-state comparison, where adding more copies of the unknown pure states always improves the optimal averaged success probability. It highlights the difference between corresponding tasks for states and channels, which has been previously shown for quantum discrimination tasks.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>