<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Sample Complexity Lower Bound for Quantum State Tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11185</link>
    <author>Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that $\Omega(rd/\epsilon)$ copies of an unknown rank-$r$, dimension-$d$ quantum mixed state are necessary in order to learn a classical description with $1 - \epsilon$ fidelity. This improves upon the tomography lower bounds obtained by Haah, et al. and Wright.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11246</link>
    <author>Cica Gustiani, Richard Meister, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods offer a highly promising route to exploiting quantum computers for chemistry tasks. Here we employ methods described in a sister paper to the present report, entitled ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits, in order to solve problems using adaptively evolving quantum circuits. Consistent with prior authors we find that this approach can outperform human-designed circuits such as the coupled-cluster or hardware-efficient ansätze, and we make comparisons for larger instances up to 14 qubits. Moreover we introduce a novel approach to constraining the circuit evolution in the physically relevant subspace, finding that this greatly improves performance and compactness of the circuits. We consider both static and dynamics properties of molecular systems. The emulation environments used is QuESTlink; all resources are open source and linked from this paper.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical surrogates for quantum learning models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11740</link>
    <author>Franz J. Schreiber, Jens Eisert, Johannes Jakob Meyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The advent of noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers has put the search for possible applications to the forefront of quantum information science. One area where hopes for an advantage through near-term quantum computers are high is quantum machine learning, where variational quantum learning models based on parametrized quantum circuits are discussed. In this work, we introduce the concept of a classical surrogate, a classical model which can be efficiently obtained from a trained quantum learning model and reproduces its input-output relations. As inference can be performed classically, the existence of a classical surrogate greatly enhances the applicability of a quantum learning strategy. However, the classical surrogate also challenges possible advantages of quantum schemes. As it is possible to directly optimize the ansatz of the classical surrogate, they create a natural benchmark the quantum model has to outperform. We show that large classes of well-analyzed re-uploading models have a classical surrogate. We conducted numerical experiments and found that these quantum models show no advantage in performance or trainability in the problems we analyze. This leaves only generalization capability as possible point of quantum advantage and emphasizes the dire need for a better understanding of inductive biases of quantum learning models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploring ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11245</link>
    <author>Richard Meister, Cica Gustiani, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gate-level quantum circuits are often derived manually from higher level algorithms. While this suffices for small implementations and demonstrations, ultimately automatic circuit design will be required to realise complex algorithms using hardware-specific operations and connectivity. Here we explore methods for the ab initio creation of circuits within a machine, either a classical computer or a hybrid quantum-classical device. We consider a range of techniques including: methods for introducing new gate structures, optimisation of parameterised circuits and choices of cost functions, and efficient removal of low-value gates exploiting the quantum geometric tensor and other heuristics. Using these principles we tackle the tasks of automatic encoding of unitary processes and translation (recompilation) of a circuit from one form to another. Using emulated quantum computers with various noise-free gate sets we provide simple examples involving up to 10 qubits, corresponding to 20 qubits in the augmented space we use. Further applications of specific relevance to chemistry modelling are considered in a sister paper, 'Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry'.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Monogamy of entanglement between cones</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11805</link>
    <author>Guillaume Aubrun, Alexander Müller-Hermes, Martin Plávala</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A separable quantum state shared between parties $A$ and $B$ can be symmetrically extended to a quantum state shared between party $A$ and parties $B_1,\ldots ,B_k$ for every $k\in\mathbf{N}$. Quantum states that are not separable, i.e., entangled, do not have this property. This phenomenon is known as "monogamy of entanglement". We show that monogamy is not only a feature of quantum theory, but that it characterizes the minimal tensor product of general pairs of convex cones $\mathsf{C}_A$ and $\mathsf{C}_B$: The elements of the minimal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\min} \mathsf{C}_B$ are precisely the tensors that can be symmetrically extended to elements in the maximal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\max} \mathsf{C}^{\otimes_{\max} k}_B$ for every $k\in\mathbf{N}$. Equivalently, the minimal tensor product of two cones is the intersection of the nested sets of $k$-extendible tensors. It is a natural question when the minimal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\min} \mathsf{C}_B$ coincides with the set of $k$-extendible tensors for some finite $k$. We show that this is universally the case for every cone $\mathsf{C}_A$ if and only if $\mathsf{C}_B$ is a polyhedral cone with a base given by a product of simplices. Our proof makes use of a new characterization of products of simplices up to affine equivalence that we believe is of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>