<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum state tomography via non-convex Riemannian gradient descent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.04717</link>
    <author>Ming-Chien Hsu, En-Jui Kuo, Wei-Hsuan Yu, Jian-Feng Cai, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recovery of an unknown density matrix of large size requires huge computational resources. The recent Factored Gradient Descent (FGD) algorithm and its variants achieved state-of-the-art performance since they could mitigate the dimensionality barrier by utilizing some of the underlying structures of the density matrix. Despite their theoretical guarantee of a linear convergence rate, the convergence in practical scenarios is still slow because the contracting factor of the FGD algorithms depends on the condition number $\kappa$ of the ground truth state. Consequently, the total number of iterations can be as large as $O(\sqrt{\kappa}\ln(\frac{1}{\varepsilon}))$ to achieve the estimation error $\varepsilon$. In this work, we derive a quantum state tomography scheme that improves the dependence on $\kappa$ to the logarithmic scale; namely, our algorithm could achieve the approximation error $\varepsilon$ in $O(\ln(\frac{1}{\kappa\varepsilon}))$ steps. The improvement comes from the application of the non-convex Riemannian gradient descent (RGD). The contracting factor in our approach is thus a universal constant that is independent of the given state. Our theoretical results of extremely fast convergence and nearly optimal error bounds are corroborated by numerical results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Angle-robust Two-Qubit Gates in a Linear Ion Crystal</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.04814</link>
    <author>Zhubing Jia, Shilin Huang, Mingyu Kang, Ke Sun, Robert F. Spivey, Jungsang Kim, Kenneth R. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In trapped-ion quantum computers, two-qubit entangling gates are generated by applying spin-dependent force which uses phonons to mediate interaction between the internal states of the ions. To maintain high-fidelity two-qubit gates under fluctuating experimental parameters, robust pulse-design methods are applied to remove the residual spin-motion entanglement in the presence of motional mode frequency drifts. Here we propose an improved pulse-design method that also guarantees the robustness of the two-qubit rotation angle against uniform mode frequency drifts by combining pulses with opposite sensitivity of the angle to mode frequency drifts. We experimentally measure the performance of the designed gates and see an improvement on both gate fidelity and gate performance under uniform mode frequency offsets.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time Evolution of Uniform Sequential Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03751</link>
    <author>Nikita Astrakhantsev, Sheng-Hsuan Lin, Frank Pollmann, Adam Smith</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulating time evolution of generic quantum many-body systems using classical numerical approaches has an exponentially growing cost either with evolution time or with the system size. In this work, we present a polynomially scaling hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for time evolving a one-dimensional uniform system in the thermodynamic limit. This algorithm uses a layered uniform sequential quantum circuit as a variational ansatz to represent infinite translation-invariant quantum states. We show numerically that this ansatz requires a number of parameters polynomial in the simulation time for a given accuracy. Furthermore, this favourable scaling of the ansatz is maintained during our variational evolution algorithm. All steps of the hybrid optimisation are designed with near-term digital quantum computers in mind. After benchmarking the evolution algorithm on a classical computer, we demonstrate the measurement of observables of this uniform state using a finite number of qubits on a cloud-based quantum processing unit. With more efficient tensor contraction schemes, this algorithm may also offer improvements as a classical numerical algorithm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-classical tradeoffs and multi-controlled quantum gate decompositions in variational algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.04378</link>
    <author>Teague Tomesh, Nicholas Allen, Zain Saleem</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for unconstrained optimization problems, such as the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA), have been proposed as interesting near-term algorithms which operate under a hybrid quantum-classical execution model. Recent work has shown that the QAOA can also be applied to constrained combinatorial optimization problems by incorporating the problem constraints within the design of the variational ansatz - often resulting in quantum circuits containing many multi-controlled gate operations. This paper investigates potential resource tradeoffs for the QAOA when applied to the particular constrained optimization problem of Maximum Independent Set. We consider three variants of the QAOA which make different tradeoffs between the number of classical parameters, quantum gates, and iterations of classical optimization. We also study the quantum cost of decomposing the QAOA circuits on hardware which may support different qubit technologies and native gate sets, and compare the different algorithms using the gate decomposition score which combines the fidelity of the gate operations with the efficiency of the decomposition into a single metric. We find that all three QAOA variants can attain similar performance but the classical and quantum resource costs may vary greatly between them.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying Quantum Causal Influences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.04306</link>
    <author>Lucas Hutter, Rafael Chaves, Ranieri Nery, George Moreno, Daniel J. Brod</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Causal influences are at the core of any empirical science, the reason why its quantification is of paramount relevance for the mathematical theory of causality and applications. Quantum correlations, however, challenge our notion of cause and effect, implying that tools and concepts developed over the years having in mind a classical world, have to be reevaluated in the presence of quantum effects. Here, we propose the quantum version of the most common causality quantifier, the average causal effect (ACE), measuring how much a target quantum system is changed by interventions on its presumed cause. Not only it offers an innate manner to quantify causation in two-qubit gates but also in alternative quantum computation models such as the measurement-based version, suggesting that causality can be used as a proxy for optimizing quantum algorithms. Considering quantum teleportation, we show that any pure entangled state offers an advantage in terms of causal effects as compared to separable states. This broadness of different uses showcases that, just as in the classical case, the quantification of causal influence has foundational and applied consequences and can lead to a yet totally unexplored tool for quantum information science.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>