<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Inevitability of knowing less than nothing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14424</link>
    <author>Gilad Gour, Mark M. Wilde, Sarah Brandsen, Isabelle Jianing Geng</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A colloquial interpretation of entropy is that it is the knowledge gained upon learning the outcome of a random experiment. Conditional entropy is then interpreted as the knowledge gained upon learning the outcome of one random experiment after learning the outcome of another, possibly statistically dependent, random experiment. In the classical world, entropy and conditional entropy take only non-negative values, consistent with the intuition that one has regarding the aforementioned interpretations. However, for certain entangled states, one obtains negative values when evaluating commonly accepted and information-theoretically justified formulas for the quantum conditional entropy, leading to the confounding conclusion that one can know less than nothing in the quantum world. Here, we introduce a physically motivated framework for defining quantum conditional entropy, based on two simple postulates inspired by the second law of thermodynamics (non-decrease of entropy) and extensivity of entropy, and we argue that all plausible definitions of quantum conditional entropy should respect these two postulates. We then prove that all plausible quantum conditional entropies take on negative values for certain entangled states, so that it is inevitable that one can know less than nothing in the quantum world. All of our arguments are based on constructions of physical processes that respect the first postulate, the one inspired by the second law of thermodynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement optimization of variational quantum simulation by classical shadow and derandomization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13934</link>
    <author>Kouhei Nakaji, Suguru Endo, Yuichiro Matsuzaki, Hideaki Hakoshima</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulating large quantum systems is the ultimate goal of quantum computing. Variational quantum simulation (VQS) gives us a tool to achieve the goal in near-term devices by distributing the computation load to both classical and quantum computers. However, as the size of the quantum system becomes large, the execution of VQS becomes more and more challenging. One of the most severe challenges is the drastic increase in the number of measurements; for example, the number of measurements tends to increase by the fourth power of the number of qubits in a quantum simulation with a chemical Hamiltonian. This work aims to dramatically decrease the number of measurements in VQS by recently proposed shadow-based strategies such as classical shadow and derandomization. Even though previous literature shows that shadow-based strategies successfully optimize measurements in the variational quantum optimization (VQO), how to apply them to VQS was unclear due to the gap between VQO and VQS in measuring observables. In this paper, we bridge the gap by changing the way of measuring observables in VQS and propose an algorithm to optimize measurements in VQS by shadow-based strategies. Our theoretical analysis not only reveals the advantage of using our algorithm in VQS but theoretically supports using shadow-based strategies in VQO, whose advantage has only been given numerically. Additionally, our numerical experiment shows the validity of using our algorithm with a quantum chemical system.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Interpolating between Rényi entanglement entropies for arbitrary bipartitions via operator geometric means</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14438</link>
    <author>Dávid Bugár, Péter Vrana</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The asymptotic restriction problem for tensors can be reduced to finding all parameters that are normalized, monotone under restrictions, additive under direct sums and multiplicative under tensor products. The simplest such parameters are the flattening ranks, the ranks of matrices obtained by partitioning the tensor factors into two subsets. Over the complex numbers, a refinement of this problem, originating in the theory of quantum entanglement, is to find the optimal rate of entanglement transformations as a function of the error exponent. This trade-off can also be characterized in terms of the set of normalized, additive, multiplicative functionals that are monotone in a suitable sense, which includes the restriction-monotones as well. For example, the flattening ranks generalize to the (exponentiated) Rényi entanglement entropies of order $\alpha\in[0,1]$. More complicated parameters of this type are known, which interpolate between the flattening ranks or Rényi entropies for special bipartitions, with one of the parts being a single tensor factor. We introduce a new construction of subadditive and submultiplicative monotones in terms of a regularized Rényi divergence between many copies of the pure state represented by the tensor and a suitable sequence of positive operators. We give explicit families of operators that correspond to the flattening-based functionals, and show that they can be combined in a nontrivial way using weighted operator geometric means. For order parameters $\alpha\in[0,1]$, this leads to a new characterization of the previously known additive and multiplicative monotones, while for $\alpha\in[1/2,1]$ we find new submultiplicative and subadditive monotones that interpolate between the Rényi entropies for all bipartitions. In addition, we find lower bounds on the new functionals that are superadditive and supermultiplicative.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Two instances of random access code in the quantum regime</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14422</link>
    <author>Nitica Sakharwade, Michał Studziński, Michał Eckstein, Paweł Horodecki</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider two classes of quantum generalisations of Random Access Code (RAC) and study lower bounds for probabilities of success for such tasks. It provides a useful framework for the study of certain information processing tasks with constrained resources. The first class is based on a random access code with quantum inputs and output known as No-Signalling Quantum RAC (NS-QRAC) [A. Grudka et al. Phys. Rev. A 92, 052312 (2015)], where unbounded entanglement and constrained classical communication are allowed, which can be seen as quantum teleportation with constrained classical communication, for which we provide a quantum lower bound. We consider two modifications to the NS-QRAC scenario, first where unbounded entanglement and constrained quantum communication is allowed and, second where bounded entanglement and unconstrained classical communication are allowed, where we find a monogamy relation for the transmission fidelities, which -- in contrast to the usual communication schemes -- involves multiple senders and a single receiver. We provide lower bounds for these scenarios. The second class is based on a random access code with a quantum channel and shared entanglement [A. Tavakoli et al. PRX Quantum 2 (4) 040357 (2021)]. We study the set of tasks where two inputs made of two digits of $d$-base are encoded over a qudit and a maximally entangled state, which can be seen as quantum dense coding with constrained quantum communication, for which we provide quantum lower bounds for $d=2,3,4$. The encoding employed utilises Gray codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Robust Quantum Control: Analysis & Synthesis via Averaging</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14193</link>
    <author>Robert L. Kosut, Gaurav Bhole, Herschel Rabitz</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An approach is presented for robustness analysis and quantum (unitary) control synthesis based on the classic method of averaging. The result is a multicriterion optimization competing the nominal (uncertainty-free) fidelity with a well known robustness measure: the size of an interaction (error) Hamiltonian, essentially the first term in the Magnus expansion of an interaction unitary. Combining this with the fact that the topology of the control landscape at high fidelity is determined by the null space of the nominal fidelity Hessian, we arrive at a new two-stage algorithm. Once the nominal fidelity is sufficiently high, we approximate both the nominal fidelity and robustness measure as quadratics in the control increments. An optimal solution is obtained by solving a convex optimization for the control increments at each iteration to keep the nominal fidelity high and reduce the robustness measure. Additionally, by separating fidelity from the robustness measure, more flexibility is available for uncertainty modeling.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>