<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Simulating quantum circuits using efficient tensor network contraction algorithms with subexponential upper bound</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01498</link>
    <author>Thorsten B. Wahl, Sergii Strelchuk</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive a rigorous upper bound on the classical computation time of finite-ranged tensor network contractions in $d \geq 2$ dimensions. By means of the Sphere Separator Theorem, we are able to take advantage of the structure of quantum circuits to speed up contractions to show that quantum circuits of single-qubit and finite-ranged two-qubit gates can be classically simulated in subexponential time in the number of gates. In many practically relevant cases this beats standard simulation schemes. Moreover, our algorithm leads to speedups of several orders of magnitude over naive contraction schemes for two-dimensional quantum circuits on as little as an $8 \times 8$ lattice. We obtain similarly efficient contraction schemes for Google's Sycamore-type quantum circuits, instantaneous quantum polynomial-time circuits and non-homogeneous (2+1)-dimensional random quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Techniques for combining fast local decoders with global decoders under circuit-level noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01178</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Luis Goncalves, Prasahnt Sivarajah, Eric Peterson, Sebastian Grimberg</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Implementing algorithms on a fault-tolerant quantum computer will require fast decoding throughput and latency times to prevent an exponential increase in buffer times between the applications of gates. In this work we begin by quantifying these requirements. We then introduce the construction of local neural network (NN) decoders using three-dimensional convolutions. These local decoders are adapted to circuit-level noise and can be applied to surface code volumes of arbitrary size. Their application removes errors arising from a certain number of faults, which serves to substantially reduce the syndrome density. Remaining errors can then be corrected by a global decoder, such as Blossom or Union Find, with their implementation significantly accelerated due to the reduced syndrome density. However, in the circuit-level setting, the corrections applied by the local decoder introduce many vertical pairs of highlighted vertices. To obtain a low syndrome density in the presence of vertical pairs, we consider a strategy of performing a syndrome collapse which removes many vertical pairs and reduces the size of the decoding graph used by the global decoder. We also consider a strategy of performing a vertical cleanup, which consists of removing all local vertical pairs prior to implementing the global decoder. Lastly, we estimate the cost of implementing our local decoders on Field Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGAs).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tensor types and their use in physics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01135</link>
    <author>Andreas Bauer, Alexander Nietner</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The content of this paper can be roughly organized into a three-level hierarchy of generality. At the first, most general level, we introduce a new language which allows us to express various categorical structures in a systematic and explicit manner in terms of so-called 2-schemes. Although 2-schemes can formalize categorical structures such as symmetric monoidal categories, they are not limited to this, and can be used to define structures with no categorical analogue. Most categorical structures come with an effective graphical calculus such as string diagrams for symmetric monoidal categories, and the same is true more generally for interesting 2-schemes. In this work, we focus on one particular non-categorical 2-scheme, whose instances we refer to as tensor types. At the second level of the hierarchy, we work out different flavors of this 2-scheme in detail. The effective graphical calculus of tensor types is that of tensor networks or Penrose diagrams, that is, string diagrams without a flow of time. As such, tensor types are similar to compact closed categories, though there are various small but potentially important differences. Also, the two definitions use completely different mechanisms despite both being examples of 2-schemes. At the third level of the hierarchy, we provide a long list of different families of concrete tensor types, in a way which makes them accessible to concrete computations, motivated by their potential use in physics. Different tensor types describe different types of physical models, such as classical or quantum physics, deterministic or statistical physics, many-body or single-body physics, or matter with or without symmetries or fermions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Block sparsity and gauge mediated weight sharing for learning dynamical laws from data</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01591</link>
    <author>M. Götte, J. Fuksa, I. Roth, J. Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent years have witnessed an increased interest in recovering dynamical laws of complex systems in a largely data-driven fashion under meaningful hypotheses. In this work, we propose a method for scalably learning dynamical laws of classical dynamical systems from data. As a novel ingredient, to achieve an efficient scaling with the system size, block sparse tensor trains - instances of tensor networks applied to function dictionaries - are used and the self similarity of the problem is exploited. For the latter, we propose an approach of gauge mediated weight sharing, inspired by notions of machine learning, which significantly improves performance over previous approaches. The practical performance of the method is demonstrated numerically on three one-dimensional systems - the Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou system, rotating magnetic dipoles and classical particles interacting via modified Lennard-Jones potentials. We highlight the ability of the method to recover these systems, requiring 1400 samples to recover the 50 particle Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou system to residuum of $5\times10^{-7}$, 900 samples to recover the 50 particle magnetic dipole chain to residuum of $1.5\times10^{-4}$ and 7000 samples to recover the Lennard-Jones system of 10 particles to residuum $1.5\times10^{-2}$. The robustness against additive Gaussian noise is demonstrated for the magnetic dipole system.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Real-Time Krylov Theory for Quantum Computing Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01063</link>
    <author>Yizhi Shen, Katherine Klymko, James Sud, David B. Williams-Young, Wibe A. de Jong, Norm M. Tubman</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers provide new avenues to access ground and excited state properties of systems otherwise difficult to simulate on classical hardware. New approaches using subspaces generated by real-time evolution have shown efficiency in extracting eigenstate information, but the full capabilities of such approaches are still not understood. In recent work, we developed the variational quantum phase estimation (VQPE) method, a compact and efficient real-time algorithm to extract eigenvalues on quantum hardware. Here we build on that work by theoretically and numerically exploring a generalized Krylov scheme where the Krylov subspace is constructed through a parametrized real-time evolution, which applies to the VQPE algorithm as well as others. We establish an error bound that justifies the fast convergence of our spectral approximation. We also derive how the overlap with high energy eigenstates becomes suppressed from real-time subspace diagonalization and we visualize the process that shows the signature phase cancellations at specific eigenenergies. We investigate various algorithm implementations and consider performance when stochasticity is added to the target Hamiltonian in the form of spectral statistics. To demonstrate the practicality of such real-time evolution, we discuss its application to fundamental problems in quantum computation such as electronic structure predictions for strongly correlated systems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>