<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>On the Role of Quantum Coherence in Thermodynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.13612</link>
    <author>Gilad Gour</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We find necessary and sufficient conditions to determine the inter-convertibility of quantum systems under time-translation covariant evolution, and use it to solve several problems in quantum thermodynamics both in the single-shot and asymptotic regimes. It is well known that the resource theory of quantum athermality is not reversible, but in PRL 111, 250404 (2013) it was claimed that the theory becomes reversible "provided a sublinear amount of coherent superposition over energy levels is available". Here we show that the original proof of this claim is incorrect, and then provide a completely new rigorous proof for the pure-state case. A proof of the same claim for the mixed-state case is still lacking.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Only Classical Parametrised States have Optimal Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.14142</link>
    <author>Wilfred Salmon, Sergii Strelchuk, David Arvidsson-Shukur</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Measurements of quantum states form a key component in quantum-information processing. It is therefore an important task to compare measurements and furthermore decide if a measurement strategy is optimal. We introduce a framework that allows one to conclusively establish if a measurement is optimal. Our method relies on the fundamental property of expected errors of estimators, known as risk, and it does not involve optimisation over entropic quantities. The framework applies to finite sample sizes and lack of prior knowledge, as well as to the asymptotic and Bayesian settings. We prove a no-go theorem that shows that only classical states admit optimal measurements. We further consider the less restrictive notion of an approximately optimal measurement and give sufficient conditions for such measurements to exist. Finally, we generalise the notion of when an estimator is inadmissible (i.e. strictly worse than an alternative), and provide two sufficient conditions for a measurement to be inadmissible.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Infinite-randomness criticality in monitored quantum dynamics with static disorder</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.14002</link>
    <author>Aidan Zabalo, Justin H. Wilson, Michael J. Gullans, Romain Vasseur, Sarang Gopalakrishnan, David A. Huse, J. H. Pixley</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a model of monitored quantum dynamics with quenched spatial randomness: specifically, random quantum circuits with spatially varying measurement rates. These circuits undergo a measurement-induced phase transition (MIPT) in their entanglement structure, but the nature of the critical point differs drastically from the case with constant measurement rate. In particular, at the critical measurement rate, we find that the entanglement of a subsystem of size $\ell$ scales as $S \sim \sqrt{\ell}$; moreover, the dynamical critical exponent $z = \infty$. The MIPT is flanked by Griffiths phases with continuously varying dynamical exponents. We argue for this infinite-randomness scenario on general grounds and present numerical evidence that it captures some features of the universal critical properties of MIPT using large-scale simulations of Clifford circuits. These findings demonstrate that the relevance and irrelevance of perturbations to the MIPT can naturally be interpreted using a powerful heuristic known as the Harris criterion.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement entropy scaling of noisy random quantum circuits in two dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.13999</link>
    <author>Meng Zhang, Chao Wang, Shaojun Dong, Hao Zhang, Yongjian Han, Lixin He</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Whether noisy quantum devices without error correction can provide quantum advantage over classical computers is the central issue of current quantum computation. In this work, the random quantum circuits, which are used as the paradigm model to demonstrate quantum advantage, are simulated with noisy gates on experiment relevant two-dimensional architecture. With comprehensive numerical simulation and theoretical analysis, we find that the maximum achievable operator entanglement entropy, which indicates maximal simulation cost, has area law scaling with the system size for constant noise rate, implying that it is possible to efficiently simulate noisy random quantum circuits by tensor network algorithm. On the other hand, we also find that to maintain volume law scaling, the noise rate must decrease with the system size. Therefore, reducing the noise rate takes precedence over expanding the system size to demonstrate quantum advantage in random quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Mitigation via Quantum-Noise-Effect Circuit Groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.13907</link>
    <author>Yusuke Hama, Hirofumi Nishi</author>
    <pubDate>May 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Our near-term quantum computers have been built as intermediate-scale quantum devices and are fragile against quantum noise effects, namely, NISQ devices. Traditional quantum-error-correcting (QEC) codes are not implemented on such devices and to perform quantum computation in good accuracy with these machines we need to develop alternative approaches for mitigating quantum computational errors. In this work, we propose quantum error mitigation (QEM) scheme for quantum computational errors which occur due to couplings with environments during gate operations, i.e., decoherence. To establish our QEM scheme, first we estimate the quantum noise effects on single-qubit states and represent them as groups of quantum circuits, namely, quantum-noise-effect circuit groups. Then our QEM scheme is conducted by subtracting expectation values generated by the quantum-noise-effect circuit groups from that obtained by the quantum circuit for the quantum algorithm under consideration. As a result, the quantum noise effect is reduced, and we obtain approximately the ideal expectation values via the quantum-noise-effect circuit group and the number of elementary quantum circuits composing it scales polynomial with respect to the product of the depth of quantum algorithm and the number of register bits. To numerically demonstrate the validity of our QEM scheme, we run noisy quantum simulations of qubits under the amplitude damping (AD) effects for four types of quantum algorithms. Our QEM scheme is solely composed of quantum-computational operations (quantum gates and measurements), and thus, it can be conducted by any type of quantum device without having limitations on the number of register bits and error rates of quantum gates. In addition, it can be applied to error mitigation for many other types of quantum noise effects as well as noisy quantum computing of long-depth quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>