<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A mathematical framework for quantum Hamiltonian simulation and duality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11941</link>
    <author>Harriet Apel, Toby Cubitt</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Analogue Hamiltonian simulation is a promising near-term application of quantum computing and has recently been put on a theoretical footing. In Hamiltonian simulation, a physical Hamiltonian is engineered to have identical physics to another - often very different - Hamiltonian. This is qualitatively similar to the notion of duality in physics, whereby two superficially different theories are mathematically equivalent in some precise sense. However, existing characterisations of Hamiltonian simulations are not sufficiently general to extend to all dualities in physics. In particular, they cannot encompass the important cases of strong/weak and high-temperature/low-temperature dualities. In this work, we give three physically motivated axiomatisations of duality, formulated respectively in terms of observables, partition functions and entropies. We prove that these axiomatisations are equivalent, and characterise the mathematical form that any duality satisfying these axioms must take. A building block in one of our results is a strengthening of earlier results on entropy-preserving maps to maps that are entropy-preserving up to an additive constant, which we prove decompose as a direct sum of unitary and anti-unitary components, which may be of independent mathematical interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Alternating Layered Variational Quantum Circuits Can Be Classically Optimized Efficiently Using Classical Shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11623</link>
    <author>Afrad Basheer, Yuan Feng, Christopher Ferrie, Sanjiang Li</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms (VQAs) are the quantum analog of classical neural networks (NNs). A VQA consists of a parameterized quantum circuit (PQC) which is composed of multiple layers of ansatzes (simpler PQCs, which are an analogy of NN layers) that differ only in selections of parameters. Previous work has identified the alternating layered ansatz as potentially a new standard ansatz in near-term quantum computing. Indeed, shallow alternating layered VQAs are easy to implement and have been shown to be both trainable and expressive. In this work, we introduce a training algorithm with an exponential reduction in training cost of such VQAs. Moreover, our algorithm uses classical shadows of quantum input data, and can hence be run on a classical computer with rigorous performance guarantees. We demonstrate 2--3 orders of magnitude improvement in the training cost using our algorithm for the example problems of finding state preparation circuits and the quantum autoencoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>No [[n, k, d < 86]] code can violate the quantum Hamming bound</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11800</link>
    <author>Emanuel Dallas, Faidon Andreadakis, Daniel Lidar</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It is well-known that pure quantum error correcting codes (QECCs) are constrained by a quantum version of the Hamming bound. Whether impure codes also obey such a bound, however, remains a long-standing question with practical implications for the efficacy of QECCs. We employ a combination of previously derived bounds on QECCs to demonstrate that a subset of all codes must obey the quantum Hamming bound. Specifically, we combine an analytical bound due to Rains with a numerical bound due to Li and Xing to show that no [[n,k,d < 86]] code can violate the quantum Hamming bound.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A SAT Encoding for Optimal Clifford Circuit Synthesis</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11713</link>
    <author>Sarah Schneider, Lukas Burgholzer, Robert Wille</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Executing quantum algorithms on a quantum computer requires compilation to representations that conform to all restrictions imposed by the device. Due to device's limited coherence times and gate fidelities, the compilation process has to be optimized as much as possible. To this end, an algorithm's description first has to be synthesized using the device's gate library. In this paper, we consider the optimal synthesis of Clifford circuits -- an important subclass of quantum circuits, with various applications. Such techniques are essential to establish lower bounds for (heuristic) synthesis methods and gauging their performance. Due to the huge search space, existing optimal techniques are limited to a maximum of six qubits. The contribution of this work is twofold: First, we propose an optimal synthesis method for Clifford circuits based on encoding the task as a satisfiability (SAT) problem and solving it using a SAT solver in conjunction with a binary search scheme. The resulting tool is demonstrated to synthesize optimal circuits for up to $26$ qubits -- more than four times as many as the current state of the art. Second, we experimentally show that the overhead introduced by state-of-the-art heuristics exceeds the lower bound by $27\%$ on average. The resulting tool is publicly available at https://github.com/cda-tum/qmap.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>No graph states can be prepared in quantum networks with bipartite sources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12099</link>
    <author>Owidiusz Makuta, Laurens T. Ligthart, Remigiusz Augusiak</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In research concerning quantum networks, it is often assumed that the parties can classically communicate with each other. However, classical communication might introduce substantial delay to the network, especially if it is large. As the latency of a network is one of its most important characteristics, it is interesting to consider quantum networks in which parties cannot communicate classically and ask what limitations this assumption imposes on the possibility of preparing multipartite states in such networks. We show that graph states of arbitrary prime local dimension known for their numerous applications in quantum information cannot be generated in a quantum network in which parties are connected via sources of bipartite quantum states and the classical communication is replaced by some pre-shared classical correlations. We then generalise our result to arbitrary quantum states that are sufficiently close to graph states.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>