<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadows with Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03272</link>
    <author>Kaifeng Bu, Dax Enshan Koh, Roy J. Garcia, Arthur Jaffe</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The classical shadow estimation protocol is a noise-resilient and sample-efficient quantum algorithm for learning the properties of quantum systems. Its performance depends on the choice of a unitary ensemble, which must be chosen by a user in advance. What is the weakest assumption that can be made on the chosen unitary ensemble that would still yield meaningful and interesting results? To address this question, we consider the class of Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles, i.e. unitary ensembles that are invariant under multiplication by a Pauli operator. This class includes many previously studied ensembles like the local and global Clifford ensembles as well as locally scrambled unitary ensembles. For this class of ensembles, we provide an explicit formula for the reconstruction map corresponding to the shadow channel and give explicit sample complexity bounds. In addition, we provide two applications of our results. Our first application is to locally scrambled unitary ensembles, where we give explicit formulas for the reconstruction map and sample complexity bounds that circumvent the need to solve an exponential-sized linear system. Our second application is to the classical shadow tomography of quantum channels with Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles. Our results pave the way for more efficient or robust protocols for predicting important properties of quantum states, such as their fidelity, entanglement entropy, and quantum Fisher information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Transitions in Entanglement Complexity in Random Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02648</link>
    <author>Sarah True, Alioscia Hamma</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement is the defining characteristic of quantum mechanics. Bipartite entanglement is characterized by the von Neumann entropy. Entanglement is not just described by a number, however; it is also characterized by its level of complexity. The complexity of entanglement is at the root of the onset of quantum chaos, universal distribution of entanglement spectrum statistics, difficulty of the disentangling algorithm, and temporal entanglement fluctuations. In this paper, we numerically show how a crossover from a simple pattern of entanglement to a universal, complex pattern can be driven by doping a random Clifford circuit with $T$ gates. This work shows that quantum complexity and complex entanglement stem from the conjunction of entanglement and non-stabilizer resources, also known as magic.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Identification of topological phases using classically-optimized variational quantum eigensolver</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02909</link>
    <author>Ken N. Okada, Keita Osaki, Kosuke Mitarai, Keisuke Fujii</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) is regarded as a promising candidate of hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for the near-term quantum computers. Meanwhile, VQE is confronted with a challenge that statistical error associated with the measurement as well as systematic error could significantly hamper the optimization. To circumvent this issue, we propose classically-optimized VQE (co-VQE), where the whole process of the optimization is efficiently conducted on a classical computer. The efficacy of the method is guaranteed by the observation that quantum circuits with a constant (or logarithmic) depth are classically tractable via simulations of local subsystems. In co-VQE, we only use quantum computers to measure nonlocal quantities after the parameters are optimized. As proof-of-concepts, we present numerical experiments on quantum spin models with topological phases. After the optimization, we identify the topological phases by nonlocal order parameters as well as unsupervised machine learning on inner products between quantum states. The proposed method maximizes the advantage of using quantum computers while avoiding strenuous optimization on noisy quantum devices. Furthermore, in terms of quantum machine learning, our study shows an intriguing approach that employs quantum computers to generate data of quantum systems while using classical computers for the learning process.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Locally mediated entanglement through gravity from first principles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03368</link>
    <author>Marios Christodoulou, Andrea Di Biagio, Markus Aspelmeyer, Časlav Brukner, Carlo Rovelli, Richard Howl</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Observing entanglement generation mediated by a local field certifies that the field cannot be classical. This information-theoretic argument is at the heart of the race to observe gravity-mediated entanglement in a `table-top' experiment. Previous derivations of the effect assume the locality of interactions, while using an instantaneous interaction to derive the effect. We correct this by giving a first principles derivation of mediated entanglement using linearised gravity. The framework is Lorentz covariant -- thus local -- and yields Lorentz and gauge invariant expressions for the relevant quantum observables. For completeness we also cover the electromagnetic case. An experimental consequence of our analysis is the possibility to observe *retarded* mediated entanglement, which avoids the need of taking relativistic locality as an assumption. This is a difficult experiment for gravity, but could be feasible for electromagnetism. Our results confirm that the entanglement is dynamically mediated by the gravitational field.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Methods and Results for Quantum Optimal Pulse Control on Superconducting Qubit Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03260</link>
    <author>Elisha Siddiqui Matekole, Yao-Lung L. Fang, Meifeng Lin</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The effective use of current Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) devices is often limited by the noise which is caused by interaction with the environment and affects the fidelity of quantum gates. In transmon qubit systems, the quantum gate fidelity can be improved by applying control pulses that can minimize the effects of the environmental noise. In this work, we employ physics-guided quantum optimal control strategies to design optimal pulses driving quantum gates on superconducting qubit systems. We test our results by conducting experiments on the IBM Q hardware using their OpenPulse API. We compare the performance of our pulse-optimized quantum gates against the default quantum gates and show that the optimized pulses improve the fidelity of the quantum gates, in particular the single-qubit gates. We discuss the challenges we encountered in our work and point to possible future improvements.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>