<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Decohering Tensor Network Quantum Machine Learning Models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01195</link>
    <author>Haoran Liao, Ian Convy, Zhibo Yang, K. Birgitta Whaley</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tensor network quantum machine learning (QML) models are promising applications on near-term quantum hardware. While decoherence of qubits is expected to decrease the performance of QML models, it is unclear to what extent the diminished performance can be compensated for by adding ancillas to the models and accordingly increasing the virtual bond dimension of the models. We investigate here the competition between decoherence and adding ancillas on the classification performance of two models, with an analysis of the decoherence effect from the perspective of regression. We present numerical evidence that the fully-decohered unitary tree tensor network (TTN) with two ancillas performs at least as well as the non-decohered unitary TTN, suggesting that it is beneficial to add at least two ancillas to the unitary TTN regardless of the amount of decoherence may be consequently introduced.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Software Tools for Decoding Quantum Low-Density Parity Check Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01180</link>
    <author>Lucas Berent, Lukas Burgholzer, Robert Wille</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Error Correction (QEC) is an essential field of research towards the realization of large-scale quantum computers. On the theoretical side, a lot of effort is put into designing error-correcting codes that protect quantum data from errors, which inevitably happen due to the noisy nature of quantum hardware and quantum bits (qubits). Protecting data with an error-correcting code necessitates means to recover the original data, given a potentially corrupted data set-a task referred to as decoding. It is vital that decoding algorithms can recover error-free states in an efficient manner. While theoretical properties of recent QEC methods have been extensively studied, good techniques to analyze their performance in practically more relevant settings is still a widely unexplored area. In this work, we propose a set of software tools that allows to numerically experiment with so-called Quantum Low-Density Parity Check codes (QLDPC codes)-a broad class of codes, some of which have recently been shown to be asymptotically good. Based on that, we provide an implementation of a general decoder for QLDPC codes. On top of that, we propose an efficient heuristic decoder that tackles the runtime bottlenecks of the general QLDPC decoder while still maintaining comparable decoding performance. These tools eventually allow to confirm theoretical results around QLDPC codes in a more practical setting and showcase the value of software tools (in addition to theoretical considerations) for investigating codes for practical applications. The resulting tool, which is publicly available at https://github.com/lucasberent/qecc under the MIT license, is meant to provide a playground for the search for "practically good" quantum codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Shuttling an electron spin through a silicon quantum dot array</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00920</link>
    <author>A.M.J. Zwerver, S.V. Amitonov, S.L. de Snoo, M.T. Mądzik, M. Russ, A. Sammak, G. Scappucci, L.M.K. Vandersypen</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Coherent links between qubits separated by tens of micrometers are expected to facilitate scalable quantum computing architectures for spin qubits in electrically-defined quantum dots. These links create space for classical on-chip control electronics between qubit arrays, which can help to alleviate the so-called wiring bottleneck. A promising method of achieving coherent links between distant spin qubits consists of shuttling the spin through an array of quantum dots. Here, we use a linear array of four tunnel-coupled quantum dots in a 28Si/SiGe heterostructure to create a short quantum link. We move an electron spin through the quantum dot array by adjusting the electrochemical potential for each quantum dot sequentially. By pulsing the gates repeatedly, we shuttle an electron forward and backward through the array up to 250 times, which corresponds to a total distance of approximately 80 \mum. We make an estimate of the spin-flip probability per hop in these experiments and conclude that this is well below 0.01% per hop.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficiency of estimators for locally asymptotically normal quantum statistical models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00832</link>
    <author>Akio Fujiwara, Koichi Yamagata</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We herein establish an asymptotic representation theorem for locally asymptotically normal quantum statistical models. This theorem enables us to study the asymptotic efficiency of quantum estimators such as quantum regular estimators and quantum minimax estimators, leading to a universal tight lower bound beyond the i.i.d. assumption. This formulation complements the theory of quantum contiguity developed in the previous paper [Fujiwara and Yamagata, Bernoulli 26 (2020) 2105-2141], providing a solid foundation of the theory of weak quantum local asymptotic normality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dependence of measurement outcomes on the dynamics of quantum coherent interactions between the system and the meter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00751</link>
    <author>Tomonori Matsushita, Holger F. Hofmann</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Information about the internal properties of a system can only be obtained through interactions of the system with an external meter. However, such interactions generally result in entanglement between the system and the meter, making it difficult to trace the measurement result back to a specific value of the physical property in the system. It is therefore possible that the outcomes of quantum measurements depend in a non-trivial manner on the dynamics of the measurement interaction, possibly providing a physical explanation for the role of measurement contexts in quantum mechanics. Here, we show that the effects of the measurement interaction on the meter can be described entirely in terms of the quantum coherent system dynamics associated with the back-action on the system. For sufficiently small back-action uncertainties, the physical property of the system is described by a weak value obtained from the Hamilton-Jacobi equation of the back-action dynamics. At higher measurement resolutions, the observed values are determined by quantum interferences between different amounts of back-action. Eigenvalues emerge when the quantum interferences between different back-actions correspond to a Fourier transform in the back-action parameter. We conclude that the values of physical properties obtained in quantum measurements originate from the quantum coherent properties of the back-action dynamics generated by that physical property during an interaction. Measurement outcomes represent elements of the dynamics and cannot be explained by measurement independent elements of reality.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>