<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Refuting spectral compatibility of quantum marginals</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06349</link>
    <author>Felix Huber, Nikolai Wyderka</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The spectral variant of the quantum marginal problem asks: Given prescribed spectra for a set of quantum marginals, does there exist a compatible joint state? The main idea of this work is a symmetry-reduced semidefinite programming hierarchy for detecting incompatible spectra. The hierarchy can provide refutations that are dimension-free, certifying incompatibility in all local dimensions. It equally applies to the compatibility of local unitary invariants, to the sums of Hermitian matrices problem, to optimize trace polynomials on the positive cone, and to certify vanishing Kronecker coefficients.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hardware optimized parity check gates for superconducting surface codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06382</link>
    <author>Matthew J. Reagor, Thomas C. Bohdanowicz. David Rodriguez Perez, Eyob A. Sete, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Error correcting codes use multi-qubit measurements to realize fault-tolerant quantum logic steps. In fact, the resources needed to scale-up fault-tolerant quantum computing hardware are largely set by this task. Tailoring next-generation processors for joint measurements, therefore, could result in improvements to speed, accuracy, or cost -- accelerating the development large-scale quantum computers. Here, we motivate such explorations by analyzing an unconventional surface code based on multi-body interactions between superconducting transmon qubits. Our central consideration, Hardware Optimized Parity (HOP) gates, achieves stabilizer-type measurements through simultaneous multi-qubit conditional phase accumulation. Despite the multi-body effects that underpin this approach, our estimates of logical faults suggest that this design can be at least as robust to realistic noise as conventional designs. We show a higher threshold of $1.25 \times 10^{-3}$ compared to the standard code's $0.79 \times 10^{-3}$. However, in the HOP code the logical error rate decreases more slowly with decreasing physical error rate. Our results point to a fruitful path forward towards extending gate-model platforms for error correction at the dawn of its empirical development.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ultimate limits of exoplanet spectroscopy: a quantum approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06050</link>
    <author>Zixin Huang, Christian Schwab, Cosmo Lupo</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One of the big challenges in exoplanet science is to determine the atmospheric makeup of extrasolar planets, and to find biosignatures that hint at the existence of biochemical processes on another world. The biomarkers we are trying to detect are gases in the exoplanet atmosphere like oxygen or methane, which have deep absorption features in the visible and near-infrared spectrum. Here we establish the ultimate quantum limit for determining the presence or absence of a spectral absorption line, for a dim source in the presence of a much brighter stellar source. We characterise the associated error exponent in both the frameworks of symmetric and asymmetric hypothesis testing. We found that a structured measurement based on spatial demultiplexing allows us to decouple the light coming from the planet and achieve the ultimate quantum limits. If the planet has intensity $\epsilon \ll 1$ relative to the star, we show that this approach significantly outperforms direct spectroscopy yielding an improvement of the error exponent by a factor $1/\epsilon$. We find the optimal measurement, which is a combination of interferometric techniques and spectrum analysis.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error mitigation for rotation symmetric bosonic codes with symmetry expansion</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06164</link>
    <author>Suguru Endo, Yasunari Suzuki, Kento Tsubouchi, Rui Asaoka, Kaoru Yamamoto, Yuichiro Matsuzaki, Yuuki Tokunaga</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The rotation symmetric bosonic code (RSBC) is a unified framework of practical bosonic codes that have rotation symmetries, such as cat codes and binomial codes. While cat codes achieve the break-even point in which the coherence time of the encoded qubits exceeds that of unencoded qubits, with binomial codes nearly approaching that point, the state preparation fidelity needs to be still improved for practical quantum computing. Concerning this problem, we investigate the framework of symmetry expansion, a class of quantum error mitigation that virtually projects the state onto the noise-free symmetric subspace by exploiting the system's intrinsic symmetries and post-processing of measurement outcomes. Although symmetry expansion has been limited to error mitigation of quantum states immediately before measurement, we successfully generalize symmetry expansion for state preparation. To implement our method, we use an ancilla qubit and only two controlled-rotation gates via dispersive interactions between the bosonic code states and the ancilla qubit. Interestingly, this method also allows us to virtually prepare the RSBC states only from easy-to-prepare states, e.g., coherent states. We also discuss that the conventional symmetry expansion protocol can be applied to improve the computation fidelity when the symmetries of rotation bosonic codes are unavailable due to low measurement fidelity. By giving comprehensive analytical and numerical arguments regarding the trace distance between the error-mitigated state and the ideal state and the sampling cost of quantum error mitigation, we show that symmetry expansion dramatically suppresses the effect of photon loss. Our novel error mitigation method will significantly enhance computation accuracy in the near-term bosonic quantum computing paradigm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generating $k$ EPR-pairs from an n-party resource state</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06497</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Yash Sharma, Mario Szegedy, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Motivated by quantum network applications over classical channels, we initiate the study of $n$-party resource states from which LOCC protocols can create EPR-pairs between any $k$ disjoint pairs of parties. We give constructions of such states where $k$ is not too far from the optimal $n/2$ while the individual parties need to hold only a constant number of qubits. In the special case when each party holds only one qubit, we describe a family of $n$-qubit states with $k$ proportional to $\log n$ based on Reed-Muller codes, as well as small numerically found examples for $k=2$ and $k=3$. We also prove some lower bounds, for example showing that if $k=n/2$ then the parties must have at least $\Omega(\log\log n)$ qubits each.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>