<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>On the computational hardness needed for quantum cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.04101</link>
    <author>Zvika Brakerski, Ran Canetti, Luowen Qian</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the classical model of computation, it is well established that one-way functions (OWF) are essential for almost every computational cryptographic application. In the quantum setting, however, OWFs appear not to be essential (Kretschmer 2021; Ananth et al., Morimae and Yamakawa 2022), and the question of whether a minimal primitive exists remains open. We consider EFI pairs -- efficiently samplable, statistically far but computationally indistinguishable pairs of distributions. Building on the work of Yan (2022) which shows equivalence between EFI pairs and statistical commitment schemes, we show that EFI pairs are necessary and sufficient for a large class of quantum-cryptographic applications. Specifically, while it was known how to construct commitments schemes, oblivious transfer, and general secure multiparty computation from any EFI, we show how to construct EFI pairs from minimalistic versions of each one of these primitives. We also construct from EFI quantum computational zero knowledge ($\mathsf{QCZK}$) proofs for all of $\mathsf{QIP}$, and construct EFI pairs from essentially any non-trivial $\mathsf{QCZK}$. This suggests that, for much of quantum cryptography, EFI pairs play a similar role to that played by OWFs in the classical setting: they are simple to describe, essential, and also serve as a linchpin for demonstrating equivalence between primitives.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Shortest Route to Non-Abelian Topological Order on a Quantum Processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03964</link>
    <author>Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Ruben Verresen, Ashvin Vishwanath</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A highly coveted goal is to realize emergent non-Abelian gauge theories and their anyonic excitations, which encode decoherence-free quantum information. While measurements in quantum devices provide new hope for scalably preparing such long-range entangled states, existing protocols using the experimentally established ingredients of a finite-depth circuit and a single round of measurement produce only Abelian states. Surprisingly, we show there exists a broad family of non-Abelian states -- namely those with a Lagrangian subgroup -- which can be created using these same minimal ingredients, bypassing the need for new resources such as feed-forward. To illustrate that this provides realistic protocols, we show how $D_4$ non-Abelian topological order can be realized, e.g., on Google's quantum processors using a depth-11 circuit and a single layer of measurements. Our work opens the way towards the realization and manipulation of non-Abelian topological orders, and highlights counter-intuitive features of the complexity of non-Abelian phases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum optimization with arbitrary connectivity using Rydberg atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03965</link>
    <author>Minh-Thi Nguyen, Jin-Guo Liu, Jonathan Wurtz, Mikhail D. Lukin, Sheng-Tao Wang, Hannes Pichler</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Programmable quantum systems based on Rydberg atom arrays have recently been used for hardware-efficient tests of quantum optimization algorithms [Ebadi et al., Science, 376, 1209 (2022)] with hundreds of qubits. In particular, the maximum independent set problem on the so-called unit-disk graphs, was shown to be efficiently encodable in such a quantum system. Here, we extend the classes of problems that can be efficiently encoded in Rydberg arrays by constructing explicit mappings from the original computation problems to maximum weighted independent set problems on unit-disk graphs, with at most a quadratic overhead in the number of qubits. We analyze several examples, including: maximum weighted independent set on graphs with arbitrary connectivity, quadratic unconstrained binary optimization problems with arbitrary or restricted connectivity, and integer factorization. Numerical simulations on small system sizes indicate that the adiabatic time scale for solving the mapped problems is strongly correlated with that of the original problems. Our work provides a blueprint for using Rydberg atom arrays to solve a wide range of combinatorial optimization problems with arbitrary connectivity, beyond the restrictions imposed by the hardware geometry.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Preservation of entanglement in local noisy channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.04422</link>
    <author>Priya Ghosh, Kornikar Sen, Ujjwal Sen</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement subject to noise can not be shielded against decaying. But, in case of many noisy channels, the degradation can be partially prevented by using local unitary operations. We consider the effect of local noise on shared quantum states and evaluate the amount of entanglement that can be preserved from deterioration. The amount of saved entanglement not only depends on the strength of the channel but also on the type of the channel, and in particular, it always vanishes for the depolarizing channel. The main motive of this work is to analyze the reason behind this dependency of saved entanglement by inspecting properties of the corresponding channels. In this context, we quantify and explore the biasnesses of channels towards the different states on which they act. We postulate that all biasness measures must vanish for depolarizing channels, and subsequently introduce a few measures of biasness. We also consider the entanglement capacities of channels. We observe that the joint behaviour of the biasness quantifiers and the entanglement capacity explains the nature of saved entanglement. Furthermore, we find a pair of upper bounds on saved entanglement which are noticed to imitate the graphical nature of the latter.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement barrier and its symmetry resolution: theory and experiment</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.04393</link>
    <author>Aniket Rath, Vittorio Vitale, Sara Murciano, Matteo Votto, Jérôme Dubail, Richard Kueng, Cyril Branciard, Pasquale Calabrese, Benoît Vermersch</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The operator entanglement (OE) is a key quantifier of the complexity of a reduced density matrix. In out-of-equilibrium situations, e.g. after a quantum quench of a product state, it is expected to exhibit an entanglement barrier. The OE of a reduced density matrix initially grows linearly as entanglement builds up between the local degrees of freedom, it then reaches a maximum, and ultimately decays to a small finite value as the reduced density matrix converges to a simple stationary state through standard thermalization mechanisms. Here, by performing a new data analysis of the published experimental results of [Brydges et al., Science 364, 260 (2019)], we obtain the first experimental measurement of the OE of a subsystem reduced density matrix in a quantum many-body system. We employ the randomized measurements toolbox and we introduce and develop a new efficient method to post-process experimental data in order to extract higher-order density matrix functionals and access the OE. The OE thus obtained displays the expected barrier as long as the experimental system is large enough. For smaller systems, we observe a barrier with a double-peak structure, whose origin can be interpreted in terms of pairs of quasi-particles being reflected at the boundary of the qubit chain. As $U(1)$ symmetry plays a key role in our analysis, we introduce the notion of symmetry resolved operator entanglement (SROE), in addition to the total OE. To gain further insights into the SROE, we provide a thorough theoretical analysis of this new quantity in chains of non-interacting fermions, which, in spite of their simplicity, capture most of the main features of OE and SROE. In particular, we uncover three main physical effects: the presence of a barrier in any charge sector, a time delay for the onset of the growth of SROE, and an effective equipartition between charge sectors.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>