<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Finite-rate sparse quantum codes aplenty</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03562</link>
    <author>Maxime Tremblay, Guillaume Duclos-Cianci, Stefanos Kourtis</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a methodology for generating random multi-qubit stabilizer codes based on solving a constraint satisfaction problem (CSP) on random bipartite graphs. This framework allows us to enforce stabilizer commutation, X/Z balancing, finite rate, sparsity, and maximum-degree constraints simultaneously in a CSP that we can then solve numerically. Using a state-of-the-art CSP solver, we obtain convincing evidence for the existence of a satisfiability threshold. Furthermore, the extent of the satisfiable phase increases with the number of qubits. In that phase, finding sparse codes becomes an easy problem. Moreover, we observe that the sparse codes found in the satisfiable phase practically achieve the channel capacity for erasure noise. Our results show that intermediate-size finite-rate sparse quantum codes are easy to find, while also demonstrating a flexible methodology for generating good codes with custom properties. We therefore establish a complete and customizable pipeline for random quantum code discovery that can be geared towards near to mid-term quantum processor layouts.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simple master equations for describing driven systems subject to classical non-Markovian noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03980</link>
    <author>Peter Groszkowski, Alireza Seif, Jens Koch, A. A. Clerk</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Driven quantum systems subject to non-Markovian noise are typically difficult to model even if the noise is classical. We present a systematic method based on generalized cumulant expansions for deriving a time-local master equation for such systems. This master equation has an intuitive form that directly parallels a standard Lindblad equation, but contains several surprising features: the combination of driving and non-Markovianity results in effective time-dependent dephasing rates that can be negative, and the noise can generate Hamiltonian renormalizations even though it is classical. We analyze in detail the highly relevant case of a Rabi-driven qubit subject to various kinds of non-Markovian noise including $1/f$ fluctuations, finding an excellent agreement between our master equation and numerically-exact simulations over relevant timescales. The approach outlined here is more accurate than commonly employed phenomenological master equations which ignore the interplay between driving and noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dynamical decoupling for superconducting qubits: a performance survey</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03670</link>
    <author>Nic Ezzell, Bibek Pokharel, Lina Tewala, Gregory Quiroz, Daniel A. Lidar</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Dynamical Decoupling (DD) is perhaps the simplest and least resource-intensive error suppression strategy for improving quantum computer performance. Here we report on a large-scale survey of the performance of 60 different DD sequences from 10 families, including basic as well as advanced sequences with high order error cancellation properties and built-in robustness. The survey is performed using three different superconducting-qubit IBMQ devices, with the goal of assessing the relative performance of the different sequences in the setting of arbitrary quantum state preservation. We find that the high-order universally robust (UR) and quadratic DD (QDD) sequences generally outperform all other sequences across devices and pulse interval settings. Surprisingly, we find that DD performance for basic sequences such as CPMG and XY4 can be made to nearly match that of UR and QDD by optimizing the pulse interval, with the optimal interval being substantially larger than the minimum interval possible on each device.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Rotated ansatz for approximate counterdiabatic driving</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03553</link>
    <author>Glen Bigan Mbeng, Wolfgang Lechner</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Approximate counterdiabatic (CD) protocols are a powerful tool to enhance quantum adiabatic processes that allow to reliably manipulate quantum systems on short time scales. However, implementing CD protocols entails the introduction of additional control fields in the Hamiltonian, often associated with highly non-local multi-body interactions. Here, we introduce a novel variational rotated ansatz (RA) to systematically generate experimentally accessible approximate CD protocols. We numerically benchmark our approach on state preparation and adiabatic quantum computing algorithms, and find that using RA protocols significantly enhances their performances.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Emergent Higher-Symmetry Protected Topological Orders in the Confined Phase of $U(1)$ Gauge Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03544</link>
    <author>Salvatore D. Pace, Xiao-Gang Wen</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider compact $U^\kappa(1)$ gauge theory in 3+1D with the $2\pi$-quantized topological term ${\sum_{I, J =1}^\kappa\frac{K_{IJ}}{4\pi}\int_{M^4}F^I\wedge F^J}$. At energies below the gauge charges' gaps but above the monopoles' gaps, this field theory has an emergent ${\mathbb{Z}_{k_1}^{(1)}\times\mathbb{Z}_{k_2}^{(1)}\times\cdots}$ 1-symmetry, where $k_i$ are the diagonal elements of the Smith normal form of $K$ and $\mathbb{Z}_{0}^{(1)}$ is regarded as $U(1)^{(1)}$. In the $U^\kappa(1)$ confined phase, the boundary's IR properties are described by Chern-Simons field theory and has a ${\mathbb{Z}_{k_1}^{(1)}\times\mathbb{Z}_{k_2}^{(1)}\times\cdots}$ 1-symmetry that can be anomalous. To show these results, we develop a bosonic lattice model whose IR properties are described by this field theory, thus acting as its UV completion. The lattice model in the aforementioned limit has an exact ${\mathbb{Z}_{k_1}^{(1)}\times\mathbb{Z}_{k_2}^{(1)}\times\cdots}$ 1-symmetry. We find that a gapped phase of the lattice model, corresponding to the confined phase of the $U^\kappa(1)$ gauge theory, is a symmetry protected topological (SPT) phase for the ${\mathbb{Z}_{k_1}^{(1)}\times\mathbb{Z}_{k_2}^{(1)}\times\cdots}$ 1-symmetry, whose SPT invariant is ${e^{i\pi\sum_{I, J}K_{IJ}\int B_I\smile B_J+B_I\underset{1}{\smile} d B_J}e^{i\pi\sum_{I< J}K_{IJ}\int d B_I\underset{2}{\smile}d B_J}}$. Here, the background 2-cochains $B_I$ satisfy ${d B_I=\sum_I B_{I}K_{IJ} = 0}$ mod $1$ and describe the symmetry twist of the ${\mathbb{Z}_{k_1}^{(1)}\times\mathbb{Z}_{k_2}^{(1)}\times\cdots}$ 1-symmetry. We apply this general result to a few examples with simple $K$ matrices. We find the non-trivial SPT order in the confined phases of these models and discuss its classifications using the fourth cohomology group of the corresponding 2-group.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>