<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Bi-PPT channels are entanglement breaking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01685</link>
    <author>Alexander Müller-Hermes, Satvik Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a recent paper, Hirche and Leditzky introduced the notion of bi-PPT channels which are quantum channels that stay completely positive under composition with a transposition and such that the same property holds for one of their complementary channels. They asked whether there are examples of such channels that are not antidegradable. We show that this is not the case, since bi-PPT channels are always entanglement breaking. We also show that degradable quantum channels staying completely positive under composition with a transposition are entanglement breaking.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Diagrammatic Analysis for Parameterized Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01307</link>
    <author>Tobias Stollenwerk, Stuart Hadfield</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Diagrammatic representations of quantum algorithms and circuits offer novel approaches to their design and analysis. In this work, we describe extensions of the ZX-calculus especially suitable for parameterized quantum circuits, in particular for computing observable expectation values as functions of or for fixed parameters, which are important algorithmic quantities in a variety of applications ranging from combinatorial optimization to quantum chemistry. We provide several new ZX-diagram rewrite rules and generalizations for this setting. In particular, we give formal rules for dealing with linear combinations of ZX-diagrams, where the relative complex-valued scale factors of each diagram must be kept track of, in contrast to most previously studied single-diagram realizations where these coefficients can be effectively ignored. This allows us to directly import a number useful relations from the operator analysis to ZX-calculus setting, including causal cone and quantum gate commutation rules. We demonstrate that the diagrammatic approach offers useful insights into algorithm structure and performance by considering several ansätze from the literature including realizations of hardware-efficient ansätze and QAOA. We find that by employing a diagrammatic representation, calculations across different ansätze can become more intuitive and potentially easier approach systematically than by alternative means. Finally, we outline how diagrammatic approaches may aid in the design and study of new and more effective quantum circuit ansätze.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complexity and entanglement in non-local computation and holography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.00908</link>
    <author>Alex May</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Does gravity constrain computation? We study this question using the AdS/CFT correspondence, where computation in the presence of gravity can be related to non-gravitational physics in the boundary theory. In AdS/CFT, computations which happen locally in the bulk are implemented in a particular non-local form in the boundary, which in general requires distributed entanglement. In particular, we argue that the area of a particular surface called the ridge, associated to a bulk subregion, is equal to the mutual information available in the boundary to perform the computation non-locally. We further argue the complexity of the local operation controls the amount of entanglement needed to implement it non-locally, and that in particular the complexity and entanglement cost are related by a polynomial. If this relationship holds, gravity constrains the complexity of operations within the scattering region to be polynomial in the area of the ridge.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Spectral estimation for stoquastic Hamiltonians: a comparison between classical imaginary-time evolution and quantum real-time evolution</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01113</link>
    <author>Maarten Stroeks, Jonas Helsen, Barbara Terhal</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a classical Monte Carlo (MC) scheme which efficiently estimates an imaginary-time, decaying signal for stoquastic (i.e. sign-problem-free) local Hamiltonians. The decay rates in this signal correspond to Hamiltonian eigenvalues (with associated eigenstates present in an initial state) and can be classically extracted using a classical signal processing method like ESPRIT. We compare the efficiency of this MC scheme to its quantum counterpart in which one extracts eigenvalues of a general local Hamiltonian from a real-time, oscillatory signal obtained through quantum phase estimation circuits, again using the ESPRIT method. We prove that the ESPRIT method can resolve S = poly(n) eigenvalues, assuming a 1/poly(n) gap between them, with poly(n) quantum and classical effort through the quantum phase estimation circuits. We prove that our Monte Carlo scheme plus the ESPRIT method can resolve S = O(1) eigenvalues, assuming a 1/poly(n) gap between them, with poly(n) purely classical effort for stoquastic Hamiltonians. These results thus quantify some opportunities and limitations of classical Monte Carlo methods for spectral estimation of stoquastic Hamiltonians. We numerically compare these MC and QPE eigenvalue estimation schemes by implementing them for an archetypal stoquastic Hamiltonian system: the transverse field Ising chain.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Polynomial Bounds On Parallel Repetition For All 3-Player Games With Binary Inputs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.00858</link>
    <author>Uma Girish, Kunal Mittal, Ran Raz, Wei Zhan</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove that for every 3-player (3-prover) game $\mathcal G$ with value less than one, whose query distribution has the support $\mathcal S = \{(1,0,0), (0,1,0), (0,0,1)\}$ of hamming weight one vectors, the value of the $n$-fold parallel repetition $\mathcal G^{\otimes n}$ decays polynomially fast to zero; that is, there is a constant $c = c(\mathcal G)>0$ such that the value of the game $\mathcal G^{\otimes n}$ is at most $n^{-c}$. Following the recent work of Girish, Holmgren, Mittal, Raz and Zhan (STOC 2022), our result is the missing piece that implies a similar bound for a much more general class of multiplayer games: For $\textbf{every}$ 3-player game $\mathcal G$ over $\textit{binary questions}$ and $\textit{arbitrary answer lengths}$, with value less than 1, there is a constant $c = c(\mathcal G)>0$ such that the value of the game $\mathcal G^{\otimes n}$ is at most $n^{-c}$. Our proof technique is new and requires many new ideas. For example, we make use of the Level-$k$ inequalities from Boolean Fourier Analysis, which, to the best of our knowledge, have not been explored in this context prior to our work.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>