<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Time-Efficient Constant-Space-Overhead Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08826</link>
    <author>Hayata Yamasaki, Masato Koashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Scalable realization of quantum computation to attain substantial speedups over classical computation requires fault tolerance. Conventionally, fault-tolerant quantum computation (FTQC) demands excessive space overhead of physical qubits per logical qubit. A more recent protocol to achieve constant-space-overhead FTQC using quantum low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes thus attracts considerable attention but suffers from another drawback: it incurs polynomially long time overhead. We construct an alternative avenue of FTQC to achieve constant space overhead and only quasi-polylogarithmic time overhead simultaneously via techniques for using concatenations of different quantum Hamming codes rather than quantum LDPC codes. Our protocol achieves FTQC even if a decoder has nonzero runtime, unlike the existing constant-space-overhead protocol. These results establish a foundation for realizing FTQC within feasibly bounded space overhead yet negligibly tiny slowdown.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Achievable error exponents of data compression with quantum side information and communication over symmetric classical-quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08899</link>
    <author>Joseph M. Renes</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A fundamental quantity of interest in Shannon theory, classical or quantum, is the optimal error exponent of a given channel W and rate R: the constant E(W,R) which governs the exponential decay of decoding error when using ever larger codes of fixed rate R to communicate over ever more (memoryless) instances of a given channel W. Here I show that a bound by Hayashi [CMP 333, 335 (2015)] for an analogous quantity in privacy amplification implies a lower bound on the error exponent of communication over symmetric classical-quantum channels. The resulting bound matches Dalai's [IEEE TIT 59, 8027 (2013)] sphere-packing upper bound for rates above a critical value, and reproduces the well-known classical result for symmetric channels. The argument proceeds by first relating the error exponent of privacy amplification to that of compression of classical information with quantum side information, which gives a lower bound that matches the sphere-packing upper bound of Cheng et al. [IEEE TIT 67, 902 (2021)]. In turn, the polynomial prefactors to the sphere-packing bound found by Cheng et al. may be translated to the privacy amplification problem, sharpening a recent result by Li, Yao, and Hayashi [arXiv:2111.01075 [quant-ph]], at least for linear randomness extractors.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Landau-Forbidden Quantum Criticality in Rydberg Quantum Simulators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08829</link>
    <author>Jong Yeon Lee, Joshua Ramette, Max A. Metlitski, Vladan Vuletic, Wen Wei Ho, Soonwon Choi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Landau-Ginzburg-Wilson theory of phase transitions precludes a continuous transition between two phases that spontaneously break distinct symmetries. However, quantum mechanical effects can intertwine the symmetries, giving rise to an exotic phenomenon called deconfined quantum criticality (DQC). In this work, we study the ground state phase diagram of a one-dimensional array of individually trapped neutral atoms interacting strongly via Rydberg states, and demonstrate through extensive numerical simulations that it hosts a variety of symmetry-breaking phases and their transitions including DQC. We show how an enlarged, emergent continuous symmetry arises at the DQCs, which can be experimentally observed in the joint distribution of two distinct order parameters, obtained within measurement snapshots in the standard computational basis. Our findings highlight quantum simulators of Rydberg atoms not only as promising platforms to experimentally realize such exotic phenomena, but also as unique ones allowing access to physical properties not obtainable in traditional experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Emergent Quantum Mechanics at the Boundary of a Local Classical Lattice Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.09465</link>
    <author>Kevin Slagle, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We formulate a conceptually new model in which quantum mechanics emerges from classical mechanics. Given a local Hamiltonian $H$ acting on $n$ qubits, we define a local classical model with an additional spatial dimension whose boundary dynamics is described by Schrodinger's equation and $H$. The bulk consists of a lattice of classical bits that propagate towards the boundary through a circuit of stochastic matrices. The bits reaching the boundary are governed by a probability distribution whose deviation from the uniform distribution can be interpreted as the quantum-mechanical wavefunction. Bell nonlocality is achieved because information can move through the bulk much faster than the boundary speed of light. We analytically estimate how much the model deviates from quantum mechanics, and we validate these estimates using computer simulations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Near-Linear Time Sampler for the Ising Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.09391</link>
    <author>Xiaoyu Chen, Xinyuan Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a near-linear time sampler for the Gibbs distribution of the ferromagnetic Ising models with edge activities $\boldsymbol{\beta} > 1$ and external fields $\boldsymbol{\lambda}<1$ (or symmetrically, $\boldsymbol{\lambda}>1$) on general graphs with bounded or unbounded maximum degree. Our algorithm is based on the field dynamics given in [CLV21]. We prove the correctness and efficiency of our algorithm by establishing spectral independence of distribution of the random cluster model and the rapid mixing of Glauber dynamics on the random cluster model in a low-temperature regime, which may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>