<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>On the Super-exponential Quantum Speedup of Equivariant Quantum Machine Learning Algorithms with SU($d$) Symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07250</link>
    <author>Han Zheng, Zimu Li, Junyu Liu, Sergii Strelchuk, Risi Kondor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a framework of the equivariant convolutional algorithms which is tailored for a number of machine-learning tasks on physical systems with arbitrary SU($d$) symmetries. It allows us to enhance a natural model of quantum computation--permutational quantum computing (PQC) [Quantum Inf. Comput., 10, 470-497 (2010)] --and defines a more powerful model: PQC+. While PQC was shown to be effectively classically simulatable, we exhibit a problem which can be efficiently solved on PQC+ machine, whereas the best known classical algorithms runs in $O(n!n^2)$ time, thus providing strong evidence against PQC+ being classically simulatable. We further discuss practical quantum machine learning algorithms which can be carried out in the paradigm of PQC+.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Toys can't play: physical agents in Spekkens' theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07445</link>
    <author>Ladina Hausmann, Nuriya Nurgalieva, Lídia del Rio</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Information is physical, and for a physical theory to be universal, it should model observers as physical systems, with concrete memories where they store the information acquired through experiments and reasoning. Here we address these issues in Spekkens' toy theory, a non-contextual epistemically restricted model that partially mimics the behaviour of quantum mechanics. We propose a way to model physical implementations of agents, memories, measurements, conditional actions and information processing. We find that the actions of toy agents are severely limited: although there are non-orthogonal states in the theory, there is no way for physical agents to consciously prepare them. Their memories are also constrained: agents cannot forget in which of two arbitrary states a system is. Finally, we formalize the process of making inferences about other agents' experiments and model multi-agent experiments like Wigner's friend. Unlike quantum theory or box world, in the toy theory there are no inconsistencies when physical agents reason about each other's knowledge.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Demonstrating scalable randomized benchmarking of universal gate sets</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07272</link>
    <author>Jordan Hines, Marie Lu, Ravi K. Naik, Akel Hashim, Jean-Loup Ville, Brad Mitchell, John Mark Kriekebaum, David I. Santiago, Stefan Seritan, Erik Nielsen, Robin Blume-Kohout, Kevin Young, Irfan Siddiqi, Birgitta Whaley, Timothy Proctor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Randomized benchmarking (RB) protocols are the most widely used methods for assessing the performance of quantum gates. However, the existing RB methods either do not scale to many qubits or cannot benchmark a universal gate set. Here, we introduce and demonstrate a technique for scalable RB of many universal and continuously parameterized gate sets, using a class of circuits called randomized mirror circuits. Our technique can be applied to a gate set containing an entangling Clifford gate and the set of arbitrary single-qubit gates, as well as gate sets containing controlled rotations about the Pauli axes. We use our technique to benchmark universal gate sets on four qubits of the Advanced Quantum Testbed, including a gate set containing a controlled-S gate and its inverse, and we investigate how the observed error rate is impacted by the inclusion of non-Clifford gates. Finally, we demonstrate that our technique scales to many qubits with experiments on a 27-qubit IBM Q processor. We use our technique to quantify the impact of crosstalk on this 27-qubit device, and we find that it contributes approximately 2/3 of the total error per gate in random many-qubit circuit layers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Demonstration of algorithmic quantum speedup</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07647</link>
    <author>Bibek Pokharel, Daniel A. Lidar</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms theoretically outperform classical algorithms in solving problems of increasing size, but computational errors must be kept to a minimum to realize this potential. Despite the development of increasingly capable quantum computers (QCs), an experimental demonstration of a provable algorithmic quantum speedup employing today's non-fault-tolerant, noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices has remained elusive. Here, we unequivocally demonstrate such a speedup, quantified in terms of the scaling with the problem size of the time-to-solution metric. We implement the single-shot Bernstein-Vazirani algorithm, which solves the problem of identifying a hidden bitstring that changes after every oracle query, utilizing two different 27-qubit IBM Quantum (IBMQ) superconducting processors. The speedup is observed on only one of the two QCs (ibmq_montreal) when the quantum computation is protected by dynamical decoupling (DD) -- a carefully designed sequence of pulses applied to the QC that suppresses its interaction with the environment, but not without DD. In contrast to recent quantum supremacy demonstrations, the quantum speedup reported here does not rely on any additional assumptions or complexity-theoretic conjectures and solves a bona fide computational problem, in the setting of a game with an oracle and a verifier.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Bayesian Error Mitigation Employing Poisson Modelling over the Hamming Spectrum for Quantum Error Mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07237</link>
    <author>Samuel Stein, Nathan Wiebe, Yufei Ding, James Ang, Ang Li</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing technology has grown rapidly in recent years, with new technologies being explored, error rates being reduced, and quantum processors qubit capacity growing. However, near term quantum algorithms are still unable to be induced without compounding consequential levels of noise, leading to non trivial erroneous results. Quantum Error Correction (in situ error mitigation) and Quantum Error Mitigation (post induction error mitigation) are promising fields of research within the quantum algorithm scene, aiming to alleviate quantum errors, increasing the overall fidelity and hence the overall quality of circuit induction. Earlier this year, a pioneering work, namely HAMMER, published in ASPLOS 22 demonstrated the existence of a latent structure regarding post circuit induction errors when mapping to the Hamming spectrum. However, they intuitively assumed that errors occur in local clusters, and that at higher average Hamming distances this structure falls away. In this work, we show that such a correlation structure is not only local but extends certain non local clustering patterns which can be precisely described by a Poisson distribution model taking the input circuit, the device run time status (i. e. calibration statistics), and qubit topology into consideration. Using this quantum error characterizing model, we developed an iterative algorithm over the generated Bayesian network state graph for post induction error mitigation. Thanks to more precise modeling of the error distribution latent structure and the new iterative method, our Q Beep approach provides state of the art performance and can boost circuit execution fidelity by up to 234.6% on Bernstein Vazirani circuits and on average 71.0% on QAOA solution quality, using 16 practical IBMQ quantum processors. For other benchmarks such as those in QASMBench, the fidelity improvement is up to 17.8%.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>