<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Learning quantum processes without input control</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05005</link>
    <author>Marco Fanizza, Yihui Quek, Matteo Rosati</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a general statistical learning theory for processes that take as input a classical random variable and output a quantum state. This is a practically motivated setting where the learner wants to find an approximate representation of an unknown quantum process, without having control on the classical inputs that govern the process itself, e.g., in learning astronomical processes, studying disordered systems and biological processes not controlled by the observer. We provide an algorithm for learning with high probability in this setting with a finite amount of samples, even if the concept class is infinite. To do this, we review and adapt existing algorithms for shadow tomography and hypothesis selection, and combine their guarantees with the uniform convergence on the data of the loss functions of interest. As a by-product we obtain sufficient conditions for performing shadow tomography of classical-quantum states with a number of copies which depend only on the dimension of the quantum register. We give concrete examples of processes that can be learned in this manner, based on quantum circuits or physically motivated scenarios like systems subject to Hamiltonians with random perturbations or data-dependent phase-shifts.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Overcoming leakage in scalable quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.04728</link>
    <author>Kevin C. Miao, Matt McEwen, Juan Atalaya, Dvir Kafri, Leonid P. Pryadko, Andreas Bengtsson, Alex Opremcak, Kevin J. Satzinger, Zijun Chen, Paul V. Klimov, Chris Quintana, Rajeev Acharya, Kyle Anderson, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Joseph C. Bardin, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, et al (97)</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Leakage of quantum information out of computational states into higher energy states represents a major challenge in the pursuit of quantum error correction (QEC). In a QEC circuit, leakage builds over time and spreads through multi-qubit interactions. This leads to correlated errors that degrade the exponential suppression of logical error with scale, challenging the feasibility of QEC as a path towards fault-tolerant quantum computation. Here, we demonstrate the execution of a distance-3 surface code and distance-21 bit-flip code on a Sycamore quantum processor where leakage is removed from all qubits in each cycle. This shortens the lifetime of leakage and curtails its ability to spread and induce correlated errors. We report a ten-fold reduction in steady-state leakage population on the data qubits encoding the logical state and an average leakage population of less than $1 \times 10^{-3}$ throughout the entire device. The leakage removal process itself efficiently returns leakage population back to the computational basis, and adding it to a code circuit prevents leakage from inducing correlated error across cycles, restoring a fundamental assumption of QEC. With this demonstration that leakage can be contained, we resolve a key challenge for practical QEC at scale.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reducing the qubit requirement of Jordan-Wigner encodings of $N$-mode, $K$-fermion systems from $N$ to $\lceil \log_2 {N \choose K} \rceil$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.04501</link>
    <author>Brent Harrison, Dylan Nelson, Daniel Adamiak, James Whitfield</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>To simulate a fermionic system on a quantum computer, it is necessary to encode the state of the fermions onto qubits. Fermion-to-qubit mappings such as the Jordan-Wigner and Bravyi-Kitaev transformations do this using $N$ qubits to represent systems of $N$ fermionic modes. In this work, we demonstrate that for particle number conserving systems of $K$ fermions and $N$ modes, the qubit requirement can be reduced to the information theoretic minimum of $\lceil \log_2 {N \choose K} \rceil$. This will improve the feasibility of simulation of molecules and many-body systems on near-term quantum computers with limited qubit number.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational quantum chemistry requires gate-error probabilities below the fault-tolerance threshold</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.04505</link>
    <author>Kieran Dalton, Christopher K. Long, Yordan S. Yordanov, Charles G. Smith, Crispin H. W. Barnes, Normann Mertig, David R. M. Arvidsson-Shukur</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) is a leading contender for useful quantum advantage in the NISQ era. The interplay between quantum processors and classical optimisers is believed to make the VQE noise resilient. Here, we probe this hypothesis. We use full density-matrix simulations to rank the noise resilience of leading gate-based VQE algorithms in ground-state computations on a range of molecules. We find that, in the presence of noise: (i) ADAPT-VQEs that construct ansatz circuits iteratively outperform VQEs that use "fixed" ansatz circuits; and (ii) ADAPT-VQEs perform better when circuits are constructed from gate-efficient elements rather than physically-motivated ones. Our results show that, for a wide range of molecules, even the best-performing VQE algorithms require gate-error probabilities on the order of $10^{-6}$ to $10^{-4}$ to reach chemical accuracy. This is significantly below the fault-tolerance thresholds of most error-correction protocols. Further, we estimate that the maximum allowed gate-error probability scales inversely with the number of noisy (two-qubit) gates. Our results indicate that useful chemistry calculations with current gate-based VQEs are unlikely to be successful on near-term hardware without error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Resource frugal optimizer for quantum machine learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.04965</link>
    <author>Charles Moussa, Max Hunter Gordon, Michal Baczyk, M. Cerezo, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum-enhanced data science, also known as quantum machine learning (QML), is of growing interest as an application of near-term quantum computers. Variational QML algorithms have the potential to solve practical problems on real hardware, particularly when involving quantum data. However, training these algorithms can be challenging and calls for tailored optimization procedures. Specifically, QML applications can require a large shot-count overhead due to the large datasets involved. In this work, we advocate for simultaneous random sampling over both the dataset as well as the measurement operators that define the loss function. We consider a highly general loss function that encompasses many QML applications, and we show how to construct an unbiased estimator of its gradient. This allows us to propose a shot-frugal gradient descent optimizer called Refoqus (REsource Frugal Optimizer for QUantum Stochastic gradient descent). Our numerics indicate that Refoqus can save several orders of magnitude in shot cost, even relative to optimizers that sample over measurement operators alone.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>