<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Grothendieck inequalities characterize converses to the polynomial method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08559</link>
    <author>Jop Briët, Francisco Escudero Gutiérrez, Sander Gribling</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A surprising 'converse to the polynomial method' of Aaronson et al. (CCC'16) shows that any bounded quadratic polynomial can be computed exactly in expectation by a 1-query algorithm up to a universal multiplicative factor related to the famous Grothendieck constant. Here we show that such a result does not generalize to quartic polynomials and 2-query algorithms, even when we allow for additive approximations. We also show that the additive approximation implied by their result is tight for bounded bilinear forms, which gives a new characterization of the Grothendieck constant in terms of 1-query quantum algorithms. Along the way we provide reformulations of the completely bounded norm of a form, and its dual norm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From time-reversal symmetry to quantum Bayes' rules</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08088</link>
    <author>Arthur J. Parzygnat, James Fullwood</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bayes' rule $\mathbb{P}(B|A)\mathbb{P}(A)=\mathbb{P}(A|B)\mathbb{P}(B)$ is one of the simplest yet most profound, ubiquitous, and far-reaching results of classical probability theory, with applications in decision making, artificial intelligence, weather forecasts, betting strategies, and more generally statistical inference. Many attempts have been made to extend this rule to quantum systems, the significance of which we are only beginning to understand. In this work, we develop a systematic framework for defining Bayes' rule in the quantum setting, and we show that a vast majority of the proposed quantum Bayes' rules appearing in the literature are all instances of our definition. Moreover, our Bayes' rule is based upon a simple relationship between the notions of \emphstate over time and a time-reversal symmetry map, both of which are introduced here.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classically Simulating Quantum Supremacy IQP Circuits trough a Random Graph Approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08609</link>
    <author>Julien Codsi, John van de Wetering</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Supremacy is a demonstration of a computation by a quantum computer that can not be performed by the best classical computer in a reasonable time. A well-studied approach to demonstrating this on near-term quantum computers is to use random circuit sampling. It has been suggested that a good candidate for demonstrating quantum supremacy with random circuit sampling is to use \emphIQP circuits. These are quantum circuits where the unitary it implements is diagonal. In this paper we introduce improved techniques for classically simulating random IQP circuits. We find a simple algorithm to calculate an amplitude of an $n$-qubit IQP circuit with dense random two-qubit interactions in time $O(\frac{\log^2 n}{n} 2^n )$, which for sparse circuits (where each qubit interacts with $O(\log n)$ other qubits) runs in $o(2^n/\text{poly}(n))$ for any given polynomial. Using a more complicated stabiliser decomposition approach we improve the algorithm for dense circuits to $O\left(\frac{(\log n)^{4-\beta}}{n^{2-\beta}} 2^n \right)$ where $\beta \approx 0.396$. We benchmarked our algorithm and found that we can simulate up to 50-qubit circuits in a couple of minutes on a laptop. We estimate that 70-qubit circuits are within reach for a large computing cluster.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Approximate counting using Taylor's theorem: a survey</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08143</link>
    <author>Viresh Patel, Guus Regts</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this article we consider certain well-known polynomials associated with graphs including the independence polynomial and the chromatic polynomial. These polynomials count certain objects in graphs: independent sets in the case of the independence polynomial and proper colourings in the case of the chromatic polynomial. They also have interpretations as partition functions in statistical physics. The algorithmic problem of (approximately) computing these types of polynomials has been studied for close to 50 years, especially using Markov chain techniques. Around eight years ago, Barvinok devised a new algorithmic approach based on Taylor's theorem for computing the permanent of certain matrices, and the approach has been applied to various graph polynomials since then. This article is intended as a gentle introduction to the approach as well as a partial survey of associated techniques and results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Surface codes, quantum circuits, and entanglement phases</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08084</link>
    <author>Jan Behrends, Florian Venn, Benjamin Béri</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Surface codes$\unicode{x2014}$leading candidates for quantum error correction (QEC)$\unicode{x2014}$and entanglement phases$\unicode{x2014}$a key notion for many-body quantum dynamics$\unicode{x2014}$have heretofore been unrelated. Here, we establish a link between the two. We map two-dimensional (2D) surface codes under a class of incoherent or coherent errors (bit flips or uniaxial rotations) to $(1+1)$D free-fermion quantum circuits via Ising models. We show that the error-correcting phase implies a topologically nontrivial area law for the circuit's 1D long-time state $|\Psi_\infty\rangle$. Above the error threshold, we find a topologically trivial area law for incoherent errors and logarithmic entanglement in the coherent case. In establishing our results, we formulate 1D parent Hamiltonians for $|\Psi_\infty\rangle$ via linking Ising models and 2D scattering networks, the latter displaying respective insulating and metallic phases and setting the 1D fermion gap and topology via their localization length and topological invariant. We expect our results to generalize to a duality between the error-correcting phase of ($d+1$)D topological codes and $d$-dimensional area laws; this can facilitate assessing code performance under various errors. The approach of combining Ising models, scattering networks, and parent Hamiltonians can be generalized to other fermionic circuits and may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>