<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Wasserstein Complexity of Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06306</link>
    <author>Lu Li, Kaifeng Bu, Dax Enshan Koh, Arthur Jaffe, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a unitary transformation, what is the size of the smallest quantum circuit that implements it? This quantity, known as the quantum circuit complexity, is a fundamental property of quantum evolutions that has widespread applications in many fields, including quantum computation, quantum field theory, and black hole physics. In this letter, we obtain a new lower bound for the quantum circuit complexity in terms of a novel complexity measure that we propose for quantum circuits, which we call the quantum Wasserstein complexity. Our proposed measure is based on the quantum Wasserstein distance of order one (also called the quantum earth mover's distance), a metric on the space of quantum states. We also prove several fundamental and important properties of our new complexity measure, which stand to be of independent interest. Finally, we show that our new measure also provides a lower bound for the experimental cost of implementing quantum circuits, which implies a quantum limit on converting quantum resources to computational resources. Our results provide novel applications of the quantum Wasserstein distance and pave the way for a deeper understanding of the resources needed to implement a quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On establishing learning separations between classical and quantum machine learning with classical data</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06339</link>
    <author>Casper Gyurik, Vedran Dunjko</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Despite years of effort, the quantum machine learning community has only been able to show quantum learning advantages for certain contrived cryptography-inspired datasets in the case of classical data. In this note, we discuss the challenges of finding learning problems that quantum learning algorithms can learn much faster than any classical learning algorithm, and we study how to identify such learning problems. Specifically, we reflect on the main concepts in computational learning theory pertaining to this question, and we discuss how subtle changes in definitions can mean conceptually significantly different tasks, which can either lead to a separation or no separation at all. Moreover, we study existing learning problems with a provable quantum speedup to distill sets of more general and sufficient conditions (i.e., ``checklists'') for a learning problem to exhibit a separation between classical and quantum learners. These checklists are intended to streamline one's approach to proving quantum speedups for learning problems, or to elucidate bottlenecks. Finally, to illustrate its application, we analyze examples of potential separations (i.e., when the learning problem is build from computational separations, or when the data comes from a quantum experiment) through the lens of our approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring incompatibility and clustering quantum observables with a quantum switch</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06210</link>
    <author>Ning Gao, Dantong Li, Anchit Mishra, Junchen Yan, Kyrylo Simonov, Giulio Chiribella</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The existence of incompatible observables is a cornerstone of quantum mechanics and a valuable resource in quantum technologies. Here we introduce a measure of incompatibility, called the mutual eigenspace disturbance (MED), which quantifies the amount of disturbance induced by the measurement of a sharp observable on the eigenspaces of another. The MED is a faithful measure of incompatibility for sharp observables and provides a metric on the space of von Neumann measurements. It can be efficiently estimated by letting the measurements act in an indefinite order, using a setup known as the quantum switch. Thanks to these features, the MED can be used in quantum machine learning tasks, such as clustering quantum measurement devices based on their mutual compatibility. We demonstrate this application by providing an unsupervised algorithm that clusters unknown von Neumann measurements. Our algorithm is robust to noise can be used to identify groups of observers that share approximately the same measurement context.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Algebraic Aspects of Boundaries in the Kitaev Quantum Double Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06317</link>
    <author>Alexander Cowtan, Shahn Majid</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide a systematic treatment of boundaries based on subgroups $K\subseteq G$ with the Kitaev quantum double $D(G)$ model in the bulk. The boundary sites are representations of a $*$-subalgebra $\Xi\subseteq D(G)$ and we explicate its structure as a strong $*$-quasi-Hopf algebra dependent on a choice of transversal $R$. We provide decomposition formulae for irreducible representations of $D(G)$ pulled back to $\Xi$. We also provide explicitly the monoidal equivalence of the category of $\Xi$-modules and the category of $G$-graded $K$-bimodules and use this to prove that different choices of $R$ are related by Drinfeld cochain twists. Examples include $S_{n-1}\subset S_n$ and an example related to the octonions where $\Xi$ is also a Hopf quasigroup. As an application of our treatment, we study patches with boundaries based on $K=G$ horizontally and $K=\{e\}$ vertically and show how these could be used in a quantum computer using the technique of lattice surgery.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Crosstalk Robust Quantum Control</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05978</link>
    <author>Zeyuan Zhou, Ryan Sitler, Yasuo Oda, Kevin Schultz, Gregory Quiroz</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The prevalence of quantum crosstalk in current quantum devices poses challenges for achieving high-fidelity quantum logic operations and reliable quantum processing. Through quantum control theory, we develop an analytical condition for achieving crosstalk-robust single-qubit control of multi-qubit systems. We examine the effects of quantum crosstalk via a cumulant expansion and develop a condition to suppress the leading order contributions to the dynamics. The efficacy of the condition is illustrated in the domains of quantum state preservation and noise characterization through the development of crosstalk-robust dynamical decoupling and quantum noise spectroscopy (QNS) protocols. Using the IBM Quantum Experience, crosstalk-robust state preservation is demonstrated on 27 qubits, where a $3\times$ improvement in coherence decay is observed for single-qubit product and multipartite entangled states. Through the use of noise injection, we experimentally demonstrate crosstalk-robust dephasing QNS on a seven qubit processor, where a $10^4$ improvement in reconstruction accuracy over ``cross-susceptible" alternatives is found. Together, these experiments highlight the significant impact the crosstalk mitigation condition can have on improving multi-qubit characterization and control on current quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>