<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Tailoring three-dimensional topological codes for biased noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02116</link>
    <author>Eric Huang, Arthur Pesah, Christopher T. Chubb, Michael Vasmer, Arpit Dua</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tailored topological stabilizer codes in two dimensions have been shown to exhibit high storage threshold error rates and improved subthreshold performance under biased Pauli noise. Three-dimensional (3D) topological codes can allow for several advantages including a transversal implementation of non-Clifford logical gates, single-shot decoding strategies, parallelized decoding in the case of fracton codes as well as construction of fractal lattice codes. Motivated by this, we tailor 3D topological codes for enhanced storage performance under biased Pauli noise. We present Clifford deformations of various 3D topological codes, such that they exhibit a threshold error rate of $50\%$ under infinitely biased Pauli noise. Our examples include the 3D surface code on the cubic lattice, the 3D surface code on a checkerboard lattice that lends itself to a subsystem code with a single-shot decoder, the 3D color code, as well as fracton models such as the X-cube model, the Sierpinski model and the Haah code. We use the belief propagation with ordered statistics decoder (BP-OSD) to study threshold error rates at finite bias. We also present a rotated layout for the 3D surface code, which uses roughly half the number of physical qubits for the same code distance under appropriate boundary conditions. Imposing coprime periodic dimensions on this rotated layout leads to logical operators of weight $O(n)$ at infinite bias and a corresponding $\exp[-O(n)]$ subthreshold scaling of the logical failure rate, where $n$ is the number of physical qubits in the code. Even though this scaling is unstable due to the existence of logical representations with $O(1)$ low-rate Pauli errors, the number of such representations scales only polynomially for the Clifford-deformed code, leading to an enhanced effective distance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Invertible subalgebras</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02086</link>
    <author>Jeongwan Haah</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce invertible subalgebras of local operator algebras on lattices. An invertible subalgebra is defined to be one such that every local operator can be locally expressed by elements of the inveritible subalgebra and those of the commutant. On a two-dimensional lattice, an invertible subalgebra hosts a chiral anyon theory by a commuting Hamiltonian, which is believed not to be possible on a full local operator algebra. We prove that the stable equivalence classes of $D$-dimensional invertible subalgebras form an abelian group under tensor product, isomorphic to the group of all $D+1$ dimensional QCA modulo blending equivalence and shifts. In an appendix, we consider a metric on the group of all QCA on infinite lattices and prove that the metric completion contains the time evolution by local Hamiltonians, which is only approximately locality-preserving. Our metric topology is strictly finer than the strong topology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Conventions for Quantum Pseudocode</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02559</link>
    <author>E. Knill</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A few conventions for thinking about and writing quantum pseudocode are proposed. The conventions can be used for presenting any quantum algorithm down to the lowest level and are consistent with a quantum random access machine (QRAM) model for quantum computing. In principle a formal version of quantum pseudocode could be used in a future extension of a conventional language.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Discrete mean estimates and the Landau-Siegel zero</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02515</link>
    <author>Yitang Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Let $\chi$ be a real primitive character to the modulus $D$. It is proved that $$ L(1,\chi)≫(\log D)^-2022 $$ where the implied constant is absolute and effectively computable. In the proof, the lower bound for $L(1,\chi)$ is first related to the distribution of zeros of a family of Dirichlet $L$-functions in a certain region, and some results on the gaps between consecutive zeros are derived. Then, by evaluating certain discrete means of the large sieve type, a contradiction can be obtained if $L(1,\chi)$ is too small.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficiently computing the Uhlmann fidelity for density matrices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02623</link>
    <author>Andrew Baldwin, Jonathan A. Jones</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of efficiently computing the Uhlmann fidelity in the case when explicit density matrix descriptions are available. We derive an alternative formula which is simpler to evaluate numerically, saving a factor of 10 in time for large matrices.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>