<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A super-polynomial quantum advantage for combinatorial optimization problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08678</link>
    <author>Niklas Pirnay, Vincent Ulitzsch, Frederik Wilde, Jens Eisert, Jean-Pierre Seifert</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Combinatorial optimization - a field of research addressing problems that feature strongly in a wealth of practical and industrial contexts - has been identified as one of the core potential fields of applicability of near-term quantum computers. It is still unclear, however, to what extent variational quantum algorithms can actually outperform classical algorithms for this type of problems. In this work, by resorting to computational learning theory and cryptographic notions, we prove that fault-tolerant quantum computers feature a super-polynomial advantage over classical computers in approximating solutions to combinatorial optimization problems. Specifically, building on seminal work of Kearns and Valiant, we construct special instances of the integer programming problem (which in its most general form is NP-complete) that we prove to be hard-to-approximate classically but give an efficient quantum algorithm to approximate the optimal solution of those instances, hence showing a super-polynomial quantum advantage. This result shows that quantum devices have the power to approximate combinatorial optimization solutions beyond the reach of classical efficient algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noisy Stabilizer Formalism</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08677</link>
    <author>Maria Flors Mor-Ruiz, Wolfgang Dür</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Despite the exponential overhead to describe general multi-qubit quantum states and processes, efficient methods for certain state families and operations have been developed and utilised. The stabilizer formalism and the Gottesman-Knill theorem, where pure stabilizer or graph states are manipulated by Clifford operations and Pauli measurements, are prominent examples, and these states play a major role in many applications in quantum technologies. Here we develop a noisy stabilizer formalism, i.e., a method that allows one not only to efficiently describe and follow pure states under Clifford operations and Pauli measurements but also Pauli noise processes acting on such stabilizer states, including uncorrelated and correlated dephasing and single- or multi-qubit depolarizing noise. The method scales linearly in the number of qubits of the initial state, but exponentially in the size of the target state. Thus, whenever a noisy stabilizer state is manipulated by means of local Pauli measurements such that a multipartite entangled state of a few qubits is generated, one can efficiently describe the resulting state.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Upper Bounds on the Distillable Randomness of Bipartite Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.09073</link>
    <author>Ludovico Lami, Bartosz Regula, Xin Wang, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The distillable randomness of a bipartite quantum state is an information-theoretic quantity equal to the largest net rate at which shared randomness can be distilled from the state by means of local operations and classical communication. This quantity has been widely used as a measure of classical correlations, and one version of it is equal to the regularized Holevo information of the ensemble that results from measuring one share of the state. However, due to the regularization, the distillable randomness is difficult to compute in general. To address this problem, we define measures of classical correlations and prove a number of their properties, most importantly that they serve as upper bounds on the distillable randomness of an arbitrary bipartite state. We then further bound these measures from above by some that are efficiently computable by means of semi-definite programming, we evaluate one of them for the example of an isotropic state, and we remark on the relation to quantities previously proposed in the literature.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient validation of Boson Sampling from binned photon-number distributions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.09643</link>
    <author>Benoit Seron, Leonardo Novo, Alex Arkhipov, Nicolas J. Cerf</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In order to substantiate claims of quantum computational advantage, it is crucial to develop efficient methods for validating the experimental data. We propose a test of the correct functioning of a boson sampler with single-photon inputs that is based on how photons distribute among partitions of the output modes. Our method is versatile and encompasses previous validation tests based on bunching phenomena, marginal distributions, and even some suppression laws. We show via theoretical arguments and numerical simulations that binned-mode photon number distributions can be used in practical scenarios to efficiently distinguish ideal boson samplers from those affected by realistic imperfections, especially partial distinguishability of the photons.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Bonsai algorithm: grow your own fermion-to-qubit mapping</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.09731</link>
    <author>Aaron Miller, Zoltán Zimborás, Stefan Knecht, Sabrina Maniscalco, Guillermo García-Pérez</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fermion-to-qubit mappings are used to represent fermionic modes on quantum computers, an essential first step in many quantum algorithms for electronic structure calculations. In this work, we present a formalism to design flexible fermion-to-qubit mappings from ternary trees. We discuss in an intuitive manner the connection between the generating trees' structure and certain properties of the resulting mapping, such as Pauli weight and the delocalisation of mode occupation. Moreover, we introduce a recipe that guarantees Fock basis states are mapped to computational basis states in qubit space, a desirable property for many applications in quantum computing. Based on this formalism, we introduce the Bonsai algorithm, which takes as input the potentially limited topology of the qubit connectivity of a quantum device and returns a tailored fermion-to-qubit mapping that reduces the SWAP overhead with respect to other paradigmatic mappings. We illustrate the algorithm by producing mappings for the heavy-hexagon topology widely used in IBM quantum computers. The resulting mappings have a favourable Pauli weight scaling $\mathcal{O}(\sqrt{N})$ on this connectivity, while ensuring that no SWAP gates are necessary for single excitation operations.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>