<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Fully undistillable quantum states are separable</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05193</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Nilanjana Datta</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Assume that Alice, Bob, and Eve share a tripartite pure state $|\psi_{ABE}\rangle$. We prove that if Alice cannot distill entanglement with either Bob or Eve using $|\psi_{ABE}\rangle$ and local operations with any one of the following configurations for classical communication: $(A\to B, A\leftrightarrow E), (A\leftrightarrow B, A\to E),$ and $(A\leftrightarrow B, A\leftrightarrow E)$, then the same is also true for the other two configurations. Moreover, this happens precisely when the state is such that both its reductions $\rho_{AB}$ and $\rho_{AE}$ are separable, which is further equivalent to the reductions being PPT. This, in particular, implies that any NPT bipartite state is such that either the state itself or its complement is 2-way distillable. In proving these results, we first obtain an explicit lower bound on the 2-way distillable entanglement of low rank bipartite states. Furthermore, we show that even though not all low rank states are 1-way distillable, a randomly sampled low rank state will almost surely be 1-way distillable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The QAOA gets stuck starting from a good classical string</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05089</link>
    <author>Madelyn Cain, Edward Farhi, Sam Gutmann, Daniel Ranard, Eugene Tang</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) is designed to maximize a cost function over bit strings. While the initial state is traditionally a superposition over all strings, it is natural to try expediting the QAOA: first use a classical algorithm to produce some good string, and then run the ordinary QAOA starting in the computational basis state associated with that string. Here we report numerical experiments that this method of initializing the QAOA fails dramatically, exhibiting little to no improvement of the cost function. We investigate criteria for the rare instances in which there is any improvement at all, and we provide a statistical argument for the more typical case of no improvement. The statistical argument holds for any string that locally mimics the thermal ensemble at the appropriate temperature. Our numerical experiments indicate this property holds for typical good strings. We emphasize that our negative results only apply to our simple incarnation of the warm-start QAOA and may not apply to other approaches in the literature. We hope that our theoretical analysis will inform future algorithm design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Linear programming with unitary-equivariant constraints</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05713</link>
    <author>Dmitry Grinko, Maris Ozols</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Unitary equivariance is a natural symmetry that occurs in many contexts in physics and mathematics. Optimization problems with such symmetry can often be formulated as semidefinite programs for a $d^{p+q}$-dimensional matrix variable that commutes with $U^{\otimes p} \otimes \bar{U}^{\otimes q}$, for all $U \in \mathrm{U}(d)$. Solving such problems naively can be prohibitively expensive even if $p+q$ is small but the local dimension $d$ is large. We show that, under additional symmetry assumptions, this problem reduces to a linear program that can be solved in time that does not scale in $d$, and we provide a general framework to execute this reduction under different types of symmetries. The key ingredient of our method is a compact parametrization of the solution space by linear combinations of walled Brauer algebra diagrams. This parametrization requires the idempotents of a Gelfand--Tsetlin basis, which we obtain by adapting a general method arXiv:1606.08900 inspired by the Okounkov--Vershik approach. To illustrate potential applications, we use several toy examples from quantum information: deciding the principal eigenvalue of a quantum state, quantum majority vote, and asymmetric cloning. We also outline a possible route for extending our method to general unitary-equivariant semidefinite programs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A density-matrix renormalisation group algorithm for simulating quantum circuits with a finite fidelity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05612</link>
    <author>Thomas Ayral, Thibaud Louvet, Yiqing Zhou, Cyprien Lambert, E. Miles Stoudenmire, Xavier Waintal</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop a density-matrix renormalization group (DMRG) algorithm for the simulation of quantum circuits. This algorithm can be seen as the extension of time-dependent DMRG from the usual situation of hermitian Hamiltonian matrices to quantum circuits defined by unitary matrices. For small circuit depths, the technique is exact and equivalent to other matrix product state (MPS) based techniques. For larger depths, it becomes approximate in exchange for an exponential speed up in computational time. Like an actual quantum computer, the quality of the DMRG results is characterized by a finite fidelity. However, unlike a quantum computer, the fidelity depends strongly on the quantum circuit considered. For the most difficult possible circuit for this technique, the so-called "quantum supremacy" benchmark of Google Inc. , we find that the DMRG algorithm can generate bit strings of the same quality as the seminal Google experiment on a single computing core. For a more structured circuit used for combinatorial optimization (Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm or QAOA), we find a drastic improvement of the DMRG results with error rates dropping by a factor of 100 compared with random quantum circuits. Our results suggest that the current bottleneck of quantum computers is their fidelities rather than the number of qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Catalysis of entanglement and other quantum resources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05694</link>
    <author>Chandan Datta, Tulja Varun Kondra, Marek Miller, Alexander Streltsov</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In chemistry, a catalyst is a substance which enables a chemical reaction or increases its rate, while remaining unchanged in the process. Instead of chemical reactions, quantum catalysis enhances our ability to convert quantum states into each other under physical constraints. The nature of the constraints depends on the problem under study, and can arise, e.g., from energy preservation. In this article we review the most recent developments of quantum catalysis, and give also a historical overview of this research direction. We focus on catalysis of quantum entanglement and coherence, and also discuss this phenomenon in quantum thermodynamics and general quantum resource theories. We review applications of quantum catalysis, and discuss also the recent efforts on universal catalysis, where the quantum state of the catalyst does not depend on the states to be transformed. Catalytic embezzling is also considered, a phenomenon which occurs if the state of the catalyst can change in the transition.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>