<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Hunting for quantum-classical crossover in condensed matter problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14109</link>
    <author>Nobuyuki Yoshioka, Tsuyoshi Okubo, Yasunari Suzuki, Yuki Koizumi, Wataru Mizukami</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The intensive pursuit for quantum algorithms with speedup in terms of computational complexity has further led to this modernized crucial question: \it When and how will quantum computers outperform classical computers?. The next milestone in the context of this quantum transcendence is undoubtedly the realization of quantum acceleration in practical problems. Here we provide a clear evidence and arguments that the primary target is likely to be condensed matter physics. Our primary contributions are summarized as follows: 1) Proposal of systematic error/runtime analysis on state-of-the-art classical algorithm based on tensor networks; 2) Dedicated and high-resolution analysis on quantum resource performed at the level of executable logical instructions; 3) Clarification of quantum-classical crosspoint for ground-state simulation to be within runtime of hours using only a few hundreds of thousand physical qubits for 2d Heisenberg and 2d Fermi-Hubbard models. To our knowledge, we argue that condensed matter problems offer the earliest platform for demonstration of practical quantum advantage that is order-of-magnitude more feasible than ever known candidates, in terms of both qubit counts and total runtime.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Holography as a resource for non-local quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.13500</link>
    <author>Kfir Dolev, Sam Cree</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>If two parties share sufficient entanglement, they are able to implement any channel on a shared bipartite state via non-local quantum computation -- a protocol consisting of local operations and a single simultaneous round of quantum communication. Such a protocol can occur in the AdS/CFT correspondence, with the two parties represented by regions of the CFT, and the holographic state serving as a resource to provide the necessary entanglement. This boundary non-local computation is dual to the local implementation of a channel in the bulk AdS theory. Previous work on this phenomenon was obstructed by the divergent entanglement between adjacent CFT regions, and tried to circumvent this issue by assuming that certain regions are irrelevant. However, the absence of these regions introduces violent phenomena that prevent the CFT from implementing the protocol. Instead, we resolve the issue of divergent entanglement by using a finite-memory quantum simulation of the CFT. We show that any finite-memory quantum system on a circular lattice yields a protocol for non-local quantum computation. In the case of a quantum simulation of a holographic CFT, we carefully show that this protocol implements the channel performed by the local bulk dynamics. Under plausible physical assumptions about quantum computation in the bulk, our results imply that non-local quantum computation can be performed for any polynomially complex unitary with a polynomial amount of entanglement. Finally, we provide a concrete example of a holographic code whose bulk dynamics correspond to a Clifford gate, and use our results to show that this corresponds to a non-local quantum computation protocol for this gate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning to predict arbitrary quantum processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14894</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Sitan Chen, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an efficient machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting any unknown quantum process $\mathcal{E}$ over $n$ qubits. For a wide range of distributions $\mathcal{D}$ on arbitrary $n$-qubit states, we show that this ML algorithm can learn to predict any local property of the output from the unknown process $\mathcal{E}$, with a small average error over input states drawn from $\mathcal{D}$. The ML algorithm is computationally efficient even when the unknown process is a quantum circuit with exponentially many gates. Our algorithm combines efficient procedures for learning properties of an unknown state and for learning a low-degree approximation to an unknown observable. The analysis hinges on proving new norm inequalities, including a quantum analogue of the classical Bohnenblust-Hille inequality, which we derive by giving an improved algorithm for optimizing local Hamiltonians. Overall, our results highlight the potential for ML models to predict the output of complex quantum dynamics much faster than the time needed to run the process itself.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The power of noisy quantum states and the advantage of resource dilution</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14192</link>
    <author>Marek Miller, Manfredi Scalici, Alexander Streltsov</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement distillation allows to convert noisy quantum states into singlets, which can in turn be used for various quantum technological tasks, such as quantum teleportation and quantum key distribution. Entanglement dilution is the inverse process: singlets are converted into quantum states with less entanglement. While the usefulness of distillation is apparent, practical applications of entanglement dilution are less obvious. Here, we show that entanglement dilution can increase the resilience of shared quantum states to local noise. The increased resilience is observed even if diluting singlets into states with arbitrarily little entanglement. We extend our analysis to other quantum resource theories, such as quantum coherence, quantum thermodynamics, and purity. For these resource theories, we demonstrate that diluting pure quantum states into noisy ones can be advantageous for protecting the system from noise. Our results demonstrate the usefulness of quantum resource dilution, and provide a rare example for an advantage of noisy quantum states over pure states in quantum information processing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Smallest Code with Transversal T</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14066</link>
    <author>Stergios Koutsioumpas, Darren Banfield, Alastair Kay</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove that the smallest distance 3 Quantum Error Correcting Code with a transversal gate outside the Clifford group is the well-known 15-qubit Reed-Muller code, also known as a tri-orthogonal code. Our result relies on fewer assumptions than previous works. We further extend this result by finding the minimal code that also possesses any other non Clifford transversal single-qubit gate.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>