<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Simulating scalar field theories on quantum computers with limited resources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07985</link>
    <author>Andy C. Y. Li, Alexandru Macridin, Stephen Mrenna, Panagiotis Spentzouris</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a quantum algorithm for implementing $\phi^4$ lattice scalar field theory on qubit computers. The field is represented in the discretized field amplitude basis. The number of qubits and elementary gates required by the implementation of the evolution operator is proportional to the lattice size. The algorithm allows efficient $\phi^4$ state preparation for a large range of input parameters in both the normal and broken symmetry phases. The states are prepared using a combination of variational and adiabatic evolution methods. First, the ground state of a local Hamiltonian, which includes the $\phi^4$ self-interaction, is prepared using short variational circuits. Next, this state is evolved by switching on the coupling between the lattice sites adiabatically. The parameters defining the local Hamiltonian are adjustable and constitute the input of our algorithm. We present a method to optimize these parameters in order to reduce the adiabatic time required for state preparation. For preparing broken symmetry states, the adiabatic evolution problems caused by crossing the phase transition critical line and by the degeneracy of the broken symmetry ground state can be addressed using an auxiliary external field which gradually turns off during the adiabatic process. We show that the time dependence of the external field during the adiabatic evolution is important for addressing the broken symmetry ground state degeneracy. The adiabatic time dependence on the inverse error tolerance can be reduced from quadratic to linear by using a field strength that decreases exponentially in time relative to one that decreases linearly.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Representation Theory for Geometric Quantum Machine Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07980</link>
    <author>Michael Ragone, Paolo Braccia, Quynh T. Nguyen, Louis Schatzki, Patrick J. Coles, Frederic Sauvage, Martin Larocca, M. Cerezo</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent advances in classical machine learning have shown that creating models with inductive biases encoding the symmetries of a problem can greatly improve performance. Importation of these ideas, combined with an existing rich body of work at the nexus of quantum theory and symmetry, has given rise to the field of Geometric Quantum Machine Learning (GQML). Following the success of its classical counterpart, it is reasonable to expect that GQML will play a crucial role in developing problem-specific and quantum-aware models capable of achieving a computational advantage. Despite the simplicity of the main idea of GQML -- create architectures respecting the symmetries of the data -- its practical implementation requires a significant amount of knowledge of group representation theory. We present an introduction to representation theory tools from the optics of quantum learning, driven by key examples involving discrete and continuous groups. These examples are sewn together by an exposition outlining the formal capture of GQML symmetries via "label invariance under the action of a group representation", a brief (but rigorous) tour through finite and compact Lie group representation theory, a reexamination of ubiquitous tools like Haar integration and twirling, and an overview of some successful strategies for detecting symmetries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optical coherent feedback control of a mechanical oscillator</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07674</link>
    <author>Maryse Ernzer, Manel Bosch Aguilera, Matteo Brunelli, Gian-Luca Schmid, Christoph Bruder, Patrick P. Potts, Philipp Treutlein</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Feedback is a powerful and ubiquitous technique both in classical and quantum system control. In its standard implementation it relies on measuring the state of a system, classically processing and feeding back the extracted information. In quantum physics, however, measurements not only read out the state of the system, but also modify it irreversibly. A different kind of feedback which coherently processes and feeds back quantum signals without actually measuring the system is possible. This is known as coherent feedback. Here, we report on the realization of an optical coherent feedback platform to control the motional state of a nanomechanical membrane in an optical cavity. The coherent feedback loop consists of a light field interacting twice with the same mechanical mode through different cavity modes, without any measurement taking place. Tuning the optical phase and delay of the feedback loop allows us to control the motional state of the mechanical oscillator, its resonance frequency and damping rate, the latter of which we use to cool the membrane close to the quantum ground state. We present here a theoretical description and experimental realization of this scheme. Our theoretical analysis provides the optimal cooling conditions, showing that this new technique enables ground-state cooling. Experimentally, we show that we can cool the membrane to a state with $\bar{n}_m = 4.89 \pm 0.14 $ phonons ($480\,\mu$K) in a ${20}\,$K environment. This lies below the theoretical limit of cavity dynamical backaction cooling in the unresolved sideband regime. Our feedback scheme is very versatile, offering new opportunities for quantum control in a variety of optomechanical systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tidal Disruption of Main-Sequence Stars by Intermediate-Mass Black Holes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.08002</link>
    <author>Fulya Kıroğlu, James C. Lombardi Jr., Kyle Kremer, Giacomo Fragione, Shane Fogarty, Frederic A. Rasio</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study close encounters of a $1\,M_{\odot}$ middle-age main-sequence star (modelled using MESA) with massive black holes through hydrodynamic simulations, and explore in particular the dependence of the outcomes on the black hole mass. We consider here black holes in the intermediate-mass range, $M_{\rm BH}= 100-10^4\,M_{\odot}$. Possible outcomes vary from a small tidal perturbation for weak encounters all the way to partial or full disruption for stronger encounters. We find that stronger encounters lead to increased mass loss at the first pericenter passage, in many cases ejecting the partially disrupted star on an unbound orbit. For encounters that initially produce a bound system, with only partial stripping of the star, the fraction of mass stripped from the star increases with each subsequent pericenter passage and a stellar remnant of finite mass is ultimately ejected in all cases. We also find that the number of successive close passages before ejection decreases as we go from the stellar-mass black hole to the intermediate-mass black hole regime. For instance, after an initial encounter right at the classical tidal disruption limit, a $1\,M_{\odot}$ star undergoes 16 (5) pericenter passages before ejection from a $10\,M_{\odot}$ ($100\,M_{\odot}$) black hole. Observations of consecutive electromagnetic flares from these repeated close passages could in principle be used to determine the mass of the black hole, thus possibly proving the existence of intermediate-mass black holes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learnable Polyphase Sampling for Shift Invariant and Equivariant Convolutional Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.08001</link>
    <author>Renan A. Rojas-Gomez, Teck-Yian Lim, Alexander G. Schwing, Minh N. Do, Raymond A. Yeh</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose learnable polyphase sampling (LPS), a pair of learnable down/upsampling layers that enable truly shift-invariant and equivariant convolutional networks. LPS can be trained end-to-end from data and generalizes existing handcrafted downsampling layers. It is widely applicable as it can be integrated into any convolutional network by replacing down/upsampling layers. We evaluate LPS on image classification and semantic segmentation. Experiments show that LPS is on-par with or outperforms existing methods in both performance and shift consistency. For the first time, we achieve true shift-equivariance on semantic segmentation (PASCAL VOC), i.e., 100% shift consistency, outperforming baselines by an absolute 3.3%.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>