<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Scrambling Dynamics and Out-of-Time Ordered Correlators in Quantum Many-Body Systems: a Tutorial</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.07060</link>
    <author>Shenglong Xu, Brian Swingle</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This tutorial article introduces the physics of quantum information scrambling in quantum many-body systems. The goals are to understand how to quantify the spreading of quantum information precisely and how causality emerges in complex quantum systems. We introduce the general framework to study the dynamics of quantum information, including detection and decoding. We show that the dynamics of quantum information is closely related to operator dynamics in the Heisenberg picture, and, in certain circumstances, can be precisely quantified by the so-called out-the-time ordered correlator (OTOC). The general behavior of OTOC is discussed based on several toy models, including the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model, random circuit models, and Brownian models, in which OTOC is analytically tractable. We introduce numerical methods, both exact diagonalization and tensor network methods, to calculate OTOC for generic quantum many-body systems. We also survey current experiment schemes to measure OTOC in various quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing quantum circuits with Riemannian gradient-flow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06976</link>
    <author>Roeland Wiersema, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms are a promising class of algorithms that can be performed on currently available quantum computers. In most settings, the free parameters of a variational circuit are optimized using a classical optimizer that updates parameters in Euclidean geometry. Since quantum circuits are elements of the special unitary group, we can consider an alternative optimization perspective that depends on the structure of this group. In this work, we investigate a Riemannian optimization scheme over the special unitary group and we discuss its implementation on a quantum computer. We illustrate that the resulting Riemannian gradient-flow algorithm has favorable optimization properties for deep circuits and that an approximate version of this algorithm can be performed on near-term hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>State Preparation Boosters for Early Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06978</link>
    <author>Guoming Wang, Sukin Sim, Peter D. Johnson</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing is believed to be particularly useful for the simulation of chemistry and materials, among the various applications. In recent years, there have been significant advancements in the development of near-term quantum algorithms for quantum simulation, including VQE and many of its variants. However, for such algorithms to be useful, they need to overcome several critical barriers including the inability to prepare high-quality approximations of the ground state. Current challenges to state preparation, including barren plateaus and the high-dimensionality of the optimization landscape, make state preparation through ansatz optimization unreliable. In this work, we introduce the method of ground state boosting, which uses a limited-depth quantum circuit to reliably increase the overlap with the ground state. This circuit, which we call a booster, can be used to augment an ansatz from VQE or be used as a stand-alone state preparation method. The booster converts circuit depth into ground state overlap in a controllable manner. We numerically demonstrate the capabilities of boosters by simulating the performance of a particular type of booster, namely the Gaussian booster, for preparing the ground state of $N_2$ molecular system. Beyond ground state preparation as a direct objective, many quantum algorithms, such as quantum phase estimation, rely on high-quality state preparation as a subroutine. Therefore, we foresee ground state boosting and similar methods as becoming essential algorithmic components as the field transitions into using early fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hardware-efficient entangled measurements for variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06979</link>
    <author>Francisco Escudero, David Fernández-Fernández, Gabriel Jaumà, Guillermo F. Peñas, Luciano Pereira</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational algorithms have received significant attention in recent years due to their potential to solve practical problems in noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. A fundamental step of these algorithms is the evaluation of the expected value of Hamiltonians. Efficient schemes to perform this task are required to speed up these algorithm. The standard approach employs local measurements of Pauli operators, which requires a large number of circuits. An alternative is to make use of entangled measurements, which significantly reduce the number of circuits but involve entangling gates between non-physically connected qubits, introducing intermediate entangling operations that increase the depth of the circuits. As a solution to this problem we propose hardware-efficient entangled measurements (HEEM), that is, measurements that only permit entanglement between physically connected qubits. We show that this strategy enhances the evaluation of molecular Hamiltonians in NISQ devices because it reduces the number of circuits required without increasing their depth. We provide quantitative metrics of how this approach offers better results than only local measurements and arbitrarily entangled ones. We estimate with classical simulators and quantum hardware the ground state energy of the H$_2$O molecule by the variational quantum eigensolver using HEEM.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A tensor-based entanglement measure for mixed states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.07420</link>
    <author>Christian Carisch, Oded Zilberberg</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement is a key resource for quantum technologies and is at the root of exciting many-body phenomena. Nevertheless, quantifying the amount of entanglement in a real-world quantum system is challenging when it interacts with its environment. Here, we devise an entanglement measure for such realistic open systems. Our measure relies on a tensor-network representation of the system's density matrix and is readily computed using our presented algorithm. We showcase the virtues of our scheme using a case study of spinless particles moving on a chain in presence of dephasing. Crucially, our approach distinguishes classical from quantum correlations in a broad plethora of systems and motivates efficient experimental entanglement quantification.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>