<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Syndrome-Derived Error Rates as a Benchmark of Quantum Hardware</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00553</link>
    <author>James R. Wootton</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correcting codes are designed to pinpoint exactly when and where errors occur in quantum circuits. This feature is the foundation of their primary task: to support fault-tolerant quantum computation. However, this feature could used as the basis of benchmarking: By analyzing the outputs of even small-scale quantum error correction circuits, a detailed picture can be constructed of error processes across a quantum device. Here we perform an example of such an analysis, using the results of small repetition codes to determine the error rate of each qubit while idle during a syndrome measurement. This provides an idea of the errors experienced by the qubits across a device while they are part of the kind of circuit that we expect to be typical in fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Disorder-Assisted Assembly of Strongly Correlated Fluids of Light</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00577</link>
    <author>Brendan Saxberg, Andrei Vrajitoarea, Gabrielle Roberts, Margaret G. Panetta, Jonathan Simon, David I. Schuster</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Guiding many-body systems to desired states is a central challenge of modern quantum science, with applications from quantum computation to many-body physics and quantum-enhanced metrology. Approaches to solving this problem include step-by-step assembly, reservoir engineering to irreversibly pump towards a target state, and adiabatic evolution from a known initial state. Here we construct low-entropy quantum fluids of light in a Bose Hubbard circuit by combining particle-by-particle assembly and adiabatic preparation. We inject individual photons into a disordered lattice where the eigenstates are known & localized, then adiabatically remove this disorder, allowing quantum fluctuations to melt the photons into a fluid. Using our plat-form, we first benchmark this lattice melting technique by building and characterizing arbitrary single-particle-in-a-box states, then assemble multi-particle strongly correlated fluids. Inter-site entanglement measurements performed through single-site tomography indicate that the particles in the fluid delocalize, while two-body density correlation measurements demonstrate that they also avoid one another, revealing Friedel oscillations characteristic of a Tonks-Girardeau gas. This work opens new possibilities for preparation of topological and otherwise exotic phases of synthetic matter.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental Simulation of Loop Quantum Gravity on a Photonic Chip</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00557</link>
    <author>Reinier van der Meer, Zichang Huang, Malaquias Correa Anguita, Dongxue Qu, Peter Hooijschuur, Hongguang Liu, Muxin Han, Jelmer J. Renema, Lior Cohen</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The unification of general relativity and quantum theory is one of the fascinating problems of modern physics. One leading solution is Loop Quantum Gravity (LQG). Simulating LQG may be important for providing predictions which can then be tested experimentally. However, such complex quantum simulations cannot run efficiently on classical computers, and quantum computers or simulators are needed. Here, we experimentally demonstrate quantum simulations of spinfoam amplitudes of LQG on an integrated photonics quantum processor. We simulate a basic transition of LQG and show that the derived spinfoam vertex amplitude falls within 4% error with respect to the theoretical prediction, despite experimental imperfections. We also discuss how to generalize the simulation for more complex transitions, in realistic experimental conditions, which will eventually lead to a quantum advantage demonstration as well as expand the toolbox to investigate LQG.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bipartite entanglement and the arrow of time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00024</link>
    <author>Markus Frembs</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide a new perspective on the close relationship between entanglement and time. Our main focus is on bipartite entanglement, where this connection is foreshadowed both in the positive partial transpose criterion due to Peres [A. Peres, Phys. Rev. Lett., 77, 1413 (1996)] and in the classification of quantum within more general non-signalling bipartite correlations [M. Frembs and A. Döring, arXiv:2204.11471]. Extracting the relevant common features, we identify a necessary and sufficient condition for bipartite entanglement in terms of a compatibility condition with respect to time orientations in local observable algebras, which express the dynamics in the respective subsystems. We discuss the relevance of the latter in the broader context of von Neumann algebras and the thermodynamical notion of time naturally arising within the latter.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Thirty milliseconds in the life of a supercooled liquid</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00491</link>
    <author>Camille Scalliet, Benjamin Guiselin, Ludovic Berthier</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We combine the swap Monte Carlo algorithm to long multi-CPU molecular dynamics simulations to analyse the equilibrium relaxation dynamics of model supercooled liquids over a time window covering ten orders of magnitude for temperatures down to the experimental glass transition temperature $T_g$. The analysis of time correlation functions coupled to spatio-temporal resolution of particle motion allow us to elucidate the nature of the equilibrium dynamics in deeply supercooled liquids. We find that structural relaxation starts at early times in rare localised regions characterised by a waiting time distribution that develops a power law near $T_g$. At longer times, relaxation events accumulate with increasing probability in these regions as $T_g$ is approached. This accumulation leads to a power-law growth of the linear extension of relaxed domains with time, with a large dynamic exponent. Past the average relaxation time, unrelaxed domains slowly shrink with time due to relaxation events happening at their boundaries. Our results provide a complete microscopic description of the particle motion responsible for key experimental signatures of glassy dynamics, from the shape and temperature evolution of relaxation spectra to the core features of dynamic heterogeneity. They also provide a microscopic basis for the emergence of dynamic facilitation in deeply supercooled liquids and allow us to critically reassess theoretical descriptions of the glass transition.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>