<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Sparse random Hamiltonians are quantumly easy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03394</link>
    <author>Chi-Fang Chen, Alexander M. Dalzell, Mario Berta, Fernando G.S.L. Brandão, Joel A. Tropp</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A candidate application for quantum computers is to simulate the low-temperature properties of quantum systems. For this task, there is a well-studied quantum algorithm that performs quantum phase estimation on an initial trial state that has a nonnegligible overlap with a low-energy state. However, it is notoriously hard to give theoretical guarantees that such a trial state can be prepared efficiently. Moreover, the heuristic proposals that are currently available, such as with adiabatic state preparation, appear insufficient in practical cases. This paper shows that, for most random sparse Hamiltonians, the maximally mixed state is a sufficiently good trial state, and phase estimation efficiently prepares states with energy arbitrarily close to the ground energy. Furthermore, any low-energy state must have nonnegligible quantum circuit complexity, suggesting that low-energy states are classically nontrivial and phase estimation is the optimal method for preparing such states (up to polynomial factors). These statements hold for two models of random Hamiltonians: (i) a sum of random signed Pauli strings and (ii) a random signed $d$-sparse Hamiltonian. The main technical argument is based on some new results in nonasymptotic random matrix theory. In particular, a refined concentration bound for the spectral density is required to obtain complexity guarantees for these random Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>High threshold codes for neutral atom qubits with biased erasure errors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03063</link>
    <author>Kaavya Sahay, Junlan Jin, Jahan Claes, Jeff D. Thompson, Shruti Puri</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The requirements for fault-tolerant quantum error correction can be simplified by leveraging structure in the noise of the underlying hardware. In this work, we identify a new type of structured noise motivated by neutral atom qubits, biased erasure errors, which arises when qubit errors are dominated by detectable leakage from only one of the computational states of the qubit. We study the performance of this model using gate-level simulations of the XZZX surface code. Using the predicted erasure fraction and bias of metastable $^{171}$Yb qubits, we find a threshold of 8.2%, which is 1.9 times higher than the threshold for unbiased erasures, and 7.5 times higher than the threshold for depolarizing errors. Surprisingly, the improved threshold is achieved without bias-preserving controlled-not gates, and instead results from the lower noise entropy in this model. We also introduce an XZZX cluster state construction for measurement-based error correction, hybrid-fusion, that is optimized for this noise model. By combining fusion operations and deterministic entangling gates, this construction preserves the intrinsic symmetry of the XZZX code, leading to a higher threshold of 10.3% and enabling the use of rectangular codes with fewer qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing the quantumness of gravity without entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03075</link>
    <author>Ludovico Lami, Julen S. Pedernales, Martin B. Plenio</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a conceptually new class of dynamical experiments whose goal is to falsify the hypothesis that an interaction between quantum systems is mediated by a purely local classical field. The systems we study implement a dynamics that cannot be simulated by means of local operations and classical communication (LOCC), even when no entanglement is ever generated at any point in the process. Using tools from quantum information theory, we quantify the maximal fidelity of simulation that a local classical interaction could attain while employing only LOCC. Under our assumptions, if an experiment detects a fidelity larger than that threshold then a local classical description of the interaction is no longer possible. As a prominent application of this scheme, we study a general system of quantum harmonic oscillators initialised in normally distributed coherent states and interacting via Newtonian gravity, and discuss a possible physical implementation with torsion pendula. One of our main technical contributions is the calculation of the above bound on the maximal LOCC simulation fidelity for this family of systems. As opposed to existing tests based on the detection of gravitationally mediated entanglement, our proposal works with coherent states alone, and thus it does not require the generation of largely delocalised states of motion nor the detection of entanglement.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Nuclear shell-model simulation in digital quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03641</link>
    <author>A. Pérez-Obiol, A. M. Romero, J. Menéndez, A. Rios, A. García-Sáez, B. Juliá-Díaz</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The nuclear shell model is one of the prime many-body methods to study the structure of atomic nuclei, but it is hampered by an exponential scaling on the basis size as the number of particles increases. We present a shell-model quantum circuit design strategy to find nuclear ground states that circumvents this limitation by exploiting an adaptive variational quantum eigensolver algorithm. Our circuit implementation is in excellent agreement with classical shell-model simulations for a dozen of light and medium-mass nuclei, including neon and calcium isotopes. We quantify the circuit depth, width and number of gates to encode realistic shell-model wavefunctions. Our strategy also addresses explicitly energy measurements and the required number of circuits to perform them. Our simulated circuits approach the benchmark results exponentially with a polynomial scaling in quantum resources for each nucleus and configuration space. Our work paves the way for quantum computing shell-model studies across the nuclear chart.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Comment on "Geometry of the quantum set on no-signaling faces"</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03529</link>
    <author>Mateus Araújo</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In Ref. [1] the authors claim that the Almost Quantum set of correlations cannot reproduce two points on the boundary of the quantum set of correlations. This claim is incorrect. The underlying issue is that the associated SDP is not strictly feasible, which makes the numerical solvers give unreliable answers. We give analytical proofs that both points are indeed reproduced by Almost Quantum.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>