<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Towards near-term quantum simulation of materials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15256</link>
    <author>Laura Clinton, Toby Cubitt, Brian Flynn, Filippo Maria Gambetta, Joel Klassen, Ashley Montanaro, Stephen Piddock, Raul A. Santos, Evan Sheridan</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulation of materials is one of the most promising applications of quantum computers. On near-term hardware the crucial constraint on these simulations is circuit depth. Many quantum simulation algorithms rely on a layer of unitary evolutions generated by each term in a Hamiltonian. This appears in time-dynamics as a single Trotter step, and in variational quantum eigensolvers under the Hamiltonian variational ansatz as a single ansatz layer. We present a new quantum algorithm design for materials modelling where the depth of a layer is independent of the system size. This design takes advantage of the locality of materials in the Wannier basis and employs a tailored fermionic encoding that preserves locality. We analyse the circuit costs of this approach and present a compiler that transforms density functional theory data into quantum circuit instructions -- connecting the physics of the material to the simulation circuit. The compiler automatically optimises circuits at multiple levels, from the base gate level to optimisations derived from the physics of the specific target material. We present numerical results for materials spanning a wide structural and technological range. Our results demonstrate a reduction of many orders of magnitude in circuit depth over standard prior methods that do not consider the structure of the Hamiltonian. For example our results improve resource requirements for Strontium Vanadate (SrVO$_3$) from 864 to 180 qubits for a $3\times3\times3$ lattice, and the circuit depth of a single Trotter or variational layer from $7.5\times 10^8$ to depth $730$. Although this is still beyond current hardware, our results show that materials simulation may be feasible on quantum computers without necessarily requiring scalable, fault-tolerant quantum computers, provided quantum algorithm design incorporates understanding of the materials and applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Characterizing and mitigating coherent errors in a trapped ion quantum processor using hidden inverses</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.14225</link>
    <author>Swarnadeep Majumder, Christopher G. Yale, Titus D. Morris, Daniel S. Lobser, Ashlyn D. Burch, Matthew N. H. Chow, Melissa C. Revelle, Susan M. Clark, Raphael C. Pooser</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing testbeds exhibit high-fidelity quantum control over small collections of qubits, enabling performance of precise, repeatable operations followed by measurements. Currently, these noisy intermediate-scale devices can support a sufficient number of sequential operations prior to decoherence such that small algorithms can be performed reliably. While the results of these algorithms are imperfect, these imperfections can help bootstrap quantum computer testbed development. Demonstrations of these small algorithms over the past few years, coupled with the idea that imperfect algorithm performance can be caused by several dominant noise sources in the quantum processor, which can be measured and calibrated during algorithm execution or in post-processing, has led to the use of noise mitigation to improve typical computational results. Conversely, small benchmark algorithms coupled with noise mitigation can help diagnose the nature of the noise, whether systematic or purely random. Here, we outline the use of coherent noise mitigation techniques as a characterization tool in trapped-ion testbeds. We perform model-fitting of the noisy data to determine the noise source based on realistic physics focused noise models and demonstrate that systematic noise amplification coupled with error mitigation schemes provides useful data for noise model deduction. Further, in order to connect lower level noise model details with application specific performance of near term algorithms, we experimentally construct the loss landscape of a variational algorithm under various injected noise sources coupled with error mitigation techniques. This type of connection enables application-aware hardware codesign, in which the most important noise sources in specific applications, like quantum chemistry, become foci of improvement in subsequent hardware generations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-assisted Monte Carlo algorithms for fermions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.14903</link>
    <author>Xiaosi Xu, Ying Li</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing is a promising way to systematically solve the longstanding computational problem, the ground state of a many-body fermion system. Many efforts have been made to realise certain forms of quantum advantage in this problem, for instance, the development of variational quantum algorithms. A recent work by Huggins et al. reports a novel candidate, i.e. a quantum-classical hybrid Monte Carlo algorithm with a reduced bias in comparison to its fully-classical counterpart. In this paper, we propose a family of scalable quantum-assisted Monte Carlo algorithms where the quantum computer is used at its minimal cost and still can reduce the bias. By incorporating a Bayesian inference approach, we can achieve this quantum-facilitated bias reduction with a much smaller quantum-computing cost than taking empirical mean in amplitude estimation. Besides, we show that the hybrid Monte Carlo framework is a general way to suppress errors in the ground state obtained from classical algorithms. Our work provides a Monte Carlo toolkit for achieving quantum-enhanced calculation of fermion systems on near-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Unifying Kitaev magnets, kagome dimer models and ruby Rydberg spin liquids</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15302</link>
    <author>Ruben Verresen, Ashvin Vishwanath</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The exploration of quantum spin liquids (QSLs) has been guided by different approaches including the resonating valence bond (RVB) picture, deconfined lattice gauge theories and the Kitaev model. More recently, a spin liquid ground state was numerically established on the ruby lattice, inspired by the Rydberg blockade mechanism. Here we unify these varied approaches in a single parent Hamiltonian, in which local fluctuations of anyons stabilize deconfinement. The parent Hamiltonian is defined on kagomé triangles -- each hosting four RVB-like states -- and includes only Ising interactions and single-site transverse fields. In the weak-field limit, the ruby spin liquid and exactly soluble kagomé dimer models are recovered, while the strong-field limit reduces to the Kitaev honeycomb model, thereby unifying three seemingly different approaches to QSLs. We similarly obtain the chiral Yao-Kivelson model, honeycomb toric code and a new spin-1 quadrupolar Kitaev model. The last is shown to be in a QSL phase by a non-local mapping to the kagomé Ising antiferromagnet. We demonstrate various applications of our framework, including (a) an adiabatic deformation of the ruby lattice model to the exactly soluble kagomé dimer model, conclusively establishing the QSL phase in the former; and (b) demystifying the dynamical protocol for measuring off-diagonal strings in the Rydberg implementation of the ruby lattice spin liquid. More generally, we find an intimate connection between Kitaev couplings and the repulsive interactions used for emergent dimer models. For instance, we show how a spin-1/2 XXZ model on the ruby lattice encodes a Kitaev honeycomb model, providing a new route toward realizing the latter in cold-atom or solid-state systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tensor Network States with Low-Rank Tensors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15296</link>
    <author>Hao Chen, Thomas Barthel</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tensor networks are used to efficiently approximate states of strongly-correlated quantum many-body systems. More generally, tensor network approximations may allow to reduce the costs for operating on an order-$N$ tensor from exponential to polynomial in $N$, and this has become a popular approach for machine learning. We introduce the idea of imposing low-rank constraints on the tensors that compose the tensor network. With this modification, the time and space complexities for the network optimization can be substantially reduced while maintaining high accuracy. We detail this idea for tree tensor network states (TTNS) and projected entangled-pair states. Simulations of spin models on Cayley trees with low-rank TTNS exemplify the effect of rank constraints on the expressive power. We find that choosing the tensor rank $r$ to be on the order of the bond dimension $m$, is sufficient to obtain high-accuracy groundstate approximations and to substantially outperform standard TTNS computations. Thus low-rank tensor networks are a promising route for the simulation of quantum matter and machine learning on large data sets.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>