<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Autonomous quantum error correction and fault-tolerant quantum computation with squeezed cat qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.13406</link>
    <author>Qian Xu, Guo Zheng, Yu-Xin Wang, Peter Zoller, Aashish A. Clerk, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose an autonomous quantum error correction scheme using squeezed cat (SC) code against the dominant error source, excitation loss, in continuous-variable systems. Through reservoir engineering, we show that a structured dissipation can stabilize a two-component SC while autonomously correcting the errors. The implementation of such dissipation only requires low-order nonlinear couplings among three bosonic modes or between a bosonic mode and a qutrit. While our proposed scheme is device independent, it is readily implementable with current experimental platforms such as superconducting circuits and trapped-ion systems. Compared to the stabilized cat, the stabilized SC has a much lower dominant error rate and a significantly enhanced noise bias. Furthermore, the bias-preserving operations for the SC have much lower error rates. In combination, the stabilized SC leads to substantially better logical performance when concatenating with an outer discrete-variable code. The surface-SC scheme achieves more than one order of magnitude increase in the threshold ratio between the loss rate $\kappa_1$ and the engineered dissipation rate $\kappa_2$. Under a practical noise ratio $\kappa_1/\kappa_2 = 10^{-3}$, the repetition-SC scheme can reach a $10^{-15}$ logical error rate even with a small mean excitation number of 4, which already suffices for practically useful quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurements of Floquet code plaquette stabilizers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.13154</link>
    <author>James R. Wootton</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recently introduced Floquet codes have already inspired several follow up works in terms of theory and simulation. Here we report the first preliminary results on their experimental implementation, using IBM Quantum hardware. Specifically, we implement the stabilizer measurements of the original Floquet code based on the honeycomb lattice model, as well as the more recently introduced Floquet Color code. The stabilizers of these are measured on a variety of systems, with the rate of syndrome changes used as a proxy for the noise of the device.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction with dissipatively stabilized squeezed cat qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.13359</link>
    <author>Timo Hillmann, Fernando Quijandría</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Noise-biased qubits are a promising route toward significantly reducing the hardware overhead associated with quantum error correction. The squeezed cat code, a non-local encoding in phase space based on squeezed coherent states, is an example of a noise-biased (bosonic) qubit with exponential error bias. Here we propose and analyze the error correction performance of a dissipatively stabilized squeezed cat qubit. We find that for moderate squeezing the bit-flip error rate gets significantly reduced in comparison with the ordinary cat qubit while leaving the phase flip rate unchanged. Additionally, we find that the squeezing enables faster and higher-fidelity gates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classically Approximating Variational Quantum Machine Learning with Random Fourier Features</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.13200</link>
    <author>Jonas Landman, Slimane Thabet, Constantin Dalyac, Hela Mhiri, Elham Kashefi</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many applications of quantum computing in the near term rely on variational quantum circuits (VQCs). They have been showcased as a promising model for reaching a quantum advantage in machine learning with current noisy intermediate scale quantum computers (NISQ). It is often believed that the power of VQCs relies on their exponentially large feature space, and extensive works have explored the expressiveness and trainability of VQCs in that regard. In our work, we propose a classical sampling method that may closely approximate a VQC with Hamiltonian encoding, given only the description of its architecture. It uses the seminal proposal of Random Fourier Features (RFF) and the fact that VQCs can be seen as large Fourier series. We provide general theoretical bounds for classically approximating models built from exponentially large quantum feature space by sampling a few frequencies to build an equivalent low dimensional kernel, and we show experimentally that this approximation is efficient for several encoding strategies. Precisely, we show that the number of required samples grows favorably with the size of the quantum spectrum. This tool therefore questions the hope for quantum advantage from VQCs in many cases, but conversely helps to narrow the conditions for their potential success. We expect VQCs with various and complex encoding Hamiltonians, or with large input dimension, to become more robust to classical approximations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universality classes of thermalization for mesoscopic Floquet systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.13444</link>
    <author>Alan Morningstar, David A. Huse, Vedika Khemani</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We identify several distinct phases of thermalization that can occur in periodically driven mesoscopic or intermediate-scale quantum chaotic systems. In doing so, we also identify a new Floquet thermal ensemble, the ``ladder ensemble", that is qualitatively distinct from the ``featureless infinite-temperature" state that has long been assumed to be the appropriate equilibrium ensemble for driven systems. The phases we find can be coarsely classified by (i) whether or not the system irreversibly exchanges energy of order $\omega$ with the drive, i.e., Floquet thermalizes, and (ii) the Floquet thermal ensemble describing the final equilibrium in systems that do Floquet thermalize. These phases are representative of regimes of behavior in mesoscopic systems, but they are sharply defined in a particular large-system limit where the drive frequency $\omega$ scales up with system size $N$ as the $N\to\infty$ limit is taken: we examine frequency scalings ranging from a weakly $N$-dependent $\omega(N) \sim \log N$, to stronger scalings ranging from $\omega(N) \sim \sqrt{N}$ to $\omega(N) \sim N$. We show that the transition where Floquet thermalization breaks down happens at an extensive drive frequency and, beyond that, systems that do not Floquet thermalize are distinguished based on the presence or absence of rare resonances across Floquet zones. We produce a thermalization phase diagram that is relevant for numerical studies of Floquet systems and experimental studies on intermediate-scale quantum simulators, both of which are limited to finite-size systems that lack a clean separation of scales between $N$ and $\omega$. A striking prediction of our work is that certain experimentally observable quench protocols from simple initial states can show Floquet thermalization to a novel type of Schrodinger-cat state that is a global superposition of states at distinct temperatures.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>