<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Improved quantum algorithms for linear and nonlinear differential equations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01054</link>
    <author>Hari Krovi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present substantially generalized and improved quantum algorithms over prior work for inhomogeneous linear and nonlinear ordinary differential equations (ODE). In Berry et al., (2017), a quantum algorithm for a certain class of linear ODEs is given, where the matrix involved needs to be diagonalizable. The quantum algorithm for linear ODEs presented here extends to many classes of non-diagonalizable matrices. The algorithm here can also be exponentially faster for certain classes of diagonalizable matrices. Our linear ODE algorithm is then applied to nonlinear differential equations using Carleman linearization (an approach taken recently by us in Liu et al., (2021)). The improvement over that result is two-fold. First, we obtain an exponentially better dependence on error. This kind of logarithmic dependence on error has also been achieved by Xue et al., (2021), but only for homogeneous nonlinear equations. Second, the present algorithm can handle any sparse, invertible matrix (that models dissipation) if it has a negative log-norm (including non-diagonalizable matrices), whereas Liu et al., (2021) and Xue et al., (2021) additionally require normality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Order preserving maps on quantum measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00725</link>
    <author>Teiko Heinosaari, Maria Anastasia Jivulescu, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the partially ordered set of equivalence classes of quantum measurements endowed with the post-processing partial order. The post-processing order is fundamental as it enables to compare measurements by their intrinsic noise and it gives grounds to define the important concept of quantum incompatibility. Our approach is based on mapping this set into a simpler partially ordered set using an order preserving map and investigating the resulting image. The aim is to ignore unnecessary details while keeping the essential structure, thereby simplifying e.g. detection of incompatibility. One possible choice is the map based on Fisher information introduced by Huangjun Zhu, known to be an order morphism taking values in the cone of positive semidefinite matrices. We explore the properties of that construction and improve Zhu's incompatibility criterion by adding a constraint depending on the number of measurement outcomes. We generalize this type of construction to other ordered vector spaces and we show that this map is optimal among all quadratic maps.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Deviation from maximal entanglement for mid-spectrum eigenstates of local Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01173</link>
    <author>Yichen Huang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a chain of $N$ spins governed by a local Hamiltonian, we consider eigenstates in a microcanonical ensemble in the middle of the energy spectrum. We prove that if the bandwidth of the ensemble is $C\ln^2N$ for a large constant $C$, then the average entanglement entropy of these eigenstates is bounded away from the maximum entropy. This result highlights the difference between the entanglement of mid-spectrum eigenstates of (chaotic) local Hamiltonians and that of random states, for the latter is nearly maximal. We also prove that the former is different from the thermodynamic entropy at the same energy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Network Nonlocality via Rigidity of Token-Counting and Color-Matching</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00905</link>
    <author>Marc-Olivier Renou, Salman Beigi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Network Nonlocality is the study of the Network Nonlocal correlations created by several independent entangled states shared in a network. In this paper, we provide the first two generic strategies to produce nonlocal correlations in large classes of networks without input. In the first one, called Token-Counting (TC), each source distributes a fixed number of tokens and each party counts the number of received tokens. In the second one, called Color-Matching (CM), each source takes a color and a party checks if the color of neighboring sources match. Using graph theoretic tools and Finner's inequality, we show that TC and CM distributions are rigid in wide classes of networks, meaning that there is essentially a unique classical strategy to simulate such correlations. Using this rigidity property, we show that certain quantum TC and CM strategies produce correlations that cannot be produced classicality. This leads us to several examples of Network Nonlocality without input. These examples involve creation of coherence throughout the whole network, which we claim to be a fingerprint of genuine forms of Network Nonlocality. This work extends a more compact parallel work [Nonlocality for Generic Networks, arXiv:2011.02769] on the same subject and provides all the required technical proofs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tweezer-programmable 2D quantum walks in a Hubbard-regime lattice</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01204</link>
    <author>Aaron W. Young, William J. Eckner, Nathan Schine, Andrew M. Childs, Adam M. Kaufman</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum walks provide a framework for understanding and designing quantum algorithms that is both intuitive and universal. To leverage the computational power of these walks, it is important to be able to programmably modify the graph a walker traverses while maintaining coherence. Here, we do this by combining the fast, programmable control provided by optical tweezer arrays with the scalable, homogeneous environment of an optical lattice. Using this new combination of tools we study continuous-time quantum walks of single atoms on a 2D square lattice, and perform proof-of-principle demonstrations of spatial search using these walks. When scaled to more particles, the capabilities demonstrated here can be extended to study a variety of problems in quantum information science and quantum simulation, including the deterministic assembly of ground and excited states in Hubbard models with tunable interactions, and performing versions of spatial search in a larger graph with increased connectivity, where search by quantum walk can be more effective.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>