<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Perturbation Theory and the Sum of Squares</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12325</link>
    <author>Matthew B. Hastings</author>
    <pubDate>May 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The sum-of-squares (SoS) hierarchy is a powerful technique based on semi-definite programming that can be used for both classical and quantum optimization problems. This hierarchy goes under several names; in particular, in quantum chemistry it is called the reduced density matrix (RDM) method. We consider the ability of this hierarchy to reproduce weak coupling perturbation theory for three different kinds of systems: spin (or qubit) systems, bosonic systems (the anharmonic oscillator), and fermionic systems with quartic interactions. For such fermionic systems, we show that degree-$4$ SoS (called $2$-RDM in quantum chemsitry) does not reproduce second order perturbation theory but degree-$6$ SoS ($3$-RDM) does (and we conjecture that it reproduces third order perturbation theory). Indeed, we identify a fragment of degree-$6$ SoS which can do this, which may be useful for practical quantum chemical calculations as it may be possible to implement this fragment with less cost than the full degree-$6$ SoS. Remarkably, this fragment is very similar to one studied by Hastings and O'Donnell for the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement incompatibility vs. Bell non-locality: an approach via tensor norms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12668</link>
    <author>Faedi Loulidi, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>May 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Measurement incompatibility and quantum non-locality are two key features of quantum theory. Violations of Bell inequalities require quantum entanglement and incompatibility of the measurements used by the two parties involved in the protocol. We analyze the converse question: for which Bell inequalities is the incompatibility of measurements enough to ensure a quantum violation? We relate the two questions by comparing two tensor norms on the space of dichotomic quantum measurements: one characterizing measurement compatibility and the second one characterizing violations of a given Bell inequality. We provide sufficient conditions for the equivalence of the two notions in terms of the matrix describing the correlation Bell inequality. We show that the CHSH inequality and its variants are the only ones satisfying it.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Convergence Theory for Over-parameterized Variational Quantum Eigensolvers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12481</link>
    <author>Xuchen You, Shouvanik Chakrabarti, Xiaodi Wu</author>
    <pubDate>May 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) is a promising candidate for quantum applications on near-term Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) computers. Despite a lot of empirical studies and recent progress in theoretical understanding of VQE's optimization landscape, the convergence for optimizing VQE is far less understood. We provide the first rigorous analysis of the convergence of VQEs in the over-parameterization regime. By connecting the training dynamics with the Riemannian Gradient Flow on the unit-sphere, we establish a threshold on the sufficient number of parameters for efficient convergence, which depends polynomially on the system dimension and the spectral ratio, a property of the problem Hamiltonian, and could be resilient to gradient noise to some extent. We further illustrate that this overparameterization threshold could be vastly reduced for specific VQE instances by establishing an ansatz-dependent threshold paralleling our main result. We showcase that our ansatz-dependent threshold could serve as a proxy of the trainability of different VQE ansatzes without performing empirical experiments, which hence leads to a principled way of evaluating ansatz design. Finally, we conclude with a comprehensive empirical study that supports our theoretical findings.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>How Much Entanglement Do Quantum Optimization Algorithms Require?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12283</link>
    <author>Yanzhu Chen, Linghua Zhu, Chenxu Liu, Nicholas J. Mayhall, Edwin Barnes, Sophia E. Economou</author>
    <pubDate>May 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many classical optimization problems can be mapped to finding the ground states of diagonal Ising Hamiltonians, for which variational quantum algorithms such as the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) provide heuristic methods. Because the solutions of such classical optimization problems are necessarily product states, it is unclear how entanglement affects their performance. An Adaptive Derivative-Assembled Problem-Tailored (ADAPT) variation of QAOA improves the convergence rate by allowing entangling operations in the mixer layers whereas it requires fewer CNOT gates in the entire circuit. In this work, we study the entanglement generated during the execution of ADAPT-QAOA. Through simulations of the weighted Max-Cut problem, we show that ADAPT-QAOA exhibits substantial flexibility in entangling and disentangling qubits. By incrementally restricting this flexibility, we find that a larger amount of entanglement entropy at earlier stages coincides with faster convergence at later stages. In contrast, while the standard QAOA quickly generates entanglement within a few layers, it cannot remove excess entanglement efficiently. Our results offer implications for favorable features of quantum optimization algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mitigating barren plateaus of variational quantum eigensolvers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.13539</link>
    <author>Xia Liu, Geng Liu, Jiaxin Huang, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms (VQAs) are expected to establish valuable applications on near-term quantum computers. However, recent works have pointed out that the performance of VQAs greatly relies on the capability of the ansatzes and is seriously limited by optimization issues such as barren plateaus (i.e., vanishing gradients). This work proposes the state efficient ansatz (SEA) for accurate quantum dynamics simulations with improved trainability. First, we show that SEA can generate an arbitrary pure state with much fewer parameters than a universal ansatz, making it efficient for tasks like ground state estimation. It also has the flexibility in adjusting the entanglement of the prepared state, which could be applied to further improve the efficiency of simulating weak entanglement. Second, we show that SEA is not a unitary 2-design even if it has universal wavefunction expressibility and thus has great potential to improve the trainability by avoiding the zone of barren plateaus. We further investigate a plethora of examples in ground state estimation and notably obtain significant improvements in the variances of derivatives and the overall optimization behaviors. This result indicates that SEA can mitigate barren plateaus by sacrificing the redundant expressibility for the target problem.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>