<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence between simulability of high-dimensional measurements and high-dimensional steering</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.04080</link>
    <author>Benjamin D.M. Jones, Roope Uola, Thomas Cope, Marie Ioannou, Sébastien Designolle, Pavel Sekatski, Nicolas Brunner</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The effect of quantum steering arises from the judicious combination of an entangled state with a set of incompatible measurements. Recently, it was shown that this form of quantum correlations can be quantified in terms of a dimension, leading to the notion of genuine high-dimensional steering. While this naturally connects to the dimensionality of entanglement (Schmidt number), we show that this effect also directly connects to a notion of dimension for measurement incompatibility. More generally, we present a general connection between the concepts of steering and measurement incompatibility, when quantified in terms of dimension. From this connection, we propose a novel twist on the problem of simulating quantum correlations. Specifically, we show how the correlations of certain high-dimensional entangled states can be exactly recovered using only shared randomness and lower-dimensional entanglement. Finally, we derive criteria for testing the dimension of measurement incompatibility, and discuss the extension of these ideas to quantum channels.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The concatenation of the Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill code with the XZZX surface code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.04383</link>
    <author>Jiaxuan Zhang, Yu-Chun Wu, Guo-Ping Guo</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bosonic codes provide an alternative option for the quantum error correction. An important category of bosonic codes called the Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) code aroused much interest recently. Theoretically, the error correction ability of GKP code is limited since it can only correct small shift errors in position and momentum quadratures. A natural approach to promote the GKP error correction for large-scale, fault-tolerant quantum computation is concatenating encoded GKP states with a stabilizer code. The performance of the XZZX surface-GKP code, i.e., the single-mode GKP code concatenated with XZZX surface code is investigated in this paper under two different noise models. Firstly, in the code-capacity noise model, the asymmetric rectangular GKP code with parameter $\lambda$ is introduced. Using the minimum weight perfect matching (MWPM) decoder combined with the continuous-variable GKP information, the optimal threshold of the XZZX-surface GKP code reaches $\sigma\approx0.67$ when $\lambda=2.1$, compared with the threshold $\sigma\approx0.60$ of the standard surface-GKP code. Secondly, we analyze the shift errors of two-qubit gates in the actual implementation, and build the full circuit-level noise model. The maximum likelihood decoding strategy is applied to each two-qubit gate with circuit-level noise, and improves the threshold from 18.6 dB in the previous work to 16.5 dB. We also estimate the overhead of the XZZX-surface GKP code which uses about 483 GKP states with squeezing more than 18.5 dB to encode a logical qubits with error rate $7.6\times10^{-6}$, compared with the qubit-based surface code using 1681 qubits to achieve almost the same logical error rate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fully undistillable quantum states are separable</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05193</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Nilanjana Datta</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Assume that Alice, Bob, and Eve share a tripartite pure state $|\psi_{ABE}\rangle$. We prove that if Alice cannot distill entanglement with either Bob or Eve using $|\psi_{ABE}\rangle$ and local operations with any one of the following configurations for classical communication: $(A\to B, A\leftrightarrow E), (A\leftrightarrow B, A\to E),$ and $(A\leftrightarrow B, A\leftrightarrow E)$, then the same is also true for the other two configurations. Moreover, this happens precisely when the state is such that both its reductions $\rho_{AB}$ and $\rho_{AE}$ are separable, which is further equivalent to the reductions being PPT. This, in particular, implies that any NPT bipartite state is such that either the state itself or its complement is 2-way distillable. In proving these results, we first obtain an explicit lower bound on the 2-way distillable entanglement of low rank bipartite states. Furthermore, we show that even though not all low rank states are 1-way distillable, a randomly sampled low rank state will almost surely be 1-way distillable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Belief Propagation with Quantum Messages for Symmetric Classical-Quantum Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.04984</link>
    <author>S. Brandsen, Avijit Mandal, Henry D. Pfister</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Belief propagation (BP) is a classical algorithm that approximates the marginal distribution associated with a factor graph by passing messages between adjacent nodes in the graph. It gained popularity in the 1990's as a powerful decoding algorithm for LDPC codes. In 2016, Renes introduced a belief propagation with quantum messages (BPQM) and described how it could be used to decode classical codes defined by tree factor graphs that are sent over the classical-quantum pure-state channel. In this work, we propose an extension of BPQM to general binary-input symmetric classical-quantum (BSCQ) channels based on the implementation of a symmetric "paired measurement". While this new paired-measurement BPQM (PMBPQM) approach is suboptimal in general, it provides a concrete BPQM decoder that can be implemented with local operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Emergence of the laws of thermodynamics for autonomous, arbitrary quantum systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.04850</link>
    <author>Cyril Elouard, Camille Lombard Latune</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Originally formulated for macroscopic machines, the laws of thermodynamics were shown during the last decades to hold for microscopic classical systems. More recently, similar thermodynamic laws were shown to hold also for quantum systems when coupled to ideal sources of work (external classical fields) and heat (systems at equilibrium). Ongoing efforts have been focusing on extending the validity of the thermodynamic laws to more realistic and non-ideal heat sources. Here, we go beyond all these extensions and show that energy exchanges between arbitrary quantum systems are structured by the laws of thermodynamics. The microscopic expression for the second law leads us to definitions for work and heat between arbitrary autonomous quantum systems, that we justify with several physical and mathematical arguments. We recover the known results from ideal work and heat sources and analyze some consequences from the general case corresponding to hybrid work and heat sources. In particular, we illustrate our general laws by proposing microscopic machines realizing thermodynamic tasks in which the roles of heat baths and work sources are all played by elementary quantum systems. Our results opens the perspective to understand and optimize the energetic performances of realistic devices, at any scale.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>