<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Time and Query Complexity Tradeoff for the Dihedral Coset Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14408</link>
    <author>Maxime Remaud, jean-Pierre Tillich</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Dihedral Coset Problem (DCP) in $Z_N$ is an important quantumly defined problem to which for instance the learning with errors problem reduces.There are several algorithms for solving it. On one hand, we have algorithms \textità la Ettinger-Høyer running in $\OO{2^{c_{\SS}\log{N}}}$ time but using $\OO{\log{N}}$ queries, for some constant $c_{\SS}$. On the other hand, algorithms \textità la Kuperberg need $\OOt{2^{\sqrt{c_{\DCP}\log{N}}}}$ time and queries, for some constant $c_{\DCP}$. Despite being the subject of a lot of studies, no algorithm using an intermediate number of queries was known up till now. It means that an attacker who has, for cost or time reasons, limited queries, will be forced to use a linear query algorithm running in exponential time. We propose an algorithm taking as a parameter the number $Q$ of queries we are allowed to do, therefore interpolating between existing algorithms. We thus explicitly show that it takes $\OOt{2^{c_{\SS}\left(\log{N}-\frac{1}{c_{\DCP}}\log^2{Q}\right)}}$ time. Our algorithm improves over algorithms \textità la Ettinger-Høyer when $Q$ is minimal and matches algorithms \textità la Kuperberg when $Q$ is maximal, while offering new possibilities in between. The key point of our algorithm is to give a degree of freedom in the way coset states are preprocessed, that we then link to the parameter $Q$ to obtain an optimal algorithm with respect to $Q$. We also introduce a new sieving procedure to assemble the constructed coset states, allowing us to retrieve the secret $s$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Concentration Inequalities for Output Statistics of Quantum Markov Processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14223</link>
    <author>Federico Girotti, Juan P. Garrahan, Mădălin Guţă</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive new concentration bounds for time averages of measurement outcomes in quantum Markov processes. This generalizes well-known bounds for classical Markov chains which provide constraints on finite time fluctuations of time-additive quantities around their averages. We employ spectral, perturbation and martingale techniques, together with noncommutative $L_2$ theory, to derive: (i) a Bernstein-type concentration bound for time averages of the measurement outcomes of a quantum Markov chain, (ii) a Hoeffding-type concentration bound for the same process, (iii) a generalization of the Bernstein-type concentration bound for counting processes of continuous time quantum Markov processes, (iv) new concentration bounds for empirical fluxes of classical Markov chains which broaden the range of applicability of the corresponding classical bounds beyond empirical averages. We also suggests potential application of our results to parameter estimation and consider extensions to reducible quantum channels, multi-time statistics and time-dependent measurements, and comment on the connection to so-called thermodynamic uncertainty relations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Linear Growth of Circuit Complexity from Brownian Dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14205</link>
    <author>Shao-Kai Jian, Gregory Bentsen, Brian Swingle</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We calculate the frame potential for Brownian clusters of $N$ spins or fermions with time-dependent all-to-all interactions. In both cases the problem can be mapped to an effective statistical mechanics problem which we study using a path integral approach. We argue that the $k$th frame potential comes within $\epsilon$ of the Haar value after a time of order $t \sim k N + k \log k + \log \epsilon^{-1}$. Using a bound on the diamond norm, this implies that such circuits are capable of coming very close to a unitary $k$-design after a time of order $t \sim k N$. We also consider the same question for systems with a time-independent Hamiltonian and argue that a small amount of time-dependent randomness is sufficient to generate a $k$-design in linear time provided the underlying Hamiltonian is quantum chaotic. These models provide explicit examples of linear complexity growth that are also analytically tractable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal quantum control via genetic algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14681</link>
    <author>Jonathon Brown, Mauro Paternostro, Alessandro Ferraro</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We devise a machine learning-enabled approach to quantum state engineering based on evolutionary algorithms. In particular, we focus on superconducting platforms and consider a network of qubits -- encoded in the states of artificial atoms with no direct coupling -- interacting via a common single-mode driven microwave resonator. The qubit-resonator couplings are assumed to be in the resonant regime and tunable in time. A genetic algorithm is designed in order to find the functional time-dependence of the couplings that optimise the fidelity between the evolved state and a variety of targets, including three-qubit GHZ and Dicke states and four-qubit graph states. We observe high quantum fidelities (above 0.96 in the worst case setting of a system of effective dimension 96) and resilience to noise, despite the algorithm being trained in the ideal noise-free setting. These results show that the genetic algorithms represent an effective approach to control quantum systems of large dimensions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multivariate trace estimation in constant quantum depth</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.15405</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Mark M. Wilde, Eneet Kaur</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>There is a folkloric belief that a depth-$\Theta(m)$ quantum circuit is needed to estimate the trace of the product of $m$ density matrices (i.e., a multivariate trace). We prove that this belief is overly conservative by constructing a constant quantum-depth circuit for the task, inspired by the method of Shor error correction. Furthermore, our circuit demands only local gates in a two dimensional circuit -- we show how to implement it in a highly parallelized way on an architecture similar to that of Google's Sycamore processor. With these features, our algorithm brings the task of multivariate trace estimation, crucial to applications in condensed matter and estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states, closer to the capabilities of near-term quantum processors. We instantiate the latter application with a theorem on estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states with ``well-behaved" polynomial approximations.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>