<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient decoding up to a constant fraction of the code length for asymptotically good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07571</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce and analyse an efficient decoder for the quantum Tanner codes of that can correct adversarial errors of linear weight. Previous decoders for quantum low-density parity-check codes could only handle adversarial errors of weight $O(\sqrt{n \log n})$. We also work on the link between quantum Tanner codes and the Lifted Product codes of Panteleev and Kalachev, and show that our decoder can be adapted to the latter. The decoding algorithm alternates between sequential and parallel procedures and converges in linear time.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Concentration of quantum equilibration and an estimate of the recurrence time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07541</link>
    <author>Jonathon Riddell, Nathan Pagliaroli, Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the dynamics of generic quantum systems concentrate around their equilibrium value when measuring at arbitrary times. This means that the probability of finding them away from equilibrium is exponentially suppressed, with a decay rate given by the effective dimension. Our result allows us to place a lower bound on the recurrence time of quantum systems, since recurrences corresponds to the rare events of finding a state away from equilibrium. In many-body systems, this bound is doubly exponential in system size. We also show corresponding results for free fermions, which display a weaker concentration and earlier recurrences.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bayesian Learning of Parameterised Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07559</link>
    <author>Samuel Duffield, Marcello Benedetti, Matthias Rosenkranz</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Currently available quantum computers suffer from constraints including hardware noise and a limited number of qubits. As such, variational quantum algorithms that utilise a classical optimiser in order to train a parameterised quantum circuit have drawn significant attention for near-term practical applications of quantum technology. In this work, we take a probabilistic point of view and reformulate the classical optimisation as an approximation of a Bayesian posterior. The posterior is induced by combining the cost function to be minimised with a prior distribution over the parameters of the quantum circuit. We describe a dimension reduction strategy based on a maximum a posteriori point estimate with a Laplace prior. Experiments on the Quantinuum H1-2 computer show that the resulting circuits are faster to execute and less noisy than the circuits trained without the dimension reduction strategy. We subsequently describe a posterior sampling strategy based on stochastic gradient Langevin dynamics. Numerical simulations on three different problems show that the strategy is capable of generating samples from the full posterior and avoiding local optima.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A note on the inner products of pure states and their antidistinguishability</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.08313</link>
    <author>Vincent Russo, Jamie Sikora</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A set of d quantum states is said to be antidistinguishable if there exists a d-outcome POVM that can perfectly identify which state was not measured. A conjecture by Havlíček and Barrett states that if a set of d pure states has small pair-wise inner products, then the set must be antidistinguishable. In this note we provide a certificate of antidistinguishability via semidefinite programming duality and use it to provide a counterexample to this conjecture when d = 4.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence in delegated quantum computing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07469</link>
    <author>Fabian Wiesner, Jens Eisert, Anna Pappa</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Delegated quantum computing (DQC) enables limited clients to perform operations that are outside their capabilities remotely on a quantum server. Protocols for DQC are usually built in the measurement-based quantum computation framework, as this allows for a natural separation of the different parts of the computation between the client and the server. The existing protocols achieve several desired properties, including security of inputs, blindness of computation and verifiability, and have also recently been extended to the multiparty setting. Two approaches are followed in DQC that demand completely different operations on the clients' side. In one, the clients are able to prepare quantum states; in the other, the clients are able to measure them. In this work, we provide a novel definition of protocol equivalence and show that these distinct DQC settings are in fact equivalent. We use the abstract cryptography framework to prove our claims and provide a novel technique that enables changing from one setting to the other. In this way, we demonstrate that both approaches can be used to perform a task with the same properties, i.e. using our proposed techniques, we can always translate from one setting to the other. We finally use our results to propose a hybrid-client model for DQC.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>