<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Constant-cost implementations of Clifford operations and multiply controlled gates using global interactions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08691</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Dmitri Maslov, Yunseong Nam</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A frequent physical-level requirement for the ability to implement quantum operations simultaneously is their commutativity. In this work, we asked if quantum computation by commuting Ising-type entangling operations and ``free'' single-qubit gates can be advantageous compared to quantum computation by the two-qubit gates and ``free'' single-qubit gates. We focused on the elements of the Clifford group and the multiply controlled gates. It turned out that such circuits and composite gates can be implemented with very little effort -- using constantly or effectively constantly many blocks of commuting sets of gates, in all cases except some with the most severe restrictions on the number of ancillary qubits available. Specifically, we show constant-cost implementations of Clifford operations with and without ancilla, constant-cost implementation of the multiply controlled gates with linearly many ancillae, and an $O(\log^*(n))$ implementation of the $n$-controlled single-target gates using logarithmically many ancillae. This shows significant (asymptotic) improvement of circuits enabled by the global gates vs those over single- and two-qubit gates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Sublinear-Time Quantum Algorithm for Approximating Partition Functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08643</link>
    <author>Arjan Cornelissen, Yassine Hamoudi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a novel quantum algorithm for estimating Gibbs partition functions in sublinear time with respect to the logarithm of the size of the state space. This is the first speed-up of this type to be obtained over the seminal nearly-linear time algorithm of Štefankovič, Vempala and Vigoda [JACM, 2009]. Our result also preserves the quadratic speed-up in precision and spectral gap achieved in previous work by exploiting the properties of quantum Markov chains. As an application, we obtain new polynomial improvements over the best-known algorithms for computing the partition function of the Ising model, and counting the number of $k$-colorings, matchings or independent sets of a graph. Our approach relies on developing new variants of the quantum phase and amplitude estimation algorithms that return nearly unbiased estimates with low variance and without destroying their initial quantum state. We extend these subroutines into a nearly unbiased quantum mean estimator that reduces the variance quadratically faster than the classical empirical mean. No such estimator was known to exist prior to our work. These properties, which are of general interest, lead to better convergence guarantees within the paradigm of simulated annealing for computing partition functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum tomography using state-preparation unitaries</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08800</link>
    <author>Joran van Apeldoorn, Arjan Cornelissen, András Gilyén, Giacomo Nannicini</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe algorithms to obtain an approximate classical description of a $d$-dimensional quantum state when given access to a unitary (and its inverse) that prepares it. For pure states we characterize the query complexity for $\ell_q$-norm error up to logarithmic factors. As a special case, we show that it takes $\widetilde{\Theta}(d/\varepsilon)$ applications of the unitaries to obtain an $\varepsilon$-$\ell_2$-approximation of the state. For mixed states we consider a similar model, where the unitary prepares a purification of the state. In this model we give an efficient algorithm for obtaining Schatten $q$-norm estimates of a rank-$r$ mixed state, giving query upper bounds that are close to optimal. In particular, we show that a trace-norm ($q=1$) estimate can be obtained with $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(dr/\varepsilon)$ queries. This improves (assuming our stronger input model) the $\varepsilon$-dependence over the algorithm of Haah et al.\ (2017) that uses a joint measurement on $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(dr/\varepsilon^2)$ copies of the state. To our knowledge, the most sample-efficient results for pure-state tomography come from setting the rank to $1$ in generic mixed-state tomography algorithms, which can be computationally demanding. We describe sample-optimal algorithms for pure states that are easy and fast to implement. Along the way we show that an $\ell_\infty$-norm estimate of a normalized vector induces a (slightly worse) $\ell_q$-norm estimate for that vector, without losing a dimension-dependent factor in the precision. We also develop an unbiased and symmetric version of phase estimation, where the probability distribution of the estimate is centered around the true value. Finally, we give an efficient method for estimating multiple expectation values, improving over the recent result by Huggins et al.\ (2021) when the measurement operators do not fully overlap.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Amplitude Estimation from Quantum Signal Processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08628</link>
    <author>Patrick Rall, Bryce Fuller</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Amplitude estimation algorithms are based on Grover's algorithm: alternating reflections about the input state and the desired outcome. But what if we are given the ability to perform arbitrary rotations, instead of just reflections? In this situation, we find that quantum signal processing lets us estimate the amplitude in a more flexible way. We leverage this technique to give improved and simplified algorithms for many amplitude estimation tasks: we perform non-destructive estimation without any assumptions on the amplitude, develop an algorithm with improved performance in practice, present a new method for unbiased amplitude estimation, and finally give a simpler method for trading quantum circuit depth for more repetitions of short circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking verified logic operations for fault tolerance</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08786</link>
    <author>Akel Hashim, Stefan Seritan, Timothy Proctor, Kenneth Rudinger, Noah Goss, Ravi K. Naik, John Mark Kreikebaum, David I. Santiago, Irfan Siddiqi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The promise of quantum computing depends upon the eventual achievement of fault-tolerant quantum error correction, which requires that the total rate of errors falls below some threshold. However, most contemporary methods for benchmarking noisy quantum processors measure average error rates (infidelities), which can differ from worst-case error rates -- defined via the diamond norm -- by orders of magnitude. One method for resolving this discrepancy is to randomize the physical implementation of quantum gates, using techniques like randomized compiling (RC). In this work, we use gate set tomography to perform precision characterization of a set of two-qubit logic gates to study RC on a superconducting quantum processor. We find that, under RC, gate errors are accurately described by a stochastic Pauli noise model without coherent errors, and that spatially-correlated coherent errors and non-Markovian errors are strongly suppressed. We further show that the average and worst-case error rates are equal for randomly compiled gates, and measure a maximum worst-case error of 0.0197(3) for our gate set. Our results show that randomized benchmarks are a viable route to both verifying that a quantum processor's error rates are below a fault-tolerance threshold, and to bounding the failure rates of near-term algorithms, if -- and only if -- gates are implemented via randomization methods which tailor noise.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>