<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Modular Commutators in Conformal Field Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00027</link>
    <author>Yijian Zou, Bowen Shi, Ian T. Lim, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The modular commutator is a recently discovered multipartite entanglement measure that quantifies the chirality of the underlying many-body quantum state. In this Letter, we derive a universal expression for the modular commutator in conformal field theories in $1+1$ dimensions and discuss its salient features. We show that the modular commutator depends only on the chiral central charge and the conformal cross ratio. We test this formula for a gapped $2+1$-dimensional system with a chiral edge, i.e., the quantum Hall state, and observe excellent agreement with numerical simulations. Furthermore, we propose the geometric dual of the modular commutator in the AdS/CFT correspondence. We argue that the modular commutator can be obtained from a set of crossing angles between intersecting Ryu-Takayanagi surfaces.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive Online Learning of Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00220</link>
    <author>Xinyi Chen, Elad Hazan, Tongyang Li, Zhou Lu, Xinzhao Wang, Rui Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the fundamental problem of shadow tomography, the goal is to efficiently learn an unknown $d$-dimensional quantum state using projective measurements. However, it is rarely the case that the underlying state remains stationary: changes may occur due to measurements, environmental noise, or an underlying Hamiltonian state evolution. In this paper we adopt tools from adaptive online learning to learn a changing state, giving adaptive and dynamic regret bounds for online shadow tomography that are polynomial in the number of qubits and sublinear in the number of measurements. Our analysis utilizes tools from complex matrix analysis to cope with complex numbers, which may be of independent interest in online learning. In addition, we provide numerical experiments that corroborate our theoretical results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental single-setting quantum state tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00019</link>
    <author>Roman Stricker, Michael Meth, Lukas Postler, Claire Edmunds, Chris Ferrie, Rainer Blatt, Philipp Schindler, Thomas Monz, Richard Kueng, Martin Ringbauer</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers solve ever more complex tasks using steadily growing system sizes. Characterizing these quantum systems is vital, yet becoming increasingly challenging. The gold-standard is quantum state tomography (QST), capable of fully reconstructing a quantum state without prior knowledge. Measurement and classical computing costs, however, increase exponentially in the system size - a bottleneck given the scale of existing and near-term quantum devices. Here, we demonstrate a scalable and practical QST approach that uses a single measurement setting, namely symmetric informationally complete (SIC) positive operator-valued measures (POVM). We implement these nonorthogonal measurements on an ion trap device by utilizing more energy levels in each ion - without ancilla qubits. More precisely, we locally map the SIC POVM to orthogonal states embedded in a higher-dimensional system, which we read out using repeated in-sequence detections, providing full tomographic information in every shot. Combining this SIC tomography with the recently developed randomized measurement toolbox ("classical shadows") proves to be a powerful combination. SIC tomography alleviates the need for choosing measurement settings at random ("derandomization"), while classical shadows enable the estimation of arbitrary polynomial functions of the density matrix orders of magnitudes faster than standard methods. The latter enables in-depth entanglement studies, which we experimentally showcase on a 5-qubit absolutely maximally entangled (AME) state. Moreover, the fact that the full tomography information is available in every shot enables online QST in real time. We demonstrate this on an 8-qubit entangled state, as well as for fast state identification. All in all, these features single out SIC-based classical shadow estimation as a highly scalable and convenient tool for quantum state characterization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Quantum and Classical Streaming Complexity of Quantum and Classical Max-Cut</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00213</link>
    <author>John Kallaugher, Ojas Parekh</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the space complexity of two graph streaming problems: Max-Cut and its quantum analogue, Quantum Max-Cut. Previous work by Kapralov and Krachun [STOC `19] resolved the classical complexity of the \emphclassical problem, showing that any $(2 - \varepsilon)$-approximation requires $\Omega(n)$ space (a $2$-approximation is trivial with $\textrm{O}(\log n)$ space). We generalize both of these qualifiers, demonstrating $\Omega(n)$ space lower bounds for $(2 - \varepsilon)$-approximating Max-Cut and Quantum Max-Cut, even if the algorithm is allowed to maintain a quantum state. As the trivial approximation algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut only gives a $4$-approximation, we show tightness with an algorithm that returns a $(2 + \varepsilon)$-approximation to the Quantum Max-Cut value of a graph in $\textrm{O}(\log n)$ space. Our work resolves the quantum and classical approximability of quantum and classical Max-Cut using $\textrm{o}(n)$ space. We prove our lower bounds through the techniques of Boolean Fourier analysis. We give the first application of these methods to sequential one-way quantum communication, in which each player receives a quantum message from the previous player, and can then perform arbitrary quantum operations on it before sending it to the next. To this end, we show how Fourier-analytic techniques may be used to understand the application of a quantum channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Defining Quantum Games</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00089</link>
    <author>Laura Piispanen, Marcel Pfaffhauser, Annakaisa Kultima, James R. Wootton</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this article, we explore the concept of quantum games and define quantum games as any type of playable games that are related to or reference quantum physics through any of three proposed aspects. The rise of the quantum computers has made it possible to think about a new wave of computer games, namely quantum computer games, games on quantum computers. But at the same time, there are also various games that are exploring quantum mechanics and related topics through digital, analogue and hybrid means. In this article we go through the emerging body of quantum games, the history of quantum games and the different ways a game may be considered a quantum game. For this we propose three dimensions for analysing and defining the phenomenon of quantum games: the perceivable dimension of quantum games, the dimension of quantum technologies and the dimension of scientific purposes.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>