<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Circuit Extraction for ZX-diagrams can be #P-hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09194</link>
    <author>Niel de Beaudrap, Aleks Kissinger, John van de Wetering</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ZX-calculus is a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computation using ZX-diagrams, a certain flexible generalisation of quantum circuits that can be used to represent linear maps from $m$ to $n$ qubits for any $m,n \geq 0$. Some applications for the ZX-calculus, such as quantum circuit optimisation and synthesis, rely on being able to efficiently translate a ZX-diagram back into a quantum circuit of comparable size. While several sufficient conditions are known for describing families of ZX-diagrams that can be efficiently transformed back into circuits, it has previously been conjectured that the general problem of circuit extraction is hard. That is, that it should not be possible to efficiently convert an arbitrary ZX-diagram describing a unitary linear map into an equivalent quantum circuit. In this paper we prove this conjecture by showing that the circuit extraction problem is #P-hard, and so is itself at least as hard as strong simulation of quantum circuits. In addition to our main hardness result, which relies specifically on the circuit representation, we give a representation-agnostic hardness result. Namely, we show that any oracle that takes as input a ZX-diagram description of a unitary and produces samples of the output of the associated quantum computation enables efficient probabilistic solutions to NP-complete problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical simulation of quantum circuits with partial and graphical stabiliser decompositions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09202</link>
    <author>Aleks Kissinger, John van de Wetering, Renaud Vilmart</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent developments in classical simulation of quantum circuits make use of clever decompositions of chunks of magic states into sums of efficiently simulable stabiliser states. We show here how, by considering certain non-stabiliser entangled states which have more favourable decompositions, we can speed up these simulations. This is made possible by using the ZX-calculus, which allows us to easily find instances of these entangled states in the simplified diagram representing the quantum circuit to be simulated. We additionally find a new technique of partial stabiliser decompositions that allow us to trade magic states for stabiliser terms. With this technique we require only $2^{\alpha t}$ stabiliser terms, where $\alpha\approx 0.396$, to simulate a circuit with T-count $t$. This matches the $\alpha$ found by Qassim et al., but whereas they only get this scaling in the asymptotic limit, ours applies for a circuit of any size. Our method builds upon a recently proposed scheme for simulation combining stabiliser decompositions and optimisation strategies implemented in the software QuiZX. With our techniques we manage to reliably simulate 50-qubit 1400 T-count hidden shift circuits in a couple of minutes on a consumer laptop.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal control of a six-qubit quantum processor in silicon</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09252</link>
    <author>Stephan G.J. Philips, Mateusz T. Mądzik, Sergey V. Amitonov, Sander L. de Snoo, Maximilian Russ, Nima Kalhor, Christian Volk, William I.L. Lawrie, Delphine Brousse, Larysa Tryputen, Brian Paquelet Wuetz, Amir Sammak, Menno Veldhorst, Giordano Scappucci, Lieven M.K. Vandersypen</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Future quantum computers capable of solving relevant problems will require a large number of qubits that can be operated reliably. However, the requirements of having a large qubit count and operating with high-fidelity are typically conflicting. Spins in semiconductor quantum dots show long-term promise but demonstrations so far use between one and four qubits and typically optimize the fidelity of either single- or two-qubit operations, or initialization and readout. Here we increase the number of qubits and simultaneously achieve respectable fidelities for universal operation, state preparation and measurement. We design, fabricate and operate a six-qubit processor with a focus on careful Hamiltonian engineering, on a high level of abstraction to program the quantum circuits and on efficient background calibration, all of which are essential to achieve high fidelities on this extended system. State preparation combines initialization by measurement and real-time feedback with quantum-non-demolition measurements. These advances will allow for testing of increasingly meaningful quantum protocols and constitute a major stepping stone towards large-scale quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Qutrit metaplectic gates are a subset of Clifford+T</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09235</link>
    <author>Andrew Glaudell, Neil J. Ross, John van de Wetering, Lia Yeh</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A popular universal gate set for quantum computing with qubits is Clifford+T, as this can be readily implemented on many fault-tolerant architectures. For qutrits, there is an equivalent T gate, that, like its qubit analogue, makes Clifford+T approximately universal, is injectable by a magic state, and supports magic state distillation. However, it was claimed that a better gate set for qutrits might be Clifford+R, where R=diag(1,1,-1) is the metaplectic gate, as certain protocols and gates could more easily be implemented using the R gate than the T gate. In this paper we show that when we have at least two qutrits, the qutrit Clifford+R unitaries form a strict subset of the Clifford+T unitaries, by finding a direct decomposition of $R \otimes \mathbb{I}$ as a Clifford+T circuit and proving that the T gate cannot be exactly synthesized in Clifford+R. This shows that in fact the T gate is at least as powerful as the R gate, up to a constant factor. Moreover, we additionally show that it is impossible to find a single-qutrit Clifford+T decomposition of the R gate, making our result tight.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simultaneous Stoquasticity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08863</link>
    <author>Jacob Bringewatt, Lucas T. Brady</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Stoquastic Hamiltonians play a role in the computational complexity of the local Hamiltonian problem as well as the study of classical simulability. In particular, stoquastic Hamiltonians can be straightforwardly simulated using Monte Carlo techniques. We address the question of whether two or more Hamiltonians may be made simultaneously stoquastic via a unitary transformation. This question has important implications for the complexity of simulating quantum annealing where quantum advantage is related to the stoquasticity of the Hamiltonians involved in the anneal. We find that for almost all problems no such unitary exists and show that the problem of determining the existence of such a unitary is equivalent to identifying if there is a solution to a system of polynomial (in)equalities in the matrix elements of the initial and transformed Hamiltonians. Solving such a system of equations is NP-hard. We highlight a geometric understanding of this problem in terms of a collection of generalized Bloch vectors.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>