<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking Quantum Simulators using Quantum Chaos</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12211</link>
    <author>Daniel K. Mark, Joonhee Choi, Adam L. Shaw, Manuel Endres, Soonwon Choi</author>
    <pubDate>May 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose and analyze a sample-efficient protocol to estimate the fidelity between an experimentally prepared state and an ideal target state, applicable to a wide class of analog quantum simulators without advanced sophisticated spatiotemporal control. Our approach utilizes newly discovered universal fluctuations emerging from generic Hamiltonian dynamics, and it does not require any fine-tuned control over state preparation, quantum evolution, or readout capability. It only needs a small number of experimental measurements, achieving near optimal sample complexity: in ideal cases, a percent-level precision is obtained with $\sim 10^3$ measurements independent of system size. Furthermore, the accuracy of our fidelity estimation improves with increasing system size. We numerically demonstrate our protocol for a variety of quantum simulator platforms such as itinerant particles on optical lattices, trapped ions, and Rydberg atoms. We discuss further applications of our method for advanced tasks such as multi-parameter estimation of quantum states and processes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Privacy and correctness trade-offs for information-theoretically secure quantum homomorphic encryption</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12127</link>
    <author>Yanglin Hu, Yingkai Ouyang, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>May 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum homomorphic encryption, which allows computation by a server directly on encrypted data, is a fundamental primitive out of which more complex quantum cryptography protocols can be built. For such constructions to be possible, quantum homomorphic encryption must satisfy two privacy properties: data privacy which ensures that the input data is private from the server, and circuit privacy which ensures that the ciphertext after the computation does not reveal any additional information about the circuit used to perform it, beyond the output of the computation itself. While circuit privacy is well-studied in classical cryptography and many homomorphic encryption schemes can be equipped with it, its quantum analogue has received little attention. Here we establish a definition of circuit privacy for quantum homomorphic encryption with information-theoretic security. Furthermore, we reduce quantum oblivious transfer to quantum homomorphic encryption. Using this reduction, our work unravels fundamental trade-offs between circuit privacy, data privacy and correctness for a broad family of quantum homomorphic encryption protocols, including schemes that allow only computation of Clifford circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Real-time correlators in chaotic quantum many-body systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.11544</link>
    <author>Adam Nahum, Sthitadhi Roy, Sagar Vijay, Tianci Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>May 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study real-time local correlators $\langle\mathcal{O}(\mathbf{x},t)\mathcal{O}(0,0)\rangle$ in chaotic quantum many-body systems. These correlators show universal structure at late times, determined by the dominant operator-space Feynman trajectories for the evolving operator $\mathcal{O}(\mathbf{x},t)$. The relevant trajectories involve the operator contracting to a point at both the initial and final time and so are structurally different from those dominating the out-of-time-order correlator. In the absence of conservation laws, correlations decay exponentially: $\langle\mathcal{O}(\mathbf{x},t)\mathcal{O}(0,0)\rangle\sim\exp(-s_\mathrm{eq} r(\mathbf{v}) t)$, where $\mathbf{v}= \mathbf{x}/ t$ defines a spacetime ray, and $r(\mathbf{v})$ is an associated decay rate. We express $r(\mathbf{v})$ in terms of cost functions for various spacetime structures. In 1+1D, operator histories can show a phase transition at a critical ray velocity $v_c$, where $r(\mathbf{v})$ is nonanalytic. At low $v$, the dominant Feynman histories are "fat": the operator grows to a size of order $t^\alpha\gg 1$ before contracting to a point again. At high $v$ the trajectories are "thin": the operator always remains of order-one size. In a Haar-random unitary circuit, this transition maps to a simple binding transition for a pair of random walks (the two spatial boundaries of the operator). In higher dimensions, thin trajectories always dominate. We discuss ways to extract the butterfly velocity $v_B$ from the time-ordered correlator, rather than the OTOC. Correlators in the random circuit may alternatively be computed with an effective Ising-like model: a special feature of the Ising weights for the Haar brickwork circuit gives $v_c=v_B$. This work addresses lattice models, but also suggests the possibility of morphological phase transitions for real-time Feynman diagrams in quantum field theories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A multi-player, multi-team nonlocal game for the toric code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12251</link>
    <author>Vir B. Bulchandani, Fiona J. Burnell, S. L. Sondhi</author>
    <pubDate>May 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Nonlocal games yield an unusual perspective on entangled quantum states. The defining property of such games is that a set of players in joint possession of an entangled state can win the game with higher probability than is allowed by classical physics. Here we construct a nonlocal game that can be won with certainty by $2N$ players if they have access to the ground state of the toric code on as many qubits. By contrast, the game cannot be won by classical players more than half the time in the large $N$ limit. Our game differs from previous examples because it arranges the players on a lattice and allows them to carry out quantum operations in teams, whose composition is dynamically specified. This is natural when seeking to characterize the degree of quantumness of non-trivial many-body states, which potentially include states in much more varied phases of matter than the toric code. We present generalizations of the toric code game to states with $\mathbb{Z}_M$ topological order.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A possibilistic no-go theorem on the Wigner's friend paradox</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12223</link>
    <author>Marwan Haddara, Eric G. Cavalcanti</author>
    <pubDate>May 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a recent work, Bong et al. [Nat. Phys. 16, 1199 (2020)] proved a no-go theorem demonstrating a contradiction between a set of assumptions called "Local Friendliness" (LF) and certain quantum phenomena on an extended version of the Wigner's friend scenario. The LF assumptions can be understood as the conjunction of two independent assumptions: Absoluteness of Observed Events (AOE) and Local Agency (LA). The proof of the LF theorem, however, implicitly assumes the validity of standard probability theory for dealing with sets of events that AOE implies to have simultaneously well-defined values. Here we present a probability-free version of the Local Friendliness theorem. The argument is phrased in the language of possibilities, which we make formal by using a modal logical approach. It relies on a slightly weaker version of Local Agency, which we call "Possibilistic Local Agency".</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>