<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum many-body systems in thermal equilibrium</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08349</link>
    <author>Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The thermal or equilibrium ensemble is one of the most ubiquitous states of matter. For models comprised of many locally interacting quantum particles, it describes a wide range of physical situations, relevant to condensed matter physics, high energy physics, quantum chemistry and quantum computing, among others. We give a pedagogical overview of some of the most important universal features about the physics and complexity of these states, which have the locality of the Hamiltonian at its core. We focus on mathematically rigorous statements, many of them inspired by ideas and tools from quantum information theory. These include bounds on their correlations, the form of the subsystems, various statistical properties, and the performance of classical and quantum algorithms. We also include a summary of a few of the most important technical tools, as well as some self-contained proofs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Beyond i.i.d. in the Resource Theory of Asymmetry: An Information-Spectrum Approach for Quantum Fisher Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08439</link>
    <author>Koji Yamaguchi, Hiroyasu Tajima</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Energetic coherence is a valuable resource for various operations, including precise measurement of time and acceleration of quantum manipulations. Recently, it has been shown that the theory of energetic coherence, called the resource theory of asymmetry, has a thermodynamic structure, as do entanglement theory and quantum thermodynamics. In the so-called i.i.d. regime, where identical copies of a state are converted into identical copies of another state, the convertibility is entirely determined by the amount of energetic coherence measured by the quantum Fisher information (QFI). This fact means that QFI takes the place of entropy in thermodynamics and entanglement entropy in entanglement theory. So far, such a correspondence between energetic coherence and entropy is known only in the i.i.d. regime. In entanglement theory and quantum thermodynamics in the non-i.i.d. regime, entropy-related quantities based on the information-spectrum method reveal a non-equilibrium thermodynamics structure. Still, it has been an open question whether a similar structure exists for energetic coherence. In this Letter, we solve this problem by constructing an information-spectrum method applicable to the quantum Fisher information content. As a result, we establish a general theory of the pure-state convertibility in the non-i.i.d. regime of the resource theory of asymmetry. The given theory reveals a non-equilibrium thermodynamic structure of energetic coherence in the non-i.i.d. regime, based on QFI rather than entropy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Boson Sampling for Generalized Bosons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08389</link>
    <author>En-Jui Kuo, Yijia Xu, Dominik Hangleiter, Andrey Grankin, Mohammad Hafezi</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce the notion of "generalized bosons" whose exchange statistics resemble those of bosons, but the local bosonic commutator $[a_i,a_i^\dagger]=1$ is replaced by an arbitrary single-mode operator that is diagonal in the generalized Fock basis. Examples of generalized bosons include boson pairs and spins. We consider the analogue of the boson sampling task for these particles and observe that its output probabilities are still given by permanents, so that the results regarding hardness of sampling directly carry over. Finally, we propose implementations of generalized boson sampling in circuit-QED and ion-trap platforms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Incompatibility of observables, channels and instruments in information theories</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07956</link>
    <author>Giacomo M. D'Ariano, Paolo Perinotti, Alessandro Tosini</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Every theory of information, including classical and quantum, can be studied in the framework of operational probabilistic theories -- where the notion of test generalizes that of quantum instrument, namely a collection of quantum operations summing to a channel, and simple rules are given for the composition of tests in parallel and in sequence. Here we study the notion of compatibility for tests of an operational probabilistic theory. Following the quantum literature, we first introduce the notion of strong compatibility, and then we illustrate its ultimate relaxation, that we deem weak compatibility. It is shown that the two notions coincide in the case of observation tests -- which are the counterpart of quantum POVMs -- while there exist weakly compatible channels that are not strongly compatible. We prove necessary and sufficient conditions for a theory to exhibit incompatible tests. We show that a theory admits of incompatible tests if and only if some information cannot be extracted without disturbance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Low Degree Testing over the Reals</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08404</link>
    <author>Vipul Arora, Arnab Bhattacharyya, Noah Fleming, Esty Kelman, Yuichi Yoshida</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of testing whether a function $f: \mathbb{R}^n \to \mathbb{R}$ is a polynomial of degree at most $d$ in the \emphdistribution-free testing model. Here, the distance between functions is measured with respect to an unknown distribution $\mathcal{D}$ over $\mathbb{R}^n$ from which we can draw samples. In contrast to previous work, we do not assume that $\mathcal{D}$ has finite support. We design a tester that given query access to $f$, and sample access to $\mathcal{D}$, makes $(d/\varepsilon)^{O(1)}$ many queries to $f$, accepts with probability $1$ if $f$ is a polynomial of degree $d$, and rejects with probability at least $2/3$ if every degree-$d$ polynomial $P$ disagrees with $f$ on a set of mass at least $\varepsilon$ with respect to $\mathcal{D}$. Our result also holds under mild assumptions when we receive only a polynomial number of bits of precision for each query to $f$, or when $f$ can only be queried on rational points representable using a logarithmic number of bits. Along the way, we prove a new stability theorem for multivariate polynomials that may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>