<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Cycle Index Polynomials and Generalized Quantum Separability Tests</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14596</link>
    <author>Zachary P. Bradshaw, Margarite L. LaBorde, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We address an outstanding question on the acceptance probability for the bipartite pure-state separability algorithm proposed by [LaBorde and Wilde, arXiv:2105.12758]. We prove that the analytical form of this expression is given by the cycle index polynomial of the symmetric group $S_k$, which is itself related to the Bell polynomials. After doing so, we derive a family of quantum separability tests, each of which is generated by a finite group; for all such algorithms, we show that the acceptance probability is determined by the cycle index polynomial of the group. Finally, we produce and analyze explicit circuit constructions for these tests, showing that the tests corresponding to the symmetric and cyclic groups can be executed with $O(k^2)$ and $O(k\log(k))$ controlled-SWAP gates, respectively, where $k$ is the number of copies of the state being tested.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Quantum Online Portfolio Optimization Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14749</link>
    <author>Debbie Lim, Patrick Rebentrost</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Portfolio optimization plays a central role in finance to obtain optimal portfolio allocations that aim to achieve certain investment goals. Over the years, many works have investigated different variants of portfolio optimization. Portfolio optimization also provides a rich area to study the application of quantum computers to obtain advantages over classical computers. In this work, we give a sampling version of an existing classical online portfolio optimization algorithm by Helmbold et al., for which we in turn develop a quantum version. The quantum advantage is achieved by using techniques such as quantum state preparation and inner product estimation. Our quantum algorithm provides a quadratic speedup in the time complexity, in terms of $n$, where $n$ is the number of assets in the portfolio. The transaction cost of both of our classical and quantum algorithms is independent of $n$ which is especially useful for practical applications with a large number of assets.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Some continuity properties of quantum Rényi divergences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00646</link>
    <author>Milán Mosonyi</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the problem of binary quantum channel discrimination with product inputs, the supremum of all type II error exponents for which the optimal type I errors go to zero is equal to the Umegaki channel relative entropy, while the infimum of all type II error exponents for which the optimal type I errors go to one is equal to the infimum of the sandwiched channel Rényi $\alpha$-divergences over all $\alpha>1$. Here we prove that these two threshold values coincide, thus proving, in particular, the strong converse property for this problem. Our proof method uses a minimax argument, which crucially relies on a newly established continuity property of the sandwiched Rényi $\alpha$-divergences for $\alpha\in(1,2]$. Motivated by this, we also prove various other continuity properties for quantum (channel) Rény divergences, which may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cross Entropy Benchmark for Measurement-Induced Phase Transitions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00609</link>
    <author>Yaodong Li, Yijian Zou, Paolo Glorioso, Ehud Altman, Matthew P. A. Fisher</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the prospects of employing the linear cross-entropy to experimentally access measurement-induced phase transitions (MIPT) without requiring any postselection of quantum trajectories. For two random circuits that are identical in the bulk but with different initial states, the linear cross-entropy $\chi$ between the bulk measurement outcome distributions in the two circuits acts as a boundary order parameter, and can be used to distinguish the volume law from area law phases. In the volume law phase (and in the thermodynamic limit) the bulk measurements cannot distinguish between the two different initial states, and $\chi = 1$. In the area law phase $\chi < 1$. For circuits with Clifford gates, we provide numerical evidence that $\chi$ can be sampled to accuracy $\epsilon$ from $O(1/\epsilon^2)$ trajectories, by running the first circuit on a quantum simulator without postselection, aided by a classical simulation of the second. We also find that for weak depolarizing noise the signature of the MIPT is still present for intermediate system sizes. In our protocol we have the freedom of choosing initial states such that the "classical" side can be simulated efficiently, while simulating the "quantum" side is still classically hard.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement of trapped-ion qubits separated by 230 meters</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14907</link>
    <author>V. Krutyanskiy, M. Galli, V. Krcmarsky, S. Baier, D. A. Fioretto, Y. Pu, A. Mazloom, P. Sekatski, M. Canteri, M. Teller, J. Schupp, J. Bate, M. Meraner, N. Sangouard, B. P. Lanyon, T. E. Northup</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We report on an elementary quantum network of two atomic ions separated by 230 m. The ions are trapped in different buildings and connected with 520(2) m of optical fiber. At each network node, the electronic state of an ion is entangled with the polarization state of a single cavity photon; subsequent to interference of the photons at a beamsplitter, photon detection heralds entanglement between the two ions. Fidelities of up to $(88.2+2.3-6.0)\%$ are achieved with respect to a maximally entangled Bell state, with a success probability of $4 \times 10^{-5}$. We analyze the routes to improve these metrics, paving the way for long-distance networks of entangled quantum processors.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>