<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Extendibility of Werner States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13743</link>
    <author>Dávid Jakab, Adrián Solymos, Zoltán Zimborás</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the two-sided symmetric extendibility problem of Werner states. The interplay of the unitary symmetry of these states and the inherent bipartite permutation symmetry of the extendibility scenario allows us to map this problem into the ground state problem of a highly symmetric spin-model Hamiltonian. We solve this ground state problem analytically by utilizing the representation theory of SU(d), in particular a result related to the dominance order of Young diagrams in Littlewood-Richarson decompositions. As a result, we obtain necessary and sufficient conditions for the extendibility of Werner states for arbitrary extension size and local dimension. Interestingly, the range of extendible states has a non-trivial trade-off between the extension sizes on the two sides. We compare our result with the two-sided extendibility problem of isotropic states, where there is no such trade-off.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Synergy Between Quantum Circuits and Tensor Networks: Short-cutting the Race to Practical Quantum Advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13673</link>
    <author>Manuel S. Rudolph, Jacob Miller, Jing Chen, Atithi Acharya, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While recent breakthroughs have proven the ability of noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices to achieve quantum advantage in classically-intractable sampling tasks, the use of these devices for solving more practically relevant computational problems remains a challenge. Proposals for attaining practical quantum advantage typically involve parametrized quantum circuits (PQCs), whose parameters can be optimized to find solutions to diverse problems throughout quantum simulation and machine learning. However, training PQCs for real-world problems remains a significant practical challenge, largely due to the phenomenon of barren plateaus in the optimization landscapes of randomly-initialized quantum circuits. In this work, we introduce a scalable procedure for harnessing classical computing resources to determine task-specific initializations of PQCs, which we show significantly improves the trainability and performance of PQCs on a variety of problems. Given a specific optimization task, this method first utilizes tensor network (TN) simulations to identify a promising quantum state, which is then converted into gate parameters of a PQC by means of a high-performance decomposition procedure. We show that this task-specific initialization avoids barren plateaus, and effectively translates increases in classical resources to enhanced performance and speed in training quantum circuits. By demonstrating a means of boosting limited quantum resources using classical computers, our approach illustrates the promise of this synergy between quantum and quantum-inspired models in quantum computing, and opens up new avenues to harness the power of modern quantum hardware for realizing practical quantum advantage.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multidimensional Quantum Walks, with Application to $k$-Distinctness</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13492</link>
    <author>Stacey Jeffery, Sebastian Zur</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While the quantum query complexity of $k$-distinctness is known to be $O\left(n^{3/4-1/4(2^k-1)}\right)$ for any constant $k \geq 4$, the best previous upper bound on the time complexity was $\widetilde{O}\left(n^{1-1/k}\right)$. We give a new upper bound of $\widetilde{O}\left(n^{3/4-1/4(2^k-1)}\right)$ on the time complexity, matching the query complexity up to polylogarithmic factors. In order to achieve this upper bound, we give a new technique for designing quantum walk search algorithms, which is an extension of the electric network framework. We also show how to solve the welded trees problem in $O(n)$ queries and $O(n^2)$ time using this new technique, showing that the new quantum walk framework can achieve exponential speedups.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Locality of gapped ground states in systems with power-law decaying interactions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13057</link>
    <author>Zhiyuan Wang, Kaden R. A. Hazzard</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It has been proved that in gapped ground states of locally-interacting quantum systems, the effect of local perturbations decays exponentially with distance. However, in systems with power-law ($1/r^\alpha$) decaying interactions, no analogous statement has been shown, and there are serious mathematical obstacles to proving it with existing methods. In this paper we prove that when $\alpha$ exceeds the spatial dimension $D$, the effect of local perturbations on local properties a distance $r$ away is upper bounded by a power law $1/r^{\alpha_1}$ in gapped ground states, provided that the perturbations do not close the spectral gap. The power-law exponent $\alpha_1$ is tight if $\alpha>2D$ and interactions are two-body, where we have $\alpha_1=\alpha$. The proof is enabled by a method that avoids the use of quasiadiabatic continuation and incorporates techniques of complex analysis. This method also improves bounds on ground state correlation decay, even in short-range interacting systems. Our work generalizes the fundamental notion that local perturbations have local effects to power-law interacting systems, with broad implications for numerical simulations and experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Naimark dilations of qubit POVMs and joint measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13588</link>
    <author>Juha-Pekka Pellonpää, Sébastien Designolle, Roope Uola</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Measurement incompatibility is one of the cornerstones of quantum theory. This phenomenon appears in many forms, of which the concept of non-joint measurability has received considerable attention in the recent years. In order to characterise this non-classical phenomenon, various analytical and numerical methods have been developed. The analytical approaches have mostly concentrated on the qubit case, as well as to scenarios involving sets of measurements with symmetries, such as position and momentum or sets of mutually unbiased bases. The numerical methods can, in principle, decide any finite-dimensional and discrete joint measurability problem, but they naturally have practical limitations in terms of computational power. These methods exclusively start from a given set of measurements and ask whether the set possesses incompatibility. Here, we take a complementary approach by asking which measurements are compatible with a given measurement. It turns out, that this question can be answered in full generality through a minimal Naimark dilation of the given measurement: the set of interest is exactly those measurements that have a block-diagonal representation in such dilation. We demonstrate the use of the technique through various qubit examples, leading to an alternative characterisation of all compatible pairs of binary qubit measurements, which retrieves the celebrated Busch criterion. We further apply the technique to special examples of trinary and continuous qubit measurements.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>