<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Deterministic constant-depth preparation of the AKLT state on a quantum processor using fusion measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.17548</link>
    <author>Kevin C. Smith, Eleanor Crane, Nathan Wiebe, S. M. Girvin</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ground state of the spin-1 Affleck, Kennedy, Lieb and Tasaki (AKLT) model is a paradigmatic example of both a matrix product state and a symmetry-protected topological phase, and additionally holds promise as a resource state for measurement-based quantum computation. Having a nonzero correlation length, the AKLT state cannot be exactly prepared by a constant-depth unitary circuit composed of local gates. In this work, we demonstrate that this no-go limit can be evaded by augmenting a constant-depth circuit with fusion measurements, such that the total preparation time is independent of system size and entirely deterministic. We elucidate our preparation scheme using the language of tensor networks, and furthermore show that the $\mathbb{Z}_2\times\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry of the AKLT state directly affords this speed-up over previously known preparation methods. To demonstrate the practical advantage of measurement-assisted preparation on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices, we carry out our protocol on an IBM Quantum processor. We measure both the string order and entanglement spectrum of prepared AKLT chains and, employing these as metrics, find improved results over the known (purely unitary) sequential preparation approach. We conclude with a demonstration of quantum teleportation using the AKLT state prepared by our measurement-assisted scheme. This work thus serves to provide an efficient strategy to prepare a specific resource in the form of the AKLT state and, more broadly, experimentally demonstrates the possibility for realizable improvement in state preparation afforded by measurement-based circuit depth reduction strategies on NISQ-era devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Complete Hierarchy of Linear Systems for Certifying Quantum Entanglement of Subspaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16389</link>
    <author>Nathaniel Johnston, Benjamin Lovitz, Aravindan Vijayaraghavan</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a hierarchy of linear systems for showing that a given subspace of pure quantum states is entangled (i.e., contains no product states). This hierarchy outperforms known methods already at the first level, and it is complete in the sense that every entangled subspace is shown to be so at some finite level of the hierarchy. It generalizes straightforwardly to the case of higher Schmidt rank, as well as the multipartite cases of completely and genuinely entangled subspaces. These hierarchies work extremely well in practice even in very large quantum systems, as they can be implemented via elementary linear algebra techniques rather than the semidefinite programming techniques that are required by previously-known hierarchies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Unclonability and Quantum Cryptanalysis: From Foundations to Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.17545</link>
    <author>Mina Doosti</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The impossibility of creating perfect identical copies of unknown quantum systems is a fundamental concept in quantum theory and one of the main non-classical properties of quantum information. This limitation imposed by quantum mechanics, famously known as the no-cloning theorem, has played a central role in quantum cryptography as a key component in the security of quantum protocols. In this thesis, we look at Unclonability in a broader context in physics and computer science and more specifically through the lens of cryptography, learnability and hardware assumptions. We introduce new notions of unclonability in the quantum world, namely quantum physical unclonability, and study the relationship with cryptographic properties and assumptions such as unforgeability, and quantum pseudorandomness. The purpose of this study is to bring new insights into the field of quantum cryptanalysis and into the notion of unclonability itself. We also discuss several applications of this new type of unclonability as a cryptographic resource for designing provably secure quantum protocols. Furthermore, we present a new practical cryptanalysis technique concerning the problem of approximate cloning of quantum states. We design a quantum machine learning-based cryptanalysis algorithm to demonstrate the power of quantum learning tools as both attack strategies and powerful tools for the practical study of quantum unclonability.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Correction in the Lowest Landau Level</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16957</link>
    <author>Yale Fan, Willy Fischler, Eric Kubischta</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop finite-dimensional versions of the quantum error-correcting codes proposed by Albert, Covey, and Preskill (ACP) for continuous-variable quantum computation on configuration spaces with nonabelian symmetry groups. Our codes can be realized by a charged particle in a Landau level on a spherical geometry -- in contrast to the planar Landau level realization of the qudit codes of Gottesman, Kitaev, and Preskill (GKP) -- or more generally by spin coherent states. Our quantum error-correction scheme is inherently approximate, and the encoded states may be easier to prepare than those of GKP or ACP.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Detecting emergent continuous symmetries at quantum criticality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.17539</link>
    <author>Mingru Yang, Bram Vanhecke, Norbert Schuch</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>New or enlarged symmetries can emerge at the low-energy spectrum of a Hamiltonian that does not possess the symmetries, if the symmetry breaking terms in the Hamiltonian are irrelevant under the renormalization group flow. In this letter, we propose a tensor network based algorithm to numerically find lattice operator approximations of the emergent conserved charges in the ground state of any quantum spin chains, without the necessity to have prior knowledge about its low-energy effective field theory. The results obtained with our method shed new light on the emergent conserved charges in the spin-1/2 $J$-$Q$ Heisenberg model and a one-dimensional version of deconfined quantum critical points (DQCP). It can also be viewed as a way to obtain the local integrals of motion of an integrable model and local parent Hamiltonians of gapless ground states.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>