<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Encoding qubits in multimode grid states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12337</link>
    <author>Baptiste Royer, Shraddha Sing, Steven M. Girvin</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Encoding logical quantum information in harmonic oscillator modes is a promising and hardware- efficient approach to the realization of a quantum computer. In this work, we propose to encode logical qubits in grid states of an ensemble of harmonic oscillator modes. We first discuss general results about these multimode bosonic codes; how to design them, how to practically implement them in different experimental platforms and how lattice symmetries can be leveraged to perform logical non-Clifford operations. We then introduce in detail two two-mode grid codes based on the hypercubic and D4 lattices, respectively, showing how to perform a universal set of logical operations. We demonstrate numerically that multimode grid codes have, compared to their single- mode counterpart, increased robustness against propagation of errors from ancillas used for error correction. Finally, we highlight some interesting links between multidimensional lattices and single- mode grid codes concatenated with qubit codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multi-round QAOA and advanced mixers on a trapped-ion quantum computer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12335</link>
    <author>Yingyue Zhu, Zewen Zhang, Bhuvanesh Sundar, Alaina M. Green, C. Huerta Alderete, Nhung H. Nguyen, Kaden R. A. Hazzard, Norbert M. Linke</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Combinatorial optimization problems on graphs have broad applications in science and engineering. The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) is a method to solve these problems on a quantum computer by applying multiple rounds of variational circuits. However, there exist several challenges limiting the real-world applications of QAOA. In this paper, we demonstrate on a trapped-ion quantum computer that QAOA results improve with the number of rounds for multiple problems on several arbitrary graphs. We also demonstrate an advanced mixing Hamiltonian that allows sampling of all optimal solutions with predetermined weights. Our results are a step towards applying quantum algorithms to real-world problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive Accelerated (Extra-)Gradient Methods with Variance Reduction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12302</link>
    <author>Zijian Liu, Ta Duy Nguyen, Alina Ene, Huy L. Nguyen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we study the finite-sum convex optimization problem focusing on the general convex case. Recently, the study of variance reduced (VR) methods and their accelerated variants has made exciting progress. However, the step size used in the existing VR algorithms typically depends on the smoothness parameter, which is often unknown and requires tuning in practice. To address this problem, we propose two novel adaptive VR algorithms: Adaptive Variance Reduced Accelerated Extra-Gradient (AdaVRAE) and Adaptive Variance Reduced Accelerated Gradient (AdaVRAG). Our algorithms do not require knowledge of the smoothness parameter. AdaVRAE uses $\mathcal{O}\left(n\log\log n+\sqrt{\frac{n\beta}{\epsilon}}\right)$ gradient evaluations and AdaVRAG uses $\mathcal{O}\left(n\log\log n+\sqrt{\frac{n\beta\log\beta}{\epsilon}}\right)$ gradient evaluations to attain an $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon)$-suboptimal solution, where $n$ is the number of functions in the finite sum and $\beta$ is the smoothness parameter. This result matches the best-known convergence rate of non-adaptive VR methods and it improves upon the convergence of the state of the art adaptive VR method, AdaSVRG. We demonstrate the superior performance of our algorithms compared with previous methods in experiments on real-world datasets.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Solving MaxCut with Quantum Imaginary Time Evolution</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12221</link>
    <author>Rizwanul Alam, George Siopsis, Rebekah Herrman, James Ostrowski, Phillip Lotshaw, Travis Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a method to solve the MaxCut problem efficiently based on quantum imaginary time evolution (QITE). We employ a linear Ansatz for unitary updates and an initial state that involve no entanglement. We apply the method to graphs with number of vertices |V| = 4,6,8,10, and show that after ten QITE steps, the average solution is 100%, 99%, 98%, 97%, respectively, of the maximum MaxCut solution. By employing an imaginary-time-dependent Hamiltonian interpolating between a given graph and a subgraph with two edges excised, we show that the modified algorithm has a 100% performance converging to the maximum solution of the MaxCut problem for all graphs up to eight vertices as well as about 100 random samples of ten-vertex graphs. This improved method has an overhead which is polynomial in the number of vertices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Differential Privacy Guarantees for Stochastic Gradient Langevin Dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11980</link>
    <author>Théo Ryffel, Francis Bach, David Pointcheval</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyse the privacy leakage of noisy stochastic gradient descent by modeling Rényi divergence dynamics with Langevin diffusions. Inspired by recent work on non-stochastic algorithms, we derive similar desirable properties in the stochastic setting. In particular, we prove that the privacy loss converges exponentially fast for smooth and strongly convex objectives under constant step size, which is a significant improvement over previous DP-SGD analyses. We also extend our analysis to arbitrary sequences of varying step sizes and derive new utility bounds. Last, we propose an implementation and our experiments show the practical utility of our approach compared to classical DP-SGD libraries.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>