<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Testing and Learning Quantum Juntas Nearly Optimally</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05898</link>
    <author>Thomas Chen, Shivam Nadimpalli, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of testing and learning quantum $k$-juntas: $n$-qubit unitary matrices which act non-trivially on just $k$ of the $n$ qubits and as the identity on the rest. As our main algorithmic results, we give (a) a $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{k})$-query quantum algorithm that can distinguish quantum $k$-juntas from unitary matrices that are "far" from every quantum $k$-junta; and (b) a $O(4^k)$-query algorithm to learn quantum $k$-juntas. We complement our upper bounds for testing quantum $k$-juntas and learning quantum $k$-juntas with near-matching lower bounds of $\Omega(\sqrt{k})$ and $\Omega(\frac{4^k}{k})$, respectively. Our techniques are Fourier-analytic and make use of a notion of influence of qubits on unitaries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Suppressing quantum errors by scaling a surface code logical qubit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.06431</link>
    <author>Rajeev Acharya, Igor Aleiner, Richard Allen, Trond I. Andersen, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Joao Basso, Andreas Bengtsson, Sergio Boixo, Gina Bortoli, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, Leon Brill, Michael Broughton, et al (138)</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Practical quantum computing will require error rates that are well below what is achievable with physical qubits. Quantum error correction offers a path to algorithmically-relevant error rates by encoding logical qubits within many physical qubits, where increasing the number of physical qubits enhances protection against physical errors. However, introducing more qubits also increases the number of error sources, so the density of errors must be sufficiently low in order for logical performance to improve with increasing code size. Here, we report the measurement of logical qubit performance scaling across multiple code sizes, and demonstrate that our system of superconducting qubits has sufficient performance to overcome the additional errors from increasing qubit number. We find our distance-5 surface code logical qubit modestly outperforms an ensemble of distance-3 logical qubits on average, both in terms of logical error probability over 25 cycles and logical error per cycle ($2.914\%\pm 0.016\%$ compared to $3.028\%\pm 0.023\%$). To investigate damaging, low-probability error sources, we run a distance-25 repetition code and observe a $1.7\times10^{-6}$ logical error per round floor set by a single high-energy event ($1.6\times10^{-7}$ when excluding this event). We are able to accurately model our experiment, and from this model we can extract error budgets that highlight the biggest challenges for future systems. These results mark the first experimental demonstration where quantum error correction begins to improve performance with increasing qubit number, illuminating the path to reaching the logical error rates required for computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A rapidly mixing Markov chain from any gapped quantum many-body system</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07044</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Giuseppe Carleo, David Gosset, Yinchen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the computational task of sampling a bit string $x$ from a distribution $\pi(x)=|\langle x|\psi\rangle|^2$, where $\psi$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian $H$. Our main result describes a direct link between the inverse spectral gap of $H$ and the mixing time of an associated continuous-time Markov Chain with steady state $\pi$. The Markov Chain can be implemented efficiently whenever ratios of ground state amplitudes $\langle y|\psi\rangle/\langle x|\psi\rangle$ are efficiently computable and the starting state of the chain satisfies a mild technical condition that can be efficiently checked. This extends a previously known relationship between sign-problem free Hamiltonians and Markov chains. The tool which enables this generalization is the so-called fixed-node Hamiltonian construction, previously used in Quantum Monte Carlo simulations to address the fermionic sign problem. We implement the proposed sampling algorithm numerically and use it to sample from the ground state of Haldane-Shastry Hamiltonian with up to 56 qubits. We observe empirically that our Markov chain based on the fixed-node Hamiltonian mixes more rapidly than the standard Metropolis-Hastings Markov chain.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Conservation laws and quantum error correction: towards a generalised matching decoder</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.06428</link>
    <author>Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A decoding algorithm is essential to any fault-tolerant quantum-computing architecture. In this perspective we explore decoding algorithms for the surface code; a prototypical quantum low-density parity-check code that underlies many of the leading efforts to demonstrate scalable quantum computing. Central to our discussion is the minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder. The decoder works by exploiting underlying structure that arises due to materialised symmetries among surface-code stabilizer elements. By concentrating on these symmetries, we begin to address the question of how a minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder might be generalised for other types of code. We approach this question first by investigating examples of matching decoders for other codes. These include decoding algorithms that have been specialised to correct for noise models that demonstrate a particular structure or bias with respect to certain types of code. In addition to this, we propose a systematic way of constructing a minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder for codes with certain characteristic properties. The properties we make use of are common among topological codes. We discuss the broader applicability of the proposal, and we suggest some questions we can address that may show us how to design a generalised matching decoder for arbitrary stabilizer codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reinforcement Learning Assisted Recursive QAOA</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.06294</link>
    <author>Yash J. Patel, Sofiene Jerbi, Thomas Bäck, Vedran Dunjko</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms such as the Quantum Approximation Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) in recent years have gained popularity as they provide the hope of using NISQ devices to tackle hard combinatorial optimization problems. It is, however, known that at low depth, certain locality constraints of QAOA limit its performance. To go beyond these limitations, a non-local variant of QAOA, namely recursive QAOA (RQAOA), was proposed to improve the quality of approximate solutions. The RQAOA has been studied comparatively less than QAOA, and it is less understood, for instance, for what family of instances it may fail to provide high quality solutions. However, as we are tackling $\mathsf{NP}$-hard problems (specifically, the Ising spin model), it is expected that RQAOA does fail, raising the question of designing even better quantum algorithms for combinatorial optimization. In this spirit, we identify and analyze cases where RQAOA fails and, based on this, propose a reinforcement learning enhanced RQAOA variant (RL-RQAOA) that improves upon RQAOA. We show that the performance of RL-RQAOA improves over RQAOA: RL-RQAOA is strictly better on these identified instances where RQAOA underperforms, and is similarly performing on instances where RQAOA is near-optimal. Our work exemplifies the potentially beneficial synergy between reinforcement learning and quantum (inspired) optimization in the design of new, even better heuristics for hard problems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>