<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Partitioning qubits in hypergraph product codes to implement logical gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10812</link>
    <author>Armanda O. Quintavalle, Paul Webster, Michael Vasmer</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The promise of high-rate low-density parity check (LDPC) codes to substantially reduce the overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation depends on constructing efficient, fault-tolerant implementations of logical gates on such codes. Transversal gates are the simplest type of fault-tolerant gate, but the potential of transversal gates on LDPC codes has hitherto been largely neglected. We investigate the transversal gates that can be implemented in hypergraph product codes, a class of LDPC codes. Our analysis is aided by the construction of a symplectic canonical basis for the logical operators of hypergraph product codes, a result that may be of independent interest. We show that in these codes transversal gates can implement Hadamard (up to logical SWAP gates) and control-Z on all logical qubits. Moreover, we show that sequences of transversal operations, interleaved with error correction, allow implementation of entangling gates between arbitrary pairs of logical qubits in the same code block. We thereby demonstrate that transversal gates can be used as the basis for universal quantum computing on LDPC codes, when supplemented with state injection.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A general framework for the composition of quantum homomorphic encryption \& quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10471</link>
    <author>Yingkai Ouyang, Peter P. Rohde</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two essential primitives for universal, cloud-based quantum computation with security based on the laws of quantum mechanics, are quantum homomorphic encryption with information-theoretic security and quantum error correction. The former enables information-theoretic security of outsourced quantum computation, while the latter allows reliable and scalable quantum computations in the presence of errors. Previously these ingredients have been considered in isolation from one another. By establishing group-theoretic requirements that these two ingredients must satisfy, we provide a general framework for composing them. Namely, a quantum homomorphic encryption scheme enhanced with quantum error correction can directly inherit its properties from its constituent quantum homomorphic encryption and quantum error correction schemes. We apply our framework to both discrete- and continuous-variable models for quantum computation, such as Pauli-key and permutation-key encryptions in the qubit model, and displacement-key encryptions in a continuous-variable model based on Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Log-Sobolev inequality and proof of Hypothesis of the Gaussian Maximizers for the capacity of quantum noisy homodyning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10626</link>
    <author>A. S. Holevo</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the present paper we give proof that the information-transmission capacity of the approximate position measurement with the oscillator energy constraint, which underlies noisy Gaussian homodyning in quantum optics, is attained on Gaussian encoding. The proof is based on general principles of convex programming. Rather remarkably, for this particular model the method reduces the solution of the optimization problem to a generalization of the celebrated log-Sobolev inequality. We hope that this method should work also for other models lying out of the scope of the "threshold condition" ensuring that the upper bound for the capacity as a difference between the maximum and the minimum output entropies is attainable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Maximal entanglement velocity implies dual unitarity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10341</link>
    <author>Tianci Zhou, Aram W. Harrow</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A global quantum quench can be modeled by a quantum circuit with local unitary gates. In general, entanglement grows linearly at a rate given by entanglement velocity, which is upper bounded by the growth of the light cone. We show that the unitary interactions achieving the maximal rate must remain unitary if we exchange the space and time directions -- a property known as dual unitarity. Our results are robust: approximate maximal entanglement velocity also implies approximate dual unitarity. We further show that maximal entanglement velocity is always accompanied by a specific dynamical pattern of entanglement, which yields simpler analyses of several known exactly solvable models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Parameterized Sensitivity Oracles and Dynamic Algorithms using Exterior Algebras</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10819</link>
    <author>Josh Alman, Dean Hirsch</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We design the first efficient sensitivity oracles and dynamic algorithms for a variety of parameterized problems. Our main approach is to modify the algebraic coding technique from static parameterized algorithm design, which had not previously been used in a dynamic context. We particularly build off of the `extensor coding' method of Brand, Dell and Husfeldt [STOC'18], employing properties of the exterior algebra over different fields. For the $k$-Path detection problem for directed graphs, it is known that no efficient dynamic algorithm exists (under popular assumptions from fine-grained complexity). We circumvent this by designing an efficient sensitivity oracle, which preprocesses a directed graph on $n$ vertices in $2^k poly(k) n^{\omega+o(1)}$ time, such that, given $\ell$ updates (mixing edge insertions and deletions, and vertex deletions) to that input graph, it can decide in time $\ell^2 2^kpoly(k)$ and with high probability, whether the updated graph contains a path of length $k$. We also give a deterministic sensitivity oracle requiring $4^k poly(k) n^{\omega+o(1)}$ preprocessing time and $\ell^2 2^{\omega k + o(k)}$ query time, and obtain a randomized sensitivity oracle for the task of approximately counting the number of $k$-paths. For $k$-Path detection in undirected graphs, we obtain a randomized sensitivity oracle with $O(1.66^k n^3)$ preprocessing time and $O(\ell^3 1.66^k)$ query time, and a better bound for undirected bipartite graphs. In addition, we present the first fully dynamic algorithms for a variety of problems: $k$-Partial Cover, $m$-Set $k$-Packing, $t$-Dominating Set, $d$-Dimensional $k$-Matching, and Exact $k$-Partial Cover. For example, for $k$-Partial Cover we show a randomized dynamic algorithm with $2^k poly(k)polylog(n)$ update time, and a deterministic dynamic algorithm with $4^kpoly(k)polylog(n)$ update time.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>