<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Counting unitaries of T-depth one</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04163</link>
    <author>Vadym Kliuchnikov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits is $ \sum_{m=1}^{n}\tfrac{1}{m!}\prod_{k=0}^{m-1}(4^n/2^k - 2^k) \times \# \mathcal{C}_n, $ where $\#\mathcal{C}_n$ is the size of the $n$-qubit Clifford group, that is the number of unitaries of T-depth zero. The number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits grows as $2^{\Omega(n^2)} \cdot \# \mathcal{C}_n$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement estimation in tensor network states via sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04089</link>
    <author>Noa Feldman, Augustine Kshetrimayum, Jens Eisert, Moshe Goldstein</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a method for extracting meaningful entanglement measures of tensor network states in general dimensions. Current methods require the explicit reconstruction of the density matrix, which is highly demanding, or the contraction of replicas, which requires an effort exponential in the number of replicas and which is costly in terms of memory. In contrast, our method requires the stochastic sampling of matrix elements of the classically represented reduced states with respect to random states drawn from simple product probability measures constituting frames. Even though not corresponding to physical operations, such matrix elements are straightforward to calculate for tensor network states, and their moments provide the Rényi entropies and negativities as well as their symmetry-resolved components. We test our method on the one-dimensional critical XX chain and the two-dimensional toric code. Although the cost is exponential in the subsystem size, it is sufficiently moderate so that - in contrast with other approaches - accurate results can be obtained on a personal computer for relatively large subsystem sizes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>$N$-body interactions between trapped ion qubits via spin-dependent squeezing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04230</link>
    <author>Or Katz, Marko Cetina, Christopher Monroe</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a simple protocol for the single-step generation of $N$-body entangling interactions between trapped atomic ion qubits. We show that qubit state-dependent squeezing operations and displacement forces on the collective atomic motion can generate full $N$-body interactions. Similar to the Mølmer-Sørensen two-body Ising interaction at the core of most trapped ion quantum computers and simulators, the proposed operation is relatively insensitive to the state of motion. We show how this $N$-body gate operation allows the single-step implementation of a family of $N$-bit gate operations such as the powerful $N$-Toffoli gate, which flips a single qubit if and only if all other $N$-$1$ qubits are in a particular state.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Threshold detection statistics of bosonic states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04600</link>
    <author>Jacob F. F. Bulmer, Stefano Paesani, Rachel S. Chadwick, Nicolás Quesada</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In quantum photonics, threshold detectors, distinguishing between vacuum and one or more photons, such as superconducting nanowires and avalanche photodiodes, are routinely used to measure Fock and Gaussian states of light. Despite being the standard measurement scheme, there is no general closed form expression for measurement probabilities with threshold detectors, unless accepting coarse approximations or combinatorially scaling summations. Here, we present new matrix functions to fill this gap. We develop the Bristolian and the loop Torontonian functions for threshold detection of Fock and displaced Gaussian states, respectively, and connect them to each other and to existing matrix functions. By providing a unified picture of bosonic statistics for most quantum states of light, we provide novel tools for the design and analysis of photonic quantum technologies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Shortest Paths without a Map, but with an Entropic Regularizer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04551</link>
    <author>Sébastien Bubeck, Christian Coester, Yuval Rabani</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a 1989 paper titled "shortest paths without a map", Papadimitriou and Yannakakis introduced an online model of searching in a weighted layered graph for a target node, while attempting to minimize the total length of the path traversed by the searcher. This problem, later called layered graph traversal, is parametrized by the maximum cardinality $k$ of a layer of the input graph. It is an online setting for dynamic programming, and it is known to be a rather general and fundamental model of online computing, which includes as special cases other acclaimed models. The deterministic competitive ratio for this problem was soon discovered to be exponential in $k$, and it is now nearly resolved: it lies between $\Omega(2^k)$ and $O(k2^k)$. Regarding the randomized competitive ratio, in 1993 Ramesh proved, surprisingly, that this ratio has to be at least $\Omega(k^2 / \log^{1+\epsilon} k)$ (for any constant $\epsilon > 0$). In the same paper, Ramesh also gave an $O(k^{13})$-competitive randomized online algorithm. Since 1993, no progress has been reported on the randomized competitive ratio of layered graph traversal. In this work we show how to apply the mirror descent framework on a carefully selected evolving metric space, and obtain an $O(k^2)$-competitive randomized online algorithm, nearly matching the known lower bound on the randomized competitive ratio.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>