<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure qubits: Overcoming the $T_1$ limit in superconducting circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05461</link>
    <author>Aleksander Kubica, Arbel Haim, Yotam Vaknin, Fernando Brandão, Alex Retzker</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The amplitude damping time, $T_1$, has long stood as the major factor limiting quantum fidelity in superconducting circuits, prompting concerted efforts in the material science and design of qubits aimed at increasing $T_1$. In contrast, the dephasing time, $T_{\phi}$, can usually be extended above $T_1$ (via, e.g., dynamical decoupling), to the point where it does not limit fidelity. In this article we propose a scheme for overcoming the conventional $T_1$ limit on fidelity by designing qubits in a way that amplitude damping errors can be detected and converted into erasure errors. Compared to standard qubit implementations our scheme improves the performance of fault-tolerant protocols, as numerically demonstrated by the circuit-noise simulations of the surface code. We describe two simple qubit implementations with superconducting circuits and discuss procedures for detecting amplitude damping errors, performing entangling gates, and extending $T_\phi$. Our results suggest that engineering efforts should focus on improving $T_\phi$ and the quality of quantum coherent control, as they effectively become the limiting factor on the performance of fault-tolerant protocols.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New Quantum Codes from CSS Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05353</link>
    <author>Markus Grassl</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a new propagation rule for CSS codes. Starting with a CSS code $[\![n,k,d]\!]_q$, we construct a CSS code with parameters $[\![n-2,k,d-1]\!]_q$. In general, one would only obtain a code with parameters $[\![n-2,k,d-2]\!]_q$. The construction applies to asymmetric quantum codes from the CSS construction as well.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Glasses -- a review</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05417</link>
    <author>L. F. Cugliandolo, M. Mueller</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We review the research on quantum glasses, with a focus on their equilibrium dynamics and the interplay between glassiness and localization phenomena. Interesting relations with the SYK model are discussed.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-Classical Hybrid Systems and their Quasifree Transformations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05020</link>
    <author>Lars Dammeier, Reinhard F. Werner</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study continuous variable systems, in which quantum and classical degrees of freedom are combined and treated on the same footing. Thus all systems, including the inputs or outputs to a channel, may be quantum-classical hybrids. This allows a unified treatment of a large variety of quantum operations involving measurements or dependence on classical parameters. The basic variables are given by canonical operators with scalar commutators. Some variables may commute with all others and hence generate a classical subsystem. We systematically study the class of "quasifree" operations, which are characterized equivalently either by an intertwining condition for phase-space translations or by the requirement that, in the Heisenberg picture, Weyl operators are mapped to multiples of Weyl operators. This includes the well-known Gaussian operations, evolutions with quadratic Hamiltonians, and "linear Bosonic channels", but allows for much more general kinds of noise. For example, all states are quasifree. We sketch the analysis of quasifree preparation, measurement, repeated observation, cloning, teleportation, dense coding, the setup for the classical limit, and some aspects of irreversible dynamics, together with the precise salient tradeoffs of uncertainty, error, and disturbance. Although the spaces of observables and states are infinite dimensional for every non-trivial system that we consider, we treat the technicalities related to this in a uniform and conclusive way, providing a calculus that is both easy to use and fully rigorous.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Computing theta function</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05405</link>
    <author>Alexander Barvinok</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Let $f: {\Bbb R}^n \longrightarrow {\Bbb R}$ be a positive definite quadratic form and let $y \in {\Bbb R}^n$ be a point. We present a fully polynomial randomized approximation scheme (FPRAS) for computing $\sum_{x \in {\Bbb Z}^n} e^{-f(x)}$, provided the eigenvalues of $f$ lie in the interval roughly between $s$ and $e^{s}$ and for computing $\sum_{x \in {\Bbb Z}^n} e^{-f(x-y)}$, provided the eigenvalues of $f$ lie in the interval roughly between $e^{-s}$ and $s^{-1}$ for some $s \geq 3$. To compute the first sum, we represent it as the integral of an explicit log-concave function on ${\Bbb R}^n$, and to compute the second sum, we use the reciprocity relation for theta functions. Choosing $s \sim \log n$, we apply the results to test the existence of sufficiently many short integer vectors in a given subspace $L \subset {\Bbb R}^n$ or in the vicinity of $L$.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>