<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The randomized measurement toolbox</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11374</link>
    <author>Andreas Elben, Steven T. Flammia, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, John Preskill, Benoît Vermersch, Peter Zoller</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Increasingly sophisticated programmable quantum simulators and quantum computers are opening unprecedented opportunities for exploring and exploiting the properties of highly entangled complex quantum systems. The complexity of large quantum systems is the source of their power, but also makes them difficult to control precisely or characterize accurately using measured classical data. We review recently developed protocols for probing the properties of complex many-qubit systems using measurement schemes that are practical using today's quantum platforms. In all these protocols, a quantum state is repeatedly prepared and measured in a randomly chosen basis; then a classical computer processes the measurement outcomes to estimate the desired property. The randomization of the measurement procedure has distinct advantages; for example, a single data set can be employed multiple times to pursue a variety of applications, and imperfections in the measurements are mapped to a simplified noise model that can more easily be mitigated. We discuss a range of use cases that have already been realized in quantum devices, including Hamiltonian simulation tasks, probes of quantum chaos, measurements of nonlocal order parameters, and comparison of quantum states produced in distantly separated laboratories. By providing a workable method for translating a complex quantum state into a succinct classical representation that preserves a rich variety of relevant physical properties, the randomized measurement toolbox strengthens our ability to grasp and control the quantum world.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Linear-depth quantum circuits for multi-qubit controlled gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11882</link>
    <author>Adenilton J. da Silva, Daniel K. Park</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum circuit depth minimization is critical for practical applications of circuit-based quantum computation. In this work, we present a systematic procedure to decompose multi-qubit-controlled unitary gate, which is essential in many quantum algorithms, to controlled-NOT and single-qubit gates with which quantum circuit depth only increases linearly with the number of control qubits. Our algorithm does not require any ancillary qubits and achieves a quadratic reduction of the circuit depth against known methods. We demonstrate the advantage of our algorithm with proof-of-principle experiments implemented on the IBM quantum cloud platform.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Deploying an inter-European quantum network</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11359</link>
    <author>Domenico Ribezzo, Mujtaba Zahidy, Ilaria Vagniluca, Nicola Biagi, Saverio Francesconi, Tommaso Occhipinti, Leif K. Oxenløwe, Martin Lončarić, Ivan Cvitić, Mario Stipčević, Žiga Pušavec, Rainer Kaltenbaek, Anton Ramšak, Francesco Cesa, Giorgio Giorgetti, Francesco Scazza, Angelo Bassi, Paolo De Natale, Francesco Saverio Cataliotti, Massimo Inguscio, et al (2)</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Around forty years have passed since the first pioneering works have introduced the possibility of using quantum physics to strongly enhance communications safety. Nowadays Quantum Cryptography, and in particular, Quantum Key Distribution (QKD) exited the physics laboratories to become commercial technologies that increasingly trigger the attention of States, military forces, banks, and private corporations. This work takes on the challenge of bringing QKD closer to a consumer technology: optical fibers deployed and used by telecommunication companies of different States have been used to realize a quantum network, the first-ever connecting three different countries. This pushes towards the necessary coexistence of QKD and classical communications on the same infrastructure, which currently represents a main limit of this technology. Our network connects Trieste to Rijeka and Ljubljana via a trusted node in Postojna; a key rate of over 3 kbps has been achieved in the shortest link, and a 7-hour long measurement has demonstrated the system stability and reliability. Finally, the network has been used for a public demonstration of QKD at the G20 Digital Ministers' Meeting in Trieste. The reported experimental results, together with the significant interest that one of the most important events of international politics has attracted, showcase the maturity of the QKD technology bundle, placing it in the spotlight for consumer applications in the near term.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Snowmass 2021 White Paper: Tabletop experiments for infrared quantum gravity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11846</link>
    <author>Daniel Carney, Yanbei Chen, Andrew Geraci, Holger Müller, Cristian D. Panda, Philip C. E. Stamp, Jacob M. Taylor</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Progress in the quantum readout and control of mechanical devices from single atoms to large masses may enable a first generation of experiments probing the gravitational interaction in the quantum regime, conceivably within the next decade. In this Snowmass whitepaper, we briefly outline the possibilities and challenges facing the realization of these experiments. In particular, we emphasize the need for detailed theories of modifications to the usual effective QFT of gravitons in the infrared regime $E/L^3 \ll m_{\rm Pl}/\ell_{\rm Pl}^3$ in which these experiments operate, and relations to possible UV completions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The power of qutrits for non-adaptive measurement-based quantum computing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.12411</link>
    <author>Jelena Mackeprang, Daniel Bhatti, Matty J. Hoban, Stefanie Barz</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Non-locality is not only one of the most prominent quantum features but can also serve as a resource for various information-theoretical tasks. Analysing it from an information-theoretical perspective has linked it to applications such as non-adaptive measurement-based quantum computing (NMQC). In this type of quantum computing the goal is to output a multivariate function. The success of such a computation can be related to the violation of a generalised Bell inequality. So far, the investigation of binary NMQC with qubits has shown that quantum correlations can compute all Boolean functions using at most $2^n-1$ qubits, whereas local hidden variables (LHVs) are restricted to linear functions. Here, we extend these results to NMQC with qutrits and prove that quantum correlations enable the computation of all ternary functions using the generalised qutrit Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) state as a resource and at most $3^n-1$ qutrits. This yields a corresponding generalised GHZ type paradox for any ternary function that LHVs cannot compute. We give an example for an $n$-variate function that can be computed with only $n+1$ qutrits, which leads to convenient generalised qutrit Bell inequalities whose quantum bound is maximal. Finally, we prove that not all functions can be computed efficiently with qutrit NMQC by presenting a counterexample.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>