<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Is quantum advantage the right goal for quantum machine learning?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01340</link>
    <author>Maria Schuld, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Machine learning is frequently listed among the most promising applications for quantum computing. This is in fact a curious choice: Today's machine learning algorithms are notoriously powerful in practice, but remain theoretically difficult to study. Quantum computing, in contrast, does not offer practical benchmarks on realistic scales, and theory is the main tool we have to judge whether it could become relevant for a problem. In this perspective we explain why it is so difficult to say something about the practical power of quantum computers for machine learning with the tools we are currently using. We argue that these challenges call for a critical debate on whether quantum advantage and the narrative of "beating" classical machine learning should continue to dominate the literature the way it does, and provide a few examples for alternative research questions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The quantum low-rank approximation problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00811</link>
    <author>Nic Ezzell, Zoë Holmes, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a quantum version of the famous low-rank approximation problem. Specifically, we consider the distance $D(\rho,\sigma)$ between two normalized quantum states, $\rho$ and $\sigma$, where the rank of $\sigma$ is constrained to be at most $R$. For both the trace distance and Hilbert-Schmidt distance, we analytically solve for the optimal state $\sigma$ that minimizes this distance. For the Hilbert-Schmidt distance, the unique optimal state is $\sigma = \tau_R +N_R$, where $\tau_R = \Pi_R \rho \Pi_R$ is given by projecting $\rho$ onto its $R$ principal components with projector $\Pi_R$, and $N_R$ is a normalization factor given by $N_R = \frac{1- \text{Tr}(\tau_R)}{R}\Pi_R$. For the trace distance, this state is also optimal but not uniquely optimal, and we provide the full set of states that are optimal. We briefly discuss how our results have application for performing principal component analysis (PCA) via variational optimization on quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum circuit compilation and hybrid computation using Pauli-based computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01789</link>
    <author>F.C.R. Peres, Ernesto F. Galvão</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Pauli-based computation (PBC) is driven by a sequence of adaptively chosen, non-destructive measurements of Pauli observables. Any quantum circuit written in terms of the Clifford+$T$ gate set and having $t$ $T$ gates can be compiled into a PBC on $t$ qubits. Here we propose practical ways of implementing PBC as adaptive quantum circuits, and provide code to do the required classical side-processing. Our first scheme reduces the number of quantum gates to $O(t^2)$ (from a previous $O(t^3 / \log t)$ scaling) at the cost of one extra auxiliary qubit, with a possible reduction of the depth to $O(t \log t$), at the cost of $t$ additional auxiliary qubits (second scheme). We compile examples of random and hidden-shift quantum circuits into adaptive PBC circuits. We also simulate hybrid quantum computation, where a classical computer effectively extends the working memory of a small quantum computer by $k$ virtual qubits, at a cost exponential in $k$. Our results demonstrate the practical advantage of PBC techniques for circuit compilation and hybrid computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Boson bunching is not maximized by indistinguishable particles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01306</link>
    <author>Benoît Seron, Leonardo Novo, Nicolas J. Cerf</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Boson bunching is amongst the most remarkable features of quantum physics. A celebrated example in optics is the Hong-Ou-Mandel effect, where the bunching of two photons arises from a destructive quantum interference between the trajectories where they both either cross a beam splitter or are reflected. This effect takes its roots in the indistinguishability of identical photons. Hence, it is generally admitted -- and experimentally verified -- that bunching vanishes as soon as photons can be distinguished, e.g., when they occupy distinct time bins or have different polarizations. Here we disproof this alleged straightforward link between indistinguishability and bunching by exploiting a recent finding in the theory of matrix permanents. We exhibit a family of optical circuits where the bunching of photons into two modes can be significantly boosted by making them partially distinguishable via an appropriate polarization pattern. This boosting effect is already visible in a 7-photon interferometric process, making the observation of this phenomenon within reach of current photonic technology. This unexpected behavior questions our understanding of multiparticle interference in the grey zone between indistinguishable bosons and classical particles.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Reinforcement Learning via Policy Iteration</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01889</link>
    <author>El Amine Cherrat, Iordanis Kerenidis, Anupam Prakash</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing has shown the potential to substantially speed up machine learning applications, in particular for supervised and unsupervised learning. Reinforcement learning, on the other hand, has become essential for solving many decision making problems and policy iteration methods remain the foundation of such approaches. In this paper, we provide a general framework for performing quantum reinforcement learning via policy iteration. We validate our framework by designing and analyzing: \emphquantum policy evaluation methods for infinite horizon discounted problems by building quantum states that approximately encode the value function of a policy $\pi$; and \emphquantum policy improvement methods by post-processing measurement outcomes on these quantum states. Last, we study the theoretical and experimental performance of our quantum algorithms on two environments from OpenAI's Gym.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>