<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>How to simulate key properties of lithium-ion batteries with a fault-tolerant quantum computer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11890</link>
    <author>Alain Delgado, Pablo A. M. Casares, Roberto dos Reis, Modjtaba Shokrian Zini, Roberto Campos, Norge Cruz-Hernández, Arne-Christian Voigt, Angus Lowe, Soran Jahangiri, M. A. Martin-Delgado, Jonathan E. Mueller, Juan Miguel Arrazola</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>There is a pressing need to develop new rechargeable battery technologies that can offer higher energy storage, faster charging, and lower costs. Despite the success of existing methods for the simulation of battery materials, they can sometimes fall short of delivering accurate and reliable results. Quantum computing has been discussed as an avenue to overcome these issues, but only limited work has been done to outline how they may impact battery simulations. In this work, we provide a detailed answer to the following question: how can a quantum computer be used to simulate key properties of a lithium-ion battery? Based on recently-introduced first-quantization techniques, we lay out an end-to-end quantum algorithm for calculating equilibrium cell voltages, ionic mobility, and thermal stability. These can be obtained from ground-state energies of materials, which is the core calculation executed by the quantum computer using qubitization-based quantum phase estimation. The algorithm includes explicit methods for preparing approximate ground states of periodic materials in first quantization. We bring these insights together to perform the first estimation of the resources required to implement a quantum algorithm for simulating a realistic cathode material, dilithium iron silicate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complexity of quantum circuits via sensitivity, magic, and coherence</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.12051</link>
    <author>Kaifeng Bu, Roy J. Garcia, Arthur Jaffe, Dax Enshan Koh, Lu Li</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum circuit complexity-a measure of the minimum number of gates needed to implement a given unitary transformation-is a fundamental concept in quantum computation, with widespread applications ranging from determining the running time of quantum algorithms to understanding the physics of black holes. In this work, we study the complexity of quantum circuits using the notions of sensitivity, average sensitivity (also called influence), magic, and coherence. We characterize the set of unitaries with vanishing sensitivity and show that it coincides with the family of matchgates. Since matchgates are tractable quantum circuits, we have proved that sensitivity is necessary for a quantum speedup. As magic is another measure to quantify quantum advantage, it is interesting to understand the relation between magic and sensitivity. We do this by introducing a quantum version of the Fourier entropy-influence relation. Our results are pivotal for understanding the role of sensitivity, magic, and coherence in quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mutually Unbiased Measurements, Hadamard Matrices, and Superdense Coding</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11886</link>
    <author>Máté Farkas, Jędrzej Kaniewski, Ashwin Nayak</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Mutually unbiased bases (MUBs) are highly symmetric bases on complex Hilbert spaces, and the corresponding rank-1 projective measurements are ubiquitous in quantum information theory. In this work, we study a recently introduced generalization of MUBs called mutually unbiased measurements (MUMs). These measurements inherit the essential property of complementarity from MUBs, but the Hilbert space dimension is no longer required to match the number of outcomes. This operational complementarity property renders MUMs highly useful for device-independent quantum information processing. It has been shown that MUMs are strictly more general than MUBs. In this work we provide a complete proof of the characterization of MUMs that are direct sums of MUBs. We then proceed to construct new examples of MUMs that are not direct sums of MUBs. A crucial technical tool for these construction is a correspondence with quaternionic Hadamard matrices, which allows us to map known examples of such matrices to MUMs that are not direct sums of MUBs. Furthermore, we show that -- in stark contrast with MUBs -- the number of MUMs for a fixed outcome number is unbounded. Next, we focus on the use of MUMs in quantum communication. We demonstrate how any pair of MUMs with d outcomes defines a d-dimensional superdense coding protocol. Using MUMs that are not direct sums of MUBs, we disprove a recent conjecture due to Nayak and Yuen on the rigidity of superdense coding for infinitely many dimensions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An open-source linear program for testing nonclassicality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11905</link>
    <author>John H. Selby, Elie Wolfe, David Schmid, Ana Belén Sainz</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The gold standard for demonstrating that an experiment resists any classical explanation is to show that its statistics violate generalized noncontextuality. We here provide an open-source linear program for testing whether or not any given prepare-measure experiment is classically-explainable in this sense. The input to the program is simply an arbitrary set of quantum states and an arbitrary set of quantum effects; the program then determines if the Born rule statistics generated by all pairs of these can be explained by a classical (noncontextual) model. If a classical model exists, it provides an explicit model. If it does not, then it computes the minimal amount of noise that must be added such that a model does exist, and then provides this model. We generalize all these results to arbitrary generalized probabilistic theories (and accessible fragments thereof) as well; indeed, our linear program is a test of simplex-embeddability.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On converses to the polynomial method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.12303</link>
    <author>Jop Briët, Francisco Escudero Gutiérrez</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A surprising 'converse to the polynomial method' of Aaronson et al. (CCC'16) shows that any bounded quadratic polynomial can be computed exactly in expectation by a 1-query algorithm up to a universal multiplicative factor related to the famous Grothendieck constant. A natural question posed there asks if bounded quartic polynomials can be approximated by $2$-query quantum algorithms. Arunachalam, Palazuelos and the first author showed that there is no direct analogue of the result of Aaronson et al. in this case. We improve on this result in the following ways: First, we point out and fix a small error in the construction that has to do with a translation from cubic to quartic polynomials. Second, we give a completely explicit example based on techniques from additive combinatorics. Third, we show that the result still holds when we allow for a small additive error. For this, we apply an SDP characterization of Gribling and Laurent (QIP'19) for the completely-bounded approximate degree.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>