<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Exponentially tighter bounds on limitations of quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11505</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Daniel Stilck França, Sumeet Khatri, Johannes Jakob Meyer, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation has been proposed as a means to combat unavoidable errors in near-term quantum computing by classically post-processing outcomes of multiple quantum circuits. It does so in a fashion that requires no or few additional quantum resources, in contrast to fault-tolerant schemes that come along with heavy overheads. Error mitigation leads to noise reduction in small systems. In this work, however, we identify strong limitations to the degree to which quantum noise can be effectively `undone' for larger system sizes. We start out by presenting a formal framework that rigorously encapsulates large classes of meaningful and practically applied schemes for quantum error mitigation, including virtual distillation, Clifford data regression, zero-noise extrapolation and probabilistic error cancellation. With the framework in place, our technical contribution is to construct families of random circuits that are highly sensitive to noise, in the sense that even at log log(n) depth, a whisker beyond constant, quantum noise is seen to super-exponentially rapidly scramble their output into the maximally-mixed state. Our results exponentially tighten known arguments for error mitigation, but they go beyond that: Our arguments can be applied to kernel estimation or to compute the depth at which barren plateaus emerge, implying that the scrambling kicks in at exponentially smaller depths than previously thought. Our results also say that a noisy device must be sampled exponentially many times to estimate expectation values. There are classical algorithms that exhibit the same scaling in complexity. While improvements in quantum hardware will push noise levels down, if error mitigation is used, ultimately this can only lead to an exponential time quantum algorithm with a better exponent, putting up a strong obstruction to the hope for exponential quantum speedups in this setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Gauge Networks: A New Kind of Tensor Network</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.12151</link>
    <author>Kevin Slagle</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Although tensor networks are powerful tools for simulating low-dimensional quantum physics, tensor network algorithms are very computationally costly in higher spatial dimensions. We introduce quantum gauge networks: a different kind of tensor network ansatz for which the computation cost of simulations does not explicitly increase for larger spatial dimensions. We take inspiration from the gauge picture of quantum dynamics, which consists of a local wavefunction for each patch of space, with neighboring patches related by unitary connections. A quantum gauge network (QGN) has a similar structure, except the Hilbert space dimensions of the local wavefunctions and connections are truncated. We describe how a QGN can be obtained from a generic wavefunction or matrix product state (MPS). All $2k$-point correlation functions of any wavefunction for $M$ many operators can be encoded exactly by a QGN with bond dimension $O(M^k)$. In comparison, for just $k=1$, an exponentially larger bond dimension of $2^{M/6}$ is generically required for an MPS of qubits. We provide a simple QGN algorithm for approximate simulations of quantum dynamics in any spatial dimension. The approximate dynamics can achieve exact energy conservation for time-independent Hamiltonians, and spatial symmetries can also be maintained exactly. We benchmark the algorithm by simulating the quantum quench of fermionic Hamiltonians in up to three spatial dimensions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Machine Learning using the ZXW-Calculus</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11523</link>
    <author>Mark Koch</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The field of quantum machine learning (QML) explores how quantum computers can be used to more efficiently solve machine learning problems. As an application of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms, it promises a potential quantum advantages in the near term. In this thesis, we use the ZXW-calculus to diagrammatically analyse two key problems that QML applications face. First, we discuss algorithms to compute gradients on quantum hardware that are needed to perform gradient-based optimisation for QML. Concretely, we give new diagrammatic proofs of the common 2- and 4-term parameter shift rules used in the literature. Additionally, we derive a novel, generalised parameter shift rule with 2n terms that is applicable to gates that can be represented with n parametrised spiders in the ZXW-calculus. Furthermore, to the best of our knowledge, we give the first proof of a conjecture by Anselmetti et al. by proving a no-go theorem ruling out more efficient alternatives to the 4-term shift rule. Secondly, we analyse the gradient landscape of quantum ansätze for barren plateaus using both empirical and analytical techniques. Concretely, we develop a tool that automatically calculates the variance of gradients and use it to detect likely barren plateaus in commonly used quantum ansätze. Furthermore, we formally prove the existence or absence of barren plateaus for a selection of ansätze using diagrammatic techniques from the ZXW-calculus.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On amortizing convex conjugates for optimal transport</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.12153</link>
    <author>Brandon Amos</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This paper focuses on computing the convex conjugate operation that arises when solving Euclidean Wasserstein-2 optimal transport problems. This conjugation, which is also referred to as the Legendre-Fenchel conjugate or $c$-transform, is considered difficult to compute and in practice, Wasserstein-2 methods are limited by not being able to exactly conjugate the dual potentials in continuous space. I show that combining amortized approximations to the conjugate with a solver for fine-tuning is computationally easy. This combination significantly improves the quality of transport maps learned for the Wasserstein-2 benchmark by Korotin et al. (2021) and is able to model many 2-dimensional couplings and flows considered in the literature. All of the baselines, methods, and solvers in this paper are available at http://github.com/facebookresearch/w2ot</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>WikiWhy: Answering and Explaining Cause-and-Effect Questions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.12152</link>
    <author>Matthew Ho, Aditya Sharma, Justin Chang, Michael Saxon, Sharon Levy, Yujie Lu, William Yang Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>As large language models (LLMs) grow larger and more sophisticated, assessing their "reasoning" capabilities in natural language grows more challenging. Recent question answering (QA) benchmarks that attempt to assess reasoning are often limited by a narrow scope of covered situations and subject matters. We introduce WikiWhy, a QA dataset built around a novel auxiliary task: explaining why an answer is true in natural language. WikiWhy contains over 9,000 "why" question-answer-rationale triples, grounded on Wikipedia facts across a diverse set of topics. Each rationale is a set of supporting statements connecting the question to the answer. WikiWhy serves as a benchmark for the reasoning capabilities of LLMs because it demands rigorous explicit rationales for each answer to demonstrate the acquisition of implicit commonsense knowledge, which is unlikely to be easily memorized. GPT-3 baselines achieve only 38.7% human-evaluated correctness in the end-to-end answer & explain condition, leaving significant room for future improvements.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>