<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>BBGKY Hierarchy and Generalised Hydrodynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10549</link>
    <author>Bruno Bertini, Fabian H. L. Essler, Etienne Granet</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider fermions defined on a continuous one-dimensional interval and subject to weak repulsive two-body interactions. We show that it is possible to perturbatively construct an extensive number of mutually compatible conserved charges for any interaction potential. However, the contributions to the densities of these charges at second order and higher are generally non-local and become spatially localized only if the potential fulfils certain compatibility conditions. We prove that the only solution to the first of these conditions with strictly local densities of charges is the Cheon-Shigehara potential (fermionic dual to the Lieb-Liniger model), and observe numerically that the only other solutions appear to be the Calogero-Sutherland potentials. We use our construction to show how Generalized Hydrodynamics (GHD) emerges from the Bogoliubov-Born-Green-Kirkwood-Yvon hierarchy, and argue that GHD in the weak interaction regime is robust under non-integrable perturbations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>State retrieval beyond Bayes' retrodiction and reverse processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.09899</link>
    <author>Jacopo Surace, Matteo Scandi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the context of irreversible dynamics, associating to a physical process its intuitive reverse can result to be a quite ambiguous task. It is a standard choice to define the reverse process using Bayes' theorem, but, in general, this choice is not optimal. In this work we explore whether it is possible to characterise an optimal reverse map building from the concept of state retrieval maps. In doing so, we propose a set of principles that state retrieval maps should satisfy. We find out that the Bayes inspired reverse is just one case in a whole class of possible choices, which can be optimised to give a map retrieving the initial state more precisely than the Bayes rule. Our analysis has the advantage of naturally extending to the quantum regime. In fact, we find a class of reverse transformations containing the Petz recovery map as a particular case, corroborating its interpretation as quantum analogue of the Bayes retrieval. Finally, we present numerical evidences that by adding a single extra axiom one can isolate the usual reverse process derived from Bayes' theorem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Stochastic diagonal estimation: probabilistic bounds and an improved algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10684</link>
    <author>Robert A. Baston, Yuji Nakatsukasa</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of estimating the diagonal of an implicitly given matrix $A$. For such a matrix we have access to an oracle that allows us to evaluate the matrix vector product $Av$. For random variable $v$ drawn from an appropriate distribution, this may be used to return an estimate of the diagonal of the matrix $A$. Whilst results exist for probabilistic guarantees relating to the error of estimates of the trace of $A$, no such results have yet been derived for the diagonal. We analyse the number of queries $s$ required to guarantee that with probability at least $1-\delta$ the estimates of the relative error of the diagonal entries is at most $\varepsilon$. We extend this analysis to the 2-norm of the difference between the estimate and the diagonal of $A$. We prove, discuss and experiment with bounds on the number of queries $s$ required to guarantee a probabilistic bound on the estimates of the diagonal by employing Rademacher and Gaussian random variables. Two sufficient upper bounds on the minimum number of query vectors are proved, extending the work of Avron and Toledo [JACM 58(2)8, 2011], and later work of Roosta-Khorasani and Ascher [FoCM 15, 1187-1212, 2015]. We find that, generally, there is little difference between the two, with convergence going as $O(\log(1/\delta)/\varepsilon^2)$ for individual diagonal elements. However for small $s$, we find that the Rademacher estimator is superior. These results allow us to then extend the ideas of Meyer, Musco, Musco and Woodruff [SOSA, 142-155, 2021], suggesting algorithm Diag++, to speed up the convergence of diagonal estimation from $O(1/\varepsilon^2)$ to $O(1/\varepsilon)$ and make it robust to the spectrum of any positive semi-definite matrix $A$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficiently improving the performance of noisy quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10672</link>
    <author>Samuele Ferracin, Akel Hashim, Jean-Loup Ville, Ravi Naik, Arnaud Carignan-Dugas, Hammam Qassim, Alexis Morvan, David I. Santiago, Irfan Siddiqi, Joel J. Wallman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Using near-term quantum computers to achieve a quantum advantage requires efficient strategies to improve the performance of the noisy quantum devices presently available. We develop and experimentally validate two efficient error mitigation protocols named "Noiseless Output Extrapolation" and "Pauli Error Cancellation" that can drastically enhance the performance of quantum circuits composed of noisy cycles of gates. By combining popular mitigation strategies such as probabilistic error cancellation and noise amplification with efficient noise reconstruction methods, our protocols can mitigate a wide range of noise processes that do not satisfy the assumptions underlying existing mitigation protocols, including non-local and gate-dependent processes. We test our protocols on a four-qubit superconducting processor at the Advanced Quantum Testbed. We observe significant improvements in the performance of both structured and random circuits, with up to $86\%$ improvement in variation distance over the unmitigated outputs. Our experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our protocols, as well as their practicality for current hardware platforms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Online Active Learning with Dynamic Marginal Gain Thresholding</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10547</link>
    <author>Mariel A. Werner, Anastasios Angelopoulos, Stephen Bates, Michael I. Jordan</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The blessing of ubiquitous data also comes with a curse: the communication, storage, and labeling of massive, mostly redundant datasets. In our work, we seek to solve the problem at its source, collecting only valuable data and throwing out the rest, via active learning. We propose an online algorithm which, given any stream of data, any assessment of its value, and any formulation of its selection cost, extracts the most valuable subset of the stream up to a constant factor while using minimal memory. Notably, our analysis also holds for the federated setting, in which multiple agents select online from individual data streams without coordination and with potentially very different appraisals of cost. One particularly important use case is selecting and labeling training sets from unlabeled collections of data that maximize the test-time performance of a given classifier. In prediction tasks on ImageNet and MNIST, we show that our selection method outperforms random selection by up to 5-20%.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>