<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Preparing Arbitrary Continuous Functions in Quantum Registers With Logarithmic Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00519</link>
    <author>Arthur G. Rattew, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers will be able solve important problems with significant polynomial and exponential speedups over their classical counterparts, for instance in option pricing in finance, and in real-space molecular chemistry simulations. However, key applications can only achieve their potential speedup if their inputs are prepared efficiently. We effectively solve the important problem of efficiently preparing quantum states following arbitrary continuous (as well as more general) functions with complexity logarithmic in the desired resolution, and with rigorous error bounds. This is enabled by the development of a fundamental subroutine based off of the simulation of rank-1 projectors. Combined with diverse techniques from quantum information processing, this subroutine enables us to present a broad set of tools for solving practical tasks, such as state preparation, numerical integration of Lipschitz continuous functions, and superior sampling from probability density functions. As a result, our work has significant implications in a wide range of applications, for instance in financial forecasting, and in quantum simulation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>What is the temperature of a quantum state?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00017</link>
    <author>Patryk Lipka-Bartosik, Martí Perarnau-Llobet, Nicolas Brunner</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Temperature is usually defined for physical systems at thermal equilibrium. Nevertheless one may wonder if it would be possible to attribute a meaningful notion of temperature to an arbitrary quantum state, beyond simply the thermal (Gibbs) state. In this work, we propose such a notion of temperature considering an operational task, inspired by the Zeroth Law of thermodynamics. Specifically, we define two effective temperatures for quantifying the ability of a quantum system to cool down or heat up a thermal environment. In this way we can associate an operationally meaningful notion of temperature to any quantum density matrix. We provide general expressions for these effective temperatures, for both single- and many-copy systems, establishing connections to concepts previously discussed in the literature. Finally, we consider a more sophisticated scenario where the heat exchange between the system and the thermal environment is assisted by a quantum reference frame. This leads to an effect of "coherent quantum catalysis", where the use of a coherent catalyst allows for exploiting quantum energetic coherences in the system, now leading to much colder or hotter effective temperatures.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gleason's theorem for composite systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00493</link>
    <author>Markus Frembs, Andreas Döring</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gleason's theorem [A. Gleason, J. Math. Mech., \textbf6, 885 (1957)] is an important result in the foundations of quantum mechanics, where it justifies the Born rule as a mathematical consequence of the quantum formalism. Formally, it presents a key insight into the projective geometry of Hilbert spaces, showing that finitely additive measures on the projection lattice $\PH$ extend to positive linear functionals on the algebra of bounded operators $\BH$. Over many years, and by the effort of various authors, the theorem has been broadened in its scope from type I to arbitrary von Neumann algebras (without type $\text{I}_2$ factors). Here, we prove a generalisation of Gleason's theorem to composite systems. To this end, we strengthen the original result in two ways: first, we extend its scope to dilations in the sense of Naimark [M. A. Naimark, C. R. (Dokl.) Acad. Sci. URSS, n. Ser., \textbf41, 359 (1943)] and Stinespring [W. F. Stinespring, Proc. Am. Math. Soc., \textbf6, 211 (1955)] and second, we require consistency with respect to dynamical correspondences on the respective (local) algebras in the composition [E. M. Alfsen and F. W. Shultz, Commun. Math. Phys., \textbf194, 87 (1998)]. We show that neither of these conditions changes the result in the single system case, yet both are necessary to obtain a generalisation to bipartite systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Is gravitational entanglement evidence for the quantization of spacetime?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00939</link>
    <author>M. Kemal Döner, André Großardt</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Experiments witnessing the entanglement between two particles interacting only via the gravitational field have been proposed as a test whether gravity must be quantized. In the language of quantum information, a non-quantum gravitational force would be modeled by local operations with classical communication (LOCC), which cannot generate entanglement in an initially unentangled state. This idea is criticized as too constraining on possible alternatives to quantum gravity. We present a parametrized model for the gravitational interaction of quantum matter on a classical spacetime, inspired by the de Broglie-Bohm formulation of quantum mechanics, which results in entanglement and thereby provides an explicit counterexample to the claim that only a quantized gravitational field possesses this capability.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A near-term quantum algorithm for solving linear systems of equations based on the Woodbury identity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00645</link>
    <author>Daniel O'Malley, Yigit Subasi, John Golden, Robert Lowrie, Stephan Eidenbenz</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for solving linear systems of equations have generated excitement because of the potential speed-ups involved and the importance of solving linear equations in many applications. However, applying these algorithms can be challenging. The Harrow-Hassidim-Lloyd algorithm and improvements thereof require complex subroutines suitable for fault-tolerant hardware such as Hamiltonian simulation, making it ill-suited to current hardware. Variational algorithms, on the other hand, involve expensive optimization loops, which can be prone to barren plateaus and local optima. We describe a quantum algorithm for solving linear systems of equations that avoids these problems. Our algorithm is based on the Woodbury identity, which analytically describes the inverse of a matrix that is a low-rank modification of another (easily-invertible) matrix. This approach only utilizes basic quantum subroutines like the Hadamard test or the swap test, so it is well-suited to current hardware. There is no optimization loop, so barren plateaus and local optima do not present a problem. The low-rank aspect of the identity enables us to efficiently transfer information to and from the quantum computer. This approach can produce accurate results on current hardware. As evidence of this, we estimate an inner product involving the solution of a system of more than 16 million equations with 2% error using IBM's Auckland quantum computer. To our knowledge, no system of equations this large has previously been solved to this level of accuracy on a quantum computer.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>