<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence between fermion-to-qubit mappings in two spatial dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05153</link>
    <author>Yu-An Chen, Yijia Xu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We argue that all locality-preserving mappings between fermionic observables and Pauli matrices on a two-dimensional lattice can be generated from the exact bosonization in Ref. [1], whose gauge constraints project onto the subspace of the toric code with emergent fermions. Starting from the exact bosonization and applying Clifford finite-depth generalized local unitary (gLU) transformation, we can achieve all possible fermion-to-qubit mappings (up to the re-pairing of Majorana fermions). In particular, we discover a new super-compact encoding using 1.25 qubits per fermion on the square lattice, which is lower than any method in the literature. We prove the existence of fermion-to-qubit mappings with qubit-fermion ratios $r=1+ \frac{1}{2k}$ for positive integers $k$, where the proof utilizes the trivialness of quantum cellular automata (QCA) in two spatial dimensions. When the ratio approaches 1, the fermion-to-qubit mapping reduces to the 1d Jordan-Wigner transformation along a certain path in the two-dimensional lattice. Finally, we explicitly demonstrate that the Bravyi-Kitaev superfast simulation, the Verstraete-Cirac auxiliary method, Kitaev's exactly solved model, the Majorana loop stabilizer codes, and the compact fermion-to-qubit mapping can all be obtained from the exact bosonization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Consilience between QBism and Phenomenology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04734</link>
    <author>Hans Christian von Baeyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two decades after its creation, the interpretation of quantum mechanics called QBism is entering a new phase. Since it shares a personalist, subjective world-view with phenomenology, the philosophical study of human experience, there is a growing interest in the relationship between the two subjects. I call attention to the little-known philosopher Samuel Todes, whose phenomenology focused on the essential role of the human body in our understanding of the world. After reviewing this radical proposal, and illustrating it with some examples, I recommend it as an interesting mediator between the communities of physicists and phenomenologists. In addition, I argue that it may prove useful for promoting the public understanding of QBism.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum networks self-test all entangled states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05032</link>
    <author>Ivan Šupić, Joseph Bowles, Marc-Olivier Renou, Antonio Acín, Matty J. Hoban</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Certifying quantum properties with minimal assumptions is a fundamental problem in quantum information science. Self-testing is a method to infer the underlying physics of a quantum experiment only from the measured statistics. While all bipartite pure entangled states can be self-tested, little is known about how to self-test quantum states of an arbitrary number of systems. Here, we introduce a framework for network-assisted self-testing and use it to self-test any pure entangled quantum state of an arbitrary number of systems. The scheme requires the preparation of a number of singlets that scales linearly with the number of systems, and the implementation of standard projective and Bell measurements, all feasible with current technology. When all the network constraints are exploited, the obtained self-testing certification is stronger than what is achievable in any Bell-type scenario. Our work does not only solve an open question in the field, but also shows how properly designed networks offer new opportunities for the certification of quantum phenomena.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universality and sharp matrix concentration inequalities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05142</link>
    <author>Tatiana Brailovskaya, Ramon van Handel</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that, under mild assumptions, the spectrum of a sum of independent random matrices is close to that of the Gaussian random matrix whose entries have the same mean and covariance. This nonasymptotic universality principle both explains the phenomenon behind classical matrix concentration inequalities such as the matrix Bernstein inequality, and yields new sharp matrix concentration inequalities for general sums of independent random matrices when combined with the recent Gaussian theory of Bandeira, Boedihardjo, and Van Handel. As an application of our main results, we prove strong asymptotic freeness of a very general class of random matrix models with non-Gaussian, nonhomogeneous, and dependent entries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Towards real-world quantum networks: a review</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04802</link>
    <author>Shi-Hai Wei, Bo Jing, Xue-Ying Zhang, Jin-Yu Liao, Chen-Zhi Yuan, Bo-Yu Fan, Chen Lyu, Dian-Li Zhou, You Wang, Guang-Wei Deng, Hai-Zhi Song, Daniel Oblak, Guang-Can Guo, Qiang Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum networks play an extremely important role in quantum information science, with application to quantum communication, computation, metrology and fundamental tests. One of the key challenges for implementing a quantum network is to distribute entangled flying qubits to spatially separated nodes, at which quantum interfaces or transducers map the entanglement onto stationary qubits. The stationary qubits at the separated nodes constitute quantum memories realized in matter while the flying qubits constitute quantum channels realized in photons. Dedicated efforts around the world for more than twenty years have resulted in both major theoretical and experimental progress towards entangling quantum nodes and ultimately building a global quantum network. Here, we review the development of quantum networks and the experimental progress over the past two decades leading to the current state of the art for generating entanglement of quantum nodes based on various physical systems such as single atoms, cold atomic ensembles, trapped ions, diamonds with Nitrogen-Vacancy centers, solid-state host doped with rare-earth ions, etc. Along the way we discuss the merits and compare the potential of each of these systems towards realizing a quantum network.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>