<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>On the Cleaning Lemma of Quantum Coding Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04699</link>
    <author>Gleb Kalachev, Sergey Sadov</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The term "Cleaning Lemma" refers to a family of similar propositions that have been used in Quantum Coding Theory to estimate the minimum distance of a code in terms of its length and dimension. We show that the mathematical core is a simple fact of linear algebra of inner product spaces; moreover, it admits a further reduction to a combinatorial, lattice-theoretical level. Several concrete variants of the Cleaning Lemma and some additional propositions are derived as corollaries of the proposed approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement-invertible channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04493</link>
    <author>Dominic Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a well-known result \citeWerner2001, Werner classified all \emphtight quantum teleportation and dense coding schemes, showing that they correspond to \emphunitary error bases. Here tightness is a certain dimensional restriction: the quantum system to be teleported and the entangled resource must be of dimension d, and the measurement must have d^2 outcomes. In this work we generalise this classification so as to remove the dimensional restriction altogether, thereby resolving an open problem raised in that work. In fact, we classify not just teleportation and dense coding schemes, but \emphentanglement-reversible channels. These are channels between finite-dimensional C^*-algebras which are reversible with the aid of an entangled resource state, generalising ordinary reversibility of a channel. In Werner's classification, a bijective correspondence between tight teleportation and dense coding schemes was shown: swapping Alice and Bob's operations turns a teleportation scheme into a dense coding scheme and vice versa. We observe that this property generalises ordinary invertibility of a channel; we call it \emphentanglement-invertibility. We show that entanglement-invertible channels are precisely the \emphquantum bijections previously studied in the setting of quantum combinatorics \citeMusto2018, which are classified in terms of the representation theory of the quantum permutation group.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Mathematical Framework for Transformations of Physical Processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04319</link>
    <author>Matt Wilson, Giulio Chiribella</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We observe that the existence of sequential and parallel composition supermaps in higher order physics can be formalized using enriched category theory. Encouraged by physically relevant examples such as unitary supermaps and layers within higher order causal categories (HOCCs), we treat the modeling of higher order physics with enriched monoidal categories in analogy with the process theoretic framework in which physical theories are modeled with monoidal categories. We use the enriched monoidal setting to construct a suitable definition of structure-preserving map between higher order physical theories via the Grothendieck construction. We then show that the convenient feature of currying in higher order physical theories can be seen as a consequence of combining the primitive assumption of the existence of parallel and sequential composition supermaps with an additional feature of "linking". In a second application, we show more generally that categories containing infinite towers of enriched monoidal categories with full and faithful structure-preserving maps between them inevitably lead to closed monoidal structure. The aim of the proposed definitions is to give a broad framework for the study and comparison of novel causal structures in quantum theory, and, more broadly, provide a paradigm of physical theory where static and dynamical features are treated in a unified way.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ground state preparation and energy estimation on early fault-tolerant quantum computers via quantum eigenvalue transformation of unitary matrices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.05955</link>
    <author>Yulong Dong, Lin Lin, Yu Tong</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Under suitable assumptions, the algorithms in [Lin, Tong, Quantum 2020] can estimate the ground state energy and prepare the ground state of a quantum Hamiltonian with near-optimal query complexities. However, this is based on a block encoding input model of the Hamiltonian, whose implementation is known to require a large resource overhead. We develop a tool called quantum eigenvalue transformation of unitary matrices with real polynomials (QET-U), which uses a controlled Hamiltonian evolution as the input model, a single ancilla qubit and no multi-qubit control operations, and is thus suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum devices. This leads to a simple quantum algorithm that outperforms all previous algorithms with a comparable circuit structure for estimating the ground state energy. For a class of quantum spin Hamiltonians, we propose a new method that exploits certain anti-commutation relations and further removes the need of implementing the controlled Hamiltonian evolution. Coupled with Trotter based approximation of the Hamiltonian evolution, the resulting algorithm can be very suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum devices. We demonstrate the performance of the algorithm using IBM Qiskit for the transverse field Ising model. If we are further allowed to use multi-qubit Toffoli gates, we can then implement amplitude amplification and a new binary amplitude estimation algorithm, which increases the circuit depth but decreases the total query complexity. The resulting algorithm saturates the near-optimal complexity for ground state preparation and energy estimating using a constant number of ancilla qubits (no more than 3).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The spin-one Motzkin chain is gapped for any area weight $t<1$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04517</link>
    <author>Radu Andrei, Marius Lemm, Ramis Movassagh</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove a conjecture by Zhang, Ahmadain, and Klich that the spin-$1$ Motzkin chain is gapped for any area weight $t<1$. Existence of a finite spectral gap is necessary for the Motzkin Hamiltonian to belong to the Haldane phase, which has been argued to potentially be the case in recent work of Barbiero, Dell'Anna, Trombettoni, and Korepin. Our proof rests on the combinatorial structure of the ground space and the analytical verification of a finite-size criterion.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>