<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Out-of-distribution generalization for learning quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10268</link>
    <author>Matthias C. Caro, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Nicholas Ezzell, Joe Gibbs, Andrew T. Sornborger, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Generalization bounds are a critical tool to assess the training data requirements of Quantum Machine Learning (QML). Recent work has established guarantees for in-distribution generalization of quantum neural networks (QNNs), where training and testing data are assumed to be drawn from the same data distribution. However, there are currently no results on out-of-distribution generalization in QML, where we require a trained model to perform well even on data drawn from a distribution different from the training distribution. In this work, we prove out-of-distribution generalization for the task of learning an unknown unitary using a QNN and for a broad class of training and testing distributions. In particular, we show that one can learn the action of a unitary on entangled states using only product state training data. We numerically illustrate this by showing that the evolution of a Heisenberg spin chain can be learned using only product training states. Since product states can be prepared using only single-qubit gates, this advances the prospects of learning quantum dynamics using near term quantum computers and quantum experiments, and further opens up new methods for both the classical and quantum compilation of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical algorithms for many-body quantum systems at finite energies</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.09439</link>
    <author>Yilun Yang, J. Ignacio Cirac, Mari Carmen Bañuls</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate quantum inspired algorithms to compute physical observables of quantum many-body systems at finite energies. They are based on the quantum algorithms proposed in [Lu et al. PRX Quantum 2, 020321 (2021)], which use the quantum simulation of the dynamics of such systems, as well as classical filtering and sampling techniques. Here, we replace the quantum simulation by standard classical methods based on matrix product states and operators. As a result, we can address significantly larger systems than those reachable by exact diagonalization or by other algorithms. We demonstrate the performance with spin chains up to 80 sites.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dynamical simulation via quantum machine learning with provable generalization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10269</link>
    <author>Joe Gibbs, Zoë Holmes, Matthias C. Caro, Nicholas Ezzell, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Lukasz Cincio, Andrew T. Sornborger, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Much attention has been paid to dynamical simulation and quantum machine learning (QML) independently as applications for quantum advantage, while the possibility of using QML to enhance dynamical simulations has not been thoroughly investigated. Here we develop a framework for using QML methods to simulate quantum dynamics on near-term quantum hardware. We use generalization bounds, which bound the error a machine learning model makes on unseen data, to rigorously analyze the training data requirements of an algorithm within this framework. This provides a guarantee that our algorithm is resource-efficient, both in terms of qubit and data requirements. Our numerics exhibit efficient scaling with problem size, and we simulate 20 times longer than Trotterization on IBMQ-Bogota.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable measures of magic for quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10061</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, M. S. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic characterizes the degree of non-stabilizerness of quantum states. It is a crucial resource for quantum computing and a necessary condition for quantum advantage. However, quantifying magic beyond a few qubits has been a major challenge. Here, we introduce Bell magic to efficiently measure magic for any number of qubits. Our method can be easily implemented in experiments together with a cost-free error mitigation scheme. We experimentally demonstrate the transition of classically simulable stabilizer states into intractable quantum states on the IonQ quantum computer. For applications, Bell magic distinguishes stabilizer and magical states with a low measurement cost. Further, variational quantum algorithms can maximize the magic of quantum states via the shift-rule. Our results pave the way to benchmark the non-classical power of quantum computers, quantum simulators and quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Fisher information-based incompatibility criterion for quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.09963</link>
    <author>Qing-Hua Zhang, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new incompatibility criterion for quantum channels, based on the notion of (quantum) Fisher information. Our construction is based on a similar criterion for quantum measurements put forward by H.~Zhu. We then study the power of the incompatibility criterion in different scenarios. Firstly, we prove the first analytical conditions for the incompatibility of two Schur channels. Then, we study the incompatibility structure of a tuple of depolarizing channels, comparing the newly introduced criterion with the known results from asymmetric quantum cloning.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>