<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Quantum Fourier Transform Has Small Entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.08468</link>
    <author>Jielun Chen, E.M. Stoudenmire, Steven R. White</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Fourier Transform (QFT) is a key component of many important quantum algorithms, most famously as being the essential ingredient in Shor's algorithm for factoring products of primes. Given its remarkable capability, one would think it can introduce large entanglement to qubit systems and would be difficult to simulate classically. While early results showed QFT indeed has maximal operator entanglement, we show that this is entirely due to the bit reversal in the QFT. The core part of the QFT has Schmidt coefficients decaying exponentially quickly, and thus it can only generate a constant amount of entanglement regardless of the number of qubits. In addition, we show the entangling power of the QFT is the same as the time evolution of a Hamiltonian with exponentially decaying interactions, and thus a variant of the area law for dynamics can be used to understand the low entanglement intuitively. Using the low entanglement property of the QFT, we show that classical simulations of the QFT on a matrix product state with low bond dimension only take time linear in the number of qubits, providing a potential speedup over the classical fast Fourier transform (FFT) on many classes of functions. We demonstrate this speedup in test calculations on some simple functions. For data vectors of length $10^6$ to $10^8$, the speedup can be a few orders of magnitude.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Event Learning and Gentle Random Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.09155</link>
    <author>Adam Bene Watts, John Bostanci</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove the expected disturbance caused to a quantum system by a sequence of randomly ordered two-outcome projective measurements is upper bounded by the square root of the probability that at least one measurement in the sequence accepts. We call this bound the \textitGentle Random Measurement Lemma. We also extend the techniques used to prove this lemma to develop protocols for problems in which we are given sample access to an unknown state $\rho$ and asked to estimate properties of the accepting probabilities $\text{Tr}[M_i \rho]$ of a set of measurements $\{M_1, M_2, ... , M_m\}$. We call these types of problems \textitQuantum Event Learning Problems. In particular, we show randomly ordering projective measurements solves the Quantum OR problem, answering an open question of Aaronson. We also give a Quantum OR protocol which works on non-projective measurements and which outperforms both the random measurement protocol analyzed in this paper and the protocol of Harrow, Lin, and Montanaro. However, this protocol requires a more complicated type of measurement, which we call a \textitBlended Measurement. When the total (summed) accepting probability of unlikely events is bounded, we show the random and blended measurement Quantum OR protocols developed in this paper can also be used to find a measurement $M_i$ such that $\text{Tr}[M_i \rho]$ is large. We call the problem of finding such a measurement \textitQuantum Event Finding. Finally, we show Blended Measurements also give a sample-efficient protocol for \textitQuantum Mean Estimation: a problem in which the goal is to estimate the average accepting probability of a set of measurements on an unknown state.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved Product-state Approximation Algorithms for Quantum Local Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.08680</link>
    <author>Thiago Bergamaschi</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ground state energy and the free energy of Quantum Local Hamiltonians are fundamental quantities in quantum many-body physics, however, it is QMA-Hard to estimate them in general. In this paper, we develop new techniques to find classical, additive error product-state approximations for these quantities on certain families of Quantum $k$-Local Hamiltonians. Namely, those which are either dense, have low threshold rank, or are defined on a sparse graph that excludes a fixed minor, building on the methods and the systems studied by Brandão and Harrow, Gharibian and Kempe, and Bansal, Bravyi and Terhal. We present two main technical contributions. First, we discuss a connection between product-state approximations of local Hamiltonians and combinatorial graph property testing. We develop a series of weak Szemerédi regularity lemmas for $k$-local Hamiltonians, built on those of Frieze and Kannan and others. We use them to develop constant time sampling algorithms, and to characterize the `vertex sample complexity' of the Local Hamiltonian problem, in an analog to a classical result by Alon, de la Vega, Kannan and Karpinski. Second, we build on the information-theoretic product-state approximation techniques by Brandão and Harrow, extending their results to the free energy and to an asymmetric graph setting. We leverage this structure to define families of algorithms for the free energy at low temperatures, and new algorithms for certain sparse graph families.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Theory for Equivariant Quantum Neural Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.08566</link>
    <author>Quynh T. Nguyen, Louis Schatzki, Paolo Braccia, Michael Ragone, Patrick J. Coles, Frederic Sauvage, Martin Larocca, M. Cerezo</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Most currently used quantum neural network architectures have little-to-no inductive biases, leading to trainability and generalization issues. Inspired by a similar problem, recent breakthroughs in classical machine learning address this crux by creating models encoding the symmetries of the learning task. This is materialized through the usage of equivariant neural networks whose action commutes with that of the symmetry. In this work, we import these ideas to the quantum realm by presenting a general theoretical framework to understand, classify, design and implement equivariant quantum neural networks. As a special implementation, we show how standard quantum convolutional neural networks (QCNN) can be generalized to group-equivariant QCNNs where both the convolutional and pooling layers are equivariant under the relevant symmetry group. Our framework can be readily applied to virtually all areas of quantum machine learning, and provides hope to alleviate central challenges such as barren plateaus, poor local minima, and sample complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Automated quantum error mitigation based on probabilistic error reduction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.08611</link>
    <author>Benjamin McDonough, Andrea Mari, Nathan Shammah, Nathaniel T. Stemen, Misty Wahl, William J. Zeng, Peter P. Orth</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Current quantum computers suffer from a level of noise that prohibits extracting useful results directly from longer computations. The figure of merit in many near-term quantum algorithms is an expectation value measured at the end of the computation, which experiences a bias in the presence of hardware noise. A systematic way to remove such bias is probabilistic error cancellation (PEC). PEC requires a full characterization of the noise and introduces a sampling overhead that increases exponentially with circuit depth, prohibiting high-depth circuits at realistic noise levels. Probabilistic error reduction (PER) is a related quantum error mitigation method that systematically reduces the sampling overhead at the cost of reintroducing bias. In combination with zero-noise extrapolation, PER can yield expectation values with an accuracy comparable to PEC.Noise reduction through PER is broadly applicable to near-term algorithms, and the automated implementation of PER is thus desirable for facilitating its widespread use. To this end, we present an automated quantum error mitigation software framework that includes noise tomography and application of PER to user-specified circuits. We provide a multi-platform Python package that implements a recently developed Pauli noise tomography (PNT) technique for learning a sparse Pauli noise model and exploits a Pauli noise scaling method to carry out PER.We also provide software tools that leverage a previously developed toolchain, employing PyGSTi for gate set tomography and providing a functionality to use the software Mitiq for PER and zero-noise extrapolation to obtain error-mitigated expectation values on a user-defined circuit.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>