<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Candidate for a self-correcting quantum memory in two dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09767</link>
    <author>Simon Lieu, Yu-Jie Liu, Alexey V. Gorshkov</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An interesting problem in the field of quantum error correction involves finding a physical system that hosts a "self-correcting quantum memory," defined as an encoded qubit coupled to an environment that naturally wants to correct errors. To date, a quantum memory stable against finite-temperature effects is only known in four spatial dimensions or higher. Here, we take a different approach to realize a stable quantum memory by relying on a driven-dissipative environment. We propose a new model which appears to self correct against both bit-flip and phase-flip errors in two dimensions: A square lattice composed of photonic "cat qubits" coupled via dissipative terms which tend to fix errors locally. Inspired by the presence of two distinct $\mathbb{Z}_2$-symmetry-broken phases, our scheme relies on Ising-like dissipators to protect against bit flips and on a driven-dissipative photonic environment to protect against phase flips.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tensor Network Algorithms: a Route Map</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.10345</link>
    <author>Mari Carmen Bañuls</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tensor networks provide extremely powerful tools for the study of complex classical and quantum many-body problems. Over the last two decades, the increment in the number of techniques and applications has been relentless, and especially the last ten years have seen an explosion of new ideas and results that may be overwhelming for the newcomer. This short review introduces the basic ideas, the best established methods and some of the most significant algorithmic developments that are expanding the boundaries of the tensor network potential. The goal is to help the reader not only appreciate the many possibilities offered by tensor networks, but also find their way through state-of-the-art codes, their applicability and some avenues of ongoing progress.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Estimating the frame potential of large-scale quantum circuit sampling using tensor networks up to 50 qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09900</link>
    <author>Minzhao Liu, Junyu Liu, Yuri Alexeev, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop numerical protocols for estimating the frame potential, the 2-norm distance between a given ensemble and the exact Haar randomness, using the \textttQTensor platform. Our tensor-network-based algorithm has polynomial complexity for shallow circuits and is high performing using CPU and GPU parallelism. We apply the above methods to two problems: the Brown-Susskind conjecture, with local and parallel random circuits in terms of the Haar distance and the approximate $k$-design properties of the hardware efficient ansätze in quantum machine learning, which induce the barren plateau problem. We estimate frame potentials with these ensembles up to 50 qubits and $k=5$, examine the Haar distance of the hardware-efficient ansätze, and verify the Brown-Susskind conjecture numerically. Our work shows that large-scale tensor network simulations could provide important hints toward open problems in quantum information science.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The rank of contextuality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.10307</link>
    <author>Karol Horodecki, Jingfang Zhou, Maciej Stankiewicz, Roberto Salazar, Paweł Horodecki, Robert Raussendorf, Ryszard Horodecki, Ravishankar Ramanathan, Emily Tyhurst</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum contextuality is one of the most recognized resources in quantum communication and computing scenarios. We provide a new quantifier of this resource, the rank of contextuality (RC). We define RC as the minimum number of non-contextual behaviors that are needed to simulate a contextual behavior. We show that the logarithm of RC is a natural contextuality measure satisfying several properties considered in the spirit of the resource-theoretic approach. The properties include faithfulness, monotonicity, and additivity under tensor product. We also give examples of how to construct contextual behaviors with an arbitrary value of RC exhibiting a natural connection between this quantifier and the arboricity of an underlying hypergraph. We also discuss exemplary areas of research in which the new measure appears as a natural quantifier.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Pipelined correlated minimum weight perfect matching of the surface code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09828</link>
    <author>Alexandru Paler, Austin G. Fowler</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a pipeline approach to decoding the surface code using minimum weight perfect matching, including taking into account correlations between detection events. An independent no-communication parallelizable processing stage reweights the graph according to likely correlations, followed by another no-communication parallelizable stage for high confidence matching. A later general stage finishes the matching. This is a simplification of previous correlated matching techniques which required a complex interaction between general matching and re-weighting the graph. Despite this simplification, which gives correlated matching a better chance of achieving real-time processing, we find the logical error rate practically unchanged. We validate the new algorithm on the fully fault-tolerant toric, unrotated, and rotated surface codes, all with standard depolarizing noise. We expect these techniques to be applicable to a wide range of other decoders.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>