<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking Characterization Methods for Noisy Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02243</link>
    <author>Megan L. Dahlhauser, Travis S. Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Effective methods for characterizing the noise in quantum computing devices are essential for programming and debugging circuit performance. Existing approaches vary in the information obtained as well as the amount of quantum and classical resources required, with more information generally requiring more resources. Here we benchmark the characterization methods of gate set tomography, Pauli channel noise reconstruction, and empirical direct characterization for developing models that describe noisy quantum circuit performance on a 27-qubit superconducting transmon device. We evaluate these models by comparing the accuracy of noisy circuit simulations with the corresponding experimental observations. We find that the agreement of noise model to experiment does not correlate with the information gained by characterization and that the underlying circuit strongly influences the best choice of characterization approach. Empirical direct characterization scales best of the methods we tested and produced the most accurate characterizations across our benchmarks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Analytical calculation formulas for capacities of classical and classical-quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02450</link>
    <author>Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive an analytical calculation formula for the channel capacity of a classical channel without any iteration while its existing algorithms require iterations and the number of iteration depends on the required precision level. Hence, our formula is its first analytical formula without any iteration. We apply the obtained formula to examples and see how the obtained formula works in these examples. Then, we extend it to the channel capacity of a classical-quantum (cq-) channel. Many existing studies proposed algorithms for a cq-channel and all of them require iterations. Our extended analytical algorithm have also no iteration and output the exactly optimum values.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scaling Quantum Approximate Optimization on Near-term Hardware</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02247</link>
    <author>Phillip C. Lotshaw, Thien Nguyen, Anthony Santana, Alexander McCaskey, Rebekah Herrman, James Ostrowski, George Siopsis, Travis S. Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) is an approach for near-term quantum computers to potentially demonstrate computational advantage in solving combinatorial optimization problems. However, the viability of the QAOA depends on how its performance and resource requirements scale with problem size and complexity for realistic hardware implementations. Here, we quantify scaling of the expected resource requirements by synthesizing optimized circuits for hardware architectures with varying levels of connectivity. Assuming noisy gate operations, we estimate the number of measurements needed to sample the output of the idealized QAOA circuit with high probability. We show the number of measurements, and hence total time to solution, grows exponentially in problem size and problem graph degree as well as depth of the QAOA ansatz, gate infidelities, and inverse hardware graph degree. These problems may be alleviated by increasing hardware connectivity or by recently proposed modifications to the QAOA that achieve higher performance with fewer circuit layers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction using squeezed Schrödinger cat states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02570</link>
    <author>David S. Schlegel, Fabrizio Minganti, Vincenzo Savona</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bosonic quantum codes redundantly encode quantum information in the states of a quantum harmonic oscillator, making it possible to detect and correct errors. Schrödinger cat codes -- based on the superposition of two coherent states with opposite displacements -- can correct phase-flip errors induced by dephasing, but they are vulnerable to bit-flip errors induced by photon loss. Here, we develop a bosonic quantum code relying on squeezed cat states, i.e. cat states made of a linear superposition of displaced-squeezed states. Squeezed cat states allow to partially correct errors caused by photon loss, while at the same time improving the protection against dephasing. We present a comprehensive analysis of the squeezed cat code, including protocols for code generation and elementary quantum gates. We characterize the effect of both photon loss and dephasing and develop an optimal recovery protocol that is suitable to be implemented on currently available quantum hardware. We show that with moderate squeezing, and using typical parameters of state-of-the-art quantum hardware platforms, the squeezed cat code has a resilience to photon-loss errors that significantly outperforms that of the conventional cat code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Loschmidt echo and Poincaré recurrences of entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02600</link>
    <author>Leonardo Ermann, Klaus M. Frahm, Dima L Shepelyansky</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study numerically the properties of entanglement of two interacting, or noninteracting, particles evolving in a regime of quantum chaos in the quantum Chirikov standard map. Such pairs can be viewed as interacting, on noninteracting, Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen pairs in a regime of quantum chaos. The analysis is done with such tools as the Loschmidt echo of entanglement and the Poincaré recurrences of entanglement in presence of absorption. The obtained results show unusual features of the entropy of entanglement and the spectrum of Schmidt decomposition with their dependence on interactions at different quantum chaos regimes.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>