<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum majority vote</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.11729</link>
    <author>Harry Buhrman, Noah Linden, Laura Mančinska, Ashley Montanaro, Maris Ozols</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Majority vote is a basic method for amplifying correct outcomes that is widely used in computer science and beyond. While it can amplify the correctness of a quantum device with classical output, the analogous procedure for quantum output is not known. We introduce quantum majority vote as the following task: given a product state $|\psi_1\rangle \otimes \dots \otimes |\psi_n\rangle$ where each qubit is in one of two orthogonal states $|\psi\rangle$ or $|\psi^\perp\rangle$, output the majority state. We show that an optimal algorithm for this problem achieves worst-case fidelity of $1/2 + \Theta(1/\sqrt{n})$. Under the promise that at least $2/3$ of the input qubits are in the majority state, the fidelity increases to $1 - \Theta(1/n)$ and approaches $1$ as $n$ increases. We also consider the more general problem of computing any symmetric and equivariant Boolean function $f: \{0,1\}^n \to \{0,1\}$ in an unknown quantum basis, and show that a generalization of our quantum majority vote algorithm is optimal for this task. The optimal parameters for the generalized algorithm and its worst-case fidelity can be determined by a simple linear program of size $O(n)$. The time complexity of the algorithm is $O(n^4 \log n)$ where $n$ is the number of input qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decidability of fully quantum nonlocal games with noisy maximally entangled states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.10613</link>
    <author>Minglong Qin, Penghui Yao</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This paper considers the decidability of fully quantum nonlocal games with noisy maximally entangled states. Fully quantum nonlocal games are a generalization of nonlocal games, where both questions and answers are quantum and the referee performs a binary POVM measurement to decide whether they win the game after receiving the quantum answers from the players. The quantum value of a fully quantum nonlocal game is the supremum of the probability that they win the game, where the supremum is taken over all the possible entangled states shared between the players and all the valid quantum operations performed by the players. The seminal work $\mathrm{MIP}^*=\mathrm{RE}$ implies that it is undecidable to approximate the quantum value of a fully nonlocal game. This still holds even if the players are only allowed to share (arbitrarily many copies of) maximally entangled states. This paper investigates the case that the shared maximally entangled states are noisy. We prove that there is a computable upper bound on the copies of noisy maximally entangled states for the players to win a fully quantum nonlocal game with a probability arbitrarily close to the quantum value. This implies that it is decidable to approximate the quantum values of these games. Hence, the hardness of approximating the quantum value of a fully quantum nonlocal game is not robust against the noise in the shared states. This paper is built on the framework for the decidability of non-interactive simulations of joint distributions and generalizes the analogous result for nonlocal games. We extend the theory of Fourier analysis to the space of super-operators and prove several key results including an invariance principle and a dimension reduction for super-operators. These results are interesting in their own right and are believed to have further applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the monotonicity of a quantum optimal transport cost</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.11713</link>
    <author>Alexander Müller-Hermes</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the quantum generalization of the $2$-Wasserstein distance proposed by Chakrabarti et al. is not monotone under partial traces. This disproves a recent conjecture by Friedland et al. Finally, we propose a stabilized version of the original definition, which we show to be monotone under the application of general quantum channels.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lattice Problems Beyond Polynomial Time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.11693</link>
    <author>Divesh Aggarwal, Huck Bennett, Zvika Brakerski, Alexander Golovnev, Rajendra Kumar, Zeyong Li, Spencer Peters, Noah Stephens-Davidowitz, Vinod Vaikuntanathan</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the complexity of lattice problems in a world where algorithms, reductions, and protocols can run in superpolynomial time, revisiting four foundational results: two worst-case to average-case reductions and two protocols. We also show a novel protocol. 1. We prove that secret-key cryptography exists if $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{n})$-approximate SVP is hard for $2^{\varepsilon n}$-time algorithms. I.e., we extend to our setting (Micciancio and Regev's improved version of) Ajtai's celebrated polynomial-time worst-case to average-case reduction from $\widetilde{O}(n)$-approximate SVP to SIS. 2. We prove that public-key cryptography exists if $\widetilde{O}(n)$-approximate SVP is hard for $2^{\varepsilon n}$-time algorithms. This extends to our setting Regev's celebrated polynomial-time worst-case to average-case reduction from $\widetilde{O}(n^{1.5})$-approximate SVP to LWE. In fact, Regev's reduction is quantum, but ours is classical, generalizing Peikert's polynomial-time classical reduction from $\widetilde{O}(n^2)$-approximate SVP. 3. We show a $2^{\varepsilon n}$-time coAM protocol for $O(1)$-approximate CVP, generalizing the celebrated polynomial-time protocol for $O(\sqrt{n/\log n})$-CVP due to Goldreich and Goldwasser. These results show complexity-theoretic barriers to extending the recent line of fine-grained hardness results for CVP and SVP to larger approximation factors. (This result also extends to arbitrary norms.) 4. We show a $2^{\varepsilon n}$-time co-non-deterministic protocol for $O(\sqrt{\log n})$-approximate SVP, generalizing the (also celebrated!) polynomial-time protocol for $O(\sqrt{n})$-CVP due to Aharonov and Regev. 5. We give a novel coMA protocol for $O(1)$-approximate CVP with a $2^{\varepsilon n}$-time verifier. All of the results described above are special cases of more general theorems that achieve time-approximation factor tradeoffs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms and the power of forgetting</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.12447</link>
    <author>Andrew M. Childs, Matthew Coudron, Amin Shiraz Gilani</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The so-called welded tree problem provides an example of a black-box problem that can be solved exponentially faster by a quantum walk than by any classical algorithm. Given the name of a special ENTRANCE vertex, a quantum walk can find another distinguished EXIT vertex using polynomially many queries, though without finding any particular path from ENTRANCE to EXIT. It has been an open problem for twenty years whether there is an efficient quantum algorithm for finding such a path, or if the path-finding problem is hard even for quantum computers. We show that a natural class of efficient quantum algorithms provably cannot find a path from ENTRANCE to EXIT. Specifically, we consider algorithms that, within each branch of their superposition, always store a set of vertex labels that form a connected subgraph including the ENTRANCE, and that only provide these vertex labels as inputs to the oracle. While this does not rule out the possibility of a quantum algorithm that efficiently finds a path, it is unclear how an algorithm could benefit by deviating from this behavior. Our no-go result suggests that, for some problems, quantum algorithms must necessarily forget the path they take to reach a solution in order to outperform classical computation.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>