<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Short Proofs of Linear Growth of Quantum Circuit Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05668</link>
    <author>Zhi Li</author>
    <pubDate>May 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The complexity of a quantum gate, defined as the minimal number of elementary gates to build it, is an important concept in quantum information and computation. It is shown recently that the complexity of quantum gates built from random quantum circuits almost surely grows linearly with the number of building blocks. In this article, we provide two short proofs of this fact. We also discuss a discrete version of quantum circuit complexity growth.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An invitation to topological orders and category theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05565</link>
    <author>Liang Kong, Zhi-Hao Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>May 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Although it has been a well-known fact, for more than two decades, that category theory is needed for the study of topological orders, it is still a non-trivial challenge for students and working physicists to master the abstract language of category theory. In this work, for those who have no background in category theory, we explain in great details how the structure of a (braided) fusion category naturally emerges from lattice models and physical intuitions. Moreover, we show that nearly all mathematical notions and constructions in fusion categories and its representation theory, such as (monoidal) functors, Drinfeld center, module categories, Morita equivalence, condensation completion and fusion 2-categories, naturally emerge from lattice models and physical intuitions. In this process, we also introduce some basic notions and important results of topological orders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Self-Attention Neural Networks for Text Classification</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05625</link>
    <author>Guangxi Li, Xuanqiang Zhao, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An emerging direction of quantum computing is to establish meaningful quantum applications in various fields of artificial intelligence, including natural language processing (NLP). Although some efforts based on syntactic analysis have opened the door to research in Quantum NLP (QNLP), limitations such as heavy syntactic preprocessing and syntax-dependent network architecture make them impracticable on larger and real-world data sets. In this paper, we propose a new simple network architecture, called the quantum self-attention neural network (QSANN), which can make up for these limitations. Specifically, we introduce the self-attention mechanism into quantum neural networks and then utilize a Gaussian projected quantum self-attention serving as a sensible quantum version of self-attention. As a result, QSANN is effective and scalable on larger data sets and has the desirable property of being implementable on near-term quantum devices. In particular, our QSANN outperforms the best existing QNLP model based on syntactic analysis as well as a simple classical self-attention neural network in numerical experiments of text classification tasks on public data sets. We further show that our method exhibits robustness to low-level quantum noises.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multivariable quantum signal processing (M-QSP): prophecies of the two-headed oracle</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06261</link>
    <author>Zane M. Rossi, Isaac L. Chuang</author>
    <pubDate>May 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent work shows that quantum signal processing (QSP) and its multi-qubit lifted version, quantum singular value transformation (QSVT), unify and improve the presentation of most quantum algorithms. QSP/QSVT characterize the ability, by alternating ansätze, to obliviously transform the singular values of subsystems of unitary matrices by polynomial functions; these algorithms are numerically stable and analytically well-understood. That said, QSP/QSVT require consistent access to a single oracle, and say nothing about computing joint properties of two or more oracles; these can be far cheaper to compute given the ability to pit oracles against one another coherently. This work introduces a corresponding theory of QSP over multiple variables: M-QSP. Surprisingly, despite the non-existence of the fundamental theorem of algebra for multivariable polynomials, there exist necessary and sufficient conditions under which a desired stable multivariable polynomial transformation is possible. Moreover, the classical subroutines used by QSP protocols survive in the multivariable setting for non-obvious reasons. Up to a well-defined conjecture, we give proof that the family of achievable multivariable transforms is as loosely constrained as could be expected. M-QSP is numerically stable and inherits the approximative efficiency of its single-variable analogue; however, its underlying theory is substantively more complex. M-QSP provides one bridge from quantum algorithms to a rich theory of algebraic geometry over multiple variables. The unique ability of M-QSP to obliviously approximate joint functions of multiple variables coherently leads to novel speedups incommensurate with those of other quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Absolutely $k$-Incoherent Quantum States and Spectral Inequalities for Factor Width of a Matrix</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05110</link>
    <author>Nathaniel Johnston, Shirin Moein, Rajesh Pereira, Sarah Plosker</author>
    <pubDate>May 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the set of quantum states that can be shown to be $k$-incoherent based only on their eigenvalues (equivalently, we explore which Hermitian matrices can be shown to have small factor width based only on their eigenvalues). In analogy with the absolute separability problem in quantum resource theory, we call these states "absolutely $k$-incoherent", and we derive several necessary and sufficient conditions for membership in this set. We obtain many of our results by making use of recent results concerning hyperbolicity cones associated with elementary symmetric polynomials.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>