<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Fast erasure decoder for a class of quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01002</link>
    <author>Nicholas Connolly, Vivien Londe, Anthony Leverrier, Nicolas Delfosse</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a decoder for the correction of erasures with hypergraph product codes, which form one of the most popular families of quantum LDPC codes. Our numerical simulations show that this decoder provides a close approximation of the maximum likelihood decoder that can be implemented in O(N^2) bit operations where N is the length of the quantum code. A probabilistic version of this decoder can be implemented in O(N^1.5) bit operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact and efficient Lanczos method on a quantum computer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.00567</link>
    <author>William Kirby, Mario Motta, Antonio Mezzacapo</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an algorithm that uses block encoding on a quantum computer to exactly construct a Krylov space, which can be used as the basis for the Lanczos method to estimate extremal eigenvalues of Hamiltonians. While the classical Lanczos method has exponential cost in the system size to represent the Krylov states for quantum systems, our efficient quantum algorithm achieves this in polynomial time and memory. The construction presented is exact in the sense that the resulting Krylov space is identical to that of the Lanczos method, so the only approximation with respect to the Lanczos method is due to finite sample noise. This is possible because, unlike previous quantum versions of the Lanczos method, our algorithm does not require simulating real or imaginary time evolution. We provide an explicit error bound for the resulting ground state energy estimate in the presence of noise. For this method to be successful, the only requirement on the input problem is that the overlap of the initial state with the true ground state must be $\Omega(1/\text{poly}(n))$ for $n$ qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-inspired permanent identities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.00327</link>
    <author>Ulysse Chabaud, Abhinav Deshpande, Saeed Mehraban</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The permanent is pivotal to both complexity theory and combinatorics. In quantum computing, the permanent appears in the expression of output amplitudes of linear optical computations, such as in the Boson Sampling model. Taking advantage of this connection, we give quantum-inspired proofs of many existing as well as new remarkable permanent identities. Beyond their purely combinatorial applications, our results demonstrate the classical hardness of exact and approximate sampling of linear optical quantum computations with input cat states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Continuity of quantum entropic quantities via almost convexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.00922</link>
    <author>Andreas Bluhm, Ángela Capel, Paul Gondolf, Antonio Pérez-Hernández</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Based on the proofs of the continuity of the conditional entropy by Alicki, Fannes, and Winter, we introduce in this work the almost locally affine (ALAFF) method. This method allows us to prove a great variety of continuity bounds for the derived entropic quantities. First, we apply the ALAFF method to the Umegaki relative entropy. This way, we recover known almost tight bounds, but also some new continuity bounds for the relative entropy. Subsequently, we apply our method to the Belavkin-Staszewski relative entropy (BS-entropy). This yields novel explicit bounds in particular for the BS-conditional entropy, the BS-mutual and BS-conditional mutual information. On the way, we prove almost concavity for the Umegaki relative entropy and the BS-entropy, which might be of independent interest. We conclude by showing some applications of these continuity bounds in various contexts within quantum information theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gradient-descent quantum process tomography by learning Kraus operators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.00812</link>
    <author>Shahnawaz Ahmed, Fernando Quijandría, Anton Frisk Kockum</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We perform quantum process tomography (QPT) for both discrete- and continuous-variable quantum systems by learning a process representation using Kraus operators. The Kraus form ensures that the reconstructed process is completely positive. To make the process trace-preserving, we use a constrained gradient-descent (GD) approach on the so-called Stiefel manifold during optimization to obtain the Kraus operators. Our ansatz uses a few Kraus operators to avoid direct estimation of large process matrices, e.g., the Choi matrix, for low-rank quantum processes. The GD-QPT matches the performance of both compressed-sensing (CS) and projected least-squares (PLS) QPT in benchmarks with two-qubit random processes, but shines by combining the best features of these two methods. Similar to CS (but unlike PLS), GD-QPT can reconstruct a process from just a small number of random measurements, and similar to PLS (but unlike CS) it also works for larger system sizes, up to at least five qubits. We envisage that the data-driven approach of GD-QPT can become a practical tool that greatly reduces the cost and computational effort for QPT in intermediate-scale quantum systems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>