<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>On classical simulation algorithms for noisy Boson Sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11532</link>
    <author>Changhun Oh, Liang Jiang, Bill Fefferman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present a classical algorithm that approximately samples from the output distribution of certain noisy Boson Sampling experiments. This algorithm is inspired by a recent result of Aharonov, Gao, Landau, Liu and Vazirani and makes use of an observation originally due to Kalai and Kindler that the output probability of Boson Sampling experiments with a Gaussian noise model can be approximated by sparse low-degree polynomials. This observation alone does not suffice for classical sampling, because its marginal probabilities might not be approximated by sparse low-degree polynomials, and furthermore, the approximated probabilities might be negative. We solve this problem by employing the first quantization representation to give an algorithm for computing the marginal probabilities of these experiments. We prove that when the overall noise rate is constant, the algorithm runs in time quasi-polynomial in the number of input photons $N$ and accuracy. When the overall noise rate scales as $1-x_1^\gamma$ for constant $x_1$ and $\gamma=\Omega(\log N)$, the running time becomes polynomial. Furthermore, we study noisy Boson Sampling with practically relevant noise models such as partial distinguishability and photon loss. We show that the same technique does not immediately apply in these settings, leaving open the possibility of a scalable demonstration of noisy quantum advantage for these noise models in certain parameter regimes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Everything is a quantum Ising model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11917</link>
    <author>Ruben Verresen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>This work shows that any $k$-local Hamiltonian of qubits can be obtained from a 4-state 'Ising' model with $k$-local diagonal interactions and a single-site transverse field -- giving a new theoretical and experimental handle on quantum matter. In particular, the classical Ising interactions can be determined by replacing each Pauli operator with a $4 \times 4$ diagonal matrix. Subsequently tuning a large transverse field projects out two of the four states, recovering the original qubit model, with qudit generalizations. This leads to striking correspondences, such as the spin-1/2 XY and Heisenberg models arising from the large-field limit of 3-state and 4-state Potts models, respectively. Similarly, the Kitaev honeycomb model emerges from classical interactions which enforce loop states on the honeycomb lattice. These generalized Ising models also display rich physics for smaller fields, including quantum criticality and topological phases of matter. This work expands what is experimentally achievable by showing how to realize any quantum spin model using only diagonal interactions and a tuneable field -- ingredients found in, e.g., tweezer arrays of Rydberg atoms or polar molecules. More broadly, 4-state spins can also be encoded in the positions of itinerant particles, exemplified by a Bose-Hubbard model realizing the Kitaev honeycomb model -- giving an experimental path to its $\mathbb Z_2$ and non-Abelian topological quantum liquids.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Security of differential phase shift QKD from relativistic principles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11340</link>
    <author>Martin Sandfuchs, Marcus Haberland, V. Vilasini, Ramona Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The design of quantum protocols for secure key generation poses many challenges: On the one hand, they need to be practical concerning experimental realisations. On the other hand, their theoretical description must be simple enough to allow for a security proof against all possible attacks. Often, these two requirements are in conflict with each other, and the differential phase shift (DPS) QKD protocol is an excellent example of this: It is designed to be implementable with current optical telecommunication technology, which, for this protocol, comes at the cost that many standard security proof techniques do not apply to it. In this work, we give the first full security proof of DPS QKD against general attacks, including finite-size effects. The proof combines techniques from quantum information theory, quantum optics, and relativity. We first give a security proof of a QKD protocol whose security stems from relativistic constraints. We then show that DPS QKD can be formulated as an instance of the relativistic protocol. In addition, we show that coherent attacks on the DPS protocol are, in fact, stronger than collective attacks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved machine learning algorithm for predicting ground state properties</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.13169</link>
    <author>Laura Lewis, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Viet T. Tran, Sebastian Lehner, Richard Kueng, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Finding the ground state of a quantum many-body system is a fundamental problem in quantum physics. In this work, we give a classical machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting ground state properties with an inductive bias encoding geometric locality. The proposed ML model can efficiently predict ground state properties of an $n$-qubit gapped local Hamiltonian after learning from only $\mathcal{O}(\log(n))$ data about other Hamiltonians in the same quantum phase of matter. This improves substantially upon previous results that require $\mathcal{O}(n^c)$ data for a large constant $c$. Furthermore, the training and prediction time of the proposed ML model scale as $\mathcal{O}(n \log n)$ in the number of qubits $n$. Numerical experiments on physical systems with up to 45 qubits confirm the favorable scaling in predicting ground state properties using a small training dataset.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement Purification of Hypergraph States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11341</link>
    <author>Lina Vandré, Otfried Gühne</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement purification describes a primitive in quantum information processing, where several copies of noisy quantum states are distilled into few copies of nearly-pure states of high quality via local operations and classical communication. Especially in the multiparticle case, the task of entanglement purification is complicated, as many inequivalent forms of pure state entanglement exist and purification protocols need to be tailored for different target states. In this paper we present optimized protocols for the purification of hypergraph states, which form a family of multi-qubit states that are relevant from several perspectives. We start by reformulating an existing purification protocol in a graphical language. This allows for systematical optimization and we present improvements in three directions. First, one can optimize the sequences of the protocol with respect to the ordering of the parties. Second, one can use adaptive schemes, where the measurement results obtained within the protocol are used to modify the protocols. Finally, one can improve the protocol with respect to the efficiency, requiring fewer copies of noisy states to reach a certain target state.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>