<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Ultimate limits of exoplanet spectroscopy: a quantum approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06050</link>
    <author>Zixin Huang, Christian Schwab, Cosmo Lupo</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One of the big challenges in exoplanet science is to determine the atmospheric makeup of extrasolar planets, and to find biosignatures that hint at the existence of biochemical processes on another world. The biomarkers we are trying to detect are gases in the exoplanet atmosphere like oxygen or methane, which have deep absorption features in the visible and near-infrared spectrum. Here we establish the ultimate quantum limit for determining the presence or absence of a spectral absorption line, for a dim source in the presence of a much brighter stellar source. We characterise the associated error exponent in both the frameworks of symmetric and asymmetric hypothesis testing. We found that a structured measurement based on spatial demultiplexing allows us to decouple the light coming from the planet and achieve the ultimate quantum limits. If the planet has intensity $\epsilon \ll 1$ relative to the star, we show that this approach significantly outperforms direct spectroscopy yielding an improvement of the error exponent by a factor $1/\epsilon$. We find the optimal measurement, which is a combination of interferometric techniques and spectrum analysis.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The meso-inflationary QCD axion</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06421</link>
    <author>Michele Redi, Andrea Tesi</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the possibility that the axion Peccei-Quinn symmetry is spontaneously broken after the beginning of inflation. This scenario interpolates between pre-inflationary and post-inflationary axion cosmology with significant phenomenological differences from both. Since the axion is not present at the early stages of inflation large inflationary fluctuations are produced only at scales not constrained by CMB, avoiding the strongest isocurvature constraints. The energy density in isocurvature perturbations at short scales however can be comparable with the adiabatic contribution from misalignment. These large overdensities can lead to the formation of axion mini-clusters and also to constraints from Lyman-$\alpha$ forest and future CMB spectral distortion measurements. If Peccei-Quinn symmetry is broken during the first O(25) e-foldings of inflation no axions are produced from the string network but contributions from the annihilation of domain walls can further boost the abundance. This scenario is minimally realized if the Hubble scale during inflation drops below the Peccei-Quinn symmetry breaking scale but other realizations are possible.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Architectural Bottleneck Principle</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06420</link>
    <author>Tiago Pimentel, Josef Valvoda, Niklas Stoehr, Ryan Cotterell</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we seek to measure how much information a component in a neural network could extract from the representations fed into it. Our work stands in contrast to prior probing work, most of which investigates how much information a model's representations contain. This shift in perspective leads us to propose a new principle for probing, the architectural bottleneck principle: In order to estimate how much information a given component could extract, a probe should look exactly like the component. Relying on this principle, we estimate how much syntactic information is available to transformers through our attentional probe, a probe that exactly resembles a transformer's self-attention head. Experimentally, we find that, in three models (BERT, ALBERT, and RoBERTa), a sentence's syntax tree is mostly extractable by our probe, suggesting these models have access to syntactic information while composing their contextual representations. Whether this information is actually used by these models, however, remains an open question.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Infinite Variance Problem in Fermion Models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06419</link>
    <author>Andrei Alexandru, Paulo Bedaque, Andrea Carosso, Hyunwoo Oh</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Monte Carlo calculations of fermionic systems with continuous auxiliary fields frequently suffer from a diverging variance. If a system has the infinite variance problem, one cannot estimate observables reliably even with an infinite number of samples. In this paper, we explore a method to deal with this problem based on sampling according to the distribution of a system with an extra time-slice. The necessary reweighting factor is computed both perturbatively and through a secondary Monte Carlo. We show that the Monte Carlo reweigthing coupled to the use of a non-biased estimator of the reweigthing factor leads to a method that eliminates the infinite variance problem at a very small extra cost. We compute the double occupancy in the Hubbard model at half-filling to demonstrate the method and compare the results to well established results obtained by other methods.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Re-Analyze Gauss: Bounds for Private Matrix Approximation via Dyson Brownian Motion</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06418</link>
    <author>Oren Mangoubi, Nisheeth K. Vishnoi</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a symmetric matrix $M$ and a vector $\lambda$, we present new bounds on the Frobenius-distance utility of the Gaussian mechanism for approximating $M$ by a matrix whose spectrum is $\lambda$, under $(\varepsilon,\delta)$-differential privacy. Our bounds depend on both $\lambda$ and the gaps in the eigenvalues of $M$, and hold whenever the top $k+1$ eigenvalues of $M$ have sufficiently large gaps. When applied to the problems of private rank-$k$ covariance matrix approximation and subspace recovery, our bounds yield improvements over previous bounds. Our bounds are obtained by viewing the addition of Gaussian noise as a continuous-time matrix Brownian motion. This viewpoint allows us to track the evolution of eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the matrix, which are governed by stochastic differential equations discovered by Dyson. These equations allow us to bound the utility as the square-root of a sum-of-squares of perturbations to the eigenvectors, as opposed to a sum of perturbation bounds obtained via Davis-Kahan-type theorems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>