<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Algorithms for Approximating Quantum Partition Functions at Low Temperature</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06533</link>
    <author>Tyler Helmuth, Ryan L. Mann</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish an efficient approximation algorithm for the partition functions of a class of quantum spin systems at low temperature, which can be viewed as stable quantum perturbations of classical spin systems. Our algorithm is based on combining the contour representation of quantum spin systems of this type due to Borgs, Kotecký, and Ueltschi with the algorithmic framework developed by Helmuth, Perkins, and Regts, and Borgs et al.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A circuit-level protocol and analysis for twist-based lattice surgery</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05678</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Lattice surgery is a measurement-based technique for performing fault-tolerant quantum computation in two dimensions. When using the surface code, the most general lattice surgery operations require lattice irregularities called twist defects. However, implementing twist-based lattice surgery may require additional resources, such as extra device connectivity, and could lower the threshold and overall performance for the surface code. Here we provide an explicit twist-based lattice surgery protocol and its requisite connectivity layout. We also provide new stabilizer measurement circuits for measuring twist defects which are compatible with our chosen gate scheduling. We undertake the first circuit-level error correction simulations during twist-based lattice surgery using a biased depolarizing noise model. Our results indicate a slight decrease in the threshold for timelike logical failures compared to lattice surgery protocols with no twist defects in the bulk. However, comfortably below threshold (i.e. with CNOT infidelities below $5 \times 10^{-3}$), the performance degradation is mild and in fact preferable over proposed alternative twist-free schemes. Lastly, we provide an efficient scheme for measuring $Y$ operators along boundaries of surface codes which bypasses certain steps that were required in previous schemes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gaussian Elimination versus Greedy Methods for the Synthesis of Linear Reversible Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06508</link>
    <author>Timothée Goubault de Brugière, Marc Baboulin, Benoît Valiron, Simon Martiel, Cyril Allouche</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Linear reversible circuits represent a subclass of reversible circuits with many applications in quantum computing. These circuits can be efficiently simulated by classical computers and their size is polynomially bounded by the number of qubits, making them a good candidate to deploy efficient methods to reduce computational costs. We propose a new algorithm for synthesizing any linear reversible operator by using an optimized version of the Gaussian elimination algorithm coupled with a tuned LU factorization. We also improve the scalability of purely greedy methods. Overall, on random operators, our algorithms improve the state-of-the-art methods for specific ranges of problem sizes: the custom Gaussian elimination algorithm provides the best results for large problem sizes (n > 150) while the purely greedy methods provide quasi optimal results when n < 30. On a benchmark of reversible functions, we manage to significantly reduce the CNOT count and the depth of the circuit while keeping other metrics of importance (T-count, T-depth) as low as possible.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decoding techniques applied to the compilation of CNOT circuits for NISQ architectures</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06457</link>
    <author>Timothée Goubault de Brugière, Marc Baboulin, Benoît Valiron, Simon Martiel, Cyril Allouche</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Current proposals for quantum compilers require the synthesis and optimization of linear reversible circuits and among them CNOT circuits. Since these circuits represent a significant part of the cost of running an entire quantum circuit, we aim at reducing their size. In this paper we present a new algorithm for the synthesis of CNOT circuits based on the solution of the syndrome decoding problem. Our method addresses the case of ideal hardware with an all-to-all qubit connectivity and the case of near-term quantum devices with restricted connectivity. For both cases, we present benchmarks showing that our algorithm outperforms existing algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reducing the Depth of Linear Reversible Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06380</link>
    <author>Timothée Goubault de Brugière, Marc Baboulin, Benoît Valiron, Simon Martiel, Cyril Allouche</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In quantum computing the decoherence time of the qubits determines the computation time available and this time is very limited when using current hardware. In this paper we minimize the execution time (the depth) for a class of circuits referred to as linear reversible circuits, which has many applications in quantum computing (e.g., stabilizer circuits, CNOT+T circuits, etc.). We propose a practical formulation of a divide and conquer algorithm that produces quantum circuits that are twice as shallow as those produced by existing algorithms. We improve the theoretical upper bound of the depth in the worst case for some range of qubits. We also propose greedy algorithms based on cost minimization to find more optimal circuits for small or simple operators. Overall, we manage to consistently reduce the total depth of a class of reversible functions, with up to 92% savings in an ancilla-free case and up to 99% when ancillary qubits are available.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>