<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking the Planar Honeycomb Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11845</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney, Michael Newman</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We improve the planar honeycomb code by describing boundaries that need no additional physical connectivity, and by optimizing the shape of the qubit patch. We then benchmark the code using Monte Carlo sampling to estimate logical error rates and derive metrics including thresholds, lambdas, and teraquop qubit counts. We determine that the planar honeycomb code can create a logical qubit with one-in-a-trillion logical error rates using 7000 physical qubits at a 0.1% gate-level error rate (or 900 physical qubits given native two-qubit parity measurements). Our results cement the honeycomb code as a promising candidate for two-dimensional qubit architectures with sparse connectivity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Performance of planar Floquet codes with Majorana-based qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11829</link>
    <author>Adam Paetznick, Christina Knapp, Nicolas Delfosse, Bela Bauer, Jeongwan Haah, Matthew B. Hastings, Marcus P. da Silva</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction is crucial for any quantum computing platform to achieve truly scalable quantum computation. The surface code and its variants have been considered the most promising quantum error correction scheme due to their high threshold, low overhead, and relatively simple structure that can naturally be implemented in many existing qubit architectures, such as superconducting qubits. The recent development of Floquet codes offers another promising approach. By going beyond the usual paradigm of stabilizer codes, Floquet codes achieve similar performance while being constructed entirely from two-qubit measurements. This makes them particularly suitable for platforms where two-qubit measurements can be implemented directly, such as measurement-only topological qubits based on Majorana zero modes (MZMs). Here, we explain how two variants of Floquet codes can be implemented on MZM-based architectures without any auxiliary qubits for syndrome measurement and with shallow syndrome extraction sequences. We then numerically demonstrate their favorable performance. In particular, we show that they improve the threshold for scalable quantum computation in MZM-based systems by an order of magnitude, and significantly reduce space and time overheads below threshold.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bounding quantum capacities via partial orders and complementarity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11688</link>
    <author>Christoph Hirche, Felix Leditzky</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum capacities are fundamental quantities that are notoriously hard to compute and can exhibit surprising properties such as superadditivity. Thus, a vast amount of literature is devoted to finding tight and computable bounds on these capacities. We add a new viewpoint by giving operationally motivated bounds on several capacities, including the quantum capacity and private capacity of a quantum channel and the one-way distillable entanglement and private key of a quantum state. These bounds are generally phrased in terms of capacity quantities involving the complementary channel or state. As a tool to obtain these bounds, we discuss partial orders on quantum channels and states, such as the less noisy and the more capable order. Our bounds help to further understand the interplay between different capacities, as they give operational limitations on superadditivity and the difference between capacities in terms of the information-theoretic properties of the complementary channel or state. They can also be used as a new approach towards numerically bounding capacities, as discussed with some examples.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hybrid Quantum-Classical Search Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11443</link>
    <author>Ansis Rosmanis</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Search is one of the most commonly used primitives in quantum algorithm design. It is known that quadratic speedups provided by Grover's algorithm are optimal, and no faster quantum algorithms for Search exist. While it is known that at least some quantum computation is required to achieve these speedups, the existing bounds do not rule out the possibility of an equally fast hybrid quantum-classical algorithm where most of the computation is classical. In this work, we study such hybrid algorithms and we show that classical computation, unless it by itself can solve the Search problem, cannot assist quantum computation. In addition, we generalize this result to algorithms with subconstant success probabilities.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Towards a general framework of Randomized Benchmarking for non-Markovian Noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11338</link>
    <author>Pedro Figueroa-Romero, Kavan Modi, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The rapid progress in the development of quantum devices is in large part due to the availability of a wide range of characterization techniques allowing to probe, test and adjust them. Nevertheless, these methods often make use of approximations that hold in rather simplistic circumstances. In particular, assuming that error mechanisms stay constant in time and have no dependence in the past, is something that will be impossible to do as quantum processors continue scaling up in depth and size. We establish a theoretical framework for the Randomized Benchmarking protocol encompassing temporally-correlated, so-called non-Markovian noise, at the gate level, for any gate set belonging to a wide class of finite groups. We obtain a general expression for the Average Sequence Fidelity (ASF) and propose a way to obtain average gate fidelities of full non-Markovian noise processes. Moreover, we obtain conditions that are fulfilled when an ASF displays authentic non-Markovian deviations. Finally, we show that even though gate-dependence does not translate into a perturbative term within the ASF, as in the Markovian case, the non-Markovian sequence fidelity nevertheless remains stable under small gate-dependent perturbations.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>