<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Early Days of Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09964</link>
    <author>Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I recount some of my memories of the early development of quantum computation, including the discovery of the factoring algorithm, of error correcting codes, and of fault tolerance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Resource theory of quantum scrambling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.10477</link>
    <author>Roy J. Garcia, Kaifeng Bu, Arthur Jaffe</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum scrambling refers to the spread of local quantum information into the many degrees of freedom of a quantum system. In this work, we introduce a resource theory of scrambling which incorporates two mechanisms, "entanglement scrambling" and "magic scrambling". We introduce two resource monotones called the Pauli growth and the OTOC (out-of-time-ordered correlator) magic for these two mechanisms, respectively. Moreover, we show that OTOC fluctuations are bounded by the OTOC magic. This proves that small OTOC fluctuations are an indication of magic in Google's recent experiment (Science 374, 1479 (2021)). We also show that both resource monotones can be used to bound the decoding fidelity in the Hayden-Preskill protocol. These applications provide an operational interpretation of the resource monotones defined in this work.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational quantum iterative power algorithms for global optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.10470</link>
    <author>Thi Ha Kyaw, Micheline B. Soley, Brandon Allen, Paul Bergold, Chong Sun, Victor S. Batista, Alán Aspuru-Guzik</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a family of variational quantum algorithms called quantum iterative power algorithms (QIPA) that outperform existing hybrid near-term quantum algorithms of the same kind. We demonstrate the capabilities of QIPA as applied to three different global-optimization numerical experiments: the ground-state optimization of the $H_2$ molecular dissociation, search of the transmon qubit ground-state, and biprime factorization. Since our algorithm is hybrid, quantum/classical technologies such as error mitigation and adaptive variational ansatzes can easily be incorporated into the algorithm. Due to the shallow quantum circuit requirements, we anticipate large-scale implementation and adoption of the proposed algorithm across current major quantum hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient algorithms for quantum information bottleneck</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.10342</link>
    <author>Masahito Hayashi, Yuxiang Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ability to extract relevant information is critical to learning. An ingenious approach as such is the information bottleneck, an optimisation problem whose solution corresponds to a faithful and memory-efficient representation of relevant information from a large system. The advent of the age of quantum computing calls for efficient methods that work on information regarding quantum systems. Here we address this by proposing a new and general algorithm for the quantum generalisation of information bottleneck. Our algorithm excels in the speed and the definiteness of convergence compared with prior results. It also works for a much broader range of problems, including the quantum extension of deterministic information bottleneck, an important variant of the original information bottleneck problem. Notably, we discover that a quantum system can achieve strictly better performance than a classical system of the same size regarding quantum information bottleneck, providing new vision on justifying the advantage of quantum machine learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Micius quantum experiments in space</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.10236</link>
    <author>Chao-Yang Lu, Yuan Cao, Cheng-Zhi Peng, Jian-Wei Pan</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum theory has been successfully validated in numerous laboratory experiments. But would such a theory, which excellently describes the behavior of microscopic physical systems, and its predicted phenomena such as quantum entanglement, be still applicable on very large length scales? From a practical perspective, how can quantum key distribution -- where the security of establishing secret keys between distant parties is ensured by the laws of quantum mechanics -- be made technologically useful on a global scale? Due to photon loss in optical fibers and terrestrial free space, the achievable distance using direct transmission of single photons has been limited to a few hundred kilometers. A promising route to testing quantum physics over long distances and in the relativistic regimes, and thus realizing flexible global-scale quantum networks is via the use of satellites and space-based technologies, where a significant advantage is that the photon loss and turbulence predominantly occurs in the lower ~ 10 km of the atmosphere, and most of the photons' transmission path in the space is virtually in vacuum with almost zero absorption and decoherence. In this Article, we review the progress in free-space quantum experiments, with a focus on the fast-developing Micius satellite-based quantum communications. The perspective of space-ground integrated quantum networks and fundamental quantum optics experiments in space conceivable with satellites are discussed.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>