<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The QAOA with Slow Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06845</link>
    <author>Anthony Polloreno, Graeme Smith</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) was originally developed to solve combinatorial optimization problems, but has become a standard for assessing the performance of quantum computers. Fully descriptive benchmarking techniques are often prohibitively expensive for large numbers of qubits ($n \gtrsim 10$), so the QAOA often serves in practice as a computational benchmark. The QAOA involves a classical optimization subroutine that attempts to find optimal parameters for a quantum subroutine. Unfortunately, many optimizers used for the QAOA require many shots ($N \gtrsim 1000$) per point in parameter space to get a reliable estimate of the energy being minimized. However, some experimental quantum computing platforms such as neutral atom quantum computers have slow repetition rates, placing unique requirements on the classical optimization subroutine used in the QAOA in these systems. In this paper we investigate the performance of a gradient free classical optimizer for the QAOA - dual annealing - and demonstrate that optimization is possible even with $N=1$ and $n=16$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hay from the haystack: explicit examples of exponential quantum circuit complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06977</link>
    <author>Yifan Jia, Michael M. Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The vast majority of quantum states and unitaries have circuit complexity exponential in the number of qubits. In a similar vein, most of them also have exponential minimum description length, which makes it difficult to pinpoint examples of exponential complexity. In this work, we construct examples of constant description length but exponential circuit complexity. We provide infinite families such that each element requires an exponential number of two-qubit gates to be generated exactly from a product and where the same is true for the approximate generation of the vast majority of elements in the family. The results are based on sets of large transcendence degree and discussed for tensor networks, diagonal unitaries, and maximally coherent states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Power and limitations of single-qubit native quantum neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.07848</link>
    <author>Zhan Yu, Hongshun Yao, Mujin Li, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum neural networks (QNNs) have emerged as a leading strategy to establish applications in machine learning, chemistry, and optimization. While the applications of QNN have been widely investigated, its theoretical foundation remains less understood. In this paper, we formulate a theoretical framework for the expressive ability of data re-uploading quantum neural networks that consist of interleaved encoding circuit blocks and trainable circuit blocks. First, we prove that single-qubit quantum neural networks can approximate any univariate function by mapping the model to a partial Fourier series. Beyond previous works' understanding of existence, we in particular establish the exact correlations between the parameters of the trainable gates and the working Fourier coefficients, by exploring connections to quantum signal processing. Second, we discuss the limitations of single-qubit native QNNs on approximating multivariate functions by analyzing the frequency spectrum and the flexibility of Fourier coefficients. We further demonstrate the expressivity and limitations of single-qubit native QNNs via numerical experiments. As applications, we introduce natural extensions to multi-qubit quantum neural networks, which exhibit the capability of classifying real-world multi-dimensional data. We believe these results would improve our understanding of QNNs and provide a helpful guideline for designing powerful QNNs for machine learning tasks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational learning algorithms for quantum query complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.07449</link>
    <author>Zipeng Wu, Shi-Yao Hou, Chao Zhang, Lvzhou Li, Bei Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum query complexity plays an important role in studying quantum algorithms, which captures the most known quantum algorithms, such as search and period finding. A query algorithm applies $U_tO_x\cdots U_1O_xU_0$ to some input state, where $O_x$ is the oracle dependent on some input variable $x$, and $U_i$s are unitary operations that are independent of $x$, followed by some measurements for readout. In this work, we develop variational learning algorithms to study quantum query complexity, by formulating $U_i$s as parameterized quantum circuits and introducing a loss function that is directly given by the error probability of the query algorithm. We apply our method to analyze various cases of quantum query complexity, including a new algorithm solving the Hamming modulo problem with $4$ queries for the case of $5$-bit modulo $5$, answering an open question raised in arXiv:2112.14682, and the result is further confirmed by a Semidefinite Programming (SDP) algorithm. Compared with the SDP algorithm, our method can be readily implemented on the near-term Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) devices and is more flexible to be adapted to other cases such as the fractional query models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Packet Switching in Quantum Networks: A Path to Quantum Internet</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.07507</link>
    <author>Stephen DiAdamo, Bing Qi, Glen Miller, Ramana Kompella, Alireza Shabani</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Large-scale quantum networks with thousands of nodes require scalable network protocols and physical hardware to realize. In this work, we introduce packet switching as a new paradigm for quantum data transmission in both future and near-term quantum networks. We propose a classical-quantum data frame structure and explore methods of frame generation and processing. Further, we present conceptual designs for a quantum reconfigurable optical add-drop multiplexer to realize the proposed transmission scheme. Packet switching allows for a universal design for a next generation Internet where classical and quantum data share the same network protocols and infrastructure. In this new quantum networking paradigm, entanglement distribution, as with quantum key distribution, is an application built on top of the quantum network rather than as a network designed especially for those purposes. For analysis of the network model, we simulate the feasibility of quantum packet switching for some preliminary models of quantum key and entanglement distribution. Finally, we discuss how our model can be integrated with other network models toward a realization of a quantum Internet.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>