<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Preparing Many Copies of a Quantum State in the Black-Box Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11014</link>
    <author>Yassine Hamoudi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a simple quantum algorithm for preparing $K$ copies of an $N$-dimensional quantum state whose amplitudes are given by a quantum oracle. Our result extends a previous work of Grover, who showed how to prepare one copy in time $O(\sqrt{N})$. In comparison with the naive $O(K\sqrt{N})$ solution obtained by repeating this procedure~$K$ times, our algorithm achieves the optimal running time of $\theta(\sqrt{KN})$. Our technique uses a refinement of the quantum rejection sampling method employed by Grover. As a direct application, we obtain a similar speed-up for obtaining $K$ independent samples from a distribution whose probability vector is given by a quantum oracle.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Faster Quantum Algorithm for Semidefinite Programming via Robust IPM Framework</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11154</link>
    <author>Baihe Huang, Shunhua Jiang, Zhao Song, Runzhou Tao, Ruizhe Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This paper studies a fundamental problem in convex optimization, which is to solve semidefinite programming (SDP) with high accuracy. This paper follows from existing robust SDP-based interior point method analysis due to [Huang, Jiang, Song, Tao and Zhang, FOCS 2022]. While, the previous work only provides an efficient implementation in the classical setting. This work provides a novel quantum implementation. We give a quantum second-order algorithm with high-accuracy in both the optimality and the feasibility of its output, and its running time depending on $\log(1/\epsilon)$ on well-conditioned instances. Due to the limitation of quantum itself or first-order method, all the existing quantum SDP solvers either have polynomial error dependence or low-accuracy in the feasibility.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection: Hardness based on a Weak Quantum Conjecture</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11068</link>
    <author>Andris Ambainis, Harry Buhrman, Koen Leijnse, Subhasree Patro, Florian Speelman</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classically, for many computational problems one can conclude time lower bounds conditioned on the hardness of one or more of key problems: k-SAT, 3SUM and APSP. More recently, similar results have been derived in the quantum setting conditioned on the hardness of k-SAT and 3SUM. This is done using fine-grained reductions, where the approach is to (1) select a key problem $X$ that, for some function $T$, is conjectured to not be solvable by any $O(T(n)^{1-\epsilon})$ time algorithm for any constant $\epsilon > 0$ (in a fixed model of computation), and (2) reduce $X$ in a fine-grained way to these computational problems, thus giving (mostly) tight conditional time lower bounds for them. Interestingly, for Delta-Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection, classical hardness results have been derived conditioned on hardness of all three mentioned key problems. More precisely, it is proven that an $n^{3-\epsilon}$ time classical algorithm for either of these two graph problems would imply faster classical algorithms for k-SAT, 3SUM and APSP, which makes Delta-Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection worthwhile to study. In this paper, we show that an $n^{1.5-\epsilon}$ time quantum algorithm for either of these two graph problems would imply faster quantum algorithms for k-SAT, 3SUM, and APSP. We first formulate a quantum hardness conjecture for APSP and then present quantum reductions from k-SAT, 3SUM, and APSP to Delta-Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection. Additionally, based on the quantum APSP conjecture, we are also able to prove quantum lower bounds for a matrix problem and many graph problems. The matching upper bounds follow trivially for most of them, except for Delta-Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection for which we present quantum algorithms that require careful use of data structures and Ambainis' variable time search.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A route towards engineering many-body localization in real materials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.10696</link>
    <author>A. Nietner, A. Kshetrimayum, J. Eisert, B. Lake</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The interplay of interactions and disorder in a quantum many body system may lead to the elusive phenomenon of many body localization (MBL). It has been observed under precisely controlled conditions in synthetic quantum many-body systems, but to detect it in actual quantum materials seems challenging. In this work, we present a path to synthesize real materials that show signatures of many body localization by mixing different species of materials in the laboratory. To provide evidence for the functioning of our approach, we perform a detailed tensor-network based numerical analysis to study the effects of various doping ratios of the constituting materials. Moreover, in order to provide guidance to experiments, we investigate different choices of actual candidate materials. To address the challenge of how to achieve stability under heating, we study the effect of the electron-phonon coupling, focusing on effectively one dimensional materials embedded in one, two and three dimensional lattices. We analyze how this coupling affects the MBL and provide an intuitive microscopic description of the interplay between the electronic degrees of freedom and the lattice vibrations. Our work provides a guideline for the necessary conditions on the properties of the ingredient materials and, as such, serves as a road map to experimentally synthesizing real quantum materials exhibiting signatures of MBL.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Analytical bounds for non-asymptotic asymmetric state discrimination</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.10699</link>
    <author>Jason L. Pereira, Leonardo Banchi, Stefano Pirandola</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two types of errors can occur when discriminating pairs of quantum states. Asymmetric state discrimination involves minimising the probability of one type of error, subject to a constraint on the other. We give explicit expressions bounding the set of achievable errors, using the trace norm, the fidelity, and the quantum Chernoff bound. The upper bound is asymptotically tight and the lower bound is exact for pure states. Unlike asymptotic bounds, our bounds give error values instead of exponents, so can give more precise results when applied to finite-copy state discrimination problems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>