<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Publicly verifiable quantum money from random lattices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13135</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu, Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Publicly verifiable quantum money is a protocol for the preparation of quantum states that can be efficiently verified by any party for authenticity but is computationally infeasible to counterfeit. We develop a cryptographic scheme for publicly verifiable quantum money based on Gaussian superpositions over random lattices. We introduce a verification-of-authenticity procedure based on the lattice discrete Fourier transform, and subsequently prove the unforgeability of our quantum money under the hardness of the short vector problem from lattice-based cryptography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Do Quantum Circuit Born Machines Generalize?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13645</link>
    <author>Kaitlin Gili, Mohamed Hibat-Allah, Marta Mauri, Chris Ballance, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In recent proposals of quantum circuit models for generative tasks, the discussion about their performance has been limited to their ability to reproduce a known target distribution. For example, expressive model families such as Quantum Circuit Born Machines (QCBMs) have been almost entirely evaluated on their capability to learn a given target distribution with high accuracy. While this aspect may be ideal for some tasks, it limits the scope of a generative model's assessment to its ability to memorize data rather than generalize. As a result, there has been little understanding of a model's generalization performance and the relation between such capability and the resource requirements, e.g., the circuit depth and the amount of training data. In this work, we leverage upon a recently proposed generalization evaluation framework to begin addressing this knowledge gap. We first investigate the QCBM's learning process of a cardinality-constrained distribution and see an increase in generalization performance while increasing the circuit depth. In the 12-qubit example presented here, we observe that with as few as 30% of the valid patterns as the training set, the QCBM exhibits the best generalization performance toward generating unseen and valid patterns. Lastly, we assess the QCBM's ability to generalize not only to valid features, but to high-quality bitstrings distributed according to an adequately biased distribution. We see that the QCBM is able to effectively learn the bias and generate unseen samples with higher quality than those in the training set. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work in the literature that presents the QCBM's generalization performance as an integral evaluation metric for quantum generative models, and demonstrates the QCBM's ability to generalize to high-quality, desired novel samples.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matchgate Shadows for Fermionic Quantum Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13723</link>
    <author>Kianna Wan, William J. Huggins, Joonho Lee, Ryan Babbush</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>"Classical shadows" are estimators of an unknown quantum state, constructed from suitably distributed random measurements on copies of that state [Nature Physics 16, 1050-1057]. Here, we analyze classical shadows obtained using random matchgate circuits, which correspond to fermionic Gaussian unitaries. We prove that the first three moments of the Haar distribution over the continuous group of matchgate circuits are equal to those of the discrete uniform distribution over only the matchgate circuits that are also Clifford unitaries; thus, the latter forms a "matchgate 3-design." This implies that the classical shadows resulting from the two ensembles are functionally equivalent. We show how one can use these matchgate shadows to efficiently estimate inner products between an arbitrary quantum state and fermionic Gaussian states, as well as the expectation values of local fermionic operators and various other quantities, thus surpassing the capabilities of prior work. As a concrete application, this enables us to apply wavefunction constraints that control the fermion sign problem in the quantum-classical auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm (QC-AFQMC) [Nature 603, 416-420], without the exponential post-processing cost incurred by the original approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time-energy uncertainty relation for noisy quantum metrology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13707</link>
    <author>Philippe Faist, Mischa P. Woods, Victor V. Albert, Joseph M. Renes, Jens Eisert, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Detection of weak forces and precise measurement of time are two of the many applications of quantum metrology to science and technology. We consider a quantum system initialized in a pure state and whose evolution is goverened by a Hamiltonian $H$; a measurement can later estimate the time $t$ for which the system has evolved. In this work, we introduce and study a fundamental trade-off which relates the amount by which noise reduces the accuracy of a quantum clock to the amount of information about the energy of the clock that leaks to the environment. Specifically, we consider an idealized scenario in which Alice prepares an initial pure state of the clock, allows the clock to evolve for a time $t$ that is not precisely known, and then transmits the clock through a noisy channel to Bob. The environment (Eve) receives any information that is lost. We prove that Bob's loss of quantum Fisher information (QFI) about $t$ is equal to Eve's gain of QFI about a complementary energy parameter. We also prove a more general trade-off that applies when Bob and Eve wish to estimate the values of parameters associated with two non-commuting observables. We derive the necessary and sufficient conditions for the accuracy of the clock to be unaffected by the noise. These are a subset of the Knill-Laflamme error-correction conditions; states satisfying these conditions are said to form a metrological code. We provide a scheme to construct metrological codes in the stabilizer formalism. We show that there are metrological codes that cannot be written as a quantum error-correcting code with similar distance in which the Hamiltonian acts as a logical operator, potentially offering new schemes for constructing states that do not lose any sensitivity upon application of a noisy channel. We discuss applications of our results to sensing using a many-body state subject to erasure or amplitude-damping noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entropic and trace distance based measures of non-Markovianity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13183</link>
    <author>Federico Settimo, Heinz-Peter Breuer, Bassano Vacchini</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze and compare different measures for the degree of non-Markovianity in the dynamics of open quantum systems. These measures are based on the distinguishability of quantum states which is quantified, on the one hand, by the trace distance or, more generally, by the trace norm of the Helstrom matrix, and, on the other hand, by entropic quantifiers: the Jensen-Shannon divergence, the Holevo or the quantum skew divergence. We explicitly construct a qubit dynamics for which the trace norm based non-Markovianity measure is nonzero, while all the entropic measures turn out to be zero. This leads to the surprising conclusion that the non-Markovianity measure which employs the trace norm of the Helstrom matrix is strictly stronger than all entropic non-Markovianity measures.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>