<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum simulation of dynamical phase transitions in noisy quantum devices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08318</link>
    <author>Younes Javanmard, Ugne Liaubaite, Tobias J. Osborne, Luis Santos</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Zero-noise extrapolation provides an especially useful error mitigation method for noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices. Our analysis, based on matrix product density operators, of the transverse-field Ising model with depolarizing noise, reveals both advantages and inherent problems associated with zero-noise extrapolation when simulating non-equilibrium many-body dynamics. On the one hand, interestingly, noise alters systematically the behavior of the Loschmidt echo at the dynamical phase transition times, doubling the number of non-analytic points, and hence inducing an error that, inherently, cannot be mitigated. On the other, zero-noise extrapolation may be employed to recover quantum revivals of the Loschmidt echo, which would be completely missed in the absence of mitigation, and to retrieve faithfully noise-free inter-site correlations. Our results, which are in good agreement with those obtained using quantum simulators, reveal the potential of matrix product density operators for the investigation of the performance of quantum devices with a large number of qubits and deep noisy quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Highly optimized quantum circuits synthesized via data-flow engines</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07685</link>
    <author>Peter Rakyta, Gregory Morse, Jakab N치dori, Zita Majnay-Tak치cs, Oskar Mencer, Zolt치n Zimbor치s</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The formulation of quantum programs in terms of the fewest number of gate operations is crucial to retrieve meaningful results from the noisy quantum processors accessible these days. In this work, we demonstrate a use-case for Field Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) based data-flow engines (DFEs) to scale up variational quantum compilers to synthesize circuits up to $9$-qubit programs.This gate decomposer utilizes a newly developed DFE quantum computer simulator that is designed to simulate arbitrary quantum circuit consisting of single qubit rotations and controlled two-qubit gates on FPGA chips. In our benchmark with the QISKIT package, the depth of the circuits produced by the SQUANDER package (with the DFE accelerator support) were less by $97\%$ on average, while the fidelity of the circuits was still close to unity up to an error of $\sim10^{-4}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Intrinsic relationships of Quantum Resource Theories and their roles in Quantum Metrology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07975</link>
    <author>Abdallah Slaoui</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum resource theories allow us to quantify a useful quantum phenomenon, to develop new protocols for its detection and determine the exact processes that maximize its use for practical tasks. These theories aim at transforming physical phenomena, such as entanglement and quantum coherence, into useful properties for the execution of concrete tasks related to quantum information. In this thesis, we focus on the resource theories of entanglement, discord-like quantum correlations, and quantum coherence, the most intriguing quantum phenomena exploited so far in quantum information theory. We begin by presenting in detail the theoretical tools of these quantum resources, focusing on the most remarkable techniques and computational problems. In this sense, we discuss several mathematical methods that solve some problems related to their quantifications, and some analytical results for bipartite quantum systems are given. We also examine the intrinsic connections between these quantum resources by extracting the links that unite the corresponding measures. In contrast, the revolution of quantum technology has led to a growing interest in quantum metrology, and quantum entanglement has been employed to overcome the classical limit in several quantum estimation protocols. In this work, we analyze the role of quantum correlations beyond entanglement in improving the accuracy of an unknown parameter. According to our results, correlations can be captured using quantum Fisher information, and quantum discord correlations can be exploited to ensure the accuracy of phase estimation protocols. This thesis includes also the contributions on the dynamics of these quantum resources in various models of open quantum systems. Among our objectives, is to study the effects of the environment on these quantum resources and to obtain techniques to protect them from the effects of intrinsic decoherence.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complete monogamy of the multipartite quantum mutual information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07952</link>
    <author>Yu Guo, Lizhong Huang</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum mutual information (QMI) not only displays the mutual information in the system but also demonstrates some quantum correlation beyond entanglement. We explore here the two alternatives of multipartite quantum mutual information (MQMI) based on the von Neumann entropy according to the framework of the \textitcomplete measure of multi-particle quantum system. We show that these two MQMI are complete, monogamous on the three-qubit states, and one of them is not only \textitcompletely monogamous but also \textittightly complete monogamous while another one is not. Moreover, we present another two MQMI by replacing the von Neumann entropy with the Tasllis $q$-entropy from the former two ones. It is proved that one of them displays some degree of ``completeness'' as a measure of multi-particle quantum system, but the other one is not even non-negative and thus it can not be a alternative of MQMI. We also discuss the triangle relation for these three alternatives of MQMI. It is shown that the triangle inequalities hold for the former two MQMI as that of entanglement measure but the later one fails. By comparison, we found that the von Neumann entropy is better than other versions of entropy as desired when we characterize the quantum correlation in multi-particle system.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Real-time quantum error correction beyond break-even</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09116</link>
    <author>V. V. Sivak, A. Eickbusch, B. Royer, S. Singh, I. Tsioutsios, S. Ganjam, A. Miano, B. L. Brock, A. Z. Ding, L. Frunzio, S. M. Girvin, R. J. Schoelkopf, M. H. Devoret</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ambition of harnessing the quantum for computation is at odds with the fundamental phenomenon of decoherence. The purpose of quantum error correction (QEC) is to counteract the natural tendency of a complex system to decohere. This cooperative process, which requires participation of multiple quantum and classical components, creates a special type of dissipation that removes the entropy caused by the errors faster than the rate at which these errors corrupt the stored quantum information. Previous experimental attempts to engineer such a process faced an excessive generation of errors that overwhelmed the error-correcting capability of the process itself. Whether it is practically possible to utilize QEC for extending quantum coherence thus remains an open question. We answer it by demonstrating a fully stabilized and error-corrected logical qubit whose quantum coherence is significantly longer than that of all the imperfect quantum components involved in the QEC process, beating the best of them with a coherence gain of $G = 2.27 \pm 0.07$. We achieve this performance by combining innovations in several domains including the fabrication of superconducting quantum circuits and model-free reinforcement learning.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>