<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>An exact quantum hidden subgroup algorithm and applications to solvable groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04047</link>
    <author>Muhammad Imran, Gabor Ivanyos</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a polynomial time exact quantum algorithm for the hidden subgroup problem in $Z_{m^k}^n$. The algorithm uses the quantum Fourier transform modulo m and does not require factorization of m. For smooth m, i.e., when the prime factors of m are of size poly(log m), the quantum Fourier transform can be exactly computed using the method discovered independently by Cleve and Coppersmith, while for general m, the algorithm of Mosca and Zalka is available. Even for m=3 and k=1 our result appears to be new. We also present applications to compute the structure of abelian and solvable groups whose order has the same (but possibly unknown) prime factors as m. The applications for solvable groups also rely on an exact version of a technique proposed by Watrous for computing the uniform superposition of elements of subgroups.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal logic with encoded spin qubits in silicon</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03605</link>
    <author>Aaron J. Weinstein, Matthew D. Reed, Aaron M. Jones, Reed W. Andrews, David Barnes, Jacob Z. Blumoff, Larken E. Euliss, Kevin Eng, Bryan Fong, Sieu D. Ha, Daniel R. Hulbert, Clayton Jackson, Michael Jura, Tyler E. Keating, Joseph Kerckhoff, Andrey A. Kiselev, Justine Matten, Golam Sabbir, Aaron Smith, Jeffrey Wright, et al (3)</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Qubits encoded in a decoherence-free subsystem and realized in exchange-coupled silicon quantum dots are promising candidates for fault-tolerant quantum computing. Benefits of this approach include excellent coherence, low control crosstalk, and configurable insensitivity to certain error sources. Key difficulties are that encoded entangling gates require a large number of control pulses and high-yielding quantum dot arrays. Here we show a device made using the single-layer etch-defined gate electrode architecture that achieves both the required functional yield needed for full control and the coherence necessary for thousands of calibrated exchange pulses to be applied. We measure an average two-qubit Clifford fidelity of $97.1 \pm 0.2\%$ with randomized benchmarking. We also use interleaved randomized benchmarking to demonstrate the controlled-NOT gate with $96.3 \pm 0.7\%$ fidelity, SWAP with $99.3 \pm 0.5\%$ fidelity, and a specialized entangling gate that limits spreading of leakage with $93.8 \pm 0.7\%$ fidelity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Resource Marginal Problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03523</link>
    <author>Chung-Yun Hsieh, Gelo Noel M. Tabia, Yu-Chun Yin, Yeong-Cherng Liang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce the resource marginal problems, which concern the possibility of having a resource-free target subsystem compatible with a given collection of marginal density matrices. By identifying an appropriate choice of resource $R$ and target subsystem T, our problems reduce, respectively, to the well-known marginal problems for quantum states and the problem of determining if a given quantum system is a resource. More generally, we define a set of marginal states to be resource-free incompatible with a target subsystem T if all global states compatible with this set must result in a resourceful state in T. We show that this incompatibility induces a resource theory that can be quantified by a monotone. We derive necessary and sufficient conditions for this monotone to be a finite conic program and further show, via the corresponding witnesses, that resource-free incompatibility is equivalent to an operational advantage in some subchannel discrimination task. Via our framework, a clear connection can be established between any marginal problem (that involves some notion of incompatibility) for quantum states and a resource theory for quantum states. In addition, the universality of our framework leads, for example, to an immediate, quantitative understanding of the incompatibility associated with the recently-proposed entanglement marginal problems. As further applications, we provide the first example showing a form of transitivity of nonlocality (steerability) for quantum states. We discuss also the analogous framework in the dynamical regime and establish a set of theoretical results that closely mirror those obtained for a resource theory for quantum states. Again, they allow us to recover a wide variety of results related to the studies of channel marginal problems, channel resource theories, etc.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On quantum states over time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03607</link>
    <author>James Fullwood, Arthur J. Parzygnat</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In 2017, D. Horsman, C. Heunen, M. Pusey, J. Barrett, and R. Spekkens proved that there is no physically reasonable assignment that takes a quantum channel and an initial state and produces a joint state on the tensor product of the input and output spaces. The interpretation was that there is a clear distinction between space and time in the quantum setting that is not visible classically, where in the latter, one can freely use Bayes' theorem to go between joint states and marginals with noisy channels. In this paper, we prove that there actually is such a physically reasonable assignment, bypassing the no-go result of Horsman et al., and we illustrate that this is achievable by restricting the domain of their assignment to a domain which represents the given data more faithfully. This answers an open question at the end of their work, thus indicating the possibility that such a symmetry between space and time may exist in the quantum setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Shortest Paths without a Map, but with an Entropic Regularizer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04551</link>
    <author>Sébastien Bubeck, Christian Coester, Yuval Rabani</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a 1989 paper titled "shortest paths without a map", Papadimitriou and Yannakakis introduced an online model of searching in a weighted layered graph for a target node, while attempting to minimize the total length of the path traversed by the searcher. This problem, later called layered graph traversal, is parametrized by the maximum cardinality $k$ of a layer of the input graph. It is an online setting for dynamic programming, and it is known to be a rather general and fundamental model of online computing, which includes as special cases other acclaimed models. The deterministic competitive ratio for this problem was soon discovered to be exponential in $k$, and it is now nearly resolved: it lies between $\Omega(2^k)$ and $O(k2^k)$. Regarding the randomized competitive ratio, in 1993 Ramesh proved, surprisingly, that this ratio has to be at least $\Omega(k^2 / \log^{1+\epsilon} k)$ (for any constant $\epsilon > 0$). In the same paper, Ramesh also gave an $O(k^{13})$-competitive randomized online algorithm. Since 1993, no progress has been reported on the randomized competitive ratio of layered graph traversal. In this work we show how to apply the mirror descent framework on a carefully selected evolving metric space, and obtain an $O(k^2)$-competitive randomized online algorithm, nearly matching the known lower bound on the randomized competitive ratio.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>