<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Sample Complexity Lower Bound for Quantum State Tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11185</link>
    <author>Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that $\Omega(rd/\epsilon)$ copies of an unknown rank-$r$, dimension-$d$ quantum mixed state are necessary in order to learn a classical description with $1 - \epsilon$ fidelity. This improves upon the tomography lower bounds obtained by Haah, et al. and Wright.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11246</link>
    <author>Cica Gustiani, Richard Meister, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods offer a highly promising route to exploiting quantum computers for chemistry tasks. Here we employ methods described in a sister paper to the present report, entitled ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits, in order to solve problems using adaptively evolving quantum circuits. Consistent with prior authors we find that this approach can outperform human-designed circuits such as the coupled-cluster or hardware-efficient ansätze, and we make comparisons for larger instances up to 14 qubits. Moreover we introduce a novel approach to constraining the circuit evolution in the physically relevant subspace, finding that this greatly improves performance and compactness of the circuits. We consider both static and dynamics properties of molecular systems. The emulation environments used is QuESTlink; all resources are open source and linked from this paper.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploring ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11245</link>
    <author>Richard Meister, Cica Gustiani, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gate-level quantum circuits are often derived manually from higher level algorithms. While this suffices for small implementations and demonstrations, ultimately automatic circuit design will be required to realise complex algorithms using hardware-specific operations and connectivity. Here we explore methods for the ab initio creation of circuits within a machine, either a classical computer or a hybrid quantum-classical device. We consider a range of techniques including: methods for introducing new gate structures, optimisation of parameterised circuits and choices of cost functions, and efficient removal of low-value gates exploiting the quantum geometric tensor and other heuristics. Using these principles we tackle the tasks of automatic encoding of unitary processes and translation (recompilation) of a circuit from one form to another. Using emulated quantum computers with various noise-free gate sets we provide simple examples involving up to 10 qubits, corresponding to 20 qubits in the augmented space we use. Further applications of specific relevance to chemistry modelling are considered in a sister paper, 'Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry'.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal trade-off structure between symmetry, irreversibility, and quantum coherence in quantum processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11086</link>
    <author>Hiroyasu Tajima, Ryuji Takagi, Yui Kuramochi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Symmetry, irreversibility, and quantum coherence are foundational concepts in physics. Here, we present a universal trade-off relation that builds a bridge between these three concepts. This trade-off particularly reveals that (1) under a global symmetry, any attempt to induce local dynamics that change the conserved quantity will cause inevitable irreversibility, and (2) such irreversibility could be mitigated by quantum coherence. Our fundamental relation also admits broad applications in physics and quantum information processing. In the context of thermodynamics, we derive a trade-off relation between entropy production and quantum coherence in arbitrary isothermal processes. We also apply our relation to black hole physics and obtain a universal lower bound on how many bits of classical information thrown into a black hole become unreadable under the Hayden-Preskill model with the energy conservation law. This particularly shows that when the black hole is large enough, under suitable encoding, at least about $m/4$ bits of the thrown $m$ bits will be irrecoverable until 99 percent of the black hole evaporates. As an application to quantum information processing, we provide a lower bound on the coherence cost to implement an arbitrary quantum channel. We employ this bound to obtain a quantitative Wigner-Araki-Yanase theorem that comes with a clear operational meaning, as well as an error-coherence trade-off for unitary gate implementation and an error lower bound for approximate error correction with covariant encoding. Our main relation is based on quantum uncertainty relation, showcasing intimate connections between fundamental physical principles and ultimate operational capability.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Playing nonlocal games with phases of quantum matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11252</link>
    <author>Vir B. Bulchandani, Fiona J. Burnell, S. L. Sondhi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The parity game is an example of a nonlocal game: by sharing a Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) state before playing this game, the players can win with a higher probability than is allowed by classical physics. The GHZ state of $N$ qubits is also the ground state of the ferromagnetic quantum Ising model on $N$ qubits in the limit of vanishingly weak quantum fluctuations. Motivated by this observation, we examine the probability that $N$ players who share the ground state of a generic quantum Ising model, which exhibits non-vanishing quantum fluctuations, still win the parity game using the protocol optimized for the GHZ state. Our main result is a modified parity game for which this protocol asymptotically exhibits quantum advantage in precisely the ferromagnetic phase of the quantum Ising model. We further prove that the ground state of the exactly soluble $d=1+1$ transverse-field Ising model can provide a quantum advantage for the parity game over an even wider region, which includes the entire ferromagnetic phase, the critical point and part of the paramagnetic phase. By contrast, we find examples of topological phases and symmetry-protected topological (SPT) phases of matter, namely the deconfined phase of the toric code Hamiltonian and the $\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2$ SPT phase in one dimension, that do not exhibit an analogous quantum advantage away from their fixed points.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>