<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Differential Privacy: An Information Theory Perspective</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10717</link>
    <author>Christoph Hirche, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Differential privacy has been an exceptionally successful concept when it comes to providing provable security guarantees for classical computations. More recently, the concept was generalized to quantum computations. While classical computations are essentially noiseless and differential privacy is often achieved by artificially adding noise, near-term quantum computers are inherently noisy and it was observed that this leads to natural differential privacy as a feature. In this work we discuss quantum differential privacy in an information theoretic framework by casting it as a quantum divergence. A main advantage of this approach is that differential privacy becomes a property solely based on the output states of the computation, without the need to check it for every measurement. This leads to simpler proofs and generalized statements of its properties as well as several new bounds for both, general and specific, noise models. In particular, these include common representations of quantum circuits and quantum machine learning concepts. Here, we focus on the difference in the amount of noise required to achieve certain levels of differential privacy versus the amount that would make any computation useless. Finally, we also generalize the classical concepts of local differential privacy, Rényi differential privacy and the hypothesis testing interpretation to the quantum setting, providing several new properties and insights.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of nearest-neighbour quantum networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10886</link>
    <author>Frederik Hahn, Axel Dahlberg, Jens Eisert, Anna Pappa</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum communication research has in recent years shifted to include multi-partite networks for which questions of quantum network routing naturally emerge. To understand the potential for multi-partite routing, we focus on the most promising architectures for future quantum networks - those connecting nodes close to each other. Nearest-neighbour networks such as rings, lines, and grids, have been studied under different communication scenarios to facilitate the sharing of quantum resources, especially in the presence of bottlenecks. We here analyze the potential of nearest-neighbour quantum networks and identify some serious limitations, by demonstrating that rings and lines cannot overcome common bottleneck communication problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>SupermarQ: A Scalable Quantum Benchmark Suite</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11045</link>
    <author>Teague Tomesh, Pranav Gokhale, Victory Omole, Gokul Subramanian Ravi, Kaitlin N. Smith, Joshua Viszlai, Xin-Chuan Wu, Nikos Hardavellas, Margaret R. Martonosi, Frederic T. Chong</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The emergence of quantum computers as a new computational paradigm has been accompanied by speculation concerning the scope and timeline of their anticipated revolutionary changes. While quantum computing is still in its infancy, the variety of different architectures used to implement quantum computations make it difficult to reliably measure and compare performance. This problem motivates our introduction of SupermarQ, a scalable, hardware-agnostic quantum benchmark suite which uses application-level metrics to measure performance. SupermarQ is the first attempt to systematically apply techniques from classical benchmarking methodology to the quantum domain. We define a set of feature vectors to quantify coverage, select applications from a variety of domains to ensure the suite is representative of real workloads, and collect benchmark results from the IBM, IonQ, and AQT@LBNL platforms. Looking forward, we envision that quantum benchmarking will encompass a large cross-community effort built on open source, constantly evolving benchmark suites. We introduce SupermarQ as an important step in this direction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Framework for Distributed Quantum Queries in the CONGEST Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10969</link>
    <author>Joran van Apeldoorn, Tijn de Vos</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum CONGEST model is a variant of the CONGEST model, where messages consist of $O(\log(n))$ qubits. We give a general framework for implementing quantum query algorithms in Quantum CONGEST, using the concept of parallel-queries. We apply our framework for distributed quantum queries in two settings: when data is distributed over the network, and graph theoretical problems where the network defines the input. The first is slightly unusual in CONGEST but our results follow almost directly. The second is more traditional for the CONGEST model but here we require some classical CONGEST steps to get our results. In the setting with distributed data, we show how a network can schedule a meeting in one of $k$ dates using $\tilde{O}(\sqrt{kD}+D)$ rounds, with $D$ the network diameter. We also give an efficient algorithm for element distinctness: if all nodes are given numbers, then the nodes can find any duplicates in $\tilde{O}(n^{2/3}D^{1/3})$ rounds. We also generalize the protocol for the distributed Deutsch-Jozsa problem from the two-party setting considered in [arXiv:quant-ph/9802040] to general networks, giving a novel separation between exact classical and exact quantum protocols in CONGEST. When the input is the network structure itself, we almost directly recover the $O(\sqrt{nD})$ round diameter computation algorithm of Le Gall and Magniez [arXiv:1804.02917]. We also compute the radius in the same number of rounds, and give an $\epsilon$-additive approximation of the average eccentricity in $\tilde{O}(D+D^{3/2}/\epsilon)$ rounds. Finally, we give quantum speedups for the problems of cycle detection and girth computation. We detect whether a graph has a cycle of length at most $k$ in $O(D+(Dn)^{1/2-1/\Theta(k)})$ rounds. We also give a $\tilde{O}(D+(Dn)^{1/2-1/\Theta(g)})$ round algorithm for finding the girth $g$, beating the known classical lower bound.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Total insecurity of communication via strong converse for quantum privacy amplification</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11090</link>
    <author>Robert Salzmann, Nilanjana Datta</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum privacy amplification is a central task in quantum cryptography. Given shared randomness, which is initially correlated with a quantum system held by an eavesdropper, the goal is to extract uniform randomness which is decoupled from the latter. The optimal rate for this task is known to satisfy the strong converse property and we provide a lower bound on the corresponding strong converse exponent. In the strong converse region, the distance of the final state of the protocol from the desired decoupled state converges exponentially fast to its maximal value, in the asymptotic limit. We show that this necessarily leads to totally insecure communication by establishing that the eavesdropper can infer any sent messages with certainty, when given very limited extra information. In fact, we prove that in the strong converse region, the eavesdropper has an exponential advantage in inferring the sent message correctly, compared to the achievability region. Additionally we establish the following technical result, which is central to our proofs, and is of independent interest: the smoothing parameter for the smoothed max-relative entropy satisfies the strong converse property.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>