<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Syndrome-Derived Error Rates as a Benchmark of Quantum Hardware</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00553</link>
    <author>James R. Wootton</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correcting codes are designed to pinpoint exactly when and where errors occur in quantum circuits. This feature is the foundation of their primary task: to support fault-tolerant quantum computation. However, this feature could used as the basis of benchmarking: By analyzing the outputs of even small-scale quantum error correction circuits, a detailed picture can be constructed of error processes across a quantum device. Here we perform an example of such an analysis, using the results of small repetition codes to determine the error rate of each qubit while idle during a syndrome measurement. This provides an idea of the errors experienced by the qubits across a device while they are part of the kind of circuit that we expect to be typical in fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact electronic states with shallow quantum circuits through global optimisation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00085</link>
    <author>Hugh G. A. Burton, Daniel Marti-Dafcik, David P. Tew, David J. Wales</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers promise to revolutionise electronic simulations by overcoming the exponential scaling of many-electron problems. While electronic wave functions can be represented using a product of fermionic unitary operators, shallow quantum circuits for exact states have not yet been achieved. We construct universal wave functions from gate-efficient, symmetry-preserving fermionic operators by introducing an algorithm that globally optimises the wave function in the discrete ansatz design and the continuous parameter spaces. Our approach maximises the accuracy that can be obtained with near-term quantum circuits. Highly accurate numerical simulations on strongly correlated molecules, including water and molecular nitrogen, and the condensed-matter Hubbard model, demonstrate that our algorithm reliably advances the state-of-the-art, defining a new paradigm for quantum simulations featuring strong electron correlation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact dynamics in dual-unitary quantum circuits with projective measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00025</link>
    <author>Pieter W. Claeys, Marius Henry, Jamie Vicary, Austen Lamacraft</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Dual-unitary circuits have emerged as a minimal model for chaotic quantum many-body dynamics in which the dynamics of correlations and entanglement remains tractable. Simultaneously, there has been intense interest in the effect of measurements on the dynamics of quantum information in many-body systems. In this work we introduce a class of models combining dual-unitary circuits with particular projective measurements that allow the exact computation of dynamical correlations of local observables, entanglement growth, and steady-state entanglement. We identify a symmetry preventing a measurement-induced phase transition and present exact results for the intermediate critical purification phase.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental Simulation of Loop Quantum Gravity on a Photonic Chip</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00557</link>
    <author>Reinier van der Meer, Zichang Huang, Malaquias Correa Anguita, Dongxue Qu, Peter Hooijschuur, Hongguang Liu, Muxin Han, Jelmer J. Renema, Lior Cohen</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The unification of general relativity and quantum theory is one of the fascinating problems of modern physics. One leading solution is Loop Quantum Gravity (LQG). Simulating LQG may be important for providing predictions which can then be tested experimentally. However, such complex quantum simulations cannot run efficiently on classical computers, and quantum computers or simulators are needed. Here, we experimentally demonstrate quantum simulations of spinfoam amplitudes of LQG on an integrated photonics quantum processor. We simulate a basic transition of LQG and show that the derived spinfoam vertex amplitude falls within 4% error with respect to the theoretical prediction, despite experimental imperfections. We also discuss how to generalize the simulation for more complex transitions, in realistic experimental conditions, which will eventually lead to a quantum advantage demonstration as well as expand the toolbox to investigate LQG.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bipartite entanglement and the arrow of time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00024</link>
    <author>Markus Frembs</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide a new perspective on the close relationship between entanglement and time. Our main focus is on bipartite entanglement, where this connection is foreshadowed both in the positive partial transpose criterion due to Peres [A. Peres, Phys. Rev. Lett., 77, 1413 (1996)] and in the classification of quantum within more general non-signalling bipartite correlations [M. Frembs and A. Döring, arXiv:2204.11471]. Extracting the relevant common features, we identify a necessary and sufficient condition for bipartite entanglement in terms of a compatibility condition with respect to time orientations in local observable algebras, which express the dynamics in the respective subsystems. We discuss the relevance of the latter in the broader context of von Neumann algebras and the thermodynamical notion of time naturally arising within the latter.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>