<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Wasserstein Complexity of Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06306</link>
    <author>Lu Li, Kaifeng Bu, Dax Enshan Koh, Arthur Jaffe, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a unitary transformation, what is the size of the smallest quantum circuit that implements it? This quantity, known as the quantum circuit complexity, is a fundamental property of quantum evolutions that has widespread applications in many fields, including quantum computation, quantum field theory, and black hole physics. In this letter, we obtain a new lower bound for the quantum circuit complexity in terms of a novel complexity measure that we propose for quantum circuits, which we call the quantum Wasserstein complexity. Our proposed measure is based on the quantum Wasserstein distance of order one (also called the quantum earth mover's distance), a metric on the space of quantum states. We also prove several fundamental and important properties of our new complexity measure, which stand to be of independent interest. Finally, we show that our new measure also provides a lower bound for the experimental cost of implementing quantum circuits, which implies a quantum limit on converting quantum resources to computational resources. Our results provide novel applications of the quantum Wasserstein distance and pave the way for a deeper understanding of the resources needed to implement a quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On establishing learning separations between classical and quantum machine learning with classical data</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06339</link>
    <author>Casper Gyurik, Vedran Dunjko</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Despite years of effort, the quantum machine learning community has only been able to show quantum learning advantages for certain contrived cryptography-inspired datasets in the case of classical data. In this note, we discuss the challenges of finding learning problems that quantum learning algorithms can learn much faster than any classical learning algorithm, and we study how to identify such learning problems. Specifically, we reflect on the main concepts in computational learning theory pertaining to this question, and we discuss how subtle changes in definitions can mean conceptually significantly different tasks, which can either lead to a separation or no separation at all. Moreover, we study existing learning problems with a provable quantum speedup to distill sets of more general and sufficient conditions (i.e., ``checklists'') for a learning problem to exhibit a separation between classical and quantum learners. These checklists are intended to streamline one's approach to proving quantum speedups for learning problems, or to elucidate bottlenecks. Finally, to illustrate its application, we analyze examples of potential separations (i.e., when the learning problem is build from computational separations, or when the data comes from a quantum experiment) through the lens of our approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring incompatibility and clustering quantum observables with a quantum switch</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06210</link>
    <author>Ning Gao, Dantong Li, Anchit Mishra, Junchen Yan, Kyrylo Simonov, Giulio Chiribella</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The existence of incompatible observables is a cornerstone of quantum mechanics and a valuable resource in quantum technologies. Here we introduce a measure of incompatibility, called the mutual eigenspace disturbance (MED), which quantifies the amount of disturbance induced by the measurement of a sharp observable on the eigenspaces of another. The MED is a faithful measure of incompatibility for sharp observables and provides a metric on the space of von Neumann measurements. It can be efficiently estimated by letting the measurements act in an indefinite order, using a setup known as the quantum switch. Thanks to these features, the MED can be used in quantum machine learning tasks, such as clustering quantum measurement devices based on their mutual compatibility. We demonstrate this application by providing an unsupervised algorithm that clusters unknown von Neumann measurements. Our algorithm is robust to noise can be used to identify groups of observers that share approximately the same measurement context.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Evaluating the performance of sigmoid quantum perceptrons in quantum neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06198</link>
    <author>Samuel A Wilkinson, Michael J Hartmann</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum neural networks (QNN) have been proposed as a promising architecture for quantum machine learning. There exist a number of different quantum circuit designs being branded as QNNs, however no clear candidate has presented itself as more suitable than the others. Rather, the search for a ``quantum perceptron" -- the fundamental building block of a QNN -- is still underway. One candidate is quantum perceptrons designed to emulate the nonlinear activation functions of classical perceptrons. Such sigmoid quantum perceptrons (SQPs) inherit the universal approximation property that guarantees that classical neural networks can approximate any function. However, this does not guarantee that QNNs built from SQPs will have any quantum advantage over their classical counterparts. Here we critically investigate both the capabilities and performance of SQP networks by computing their effective dimension and effective capacity, as well as examining their performance on real learning problems. The results are compared to those obtained for other candidate networks which lack activation functions. It is found that simpler, and apparently easier-to-implement parametric quantum circuits actually perform better than SQPs. This indicates that the universal approximation theorem, which a cornerstone of the theory of classical neural networks, is not a relevant criterion for QNNs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-invertible Symmetries and Higher Representation Theory I</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05993</link>
    <author>Thomas Bartsch, Mathew Bullimore, Andrea E. V. Ferrari, Jamie Pearson</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The purpose of this paper is to investigate the global categorical symmetries that arise when gauging finite higher groups in three or more dimensions. The motivation is to provide a common perspective on constructions of non-invertible global symmetries in higher dimensions and a precise description of the associated symmetry categories. This paper focusses on gauging finite groups and split 2-groups in three dimensions. In addition to topological Wilson lines, we show that this generates a rich spectrum of topological surface defects labelled by 2-representations and explain their connection to condensation defects for Wilson lines. We derive various properties of the topological defects and show that the associated symmetry category is the fusion 2-category of 2-representations. This allows us to determine the full symmetry categories of certain gauge theories with disconnected gauge groups. A subsequent paper will examine gauging more general higher groups in higher dimensions.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>