<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Counting unitaries of T-depth one</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04163</link>
    <author>Vadym Kliuchnikov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits is $ \sum_{m=1}^{n}\tfrac{1}{m!}\prod_{k=0}^{m-1}(4^n/2^k - 2^k) \times \# \mathcal{C}_n, $ where $\#\mathcal{C}_n$ is the size of the $n$-qubit Clifford group, that is the number of unitaries of T-depth zero. The number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits grows as $2^{\Omega(n^2)} \cdot \# \mathcal{C}_n$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement estimation in tensor network states via sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04089</link>
    <author>Noa Feldman, Augustine Kshetrimayum, Jens Eisert, Moshe Goldstein</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a method for extracting meaningful entanglement measures of tensor network states in general dimensions. Current methods require the explicit reconstruction of the density matrix, which is highly demanding, or the contraction of replicas, which requires an effort exponential in the number of replicas and which is costly in terms of memory. In contrast, our method requires the stochastic sampling of matrix elements of the classically represented reduced states with respect to random states drawn from simple product probability measures constituting frames. Even though not corresponding to physical operations, such matrix elements are straightforward to calculate for tensor network states, and their moments provide the Rényi entropies and negativities as well as their symmetry-resolved components. We test our method on the one-dimensional critical XX chain and the two-dimensional toric code. Although the cost is exponential in the subsystem size, it is sufficiently moderate so that - in contrast with other approaches - accurate results can be obtained on a personal computer for relatively large subsystem sizes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement catalysis for quantum states and noisy channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05228</link>
    <author>Chandan Datta, Tulja Varun Kondra, Marek Miller, Alexander Streltsov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many applications of the emerging quantum technologies, such as quantum teleportation and quantum key distribution, require singlets, maximally entangled states of two quantum bits. It is thus of utmost importance to develop optimal procedures for establishing singlets between remote parties. As has been shown very recently, singlets can be obtained from other quantum states by using a quantum catalyst, an entangled quantum system which is not changed in the procedure. In this work we put this idea further, investigating properties of entanglement catalysis and its role for quantum communication. For transformations between bipartite pure states we prove the existence of a universal catalyst, which can enable all possible transformations in this setup. We demonstrate the advantage of catalysis in asymptotic settings, going beyond the typical assumption of independent and identically distributed systems. We further develop methods to estimate the number of singlets which can be established via a noisy quantum channel when assisted by entangled catalysts. For various types of quantum channels our results lead to optimal protocols, allowing to establish the maximal number of singlets with a single use of the channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Deconfinement and Error Thresholds in Holography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04710</link>
    <author>Ning Bao, Charles Cao, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the error threshold properties of holographic quantum error-correcting codes. We demonstrate that holographic CFTs admit an algebraic threshold, which is related to the confinement-deconfinement phase transition. We then apply geometric intuition from holography and the Hawking-Page phase transition to motivate the CFT result, and comment on potential extensions to other confining theories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying information scrambling via Classical Shadow Tomography on Programmable Quantum Simulators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05132</link>
    <author>Max McGinley, Sebastian Leontica, Samuel J. Garratt, Jovan Jovanovic, Steven H. Simon</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop techniques to probe the dynamics of quantum information, and implement them experimentally on an IBM superconducting quantum processor. Our protocols adapt shadow tomography for the study of time evolution channels rather than of quantum states, and rely only on single-qubit operations and measurements. We identify two unambiguous signatures of quantum information scrambling, neither of which can be mimicked by dissipative processes, and relate these to many-body teleportation. By realizing quantum chaotic dynamics in experiment, we measure both signatures, and support our results with numerical simulations of the quantum system. We additionally investigate operator growth under this dynamics, and observe behaviour characteristic of quantum chaos. As our methods require only a single quantum state at a time, they can be readily applied on a wide variety of quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>