<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Pseudoentanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.00747</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Bill Fefferman, Soumik Ghosh, Umesh Vazirani, Zixin Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum pseudorandom states are efficiently constructable states which nevertheless masquerade as Haar-random states to poly-time observers. First defined by Ji, Liu and Song, such states have found a number of applications ranging from cryptography to the AdS/CFT correspondence. A fundamental question is exactly how much entanglement is required to create such states. Haar-random states, as well as $t$-designs for $t\geq 2$, exhibit near-maximal entanglement. Here we provide the first construction of pseudorandom states with only polylogarithmic entanglement entropy across an equipartition of the qubits, which is the minimum possible. Our construction can be based on any one-way function secure against quantum attack. We additionally show that the entanglement in our construction is fully "tunable", in the sense that one can have pseudorandom states with entanglement $\Theta(f(n))$ for any desired function $\omega(\log n) \leq f(n) \leq O(n)$. More fundamentally, our work calls into question to what extent entanglement is a "feelable" quantity of quantum systems. Inspired by recent work of Gheorghiu and Hoban, we define a new notion which we call "pseudoentanglement", which are ensembles of efficiently constructable quantum states which hide their entanglement entropy. We show such states exist in the strongest form possible while simultaneously being pseudorandom states. We also describe diverse applications of our result from entanglement distillation to property testing to quantum gravity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms for classical Boolean functions via adaptive measurements: Exponential reductions in space-time resources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01252</link>
    <author>Austin K. Daniel, Akimasa Miyake</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The limited computational power of constant-depth quantum circuits can be boosted by adapting future gates according to the outcomes of mid-circuit measurements. We formulate computation of a variety of Boolean functions in the framework of adaptive measurement-based quantum computation using a cluster state resource and a classical side-processor that can add bits modulo 2, so-called $l2$-MBQC. Our adaptive approach overcomes a known challenge that computing these functions in the nonadaptive setting requires a resource state that is exponentially large in the size of the computational input. In particular, we construct adaptive $l2$-MBQC algorithms based on the quantum signal processing technique that compute the mod-$p$ functions with the best known scaling in the space-time resources (i.e., qubit count, quantum circuit depth, classical memory size, and number of calls to the side-processor). As the subject is diverse and has a long history, the paper includes reviews of several previously constructed algorithms and recasts them as adaptive $l2$-MBQCs using cluster state resources. Our results constitute an alternative proof of an old theorem regarding an oracular separation between the power of constant-depth quantum circuits and constant-depth classical circuits with unbounded fan-in NAND and mod-$p$ gates for any prime $p$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Phase space geometry and optimal state preparation in quantum metrology with collective spins</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01250</link>
    <author>Manuel H. Muñoz-Arias, Ivan H. Deutsch, Pablo M. Poggi</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We revisit well-known protocols in quantum metrology using collective spins and propose a unifying picture for optimal state preparation based on a semiclassical description in phase space. We show how this framework allows for quantitative predictions of the timescales required to prepare various metrologically useful states, and that these predictions remain accurate even for moderate system sizes, surprisingly far from the classical limit. Furthermore, this framework allows us to build a geometric picture that relates optimal (exponentially fast) entangled probe preparation to the existence of separatrices connecting saddle points in phase space. We illustrate our results with the paradigmatic examples of the two-axis counter-twisting and twisting-and-turning Hamiltonians, where we provide analytical expressions for all the relevant optimal time scales. Finally, we propose a generalization of these models to include $p$-body collective interaction (or $p$-order twisting), beyond the usual case of $p=2$. Using our geometric framework, we prove a no-go theorem for the local optimality of these models for $p>2$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum City: simulation of a practical near-term metropolitan quantum network</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01190</link>
    <author>Raja Yehia, Simon Neves, Eleni Diamanti, Iordanis Kerenidis</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present the architecture and analyze the applications of a metropolitan-scale quantum network that requires only limited hardware resources for end users. Using NetSquid, a quantum network simulation tool based on discrete events, we assess the performance of several quantum network protocols involving two or more users in various configurations in terms of topology, hardware and trust choices. Our analysis takes losses and errors into account and considers realistic parameters corresponding to present or near-term technology. Our results show that practical quantum-enhanced network functionalities are within reach today and can prepare the ground for further applications when more advanced technology becomes available.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Space-time optimized table lookup</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01133</link>
    <author>Thomas Häner, Vadym Kliuchnikov, Martin Roetteler, Mathias Soeken</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a space-time optimized circuit for the table lookup subroutine from lattice-surgery surface code primitives respecting 2D grid connectivity. Table lookup circuits are ubiquitous in quantum computing, allowing the presented circuit to be used for applications ranging from cryptography to quantum chemistry. Surface code is the leading approach to scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing pursued by industry and academia. We abstract away surface code implementation details by using a minimal set of operations supported by the surface code via lattice-surgery. Our exposition is accessible to a reader not familiar with surface codes and fault-tolerant quantum computing.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>