<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A Direct Reduction from the Polynomial to the Adversary Method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10317</link>
    <author>Aleksandrs Belovs</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The polynomial and the adversary methods are the two main tools for proving lower bounds on query complexity of quantum algorithms. Both methods have found a large number of applications, some problems more suitable for one method, some for the other. It is known though that the adversary method, in its general negative-weighted version, is tight for bounded-error quantum algorithms, whereas the polynomial method is not. By the tightness of the former, for any polynomial lower bound, there ought to exist a corresponding adversary lower bound. However, direct reduction was not known. In this paper, we give a simple and direct reduction from the polynomial method (in the form of a dual polynomial) to the adversary method. This shows that any lower bound in the form of a dual polynomial is actually an adversary lower bound of a specific form.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing quantum satisfiability</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10699</link>
    <author>Ashley Montanaro, Changpeng Shao, Dominic Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum k-SAT (the problem of determining whether a k-local Hamiltonian is frustration-free) is known to be QMA_1-complete for k >= 3, and hence likely hard for quantum computers to solve. Building on a classical result of Alon and Shapira, we show that quantum k-SAT can be solved in randomised polynomial time given the `property testing' promise that the instance is either satisfiable (by any state) or far from satisfiable by a product state; by `far from satisfiable by a product state' we mean that \epsilon n^k constraints must be removed before a product state solution exists, for some fixed \epsilon > 0. The proof has two steps: we first show that for a satisfiable instance of quantum k-SAT, most subproblems on a constant number of qubits are satisfiable by a product state. We then show that for an instance of quantum k-SAT which is far from satisfiable by a product state, most subproblems are unsatisfiable by a product state. Given the promise, quantum k-SAT may therefore be solved by checking satisfiability by a product state on randomly chosen subsystems of constant size.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Impact of Imperfect Timekeeping on Quantum Control</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10767</link>
    <author>Jake Xuereb, Paul Erker, Florian Meier, Mark T. Mitchison, Marcus Huber</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In order to unitarily evolve a quantum system, an agent requires knowledge of time, a parameter which no physical clock can ever perfectly characterise. In this letter, we study how limitations on acquiring knowledge of time impact controlled quantum operations in different paradigms. We show that the quality of timekeeping an agent has access to limits the gate complexity they are able to achieve within circuit-based quantum computation. It also exponentially impacts state preparation for measurement-based quantum computation. Another area where quantum control is relevant is quantum thermodynamics. In that context, we show that cooling a qubit can be achieved using a timer of arbitrary quality for control: timekeeping error only impacts the rate of cooling and not the achievable temperature. Our analysis combines techniques from the study of autonomous quantum clocks and the theory of quantum channels to understand the effect of imperfect timekeeping on controlled quantum dynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Any consistent coupling between classical gravity and quantum matter is fundamentally irreversible</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10261</link>
    <author>Thomas D. Galley, Flaminia Giacomini, John H. Selby</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>When gravity is sourced by a quantum system, there is tension between its role as the mediator of a fundamental interaction, which is expected to acquire nonclassical features, and its role in determining the properties of spacetime, which is inherently classical. Fundamentally, this tension should result in breaking one of the fundamental principles of quantum theory or general relativity, but it is usually hard to assess which one without resorting to a specific model. Here, we answer this question in a theory-independent way using General Probabilistic Theories (GPTs). We consider the interactions of the gravitational field with a single matter system, and derive a no-go theorem showing that when gravity is classical at least one of the following assumptions needs to be violated: (i) Matter degrees of freedom are described by fully non-classical degrees of freedom; (ii) Interactions between matter degrees of freedom and the gravitational field are reversible; (iii) Matter degrees of freedom back-react on the gravitational field. We argue that this implies that theories of classical gravity and quantum matter must be fundamentally irreversible, as is the case in the recent model of Oppenheim et al. Conversely if we require that the interaction between quantum matter and the gravitational field are reversible, then the gravitational field must be non-classical.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fermionic Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10756</link>
    <author>Takuya Yoshioka, Keita Sasada, Yuichiro Nakano, Keisuke Fujii</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers are expected to accelerate solving combinatorial optimization problems, including algorithms such as Grover adaptive search and quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA). However, many combinatorial optimization problems involve constraints which, when imposed as soft constraints in the cost function, can negatively impact the performance of the optimization algorithm. In this paper, we propose fermionic quantum approximate optimization algorithm (FQAOA) for solving combinatorial optimization problems with constraints. Specifically FQAOA tackle the constrains issue by using fermion particle number preservation to intrinsically impose them throughout QAOA. We provide a systematic guideline for designing the driver Hamiltonian for a given problem Hamiltonian with constraints. The initial state can be chosen to be a superposition of states satisfying the constraint and the ground state of the driver Hamiltonian. This property is important since FQAOA reduced to quantum adiabatic computation in the large limit of circuit depth p and improved performance, even for shallow circuits with optimizing the parameters starting from the fixed-angle determined by Trotterized quantum adiabatic evolution. We perform an extensive numerical simulation and demonstrates that proposed FQAOA provides substantial performance advantage against existing approaches in portfolio optimization problems. Furthermore, the Hamiltonian design guideline is useful not only for QAOA, but also Grover adaptive search and quantum phase estimation to solve combinatorial optimization problems with constraints. Since software tools for fermionic systems have been developed in quantum computational chemistry both for noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers and fault-tolerant quantum computers, FQAOA allows us to apply these tools for constrained combinatorial optimization problems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>