<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Observation of non-Abelian exchange statistics on a superconducting processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10255</link>
    <author>Trond I. Andersen, Yuri D. Lensky, Kostyantyn Kechedzhi, Ilya Drozdov, Andreas Bengtsson, Sabrina Hong, Alexis Morvan, Xiao Mi, Alex Opremcak, Rajeev Acharya, Richard Allen, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Gina Bortoli, et al (149)</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Indistinguishability of particles is a fundamental principle of quantum mechanics. For all elementary and quasiparticles observed to date - including fermions, bosons, and Abelian anyons - this principle guarantees that the braiding of identical particles leaves the system unchanged. However, in two spatial dimensions, an intriguing possibility exists: braiding of non-Abelian anyons causes rotations in a space of topologically degenerate wavefunctions. Hence, it can change the observables of the system without violating the principle of indistinguishability. Despite the well developed mathematical description of non-Abelian anyons and numerous theoretical proposals, their experimental observation has remained elusive for decades. Using a superconducting quantum processor, we prepare the ground state of the surface code and manipulate it via unitary operations to form wavefunctions that are described by non-Abelian anyons. By implementing a unitary protocol to move the anyons, we experimentally verify the fusion rules of non-Abelian Ising anyons and braid them to realize their statistics. Building on our technique, we study the prospect of employing the anyons for quantum computation and utilize braiding to create an entangled state of anyons encoding three logical qubits. Our work represents a key step towards topological quantum computing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Purification-based quantum error mitigation of pair-correlated electron simulations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10799</link>
    <author>T. E. O'Brien, G. Anselmetti, F. Gkritsis, V. E. Elfving, S. Polla, W. J. Huggins, O. Oumarou, K. Kechedzhi, D. Abanin, R. Acharya, I. Aleiner, R. Allen, T. I. Andersen, K. Anderson, M. Ansmann, F. Arute, K. Arya, A. Asfaw, J. Atalaya, D. Bacon, et al (156)</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An important measure of the development of quantum computing platforms has been the simulation of increasingly complex physical systems. Prior to fault-tolerant quantum computing, robust error mitigation strategies are necessary to continue this growth. Here, we study physical simulation within the seniority-zero electron pairing subspace, which affords both a computational stepping stone to a fully correlated model, and an opportunity to validate recently introduced ``purification-based'' error-mitigation strategies. We compare the performance of error mitigation based on doubling quantum resources in time (echo verification) or in space (virtual distillation), on up to $20$ qubits of a superconducting qubit quantum processor. We observe a reduction of error by one to two orders of magnitude below less sophisticated techniques (e.g. post-selection); the gain from error mitigation is seen to increase with the system size. Employing these error mitigation strategies enables the implementation of the largest variational algorithm for a correlated chemistry system to-date. Extrapolating performance from these results allows us to estimate minimum requirements for a beyond-classical simulation of electronic structure. We find that, despite the impressive gains from purification-based error mitigation, significant hardware improvements will be required for classically intractable variational chemistry simulations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error Suppression for Arbitrary-Size Black Box Quantum Operations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10733</link>
    <author>Gideon Lee, Connor T. Hann, Shruti Puri, S. M. Girvin, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Efficient suppression of errors without full error correction is crucial for applications with NISQ devices. Error mitigation allows us to suppress errors in extracting expectation values without the need for any error correction code, but its applications are limited to estimating expectation values, and cannot provide us with high-fidelity quantum operations acting on arbitrary quantum states. To address this challenge, we propose to use error filtration (EF) for gate-based quantum computation, as a practical error suppression scheme without resorting to full quantum error correction. The result is a general-purpose error suppression protocol where the resources required to suppress errors scale independently of the size of the quantum operation. We further analyze the application of EF to quantum random access memory, where EF offers a hardware-efficient error suppression.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Doubling the order of approximation via the randomized product formula</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11281</link>
    <author>Chien Hung Cho, Dominic W. Berry, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Randomization has been applied to Hamiltonian simulation in a number of ways to improve the accuracy or efficiency of product formulas. Deterministic product formulas are often constructed in a symmetric way to provide accuracy of even order 2k. We show that by applying randomized corrections, it is possible to more than double the order to 4k + 1 (corresponding to a doubling of the order of the error). In practice, applying the corrections in a quantum algorithm requires some structure to the Hamiltonian, for example the Pauli strings as are used in the simulation of quantum chemistry.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sequential Quantum Channel Discrimination</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11079</link>
    <author>Yonglong Li, Christoph Hirche, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the sequential quantum channel discrimination problem using adaptive and non-adaptive strategies. In this setting the number of uses of the underlying quantum channel is not fixed but a random variable that is either bounded in expectation or with high probability. We show that both types of error probabilities decrease to zero exponentially fast and, when using adaptive strategies, the rates are characterized by the measured relative entropy between two quantum channels, yielding a strictly larger region than that achievable by non-adaptive strategies. Allowing for quantum memory, we see that the optimal rates are given by the regularized channel relative entropy. Finally, we discuss achievable rates when allowing for repeated measurements via quantum instruments and conjecture that the achievable rate region is not larger than that achievable with POVMs by connecting the result to the strong converse for the quantum channel Stein's Lemma.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>