<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Tanner codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.13641</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tanner codes are long error correcting codes obtained from short codes and a graph, with bits on the edges and parity-check constraints from the short codes enforced at the vertices of the graph. Combining good short codes together with a spectral expander graph yields the celebrated expander codes of Sipser and Spielman, which are asymptotically good classical LDPC codes. In this work we apply this prescription to the left-right Cayley complex that lies at the heart of the recent construction of a $c^3$ locally testable code by Dinur et al. Specifically, we view this complex as two graphs that share the same set of edges. By defining a Tanner code on each of those graphs we obtain two classical codes that together define a quantum code. This construction can be seen as a simplified variant of the Panteleev and Kalachev asymptotically good quantum LDPC code, with improved estimates for its minimum distance. This quantum code is closely related to the Dinur et al. code in more than one sense: indeed, we prove a theorem that simultaneously gives a linearly growing minimum distance for the quantum code and recovers the local testability of the Dinur et al. code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical Verification of Quantum Computations in Linear Time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.13997</link>
    <author>Jiayu Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the quantum computation verification problem, a quantum server wants to convince a client that the output of evaluating a quantum circuit $C$ is some result that it claims. This problem is considered very important both theoretically and practically in quantum computation [arXiv:1709.06984], [arXiv:1704.04487], [arXiv:1209.0449]. The client is considered to be limited in computational power, and one desirable property is that the client can be completely classical, which leads to the classical verification of quantum computation (CVQC) problem. In terms of total time complexity of both the client and the server, the fastest single-server CVQC protocol so far has complexity $O(poly(\kappa)|C|^3)$ where $|C|$ is the size of the circuit to be verified, given by Mahadev [arXiv:1804.01082]. In this work, by developing new techniques, we give a new CVQC protocol with complexity $O(poly(\kappa)|C|)$, which is significantly faster than existing protocols. Our protocol is secure in the quantum random oracle model [arXiv:1008.0931] assuming the existence of noisy trapdoor claw-free functions [arXiv:1804.00640], which are both extensively used assumptions in quantum cryptography. Along the way, we also give a new classical channel remote state preparation protocol for states in $\{|+_\theta\rangle=\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}(|0\rangle+e^{i\theta\pi/4}|1\rangle):\theta\in \{0,1\cdots 7\}\}$, another basic primitive in quantum cryptography. Our protocol allows for parallel verifiable preparation of $L$ independently random states in this form (up to a constant overall error and a possibly unbounded server-side isometry), and runs in only $O(poly(\kappa)L)$ time and constant rounds; for comparison, existing works (even for possibly simpler state families) all require very large or unestimated time and round complexities [arXiv:1904.06320][arXiv:1904.06303][arXiv:2201.13445][arXiv:2201.13430].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simulability of high-dimensional quantum measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12980</link>
    <author>Marie Ioannou, Pavel Sekatski, Sébastien Designolle, Benjamin D.M. Jones, Roope Uola, Nicolas Brunner</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the compression of quantum information with respect to a given set $\mathcal{M}$ of high-dimensional measurements. This leads to a notion of simulability, where we demand that the statistics obtained from $\mathcal{M}$ and an arbitrary quantum state $\rho$ are recovered exactly by first compressing $\rho$ into a lower dimensional space, followed by some quantum measurements. A full quantum compression is possible, i.e., leaving only classical information, if and only if the set $\mathcal{M}$ is jointly measurable. Our notion of simulability can thus be seen as a quantification of measurement incompatibility in terms of dimension. After defining these concepts, we provide an illustrative examples involving mutually unbiased basis, and develop a method based on semi-definite programming for constructing simulation models. In turn we analytically construct optimal simulation models for all projective measurements subjected to white noise or losses. Finally, we discuss how our approach connects with other concepts introduced in the context of quantum channels and quantum correlations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>CAFQA: Clifford Ansatz For Quantum Accuracy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12924</link>
    <author>Gokul Subramanian Ravi, Pranav Gokhale, Yi Ding, William M. Kirby, Kaitlin N. Smith, Jonathan M. Baker, Peter J. Love, Henry Hoffmann, Kenneth R. Brown, Frederic T. Chong</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational Quantum Algorithms (VQAs) rely upon the iterative optimization of a parameterized unitary circuit with respect to an objective function. Since quantum machines are noisy and expensive resources, it is imperative to choose a VQA's ansatz appropriately and its initial parameters to be close to optimal. This work tackles the problem of finding initial ansatz parameters by proposing CAFQA, a Clifford ansatz for quantum accuracy. The CAFQA ansatz is a hardware-efficient circuit built with only Clifford gates. In this ansatz, the initial parameters for the tunable gates are chosen by searching efficiently through the Clifford parameter space via classical simulation, thereby producing a suitable stabilizer state. The stabilizer states produced are shown to always equal or outperform traditional classical initialization (e.g., Hartree-Fock), and often produce high accuracy estimations prior to quantum exploration. Furthermore, the technique is classically suited since a) Clifford circuits can be exactly simulated classically in polynomial time and b) the discrete Clifford space, while scaling exponentially in the number of qubits, is searched efficiently via Bayesian Optimization. For the Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) task of molecular ground state energy estimation up to 20 qubits, CAFQA's Clifford Ansatz achieves a mean accuracy of near 99%, recovering as much as 99.99% of the correlation energy over Hartree-Fock. Notably, the scalability of the approach allows for preliminary ground state energy estimation of the challenging Chromium dimer with an accuracy greater than Hartree-Fock. With CAFQA's initialization, VQA convergence is accelerated by a factor of 2.5x. In all, this work shows that stabilizer states are an accurate ansatz initialization for VQAs. Furthermore, it highlights the potential for quantum-inspired classical techniques to support VQAs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum computing with differentiable quantum transforms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.13414</link>
    <author>Olivia Di Matteo, Josh Izaac, Tom Bromley, Anthony Hayes, Christina Lee, Maria Schuld, Antal Száva, Chase Roberts, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a framework for differentiable quantum transforms. Such transforms are metaprograms capable of manipulating quantum programs in a way that preserves their differentiability. We highlight their potential with a set of relevant examples across quantum computing (gradient computation, circuit compilation, and error mitigation), and implement them using the transform framework of PennyLane, a software library for differentiable quantum programming. In this framework, the transforms themselves are differentiable and can be parametrized and optimized, which opens up the possibility of improved quantum resource requirements across a spectrum of tasks.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>