<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Comparison of unknown unitary channels with multiple uses</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12519</link>
    <author>Yutaka Hashimoto, Akihito Soeda, Mio Murao</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Comparison of quantum objects is a task to determine whether two unknown quantum objects are the same or different. It is one of the most basic information processing tasks for learning property of quantum objects, and comparison of quantum states, quantum channels, and quantum measurements have been investigated. In general, repeated uses of quantum objects improve the success probability of comparison. The optimal strategy of pure-state comparison, the comparison of quantum states for the case of multiple copies of each unknown pure state, is known, but the optimal strategy of unitary comparison, the comparison of quantum channels for the case of multiple uses of each unknown unitary channel, was not known due to the complication of the varieties of causal order structures among the uses of each unitary channel. In this paper, we investigate unitary comparison with multiple uses of unitary channels based on the quantum tester formalism. We obtain the optimal minimum-error and the optimal unambiguous strategies of unitary comparison of two unknown $d$-dimensional unitary channels $U_1$ and $U_2$ when $U_1$ can be used $N_1$ times and $U_2$ can be used $N_2$ times for $N_2 \ge (d-1)N_1$. These optimal strategies are implemented by parallel uses of the unitary channels, even though all sequential and adaptive strategies implementable by the quantum circuit model are considered. When the number of the smaller uses of the unitary channels $N_1$ is fixed, the optimal averaged success probability cannot be improved by adding more uses of $U_2$ than $N_2 = (d-1) N_1$. This feature is in contrast to the case of pure-state comparison, where adding more copies of the unknown pure states always improves the optimal averaged success probability. It highlights the difference between corresponding tasks for states and channels, which has been previously shown for quantum discrimination tasks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Proofs of Quantumness from Trapdoor Permutations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12390</link>
    <author>Tomoyuki Morimae, Takashi Yamakawa</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Assume that Alice can do only classical probabilistic polynomial-time computing while Bob can do quantum polynomial-time computing. Alice and Bob communicate over only classical channels, and finally Bob gets a state $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$ with some bit strings $x_0$ and $x_1$. Is it possible that Alice can know $\{x_0,x_1\}$ but Bob cannot? Such a task, called \it remote state preparations, is indeed possible under some complexity assumptions, and is bases of many quantum cryptographic primitives such as proofs of quantumness, (classical-client) blind quantum computing, (classical) verifications of quantum computing, and quantum money. A typical technique to realize remote state preparations is to use 2-to-1 trapdoor collision resistant hash functions: Alice sends a 2-to-1 trapdoor collision resistant hash function $f$ to Bob, and Bob evaluates it on superposition and measures the image. Bob's post-measurement state is $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$, where $f(x_0)=f(x_1)=y$. With the trapdoor, Alice can learn $\{x_0,x_1\}$, but due to the collision resistance, Bob cannot. This Alice's advantage can be leveraged to realize the quantum cryptographic primitives listed above. It seems that the collision resistance is essential here. In this paper, surprisingly, we show that the collision resistance is not necessary for a restricted case: we show that (non-verifiable) remote state preparations of $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$ secure against \it classical probabilistic polynomial-time Bob can be constructed from classically-secure (full-domain) trapdoor permutations. Trapdoor permutations are not likely to imply the collision resistance, because black-box reductions from collision-resistant hash functions to trapdoor permutations are known to be impossible. As an application of our result, we construct proofs of quantumness from classically-secure (full-domain) trapdoor permutations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Solvent distribution effects on quantum chemical calculations with quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12487</link>
    <author>Yuichiro Yoshida, Wataru Mizukami, Norio Yoshida</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a combination of three-dimensional reference interaction site model self-consistent field (3D-RISM-SCF) theory and the variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) to consider the solvent distribution effects within the framework of quantum-classical hybrid computing. The present method, 3D-RISM-VQE, does not include any statistical errors from the solvent configuration sampling owing to the analytical treatment of the statistical solvent distribution. We apply 3D-RISM-VQE to compute the spatial distribution functions of solvent water around a water molecule, the potential and Helmholtz energy curves of NaCl, and to conduct Helmholtz energy component analysis of H$_2$O and NH$_4^+$. Moreover, we utilize 3D-RISM-VQE to analyze the extent to which solvent effects alter the efficiency of quantum calculations compared with calculations in the gas phase using the $L^1$-norms of molecular electronic Hamiltonians. Our results demonstrate that the efficiency of quantum chemical calculations on a quantum computer in solution is virtually the same as in the gas phase.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Operator Growth in Open Quantum Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12272</link>
    <author>Thomas Schuster, Norman Y. Yao</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The spreading of quantum information in closed systems, often termed scrambling, is a hallmark of many-body quantum dynamics. In open systems, scrambling competes with noise, errors and decoherence. Here, we provide a universal framework that describes the scrambling of quantum information in open systems: we predict that the effect of open-system dynamics is fundamentally controlled by operator size distributions and independent of the microscopic error mechanism. This framework allows us to demonstrate that open quantum systems exhibit universal classes of information dynamics that fundamentally differ from their unitary counterparts. Implications for Loschmidt echo experiments and the classical simulability of open quantum dynamics will be discussed.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Extendibility of Werner States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13743</link>
    <author>D치vid Jakab, Adri치n Solymos, Zolt치n Zimbor치s</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the two-sided symmetric extendibility problem of Werner states. The interplay of the unitary symmetry of these states and the inherent bipartite permutation symmetry of the extendibility scenario allows us to map this problem into the ground state problem of a highly symmetric spin-model Hamiltonian. We solve this ground state problem analytically by utilizing the representation theory of SU(d), in particular a result related to the dominance order of Young diagrams in Littlewood-Richarson decompositions. As a result, we obtain necessary and sufficient conditions for the extendibility of Werner states for arbitrary extension size and local dimension. Interestingly, the range of extendible states has a non-trivial trade-off between the extension sizes on the two sides. We compare our result with the two-sided extendibility problem of isotropic states, where there is no such trade-off.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>