<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Sample optimal tomography of quantum Markov chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02240</link>
    <author>Li Gao, Nengkun Yu</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A state on a tripartite quantum system $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C} $ forms a Markov chain, i.e., quantum conditional independence, if it can be reconstructed from its marginal on $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}$ by a quantum operation from $\mathcal{H}_{B}$ to $\mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C}$ via the famous Petz map: a quantum Markov chain $\rho_{ABC}$ satisfies $\rho_{ABC}=\rho_{BC}^{1/2}(\rho_B^{-1/2}\rho_{AB}\rho_B^{-1/2}\otimes id_C)\rho_{BC}^{1/2}$. In this paper, we study the robustness of the Petz map for different metrics, i.e., the closeness of marginals implies the closeness of the Petz map outcomes. The robustness results are dimension-independent for infidelity $\delta$ and trace distance $\epsilon$. The applications of robustness results are The sample complexity of quantum Markov chain tomography, i.e., how many copies of an unknown quantum Markov chain are necessary and sufficient to determine the state, is $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\delta})$, and $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\epsilon^2}) $. The sample complexity of quantum Markov Chain certification, i.e., to certify whether a tripartite state equals a fixed given quantum Markov Chain $\sigma_{ABC}$ or at least $\delta$-far from $\sigma_{ABC}$, is ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\delta})$, and ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\epsilon^2})$. $\tilde{O}(\frac{\min\{d_Ad_B^3d_C^3,d_A^3d_B^3d_C\}}{\epsilon^2})$ copies to test whether $\rho_{ABC}$ is a quantum Markov Chain or $\epsilon$-far from its Petz recovery state. We generalized the tomography results into multipartite quantum system by showing $\tilde{O}(\frac{n^2\max_{i} \{d_i^2d_{i+1}^2\}}{\delta})$ copies for infidelity $\delta$ are enough for $n$-partite quantum Markov chain tomography with $d_i$ being the dimension of the $i$-th subsystem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Approximation Algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02589</link>
    <author>Robbie King</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give an approximation algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut which works by rounding an SDP relaxation to an entangled quantum state. The SDP is used to choose the parameters of a variational quantum circuit. The entangled state is then represented as the quantum circuit applied to a product state. It achieves an approximation ratio of 0.582, significantly improving on the algorithms of Anshu, Gosset, Morenz, 0.531, and Parekh, Thompson, 0.533. In addition, we also study the EPR Hamiltonian, which we argue is a natural intermediate problem which isolates some key quantum features of local Hamiltonian problems. For the EPR Hamiltonian, we give an approximation algorithm with approximation ratio $\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable and Flexible Classical Shadow Tomography with Tensor Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02093</link>
    <author>Ahmed A. Akhtar, Hong-Ye Hu, Yi-Zhuang You</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classical shadow tomography is a powerful randomized measurement protocol for predicting many properties of a quantum state with few measurements. Two classical shadow protocols have been extensively studied in the literature: the single-qubit (local) Pauli measurement, which is well suited for predicting local operators but inefficient for large operators; and the global Clifford measurement, which is efficient for low-rank operators but infeasible on near-term quantum devices due to the extensive gate overhead. In this work, we demonstrate a scalable classical shadow tomography approach for generic randomized measurements implemented with finite-depth local Clifford random unitary circuits, which interpolates between the limits of Pauli and Clifford measurements. The method combines the recently proposed locally-scrambled classical shadow tomography framework with tensor network techniques to achieve scalability for computing the classical shadow reconstruction map and evaluating various physical properties. The method enables classical shadow tomography to be performed on shallow quantum circuits with superior sample efficiency and minimal gate overhead and is friendly to noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. We show that the shallow-circuit measurement protocol provides immediate, exponential advantages over the Pauli measurement protocol for predicting quasi-local operators. It also enables a more efficient fidelity estimation compared to the Pauli measurement.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Approximate Degree of DNF and CNF Formulas</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01584</link>
    <author>Alexander A. Sherstov</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The approximate degree of a Boolean function $f\colon\{0,1\}^n\to\{0,1\}$ is the minimum degree of a real polynomial $p$ that approximates $f$ pointwise: $|f(x)-p(x)|\leq1/3$ for all $x\in\{0,1\}^n.$ For every $\delta>0,$ we construct CNF and DNF formulas of polynomial size with approximate degree $\Omega(n^{1-\delta}),$ essentially matching the trivial upper bound of $n.$ This improves polynomially on previous lower bounds and fully resolves the approximate degree of constant-depth circuits ($\text{AC}^0$), a question that has seen extensive research over the past 10 years. Previously, an $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$ lower bound was known only for $\text{AC}^0$ circuits of depth that grows with $1/\delta$ (Bun and Thaler, FOCS 2017). Moreover, our CNF and DNF formulas are the simplest possible in that they have constant width. Our result holds even for one-sided approximation, and has the following further consequences. (i) We essentially settle the communication complexity of $\text{AC}^0$ circuits in the bounded-error quantum model, $k$-party number-on-the-forehead randomized model, and $k$-party number-on-the-forehead nondeterministic model: we prove that for every $\delta>0$, these models require $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$, $\Omega(n/4^kk^2)^{1-\delta}$, and $\Omega(n/4^kk^2)^{1-\delta}$, respectively, bits of communication even for polynomial-size constant-width CNF formulas. (ii) In particular, we show that the multiparty communication class $\text{coNP}_k$ can be separated essentially optimally from $\text{NP}_k$ and $\text{BPP}_k$ by a particularly simple function, a polynomial-size constant-width CNF. (iii) We give an essentially tight separation, of $O(1)$ versus $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$, for the one-sided versus two-sided approximate degree of a function; and $O(1)$ versus $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$ for the one-sided approximate degree of a function $f$ versus its negation $\neg f$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Inequalities witnessing coherence, nonlocality, and contextuality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02670</link>
    <author>Rafael Wagner, Rui Soares Barbosa, Ernesto F. Galvão</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum coherence, nonlocality, and contextuality are key resources for quantum advantage in metrology, communication, and computation. We introduce a graph-based approach to derive classicality inequalities that bound local, non-contextual, and coherence-free models, offering a unified description of these seemingly disparate quantum resources. Our approach generalizes recently proposed basis-independent coherence witnesses, and recovers all non-contextuality inequalities of the exclusivity graph approach. Moreover, violations of certain classicality inequalities witness preparation contextuality. We describe an algorithm to find all such classicality inequalities, and use it to analyze some of the simplest scenarios.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>