<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Bosonic coding: introduction and use cases</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05714</link>
    <author>Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bosonic or continuous-variable coding is a field concerned with robust quantum information processing and communication with electromagnetic signals or mechanical modes. I review bosonic quantum memories, characterizing them as either bosonic stabilizer or bosonic Fock-state codes. I then enumerate various applications of bosonic encodings, four of which circumvent no-go theorems due to the intrinsic infinite-dimensionality of bosonic systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Continuous-variable quantum state designs: theory and applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05127</link>
    <author>Joseph T. Iosue, Kunal Sharma, Michael J. Gullans, Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We generalize the notion of quantum state designs to infinite-dimensional spaces. We first prove that, under the definition of continuous-variable (CV) state $t$-designs from Comm. Math. Phys. 326, 755 (2014), no state designs exist for $t\geq2$. Similarly, we prove that no CV unitary $t$-designs exist for $t\geq 2$. We propose an alternative definition for CV state designs, which we call rigged $t$-designs, and provide explicit constructions for $t=2$. As an application of rigged designs, we develop a design-based shadow-tomography protocol for CV states. Using energy-constrained versions of rigged designs, we define an average fidelity for CV quantum channels and relate this fidelity to the CV entanglement fidelity. As an additional result of independent interest, we establish a connection between torus $2$-designs and complete sets of mutually unbiased bases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning quantum processes without input control</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05005</link>
    <author>Marco Fanizza, Yihui Quek, Matteo Rosati</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a general statistical learning theory for processes that take as input a classical random variable and output a quantum state. This is a practically motivated setting where the learner wants to find an approximate representation of an unknown quantum process, without having control on the classical inputs that govern the process itself, e.g., in learning astronomical processes, studying disordered systems and biological processes not controlled by the observer. We provide an algorithm for learning with high probability in this setting with a finite amount of samples, even if the concept class is infinite. To do this, we review and adapt existing algorithms for shadow tomography and hypothesis selection, and combine their guarantees with the uniform convergence on the data of the loss functions of interest. As a by-product we obtain sufficient conditions for performing shadow tomography of classical-quantum states with a number of copies which depend only on the dimension of the quantum register. We give concrete examples of processes that can be learned in this manner, based on quantum circuits or physically motivated scenarios like systems subject to Hamiltonians with random perturbations or data-dependent phase-shifts.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Black-Hole Radiation Decoding is Quantum Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05491</link>
    <author>Zvika Brakerski</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose to study equivalence relations between phenomena in high-energy physics and the existence of standard cryptographic primitives, and show the first example where such an equivalence holds. A small number of prior works showed that high-energy phenomena can be explained by cryptographic hardness. Examples include using the existence of one-way functions to explain the hardness of decoding black-hole Hawking radiation (Harlow and Hayden 2013, Aaronson 2016), and using pseudorandom quantum states to explain the hardness of computing AdS/CFT dictionary (Bouland, Fefferman and Vazirani, 2020). In this work we show, for the former example of black-hole radiation decoding, that it also implies the existence of secure quantum cryptography. In fact, we show an existential equivalence between the hardness of black-hole radiation decoding and a variety of cryptographic primitives, including bit-commitment schemes and oblivious transfer protocols (using quantum communication). This can be viewed (with proper disclaimers, as we discuss) as providing a physical justification for the existence of secure cryptography. We conjecture that such connections may be found in other high-energy physics phenomena.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Overcoming leakage in scalable quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.04728</link>
    <author>Kevin C. Miao, Matt McEwen, Juan Atalaya, Dvir Kafri, Leonid P. Pryadko, Andreas Bengtsson, Alex Opremcak, Kevin J. Satzinger, Zijun Chen, Paul V. Klimov, Chris Quintana, Rajeev Acharya, Kyle Anderson, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Joseph C. Bardin, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, et al (97)</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Leakage of quantum information out of computational states into higher energy states represents a major challenge in the pursuit of quantum error correction (QEC). In a QEC circuit, leakage builds over time and spreads through multi-qubit interactions. This leads to correlated errors that degrade the exponential suppression of logical error with scale, challenging the feasibility of QEC as a path towards fault-tolerant quantum computation. Here, we demonstrate the execution of a distance-3 surface code and distance-21 bit-flip code on a Sycamore quantum processor where leakage is removed from all qubits in each cycle. This shortens the lifetime of leakage and curtails its ability to spread and induce correlated errors. We report a ten-fold reduction in steady-state leakage population on the data qubits encoding the logical state and an average leakage population of less than $1 \times 10^{-3}$ throughout the entire device. The leakage removal process itself efficiently returns leakage population back to the computational basis, and adding it to a code circuit prevents leakage from inducing correlated error across cycles, restoring a fundamental assumption of QEC. With this demonstration that leakage can be contained, we resolve a key challenge for practical QEC at scale.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>