<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Complexity of NISQ</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07234</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Jordan Cotler, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Jerry Li</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recent proliferation of NISQ devices has made it imperative to understand their computational power. In this work, we define and study the complexity class $\textsf{NISQ} $, which is intended to encapsulate problems that can be efficiently solved by a classical computer with access to a NISQ device. To model existing devices, we assume the device can (1) noisily initialize all qubits, (2) apply many noisy quantum gates, and (3) perform a noisy measurement on all qubits. We first give evidence that $\textsf{BPP}\subsetneq \textsf{NISQ}\subsetneq \textsf{BQP}$, by demonstrating super-polynomial oracle separations among the three classes, based on modifications of Simon's problem. We then consider the power of $\textsf{NISQ}$ for three well-studied problems. For unstructured search, we prove that $\textsf{NISQ}$ cannot achieve a Grover-like quadratic speedup over $\textsf{BPP}$. For the Bernstein-Vazirani problem, we show that $\textsf{NISQ}$ only needs a number of queries logarithmic in what is required for $\textsf{BPP}$. Finally, for a quantum state learning problem, we prove that $\textsf{NISQ}$ is exponentially weaker than classical computation with access to noiseless constant-depth quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Quantum Fourier Transform Has Small Entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.08468</link>
    <author>Jielun Chen, E.M. Stoudenmire, Steven R. White</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Fourier Transform (QFT) is a key component of many important quantum algorithms, most famously as being the essential ingredient in Shor's algorithm for factoring products of primes. Given its remarkable capability, one would think it can introduce large entanglement to qubit systems and would be difficult to simulate classically. While early results showed QFT indeed has maximal operator entanglement, we show that this is entirely due to the bit reversal in the QFT. The core part of the QFT has Schmidt coefficients decaying exponentially quickly, and thus it can only generate a constant amount of entanglement regardless of the number of qubits. In addition, we show the entangling power of the QFT is the same as the time evolution of a Hamiltonian with exponentially decaying interactions, and thus a variant of the area law for dynamics can be used to understand the low entanglement intuitively. Using the low entanglement property of the QFT, we show that classical simulations of the QFT on a matrix product state with low bond dimension only take time linear in the number of qubits, providing a potential speedup over the classical fast Fourier transform (FFT) on many classes of functions. We demonstrate this speedup in test calculations on some simple functions. For data vectors of length $10^6$ to $10^8$, the speedup can be a few orders of magnitude.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exponentially tighter bounds on limitations of quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11505</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Daniel Stilck França, Sumeet Khatri, Johannes Jakob Meyer, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation has been proposed as a means to combat unavoidable errors in near-term quantum computing by classically post-processing outcomes of multiple quantum circuits. It does so in a fashion that requires no or few additional quantum resources, in contrast to fault-tolerant schemes that come along with heavy overheads. Error mitigation leads to noise reduction in small systems. In this work, however, we identify strong limitations to the degree to which quantum noise can be effectively `undone' for larger system sizes. We start out by presenting a formal framework that rigorously encapsulates large classes of meaningful and practically applied schemes for quantum error mitigation, including virtual distillation, Clifford data regression, zero-noise extrapolation and probabilistic error cancellation. With the framework in place, our technical contribution is to construct families of random circuits that are highly sensitive to noise, in the sense that even at log log(n) depth, a whisker beyond constant, quantum noise is seen to super-exponentially rapidly scramble their output into the maximally-mixed state. Our results exponentially tighten known arguments for error mitigation, but they go beyond that: Our arguments can be applied to kernel estimation or to compute the depth at which barren plateaus emerge, implying that the scrambling kicks in at exponentially smaller depths than previously thought. Our results also say that a noisy device must be sampled exponentially many times to estimate expectation values. There are classical algorithms that exhibit the same scaling in complexity. While improvements in quantum hardware will push noise levels down, if error mitigation is used, ultimately this can only lead to an exponential time quantum algorithm with a better exponent, putting up a strong obstruction to the hope for exponential quantum speedups in this setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning to predict arbitrary quantum processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14894</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Sitan Chen, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an efficient machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting any unknown quantum process $\mathcal{E}$ over $n$ qubits. For a wide range of distributions $\mathcal{D}$ on arbitrary $n$-qubit states, we show that this ML algorithm can learn to predict any local property of the output from the unknown process $\mathcal{E}$, with a small average error over input states drawn from $\mathcal{D}$. The ML algorithm is computationally efficient even when the unknown process is a quantum circuit with exponentially many gates. Our algorithm combines efficient procedures for learning properties of an unknown state and for learning a low-degree approximation to an unknown observable. The analysis hinges on proving new norm inequalities, including a quantum analogue of the classical Bohnenblust-Hille inequality, which we derive by giving an improved algorithm for optimizing local Hamiltonians. Overall, our results highlight the potential for ML models to predict the output of complex quantum dynamics much faster than the time needed to run the process itself.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.00921</link>
    <author>Zhenyu Cai, Ryan Babbush, Simon C. Benjamin, Suguru Endo, William J. Huggins, Ying Li, Jarrod R. McClean, Thomas E. O'Brien</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For quantum computers to successfully solve real-world problems, it is necessary to tackle the challenge of noise: the errors which occur in elementary physical components due to unwanted or imperfect interactions. The theory of quantum fault tolerance can provide an answer in the long term, but in the coming era of `NISQ' machines we must seek to mitigate errors rather than completely remove them. This review surveys the diverse methods that have been proposed for quantum error mitigation, assesses their in-principle efficacy, and then describes the hardware demonstrations achieved to date. We identify the commonalities and limitations among the methods, noting how mitigation methods can be chosen according to the primary type of noise present, including algorithmic errors. Open problems in the field are identified and we discuss the prospects for realising mitigation-based devices that can deliver quantum advantage with an impact on science and business.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Challenges in Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15844</link>
    <author>Daniel Gottesman</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I will give an overview of what I see as some of the most important future directions in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation. In particular, I will give a brief summary of the major problems that need to be solved in fault tolerance based on low-density parity check codes and in hardware-specific fault tolerance. I will then conclude with a discussion of a possible new paradigm for designing fault-tolerant protocols based on a space-time picture of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise can be helpful for variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06723</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Frederik Wilde, Antonio Anna Mele, Liang Jiang, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Saddle points constitute a crucial challenge for first-order gradient descent algorithms. In notions of classical machine learning, they are avoided for example by means of stochastic gradient descent methods. In this work, we provide evidence that the saddle points problem can be naturally avoided in variational quantum algorithms by exploiting the presence of stochasticity. We prove convergence guarantees of the approach and its practical functioning at hand of examples. We argue that the natural stochasticity of variational algorithms can be beneficial for avoiding strict saddle points, i.e., those saddle points with at least one negative Hessian eigenvalue. This insight that some noise levels could help in this perspective is expected to add a new perspective to notions of near-term variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning many-body Hamiltonians with Heisenberg-limited scaling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03030</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Yu Tong, Di Fang, Yuan Su</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Learning a many-body Hamiltonian from its dynamics is a fundamental problem in physics. In this work, we propose the first algorithm to achieve the Heisenberg limit for learning an interacting $N$-qubit local Hamiltonian. After a total evolution time of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-1})$, the proposed algorithm can efficiently estimate any parameter in the $N$-qubit Hamiltonian to $\epsilon$-error with high probability. The proposed algorithm is robust against state preparation and measurement error, does not require eigenstates or thermal states, and only uses $\mathrm{polylog}(\epsilon^{-1})$ experiments. In contrast, the best previous algorithms, such as recent works using gradient-based optimization or polynomial interpolation, require a total evolution time of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ and $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ experiments. Our algorithm uses ideas from quantum simulation to decouple the unknown $N$-qubit Hamiltonian $H$ into noninteracting patches, and learns $H$ using a quantum-enhanced divide-and-conquer approach. We prove a matching lower bound to establish the asymptotic optimality of our algorithm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum divide and conquer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06419</link>
    <author>Andrew M. Childs, Robin Kothari, Matt Kovacs-Deak, Aarthi Sundaram, Daochen Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The divide-and-conquer framework, used extensively in classical algorithm design, recursively breaks a problem of size $n$ into smaller subproblems (say, $a$ copies of size $n/b$ each), along with some auxiliary work of cost $C^{\textrm{aux}}(n)$, to give a recurrence relation $$C(n) ≤a \,C(n/b) + C^\textrmaux(n)$$ for the classical complexity $C(n)$. We describe a quantum divide-and-conquer framework that, in certain cases, yields an analogous recurrence relation $$C_Q(n) ≤\sqrta \u2009C_Q(n/b) + O(C^\textrmaux_Q(n))$$ that characterizes the quantum query complexity. We apply this framework to obtain near-optimal quantum query complexities for various string problems, such as (i) recognizing regular languages; (ii) decision versions of String Rotation and String Suffix; and natural parameterized versions of (iii) Longest Increasing Subsequence and (iv) Longest Common Subsequence.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Unitary property testing lower bounds by polynomials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05885</link>
    <author>Adrian She, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study unitary property testing, where a quantum algorithm is given query access to a black-box unitary and has to decide whether it satisfies some property. In addition to containing the standard quantum query complexity model (where the unitary encodes a binary string) as a special case, this model contains "inherently quantum" problems that have no classical analogue. Characterizing the query complexity of these problems requires new algorithmic techniques and lower bound methods. Our main contribution is a generalized polynomial method for unitary property testing problems. By leveraging connections with invariant theory, we apply this method to obtain lower bounds on problems such as determining recurrence times of unitaries, approximating the dimension of a marked subspace, and approximating the entanglement entropy of a marked state. We also present a unitary property testing-based approach towards an oracle separation between $\mathsf{QMA}$ and $\mathsf{QMA(2)}$, a long standing question in quantum complexity theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Observation of non-Abelian exchange statistics on a superconducting processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10255</link>
    <author>Trond I. Andersen, Yuri D. Lensky, Kostyantyn Kechedzhi, Ilya Drozdov, Andreas Bengtsson, Sabrina Hong, Alexis Morvan, Xiao Mi, Alex Opremcak, Rajeev Acharya, Richard Allen, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Gina Bortoli, et al (149)</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Indistinguishability of particles is a fundamental principle of quantum mechanics. For all elementary and quasiparticles observed to date - including fermions, bosons, and Abelian anyons - this principle guarantees that the braiding of identical particles leaves the system unchanged. However, in two spatial dimensions, an intriguing possibility exists: braiding of non-Abelian anyons causes rotations in a space of topologically degenerate wavefunctions. Hence, it can change the observables of the system without violating the principle of indistinguishability. Despite the well developed mathematical description of non-Abelian anyons and numerous theoretical proposals, their experimental observation has remained elusive for decades. Using a superconducting quantum processor, we prepare the ground state of the surface code and manipulate it via unitary operations to form wavefunctions that are described by non-Abelian anyons. By implementing a unitary protocol to move the anyons, we experimentally verify the fusion rules of non-Abelian Ising anyons and braid them to realize their statistics. Building on our technique, we study the prospect of employing the anyons for quantum computation and utilize braiding to create an entangled state of anyons encoding three logical qubits. Our work represents a key step towards topological quantum computing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Circuit depth versus energy in topologically ordered systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06796</link>
    <author>Arkin Tikku, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove a nontrivial circuit-depth lower bound for preparing a low-energy state of a locally interacting quantum many-body system in two dimensions, assuming the circuit is geometrically local. For preparing any state which has an energy density of at most $\epsilon$ with respect to Kitaev's toric code Hamiltonian on a two dimensional lattice $\Lambda$, we prove a lower bound of $\Omega\left(\min\left(1/\epsilon^{\frac{1-\alpha}{2}}, \sqrt{|\Lambda|}\right)\right)$ for any $\alpha >0$. We discuss two implications. First, our bound implies that the lowest energy density obtainable from a large class of existing variational circuits (e.g., Hamiltonian variational ansatz) cannot, in general, decay exponentially with the circuit depth. Second, if long-range entanglement is present in the ground state, this can lead to a nontrivial circuit-depth lower bound even at nonzero energy density. Unlike previous approaches to prove circuit-depth lower bounds for preparing low energy states, our proof technique does not rely on the ground state to be degenerate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A classical oracle separation between QMA and QCMA</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15380</link>
    <author>Anand Natarajan, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It is a long-standing open question in quantum complexity theory whether the definition of $\textit{non-deterministic}$ quantum computation requires quantum witnesses $(\textsf{QMA})$ or if classical witnesses suffice $(\textsf{QCMA})$. We make progress on this question by constructing a randomized classical oracle separating the respective computational complexity classes. Previous separations [Aaronson-Kuperberg (CCC'07), Fefferman-Kimmel (MFCS'18)] required a quantum unitary oracle. The separating problem is deciding whether a distribution supported on regular un-directed graphs either consists of multiple connected components (yes instances) or consists of one expanding connected component (no instances) where the graph is given in an adjacency-list format by the oracle. Therefore, the oracle is a distribution over $n$-bit boolean functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum state preparation without coherent arithmetic</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14892</link>
    <author>Sam McArdle, András Gilyén, Mario Berta</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a versatile method for preparing a quantum state whose amplitudes are given by some known function. Unlike existing approaches, our method does not require handcrafted reversible arithmetic circuits, or quantum memory loads, to encode the function values. Instead, we use a template quantum eigenvalue transformation circuit to convert a low cost block encoding of the sine function into the desired function. Our method uses only 4 ancilla qubits (3 if the approximating polynomial has definite parity), providing order-of-magnitude qubit count reductions compared to state-of-the-art approaches, while using a similar number of Toffoli gates if the function can be well represented by a polynomial or Fourier approximation. Like black-box methods, the complexity of our approach depends on the 'L2-norm filling-fraction' of the function. We demonstrate the efficiency of our method for preparing states commonly used in quantum algorithms, such as Gaussian and Kaiser window states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from classical LTCs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02999</link>
    <author>Zhiyang He, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide a completely self-contained construction of a family of NLTS Hamiltonians [Freedman and Hastings, 2014] based on ideas from [Anshu, Breuckmann, and Nirkhe, 2022], [Cross, He, Natarajan, Szegedy, and Zhu, 2022] and [Eldar and Harrow, 2017]. Crucially, it does not require optimal-parameter quantum LDPC codes and can be built from simple classical LTCs such as the repetition code on an expander graph. Furthermore, it removes the constant-rate requirement from the construction of Anshu, Breuckmann, and Nirkhe.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Depth in the Random Oracle Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06454</link>
    <author>Atul Singh Arora, Andrea Coladangelo, Matthew Coudron, Alexandru Gheorghiu, Uttam Singh, Hendrik Waldner</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a comprehensive characterization of the computational power of shallow quantum circuits combined with classical computation. Specifically, for classes of search problems, we show that the following statements hold, relative to a random oracle: (a) $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}}} \neq \mathsf{BQP}$. This refutes Jozsa's conjecture [QIP 05] in the random oracle model. As a result, this gives the first instantiatable separation between the classes by replacing the oracle with a cryptographic hash function, yielding a resolution to one of Aaronson's ten semi-grand challenges in quantum computing. (b) $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}} \nsubseteq \mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}}$ and $\mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}} \nsubseteq \mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}}$. This shows that there is a subtle interplay between classical computation and shallow quantum computation. In fact, for the second separation, we establish that, for some problems, the ability to perform adaptive measurements in a single shallow quantum circuit, is more useful than the ability to perform polynomially many shallow quantum circuits without adaptive measurements. (c) There exists a 2-message proof of quantum depth protocol. Such a protocol allows a classical verifier to efficiently certify that a prover must be performing a computation of some minimum quantum depth. Our proof of quantum depth can be instantiated using the recent proof of quantumness construction by Yamakawa and Zhandry [STOC 22].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum communication complexity of linear regression</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.01601</link>
    <author>Ashley Montanaro, Changpeng Shao</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Dequantized algorithms show that quantum computers do not have exponential speedups for many linear algebra problems in terms of time and query complexity. In this work, we show that quantum computers can have exponential speedups in terms of communication complexity for some fundamental linear algebra problems. We mainly focus on solving linear regression and Hamiltonian simulation. In the quantum case, the task is to prepare the quantum state of the result. To allow for a fair comparison, in the classical case the task is to sample from the result. We investigate these two problems in two-party and multiparty models, propose near-optimal quantum protocols and prove quantum/classical lower bounds. In this process, we propose an efficient quantum protocol for quantum singular value transformation, which is a powerful technique for designing quantum algorithms. As a result, for many linear algebra problems where quantum computers lose exponential speedups in terms of time and query complexity, it is possible to have exponential speedups in terms of communication complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical simulation of short-time quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11490</link>
    <author>Dominik S. Wild, Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Locality is a key simplifying feature of many physical systems. Cluster expansion techniques provide one particular way of exploiting it. They have historically appeared in statistical physics to prove the uniqueness of Gibbs states and the decay of correlations at high temperature, among many other results. Here, we apply these techniques to quantum many-body systems evolving under local Hamiltonians. We consider the evolution of both local observables and non-local quantities such as the Loschmidt echo. We show that for a product initial state, the cluster expansion enables efficient classical computation of the dynamics up to a fixed evolution time, independent of the system size. The computational cost scales polynomially with the system size and the inverse of the approximation error. In the case of local observables, we can extend the evolution time to any constant value using analytic continuation. In more than one dimension, the resulting algorithm has a better dependence on the approximation error than algorithms based on the Lieb-Robinson bound. Our algorithms rely on the convergence of the cluster expansion, which also has important physical consequences. In particular, we establish a novel quantum speed limit, a bound on dynamical phase transitions, and a concentration bound for product states evolved for short times.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Representation Theory for Geometric Quantum Machine Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07980</link>
    <author>Michael Ragone, Paolo Braccia, Quynh T. Nguyen, Louis Schatzki, Patrick J. Coles, Frederic Sauvage, Martin Larocca, M. Cerezo</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent advances in classical machine learning have shown that creating models with inductive biases encoding the symmetries of a problem can greatly improve performance. Importation of these ideas, combined with an existing rich body of work at the nexus of quantum theory and symmetry, has given rise to the field of Geometric Quantum Machine Learning (GQML). Following the success of its classical counterpart, it is reasonable to expect that GQML will play a crucial role in developing problem-specific and quantum-aware models capable of achieving a computational advantage. Despite the simplicity of the main idea of GQML -- create architectures respecting the symmetries of the data -- its practical implementation requires a significant amount of knowledge of group representation theory. We present an introduction to representation theory tools from the optics of quantum learning, driven by key examples involving discrete and continuous groups. These examples are sewn together by an exposition outlining the formal capture of GQML symmetries via "label invariance under the action of a group representation", a brief (but rigorous) tour through finite and compact Lie group representation theory, a reexamination of ubiquitous tools like Haar integration and twirling, and an overview of some successful strategies for detecting symmetries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Autonomous quantum error correction and fault-tolerant quantum computation with squeezed cat qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.13406</link>
    <author>Qian Xu, Guo Zheng, Yu-Xin Wang, Peter Zoller, Aashish A. Clerk, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose an autonomous quantum error correction scheme using squeezed cat (SC) code against the dominant error source, excitation loss, in continuous-variable systems. Through reservoir engineering, we show that a structured dissipation can stabilize a two-component SC while autonomously correcting the errors. The implementation of such dissipation only requires low-order nonlinear couplings among three bosonic modes or between a bosonic mode and a qutrit. While our proposed scheme is device independent, it is readily implementable with current experimental platforms such as superconducting circuits and trapped-ion systems. Compared to the stabilized cat, the stabilized SC has a much lower dominant error rate and a significantly enhanced noise bias. Furthermore, the bias-preserving operations for the SC have much lower error rates. In combination, the stabilized SC leads to substantially better logical performance when concatenating with an outer discrete-variable code. The surface-SC scheme achieves more than one order of magnitude increase in the threshold ratio between the loss rate $\kappa_1$ and the engineered dissipation rate $\kappa_2$. Under a practical noise ratio $\kappa_1/\kappa_2 = 10^{-3}$, the repetition-SC scheme can reach a $10^{-15}$ logical error rate even with a small mean excitation number of 4, which already suffices for practically useful quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Event Learning and Gentle Random Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.09155</link>
    <author>Adam Bene Watts, John Bostanci</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove the expected disturbance caused to a quantum system by a sequence of randomly ordered two-outcome projective measurements is upper bounded by the square root of the probability that at least one measurement in the sequence accepts. We call this bound the Gentle Random Measurement Lemma. We also extend the techniques used to prove this lemma to develop protocols for problems in which we are given sample access to an unknown state $\rho$ and asked to estimate properties of the accepting probabilities $\text{Tr}[M_i \rho]$ of a set of measurements $\{M_1, M_2, ... , M_m\}$. We call these types of problems Quantum Event Learning Problems. In particular, we show randomly ordering projective measurements solves the Quantum OR problem, answering an open question of Aaronson. We also give a Quantum OR protocol which works on non-projective measurements and which outperforms both the random measurement protocol analyzed in this paper and the protocol of Harrow, Lin, and Montanaro. However, this protocol requires a more complicated type of measurement, which we call a Blended Measurement. When the total (summed) accepting probability of unlikely events is bounded, we show the random and blended measurement Quantum OR protocols developed in this paper can also be used to find a measurement $M_i$ such that $\text{Tr}[M_i \rho]$ is large. We call the problem of finding such a measurement Quantum Event Finding. Finally, we show Blended Measurements also give a sample-efficient protocol for Quantum Mean Estimation: a problem in which the goal is to estimate the average accepting probability of a set of measurements on an unknown state.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Greatly improved higher-order product formulae for quantum simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15817</link>
    <author>Mauro E.S. Morales, Pedro C.S. Costa, Daniel K. Burgarth, Yuval R. Sanders, Dominic W. Berry</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for simulation of Hamiltonian evolution are often based on product formulae like Trotter. The fractal method of Suzuki gives a systematic way to find arbitrarily high-order product formulae, but results in a large number of exponentials. On the other hand, an alternative way, with a minimum number of exponentials, for 6th and 8th order product formulae is given by Yoshida. In this work, we not only extended Yoshida's method to 10th order, but we also found hundreds of new 8th order product formulae. Moreover, we found an 8th order product formula that is over $1000$ times more accurate than the best product formula of Yoshida.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Purification-based quantum error mitigation of pair-correlated electron simulations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10799</link>
    <author>T. E. O'Brien, G. Anselmetti, F. Gkritsis, V. E. Elfving, S. Polla, W. J. Huggins, O. Oumarou, K. Kechedzhi, D. Abanin, R. Acharya, I. Aleiner, R. Allen, T. I. Andersen, K. Anderson, M. Ansmann, F. Arute, K. Arya, A. Asfaw, J. Atalaya, D. Bacon, et al (156)</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An important measure of the development of quantum computing platforms has been the simulation of increasingly complex physical systems. Prior to fault-tolerant quantum computing, robust error mitigation strategies are necessary to continue this growth. Here, we study physical simulation within the seniority-zero electron pairing subspace, which affords both a computational stepping stone to a fully correlated model, and an opportunity to validate recently introduced ``purification-based'' error-mitigation strategies. We compare the performance of error mitigation based on doubling quantum resources in time (echo verification) or in space (virtual distillation), on up to $20$ qubits of a superconducting qubit quantum processor. We observe a reduction of error by one to two orders of magnitude below less sophisticated techniques (e.g. post-selection); the gain from error mitigation is seen to increase with the system size. Employing these error mitigation strategies enables the implementation of the largest variational algorithm for a correlated chemistry system to-date. Extrapolating performance from these results allows us to estimate minimum requirements for a beyond-classical simulation of electronic structure. We find that, despite the impressive gains from purification-based error mitigation, significant hardware improvements will be required for classically intractable variational chemistry simulations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Random-Bond Ising Model and its dual in Hyperbolic Spaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07227</link>
    <author>Benedikt Placke, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the thermodynamic properties of the random-bond Ising model (RBIM) on closed hyperbolic surfaces using Monte Carlo and high-temperature series expansion techniques. We also analyze the dual-RBIM, that is the model that in the absence of disorder is related to the RBIM via the Kramers-Wannier duality. Even on self-dual lattices this model is different from the RBIM, unlike in the euclidean case. We explain this anomaly by a careful re-derivation of the Kramers--Wannier duality. For the (dual-)RBIM, we compute the paramagnet-to-ferromagnet phase transition as a function of both temperature $T$ and the fraction of antiferromagnetic bonds $p$. We find that as temperature is decreased in the RBIM, the paramagnet gives way to either a ferromagnet or a spin-glass phase via a second-order transition compatible with mean-field behavior. In contrast, the dual-RBIM undergoes a strongly first order transition from the paramagnet to the ferromagnet both in the absence of disorder and along the Nishimori line. We study both transitions for a variety of hyperbolic tessellations and comment on the role of coordination number and curvature. The extent of the ferromagnetic phase in the dual-RBIM corresponds to the correctable phase of hyperbolic surface codes under independent bit- and phase-flip noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement-based quantum computation in finite one-dimensional systems: string order implies computational power</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05089</link>
    <author>Robert Raussendorf, Wang Yang, Arnab Adhikary</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a new framework for assessing the power of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) on short-range entangled symmetric resource states, in spatial dimension one. It requires fewer assumptions than previously known. The formalism can handle finitely extended systems (as opposed to the thermodynamic limit), and does not require translation-invariance. Further, we strengthen the connection between MBQC computational power and string order. Namely, we establish that whenever a suitable set of string order parameters is non-zero, a corresponding set of unitary gates can be realized with fidelity arbitrarily close to unity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Floquet codes without parent subsystem codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02468</link>
    <author>Margarita Davydova, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Shankar Balasubramanian</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a new class of error-correcting dynamic codes in two and three dimensions that has no explicit connection to any parent subsystem code. The two-dimensional code, which we call the CSS Floquet code, is geometrically similar to that of the honeycomb code by Hastings and Haah, and also dynamically embeds an instantaneous toric code. However, unlike the honeycomb code it possesses an explicit CSS structure and its gauge checks do not form a subsystem code. Nevertheless, we show that our dynamic protocol conserves logical information and possesses a threshold for error correction. We generalize this construction to three dimensions and obtain a code that fault-tolerantly alternates between realizing two type-I fracton models, the checkerboard and the X-cube model. Finally, we show the compatibility of our CSS Floquet code protocol and the honeycomb code by showing the possibility of randomly switching between the two protocols without information loss while still measuring error syndromes. We call this more general aperiodic structure `dynamic tree codes', which we also generalize to three dimensions. Under a certain correlated randomness constraint, this code is error correcting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Doubling the order of approximation via the randomized product formula</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11281</link>
    <author>Chien Hung Cho, Dominic W. Berry, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Randomization has been applied to Hamiltonian simulation in a number of ways to improve the accuracy or efficiency of product formulas. Deterministic product formulas are often constructed in a symmetric way to provide accuracy of even order 2k. We show that by applying randomized corrections, it is possible to more than double the order to 4k + 1 (corresponding to a doubling of the order of the error). In practice, applying the corrections in a quantum algorithm requires some structure to the Hamiltonian, for example the Pauli strings as are used in the simulation of quantum chemistry.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Algorithms for Sampling Log-Concave Distributions and Estimating Normalizing Constants</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06539</link>
    <author>Andrew M. Childs, Tongyang Li, Jin-Peng Liu, Chunhao Wang, Ruizhe Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a convex function $f\colon\mathbb{R}^{d}\to\mathbb{R}$, the problem of sampling from a distribution $\propto e^{-f(x)}$ is called log-concave sampling. This task has wide applications in machine learning, physics, statistics, etc. In this work, we develop quantum algorithms for sampling log-concave distributions and for estimating their normalizing constants $\int_{\mathbb{R}^d}e^{-f(x)}\mathrm{d} x$. First, we use underdamped Langevin diffusion to develop quantum algorithms that match the query complexity (in terms of the condition number $\kappa$ and dimension $d$) of analogous classical algorithms that use gradient (first-order) queries, even though the quantum algorithms use only evaluation (zeroth-order) queries. For estimating normalizing constants, these algorithms also achieve quadratic speedup in the multiplicative error $\epsilon$. Second, we develop quantum Metropolis-adjusted Langevin algorithms with query complexity $\widetilde{O}(\kappa^{1/2}d)$ and $\widetilde{O}(\kappa^{1/2}d^{3/2}/\epsilon)$ for log-concave sampling and normalizing constant estimation, respectively, achieving polynomial speedups in $\kappa,d,\epsilon$ over the best known classical algorithms by exploiting quantum analogs of the Monte Carlo method and quantum walks. We also prove a $1/\epsilon^{1-o(1)}$ quantum lower bound for estimating normalizing constants, implying near-optimality of our quantum algorithms in $\epsilon$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Commitments to Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05138</link>
    <author>Sam Gunn, Nathan Ju, Fermi Ma, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>What does it mean to commit to a quantum state? In this work, we propose a simple answer: a commitment to quantum messages is binding if, after the commit phase, the committed state is hidden from the sender's view. We accompany this new definition with several instantiations. We build the first non-interactive succinct quantum state commitments, which can be seen as an analogue of collision-resistant hashing for quantum messages. We also show that hiding quantum state commitments (QSCs) are implied by any commitment scheme for classical messages. All of our constructions can be based on quantum-cryptographic assumptions that are implied by but are potentially weaker than one-way functions. Commitments to quantum states open the door to many new cryptographic possibilities. Our flagship application of a succinct QSC is a quantum-communication version of Kilian's succinct arguments for any language that has quantum PCPs with constant error and polylogarithmic locality. Plugging in the PCP theorem, this yields succinct arguments for NP under significantly weaker assumptions than required classically; moreover, if the quantum PCP conjecture holds, this extends to QMA. At the heart of our security proof is a new rewinding technique for extracting quantum information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A super-polynomial quantum-classical separation for density modelling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14936</link>
    <author>Niklas Pirnay, Ryan Sweke, Jens Eisert, Jean-Pierre Seifert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Density modelling is the task of learning an unknown probability density function from samples, and is one of the central problems of unsupervised machine learning. In this work, we show that there exists a density modelling problem for which fault-tolerant quantum computers can offer a super-polynomial advantage over classical learning algorithms, given standard cryptographic assumptions. Along the way, we provide a variety of additional results and insights, of potential interest for proving future distribution learning separations between quantum and classical learning algorithms. Specifically, we (a) provide an overview of the relationships between hardness results in supervised learning and distribution learning, and (b) show that any weak pseudo-random function can be used to construct a classically hard density modelling problem. The latter result opens up the possibility of proving quantum-classical separations for density modelling based on weaker assumptions than those necessary for pseudo-random functions.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>