
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Uncomputability of Phase Diagrams</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01631</link>
    <author>Johannes Bausch, Toby S. Cubitt, James D. Watson</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 04 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The phase diagram of a material is of central importance to describe the properties and behaviour of a condensed matter system. We prove that the general task of determining the quantum phase diagram of a many-body Hamiltonian is uncomputable, by explicitly constructing a one-parameter family of Hamiltonians for which this is the case. This work builds off recent results from Cubitt et al. and Bausch et al., proving undecidability of the spectral gap problem. However, in all previous constructions, the Hamiltonian was necessarily a discontinuous function of its parameters, making it difficult to derive rigorous implications for phase diagrams or related condensed matter questions. Our main technical contribution is to prove undecidability of the spectral gap for a continuous, single-parameter family of translationally invariant, nearest-neighbour spin-lattice Hamiltonians on a 2D square lattice: $H(\varphi)$ where $\varphi\in \mathbb R$. As well as implying uncomputablity of phase diagrams, our result also proves that undecidability can hold for a set of positive measure of a Hamiltonian's parameter space, whereas previous results only implied undecidability on a zero measure set.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Stochastic gradient descent for hybrid quantum-classical optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01155</link>
    <author>Ryan Sweke, Frederik Wilde, Johannes Meyer, Maria Schuld, Paul K. Fährmann, Barthélémy Meynard-Piganeau, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 04 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Within the context of hybrid quantum-classical optimization, gradient descent based optimizers typically require the evaluation of expectation values with respect to the outcome of parameterized quantum circuits. In this work, we explore the significant consequences of the simple observation that the estimation of these quantities on quantum hardware is a form of stochastic gradient descent optimization. We formalize this notion, which allows us to show that in many relevant cases, including VQE, QAOA and certain quantum classifiers, estimating expectation values with $k$ measurement outcomes results in optimization algorithms whose convergence properties can be rigorously well understood, for any value of $k$. In fact, even using single measurement outcomes for the estimation of expectation values is sufficient. Moreover, in many settings the required gradients can be expressed as linear combinations of expectation values -- originating, e.g., from a sum over local terms of a Hamiltonian, a parameter shift rule, or a sum over data-set instances -- and we show that in these cases $k$-shot expectation value estimation can be combined with sampling over terms of the linear combination, to obtain "doubly stochastic" gradient descent optimizers. For all algorithms we prove convergence guarantees, providing a framework for the derivation of rigorous optimization results in the context of near-term quantum devices. Additionally, we explore numerically these methods on benchmark VQE, QAOA and quantum-enhanced machine learning tasks and show that treating the stochastic settings as hyper-parameters allows for state-of-the-art results with significantly fewer circuit executions and measurements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Quantum Walk Circuits for Metropolis-Hastings Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01659</link>
    <author>Jessica Lemieux, Bettina Heim, David Poulin, Krysta Svore, Matthias Troyer</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We present a detailed circuit implementation of Szegedy's quantization of the Metropolis-Hastings walk. This quantum walk is usually defined with respect to an oracle. We find that a direct implementation of this oracle requires costly arithmetic operations and thus reformulate the quantum walk in a way that circumvents the implementation of that specific oracle and which closely follows the classical Metropolis-Hastings walk. We also present heuristic quantum algorithms that use the quantum walk in the context of discrete optimization problems and numerically study their performances. Our numerical results indicate polynomial quantum speedups in heuristic settings.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Challenges and Opportunities of Near-Term Quantum Computing Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02894</link>
    <author>A. D. Corcoles, A. Kandala, A. Javadi-Abhari, D. T. McClure, A. W. Cross, K. Temme, P. D. Nation, M. Steffen, J. M. Gambetta</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 08 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The concept of quantum computing has inspired a whole new generation of scientists, including physicists, engineers, and computer scientists, to fundamentally change the landscape of information technology. With experimental demonstrations stretching back more than two decades, the quantum computing community has achieved a major milestone over the past few years: the ability to build systems that are stretching the limits of what can be classically simulated, and which enable cloud-based research for a wide range of scientists, thus increasing the pool of talent exploring early quantum systems. While such noisy near-term quantum computing systems fall far short of the requirements for fault-tolerant systems, they provide unique testbeds for exploring the opportunities for quantum applications. Here we highlight the facets associated with these systems, including quantum software, cloud access, benchmarking quantum systems, error correction and mitigation in such systems, and understanding the complexity of quantum circuits and how early quantum applications can run on near term quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Detailed Analysis of Circuit-to-Hamiltonian Mappings</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01481</link>
    <author>James D. Watson</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 04 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The circuit-to-Hamiltonian construction has found widespread use within the field of Hamiltonian complexity, particularly for proving QMA-hardness results. In this work we examine the ground state energies of the Hamiltonian for standard clock constructions and those which require dynamic initialisation. We put exponentially tight bounds on these ground state energies and also determine improved scaling bounds in the case where there is a constant probability of the computation being rejected. Furthermore, we prove a collection of results concerning the low-energy subspace of quantum walks on a line with energy penalties appearing at any point along the walk and introduce some general tools that may be useful for such analyses.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Hamiltonian-Based Models and the Variational Quantum Thermalizer Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02071</link>
    <author>Guillaume Verdon, Jacob Marks, Sasha Nanda, Stefan Leichenauer, Jack Hidary</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new class of generative quantum-neural-network-based models called Quantum Hamiltonian-Based Models (QHBMs). In doing so, we establish a paradigmatic approach for quantum-probabilistic hybrid variational learning, where we efficiently decompose the tasks of learning classical and quantum correlations in a way which maximizes the utility of both classical and quantum processors. In addition, we introduce the Variational Quantum Thermalizer (VQT) for generating the thermal state of a given Hamiltonian and target temperature, a task for which QHBMs are naturally well-suited. The VQT can be seen as a generalization of the Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) to thermal states: we show that the VQT converges to the VQE in the zero temperature limit. We provide numerical results demonstrating the efficacy of these techniques in illustrative examples. We use QHBMs and the VQT on Heisenberg spin systems, we apply QHBMs to learn entanglement Hamiltonians and compression codes in simulated free Bosonic systems, and finally we use the VQT to prepare thermal Fermionic Gaussian states for quantum simulation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum encryption with certified deletion</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03551</link>
    <author>Anne Broadbent, Rabib Islam</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 09 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Given a ciphertext, is it possible to prove the deletion of the underlying plaintext? Since classical ciphertexts can be copied, clearly, such feat is impossible using classical information alone. In stark contrast to this, we show that quantum encodings allow such certified deletion. More precisely, we show that it is possible to encrypt classical data into a quantum ciphertext such that the recipient of the ciphertext can produce a classical string which proves to the originator that the recipient has relinquished any chance of recovering the plaintext, should the decryption key be revealed. Our scheme is feasible with current quantum technology: the honest parties only require quantum devices for single-qubit preparation and measurements, and is robust against noise in these devices. Furthermore, we provide an analysis that is suitable in the finite-key regime.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-unitary operations for ground-state calculations in near term quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01830</link>
    <author>Guglielmo Mazzola, Pauline Ollitrault, Panagiotis Barkoutsos, Ivano Tavernelli</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a quantum Monte Carlo inspired reweighting scheme to accurately compute energies from optimally short quantum circuits. This effectively hybrid quantum-classical approach features both entanglement provided by a short quantum circuit, and the presence of an effective non-unitary operator at the same time. The functional form of this projector is borrowed from classical computation and is able to filter-out high-energy components generated by a sub-optimal variational quantum heuristic ansatz. The accuracy of this approach is demonstrated numerically in finding energies of entangled ground-states of many-body lattice models. We demonstrate a practical implementation on IBM quantum hardwares up to an 8 qubits circuit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On Dimension-free Tail Inequalities for Sums of Random Matrices and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03718</link>
    <author>Chao Zhang, Min-Hsiu Hsieh, Dacheng Tao</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2019</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we present a new framework to obtain tail inequalities for sums of random matrices. Compared with existing works, our tail inequalities have the following characteristics: 1) high feasibility--they can be used to study the tail behavior of various matrix functions, e.g., arbitrary matrix norms, the absolute value of the sum of the sum of the $j$ largest singular values (resp. eigenvalues) of complex matrices (resp. Hermitian matrices); and 2) independence of matrix dimension --- they do not have the matrix-dimension term as a product factor, and thus are suitable to the scenario of high-dimensional or infinite-dimensional random matrices. The price we pay to obtain these advantages is that the convergence rate of the resulting inequalities will become slow when the number of summand random matrices is large. We also develop the tail inequalities for matrix random series and matrix martingale difference sequence. We also demonstrate usefulness of our tail bounds in several fields. In compressed sensing, we employ the resulted tail inequalities to achieve a proof of the restricted isometry property when the measurement matrix is the sum of random matrices without any assumption on the distributions of matrix entries. In probability theory, we derive a new upper bound to the supreme of stochastic processes. In machine learning, we prove new expectation bounds of sums of random matrices matrix and obtain matrix approximation schemes via random sampling. In quantum information, we show a new analysis relating to the fractional cover number of quantum hypergraphs. In theoretical computer science, we obtain randomness-efficient samplers using matrix expander graphs that can be efficiently implemented in time without dependence on matrix dimensions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Spectral sparsification of matrix inputs as a preprocessing step for quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02861</link>
    <author>Steven Herbert, Sathyawageeswar Subramanian</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 08 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We study the potential utility of classical techniques of spectral sparsification of graphs as a preprocessing step for digital quantum algorithms, in particular, for Hamiltonian simulation. Our results indicate that spectral sparsification of a graph with $n$ nodes through a sampling method, e.g.\ as in \citeSpielman2011resistances using effective resistances, gives, with high probability, a locally computable matrix $\tilde H$ with row sparsity at most $\mathcal{O}(\text{poly}\log n)$. For a symmetric matrix $H$ of size $n$ with $m$ non-zero entries, a one-time classical runtime overhead of $\mathcal{O}(m||H||t\log n/\epsilon)$ expended in spectral sparsification is then found to be useful as a way to obtain a sparse matrix $\tilde H$ that can be used to approximate time evolution $e^{itH}$ under the Hamiltonian $H$ to precision $\epsilon$. Once such a sparsifier is obtained, it could be used with a variety of quantum algorithms in the query model that make crucial use of row sparsity. We focus on the case of efficient quantum algorithms for sparse Hamiltonian simulation, since Hamiltonian simulation underlies, as a key subroutine, several quantum algorithms, including quantum phase estimation and recent ones for linear algebra. Finally, we also give two simple quantum algorithms to estimate the row sparsity of an input matrix, which achieve a query complexity of $\mathcal{O}(n^{3/2})$ as opposed to $\mathcal{O}(n^2)$ that would be required by any classical algorithm for the task.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>No-Signaling Proofs with $O(\sqrt{\log n})$ Provers are in PSPACE</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02590</link>
    <author>Dhiraj Holden, Yael Kalai</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 08 2019</pubDate>
    <description>No-signaling proofs, motivated by quantum computation, have found applications in cryptography and hardness of approximation. An important open problem is characterizing the power of no-signaling proofs. It is known that 2-prover no-signaling proofs are characterized by PSPACE, and that no-signaling proofs with $poly(n)$-provers are characterized by EXP. However, the power of $k$-prover no-signaling proofs, for $2<k<poly(n)$ remained an open problem. We show that $k$-prover no-signaling proofs (with negligible soundness) for $k=O(\sqrt{\log n})$ are contained in PSPACE. We prove this via two different routes that are of independent interest. In both routes we consider a relaxation of no-signaling called sub-no-signaling. Our main technical contribution (which is used in both our proofs) is a reduction showing how to convert any sub-no-signaling strategy with value at least $1-2^{-\Omega(k^2)}$ into a no-signaling one with value at least $2^{-O(k^2)}$. In the first route, we show that the classical prover reduction method for converting $k$-prover games into $2$-prover games carries over to the no-signaling setting with the following loss in soundness: if a $k$-player game has value less than $2^{-ck^2}$ (for some constant~$c>0$), then the corresponding 2-prover game has value at most $1 - 2^{dk^2}$ (for some constant~$d>0$). In the second route we show that the value of a sub-no-signaling game can be approximated in space that is polynomial in the communication complexity and exponential in the number of provers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Application of a resource theory of channels to communication scenarios</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01125</link>
    <author>Ryuji Takagi, Kun Wang, Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 04 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a resource theory of channels relevant to communication via quantum channels, in which the set of constant channels, useless channels for communication tasks, are considered as free resources. We find that our theory with such a simple structure is useful to address important problems in quantum Shannon theory --- in particular, we provide a converse bound for the one-shot non-signalling assisted classical capacity that leads to the first direct proof of the strong converse property for non-signalling assisted communication, as well as obtain the one-shot channel simulation cost with non-signalling assistance. Our results not only provide new perspectives to those problems, but also admit concise proofs of them, connecting the recently developed fields of resource theories to `classic' problems in quantum information theory and shedding light on the validity of resource theories of channels as effective tools to attack practical problems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>
