<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13228</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas Breuckmann, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of non-trivial complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). We prove this conjecture by showing that the recently discovered families of constant-rate and linear-distance QLDPC codes correspond to NLTS local Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Computational advantage of quantum random sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04079</link>
    <author>Dominik Hangleiter, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum random sampling is the leading proposal for demonstrating a computational advantage of quantum computers over classical computers. Recently, first large-scale implementations of quantum random sampling have arguably surpassed the boundary of what can be simulated on existing classical hardware. In this article, we comprehensively review the theoretical underpinning of quantum random sampling in terms of computational complexity and verifiability, as well as the practical aspects of its experimental implementation using superconducting and photonic devices and its classical simulation. We discuss in detail open questions in the field and provide perspectives for the road ahead, including potential applications of quantum random sampling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Towards near-term quantum simulation of materials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15256</link>
    <author>Laura Clinton, Toby Cubitt, Brian Flynn, Filippo Maria Gambetta, Joel Klassen, Ashley Montanaro, Stephen Piddock, Raul A. Santos, Evan Sheridan</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulation of materials is one of the most promising applications of quantum computers. On near-term hardware the crucial constraint on these simulations is circuit depth. Many quantum simulation algorithms rely on a layer of unitary evolutions generated by each term in a Hamiltonian. This appears in time-dynamics as a single Trotter step, and in variational quantum eigensolvers under the Hamiltonian variational ansatz as a single ansatz layer. We present a new quantum algorithm design for materials modelling where the depth of a layer is independent of the system size. This design takes advantage of the locality of materials in the Wannier basis and employs a tailored fermionic encoding that preserves locality. We analyse the circuit costs of this approach and present a compiler that transforms density functional theory data into quantum circuit instructions -- connecting the physics of the material to the simulation circuit. The compiler automatically optimises circuits at multiple levels, from the base gate level to optimisations derived from the physics of the specific target material. We present numerical results for materials spanning a wide structural and technological range. Our results demonstrate a reduction of many orders of magnitude in circuit depth over standard prior methods that do not consider the structure of the Hamiltonian. For example our results improve resource requirements for Strontium Vanadate (SrVO$_3$) from 864 to 180 qubits for a $3\times3\times3$ lattice, and the circuit depth of a single Trotter or variational layer from $7.5\times 10^8$ to depth $730$. Although this is still beyond current hardware, our results show that materials simulation may be feasible on quantum computers without necessarily requiring scalable, fault-tolerant quantum computers, provided quantum algorithm design incorporates understanding of the materials and applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A construction of Combinatorial NLTS</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02741</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of high complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). Here, we prove a weaker version called the combinatorial NLTS, where a quantum circuit lower bound is shown against states that violate a (small) constant fraction of local terms. This generalizes the prior NLETS results (Eldar and Harrow [2017]; Nirkhe, Vazirani and Yuen [2018]). Our construction is obtained by combining tensor networks with expander codes (Sipser and Spielman [1996]). The Hamiltonian is the parent Hamiltonian of a perturbed tensor network, inspired by the `uncle Hamiltonian' of Fernandez-Gonzalez et. al. [2015]. Thus, we deviate from the quantum CSS code Hamiltonians considered in most prior works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Sample Complexity Lower Bound for Quantum State Tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11185</link>
    <author>Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that $\Omega(rd/\epsilon)$ copies of an unknown rank-$r$, dimension-$d$ quantum mixed state are necessary in order to learn a classical description with $1 - \epsilon$ fidelity. This improves upon the tomography lower bounds obtained by Haah, et al. and Wright.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The learnability of Pauli noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06362</link>
    <author>Senrui Chen, Yunchao Liu, Matthew Otten, Alireza Seif, Bill Fefferman, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, several noise benchmarking algorithms have been developed to characterize noisy quantum gates on today's quantum devices. A well-known issue in benchmarking is that not everything about quantum noise is learnable due to the existence of gauge freedom, leaving open the question of what information about noise is learnable and what is not, which has been unclear even for a single CNOT gate. Here we give a precise characterization of the learnability of Pauli noise channels attached to Clifford gates, showing that learnable information corresponds to the cycle space of the pattern transfer graph of the gate set, while unlearnable information corresponds to the cut space. This implies the optimality of cycle benchmarking, in the sense that it can learn all learnable information about Pauli noise. We experimentally demonstrate noise characterization of IBM's CNOT gate up to 2 unlearnable degrees of freedom, for which we obtain bounds using physical constraints. In addition, we give an attempt to characterize the unlearnable information by assuming perfect initial state preparation. However, based on the experimental data, we conclude that this assumption is inaccurate as it yields unphysical estimates, and we obtain a lower bound on state preparation noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An efficient decoder for a linear distance quantum LDPC code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06557</link>
    <author>Shouzhen Gu, Christopher A. Pattison, Eugene Tang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent developments have shown the existence of quantum low-density parity check (qLDPC) codes with constant rate and linear distance. A natural question concerns the efficient decodability of these codes. In this paper, we present a linear time decoder for the recent quantum Tanner codes construction of asymptotically good qLDPC codes, which can correct all errors of weight up to a constant fraction of the blocklength. Our decoder is an iterative algorithm which searches for corrections within constant-sized regions. At each step, the corrections are found by reducing a locally defined and efficiently computable cost function which serves as a proxy for the weight of the remaining error.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Good Quantum LDPC Codes with Linear Time Decoders</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07750</link>
    <author>Irit Dinur, Min-Hsiu Hsieh, Ting-Chun Lin, Thomas Vidick</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We construct a new explicit family of good quantum low-density parity-check codes which additionally have linear time decoders. Our codes are based on a three-term chain $(\mathbb{F}_2^{m\times m})^V \quad \xrightarrow{\delta^0}\quad (\mathbb{F}_2^{m})^{E} \quad\xrightarrow{\delta^1} \quad \mathbb{F}_2^F$ where $V$ ($X$-checks) are the vertices, $E$ (qubits) are the edges, and $F$ ($Z$-checks) are the squares of a left-right Cayley complex, and where the maps are defined based on a pair of constant-size random codes $C_A,C_B:\mathbb{F}_2^m\to\mathbb{F}_2^\Delta$ where $\Delta$ is the regularity of the underlying Cayley graphs. One of the main ingredients in the analysis is a proof of an essentially-optimal robustness property for the tensor product of two random codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Estimating Quantum Hamiltonians via Joint Measurements of Noisy Non-Commuting Observables</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.08912</link>
    <author>Daniel McNulty, Filip B. Maciejewski, Michał Oszmaniec</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Estimation of expectation values of incompatible observables is an essential practical task in quantum computing, especially for approximating energies of chemical and other many-body quantum systems. In this work we introduce a method for this purpose based on performing a single joint measurement that can be implemented locally and whose marginals yield noisy (unsharp) versions of the target set of non-commuting Pauli observables. We derive bounds on the number of experimental repetitions required to estimate energies up to a certain precision. We compare this strategy to the classical shadow formalism and show that our method yields the same performance as the locally biased classical shadow protocol. We also highlight some general connections between the two approaches by showing that classical shadows can be used to construct joint measurements and vice versa. Finally, we adapt the joint measurement strategy to minimise the sample complexity when the implementation of measurements is assumed noisy. This can provide significant efficiency improvements compared to known generalisations of classical shadows to noisy scenarios.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient decoding up to a constant fraction of the code length for asymptotically good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07571</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce and analyse an efficient decoder for the quantum Tanner codes of that can correct adversarial errors of linear weight. Previous decoders for quantum low-density parity-check codes could only handle adversarial errors of weight $O(\sqrt{n \log n})$. We also work on the link between quantum Tanner codes and the Lifted Product codes of Panteleev and Kalachev, and show that our decoder can be adapted to the latter. The decoding algorithm alternates between sequential and parallel procedures and converges in linear time.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tight Bounds for State Tomography with Incoherent Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05265</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Brice Huang, Jerry Li, Allen Liu, Mark Sellke</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the classic question of state tomography: given copies of an unknown quantum state $\rho\in\mathbb{C}^{d\times d}$, output $\widehat{\rho}$ for which $\|\rho - \widehat{\rho}\|_{\mathsf{tr}} \le \varepsilon$. When one is allowed to make coherent measurements entangled across all copies, $\Theta(d^2/\varepsilon^2)$ copies are necessary and sufficient [Haah et al. '17, O'Donnell-Wright '16]. Unfortunately, the protocols achieving this rate incur large quantum memory overheads that preclude implementation on current or near-term devices. On the other hand, the best known protocol using incoherent (single-copy) measurements uses $O(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17], and multiple papers have posed it as an open question to understand whether or not this rate is tight. In this work, we fully resolve this question, by showing that any protocol using incoherent measurements, even if they are chosen adaptively, requires $\Omega(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies, matching the upper bound of [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17]. We do so by a new proof technique which directly bounds the "tilt" of the posterior distribution after measurements, which yields a surprisingly short proof of our lower bound, and which we believe may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive Online Learning of Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00220</link>
    <author>Xinyi Chen, Elad Hazan, Tongyang Li, Zhou Lu, Xinzhao Wang, Rui Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the fundamental problem of shadow tomography, the goal is to efficiently learn an unknown $d$-dimensional quantum state using projective measurements. However, it is rarely the case that the underlying state remains stationary: changes may occur due to measurements, environmental noise, or an underlying Hamiltonian state evolution. In this paper we adopt tools from adaptive online learning to learn a changing state, giving adaptive and dynamic regret bounds for online shadow tomography that are polynomial in the number of qubits and sublinear in the number of measurements. Our analysis utilizes tools from complex matrix analysis to cope with complex numbers, which may be of independent interest in online learning. In addition, we provide numerical experiments that corroborate our theoretical results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum mean states are nicer than you think: fast algorithms to compute states maximizing average fidelity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.08183</link>
    <author>A. Afham, Richard Kueng, Chris Ferrie</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fidelity is arguably the most popular figure of merit in quantum sciences. However, many of its properties are still unknown. In this work, we resolve the open problem of maximizing average fidelity over arbitrary finite ensembles of quantum states and derive new upper bounds. We first construct a semidefinite program whose optimal value is the maximum average fidelity and then derive fixed-point algorithms that converge to the optimal state. The fixed-point algorithms outperform the semidefinite program in terms of numerical runtime. We also derive expressions for near-optimal states that are easier to compute and upper and lower bounds for maximum average fidelity that are exact when all the states in the ensemble commute. Finally, we discuss how our results solve some open problems in Bayesian quantum tomography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Advantage in Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04078</link>
    <author>Renato Renner, Ramona Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Ever since its inception, cryptography has been caught in a vicious circle: Cryptographers keep inventing methods to hide information, and cryptanalysts break them, prompting cryptographers to invent even more sophisticated encryption schemes, and so on. But could it be that quantum information technology breaks this circle? At first sight, it looks as if it just lifts the competition between cryptographers and cryptanalysts to the next level. Indeed, quantum computers will render most of today's public key cryptosystems insecure. Nonetheless, there are good reasons to believe that cryptographers will ultimately prevail over cryptanalysts. Quantum cryptography allows us to build communication schemes whose secrecy relies only on the laws of physics as well as some minimum assumptions about the cryptographic hardware - leaving basically no room for an attack. While we are not yet there, this article provides an overview of the principles and state of the art of quantum cryptography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Resources Required to Block-Encode a Matrix of Classical Data</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.03505</link>
    <author>B. David Clader, Alexander M. Dalzell, Nikitas Stamatopoulos, Grant Salton, Mario Berta, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide modular circuit-level implementations and resource estimates for several methods of block-encoding a dense $N\times N$ matrix of classical data to precision $\epsilon$; the minimal-depth method achieves a $T$-depth of $\mathcal{O}{(\log (N/\epsilon))},$ while the minimal-count method achieves a $T$-count of $\mathcal{O}{(N\log(1/\epsilon))}$. We examine resource tradeoffs between the different approaches, and we explore implementations of two separate models of quantum random access memory (QRAM). As part of this analysis, we provide a novel state preparation routine with $T$-depth $\mathcal{O}{(\log (N/\epsilon))}$, improving on previous constructions with scaling $\mathcal{O}{(\log^2 (N/\epsilon))}$. Our results go beyond simple query complexity and provide a clear picture into the resource costs when large amounts of classical data are assumed to be accessible to quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved single-shot decoding of higher dimensional hypergraph product codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.03122</link>
    <author>Oscar Higgott, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work we study the single-shot performance of higher dimensional hypergraph product codes decoded using belief-propagation and ordered-statistics decoding [Panteleev and Kalachev, 2019]. We find that decoding data qubit and syndrome measurement errors together in a single stage leads to single-shot thresholds that greatly exceed all previously observed single-shot thresholds for these codes. For the 3D toric code and a phenomenological noise model, our results are consistent with a sustainable threshold of 7.1% for $Z$ errors, compared to the threshold of 2.90% previously found using a two-stage decoder [Quintavalle et al., 2021]. For the 4D toric code, for which both $X$ and $Z$ error correction is single-shot, our results are consistent with a sustainable single-shot threshold of 4.3% which is even higher than the threshold of 2.93% for the 2D toric code for the same noise model but using $L$ rounds of stabiliser measurement. We also explore the performance of balanced product and 4D hypergraph product codes which we show lead to a reduction in qubit overhead compared the surface code for phenomenological error rates as high as 1%.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Composite Quantum Simulations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06409</link>
    <author>Matthew Hagan, Nathan Wiebe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper we provide a framework for combining multiple quantum simulation methods, such as Trotter-Suzuki formulas and QDrift into a single composite channel that builds upon older coalescing ideas for reducing gate counts. The central idea behind our approach is to use a partitioning scheme that allocates a Hamiltonian term to the Trotter or QDrift part of a channel within the simulation. This allows us to simulate small but numerous terms using QDrift while simulating the larger terms using a high-order Trotter-Suzuki formula. We prove rigorous bounds on the diamond distance between the composite channel and the ideal simulation channel and show under what conditions the cost of implementing the composite channel is asymptotically upper bounded by the methods that comprise it for both probabilistic partitioning of terms and deterministic partitioning. Finally, we discuss strategies for determining partitioning schemes as well as methods for incorporating different simulation methods within the same framework.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Laziness, Barren Plateau, and Noise in Machine Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.09313</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Zexi Lin, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We define \emphlaziness to describe a large suppression of variational parameter updates for neural networks, classical or quantum. In the quantum case, the suppression is exponential in the number of qubits for randomized variational quantum circuits. We discuss the difference between laziness and \emphbarren plateau in quantum machine learning created by quantum physicists in \citemcclean2018barren for the flatness of the loss function landscape during gradient descent. We address a novel theoretical understanding of those two phenomena in light of the theory of neural tangent kernels. For noiseless quantum circuits, without the measurement noise, the loss function landscape is complicated in the overparametrized regime with a large number of trainable variational angles. Instead, around a random starting point in optimization, there are large numbers of local minima that are good enough and could minimize the mean square loss function, where we still have quantum laziness, but we do not have barren plateaus. However, the complicated landscape is not visible within a limited number of iterations, and low precision in quantum control and quantum sensing. Moreover, we look at the effect of noises during optimization by assuming intuitive noise models, and show that variational quantum algorithms are noise-resilient in the overparametrization regime. Our work precisely reformulates the quantum barren plateau statement towards a precision statement and justifies the statement in certain noise models, injects new hope toward near-term variational quantum algorithms, and provides theoretical connections toward classical machine learning. Our paper provides conceptual perspectives about quantum barren plateaus, together with discussions about the gradient descent dynamics in \citetogether.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical surrogates for quantum learning models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11740</link>
    <author>Franz J. Schreiber, Jens Eisert, Johannes Jakob Meyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The advent of noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers has put the search for possible applications to the forefront of quantum information science. One area where hopes for an advantage through near-term quantum computers are high is quantum machine learning, where variational quantum learning models based on parametrized quantum circuits are discussed. In this work, we introduce the concept of a classical surrogate, a classical model which can be efficiently obtained from a trained quantum learning model and reproduces its input-output relations. As inference can be performed classically, the existence of a classical surrogate greatly enhances the applicability of a quantum learning strategy. However, the classical surrogate also challenges possible advantages of quantum schemes. As it is possible to directly optimize the ansatz of the classical surrogate, they create a natural benchmark the quantum model has to outperform. We show that large classes of well-analyzed re-uploading models have a classical surrogate. We conducted numerical experiments and found that these quantum models show no advantage in performance or trainability in the problems we analyze. This leaves only generalization capability as possible point of quantum advantage and emphasizes the dire need for a better understanding of inductive biases of quantum learning models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A note on the inner products of pure states and their antidistinguishability</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.08313</link>
    <author>Vincent Russo, Jamie Sikora</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A set of d quantum states is said to be antidistinguishable if there exists a d-outcome POVM that can perfectly identify which state was not measured. A conjecture by Havlíček and Barrett states that if a set of d pure states has small pair-wise inner products, then the set must be antidistinguishable. In this note we provide a certificate of antidistinguishability via semidefinite programming duality and use it to provide a counterexample to this conjecture when d = 4.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11246</link>
    <author>Cica Gustiani, Richard Meister, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods offer a highly promising route to exploiting quantum computers for chemistry tasks. Here we employ methods described in a sister paper to the present report, entitled ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits, in order to solve problems using adaptively evolving quantum circuits. Consistent with prior authors we find that this approach can outperform human-designed circuits such as the coupled-cluster or hardware-efficient ansätze, and we make comparisons for larger instances up to 14 qubits. Moreover we introduce a novel approach to constraining the circuit evolution in the physically relevant subspace, finding that this greatly improves performance and compactness of the circuits. We consider both static and dynamics properties of molecular systems. The emulation environments used is QuESTlink; all resources are open source and linked from this paper.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Provably efficient variational generative modeling of quantum many-body systems via quantum-probabilistic information geometry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04663</link>
    <author>Faris M. Sbahi, Antonio J. Martinez, Sahil Patel, Dmitri Saberi, Jae Hyeon Yoo, Geoffrey Roeder, Guillaume Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The dual tasks of quantum Hamiltonian learning and quantum Gibbs sampling are relevant to many important problems in physics and chemistry. In the low temperature regime, algorithms for these tasks often suffer from intractabilities, for example from poor sample- or time-complexity. With the aim of addressing such intractabilities, we introduce a generalization of quantum natural gradient descent to parameterized mixed states, as well as provide a robust first-order approximating algorithm, Quantum-Probabilistic Mirror Descent. We prove data sample efficiency for the dual tasks using tools from information geometry and quantum metrology, thus generalizing the seminal result of classical Fisher efficiency to a variational quantum algorithm for the first time. Our approaches extend previously sample-efficient techniques to allow for flexibility in model choice, including to spectrally-decomposed models like Quantum Hamiltonian-Based Models, which may circumvent intractable time complexities. Our first-order algorithm is derived using a novel quantum generalization of the classical mirror descent duality. Both results require a special choice of metric, namely, the Bogoliubov-Kubo-Mori metric. To test our proposed algorithms numerically, we compare their performance to existing baselines on the task of quantum Gibbs sampling for the transverse field Ising model. Finally, we propose an initialization strategy leveraging geometric locality for the modelling of sequences of states such as those arising from quantum-stochastic processes. We demonstrate its effectiveness empirically for both real and imaginary time evolution while defining a broader class of potential applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Avoiding barren plateaus via transferability of smooth solutions in Hamiltonian Variational Ansatz</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01982</link>
    <author>Antonio Anna Mele, Glen Bigan Mbeng, Giuseppe Ernesto Santoro, Mario Collura, Pietro Torta</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A large ongoing research effort focuses on Variational Quantum Algorithms (VQAs), representing leading candidates to achieve computational speed-ups on current quantum devices. The scalability of VQAs to a large number of qubits, beyond the simulation capabilities of classical computers, is still debated. Two major hurdles are the proliferation of low-quality variational local minima, and the exponential vanishing of gradients in the cost function landscape, a phenomenon referred to as barren plateaus. Here we show that by employing iterative search schemes one can effectively prepare the ground state of paradigmatic quantum many-body models, circumventing also the barren plateau phenomenon. This is accomplished by leveraging the transferability to larger system sizes of iterative solutions, displaying an intrinsic smoothness of the variational parameters, a result that does not extend to other solutions found via random-start local optimization. Our scheme could be directly tested on near-term quantum devices, running a refinement optimization in a favorable local landscape with non-vanishing gradients.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Pair Measurement Surface Code on Pentagons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12780</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, I present a way to compile the surface code into two-body parity measurements ("pair measurements"), where the pair measurements run along the edges of a Cairo pentagonal tiling. The resulting circuit improves on prior work by Chao et al. by using fewer pair measurements per four-body stabilizer measurement (5 instead of 6) and fewer time steps per round of stabilizer measurement (6 instead of 10). Using Monte Carlo sampling, I show that these improvements increase the threshold of the surface code when compiling into pair measurements from $\approx 0.2\%$ to $\approx 0.4\%$, and also that they improve the teraquop footprint at a $0.1\%$ physical gate error rate from $\approx6000$ qubits to $\approx3000$ qubits. However, I also show that Chao et al's construction will have a smaller teraquop footprint for physical gate error rates below $\approx 0.03\%$ (due to bidirectional hook errors in my construction). I also compare to the planar honeycomb code, showing that although this work does noticeably reduce the gap between the surface code and the honeycomb code (when compiling into pair measurements), the honeycomb code is still more efficient (threshold $\approx 0.8\%$, teraquop footprint at $0.1\%$ of $\approx 1000$).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Average-case hardness of estimating probabilities of random quantum circuits with a linear scaling in the error exponent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05642</link>
    <author>Hari Krovi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the hardness of computing additive approximations to output probabilities of random quantum circuits. We consider three random circuit families, namely, Haar random, $p=1$ QAOA, and random IQP circuits. Our results are as follows. For Haar random circuits with $m$ gates, we improve on prior results by showing $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hardness of average-case additive approximations to an imprecision of $2^{-O(m)}$. Efficient classical simulation of such problems would imply the collapse of the polynomial hierarchy. For constant depth circuits i.e., when $m=O(n)$, this linear scaling in the exponent is within a constant of the scaling required to show hardness of sampling. Prior to our work, such a result was shown only for Boson Sampling in Bouland et al (2021). We also use recent results in polynomial interpolation to show $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hardness under $\mathsf{BPP}$ reductions rather than $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{NP}}$ reductions. This improves the results of prior work for Haar random circuits both in terms of the error scaling and the power of reductions. Next, we consider random $p=1$ QAOA and IQP circuits and show that in the average-case, it is $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hard to approximate the output probability to within an additive error of $2^{-O(n)}$. For $p=1$ QAOA circuits, this work constitutes the first average-case hardness result for the problem of approximating output probabilities for random QAOA circuits, which include Sherrington-Kirkpatrick and Erdös-Renyi graphs. For IQP circuits, a consequence of our results is that approximating the Ising partition function with imaginary couplings to an additive error of $2^{-O(n)}$ is hard even in the average-case, which extends prior work on worst-case hardness of multiplicative approximation to Ising partition functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Computing Quantum Monte Carlo</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.10431</link>
    <author>Yukun Zhang, Yifei Huang, Jinzhao Sun, Dingshun Lv, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing and quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) are respectively the most powerful quantum and classical computing methods for understanding many-body quantum systems. Here, we propose a hybrid quantum-classical algorithm that integrates these two methods, inheriting their distinct features in efficient representation and manipulation of quantum states and overcoming their limitations. We introduce upper bounds to non-stoquaticity indicators (NSI), which measure the sign problem, the most notable limitation of QMC. We show that our algorithm could greatly mitigate the sign problem, which decreases NSIs with the assist of quantum computing. Meanwhile, the use of quantum Monte Carlo also increases the power of noisy quantum circuits, allowing accurate computation with much shallower circuits. We numerically test and verify the method for the N2 molecule (12 qubits) and the Hubbard model (16 qubits). Our work paves the way to solving practical problems with intermediate-scale and early-fault tolerant quantum computers, with potential applications in chemistry, condensed matter physics, materials, high energy physics, etc.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement as a shortcut to long-range entangled quantum matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13527</link>
    <author>Tsung-Cheng Lu, Leonardo A. Lessa, Isaac H. Kim, Timothy H. Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The preparation of long-range entangled states using unitary circuits is limited by Lieb-Robinson bounds, but circuits with projective measurements and feedback (``adaptive circuits'') can evade such restrictions. We introduce four classes of local adaptive circuits that enable low-depth preparation of long-range entangled quantum matter characterized by gapped topological orders and conformal field theories (CFTs). The four classes are inspired by distinct physical insights, including tensor-network constructions, short-range entangled states with non-trivial braiding structures, multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (MERA), and parton constructions. A large class of topological orders, including chiral and symmetry-enriched topological orders, can be prepared in constant depth or time, and one-dimensional CFT states and non-abelian topological orders with both solvable and non-solvable groups can be prepared in depth scaling logarithmically with system size. Our work illustrates the practical and conceptual versatility of measurement for state preparation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploring ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11245</link>
    <author>Richard Meister, Cica Gustiani, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gate-level quantum circuits are often derived manually from higher level algorithms. While this suffices for small implementations and demonstrations, ultimately automatic circuit design will be required to realise complex algorithms using hardware-specific operations and connectivity. Here we explore methods for the ab initio creation of circuits within a machine, either a classical computer or a hybrid quantum-classical device. We consider a range of techniques including: methods for introducing new gate structures, optimisation of parameterised circuits and choices of cost functions, and efficient removal of low-value gates exploiting the quantum geometric tensor and other heuristics. Using these principles we tackle the tasks of automatic encoding of unitary processes and translation (recompilation) of a circuit from one form to another. Using emulated quantum computers with various noise-free gate sets we provide simple examples involving up to 10 qubits, corresponding to 20 qubits in the augmented space we use. Further applications of specific relevance to chemistry modelling are considered in a sister paper, 'Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry'.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Modular Commutators in Conformal Field Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00027</link>
    <author>Yijian Zou, Bowen Shi, Jonathan Sorce, Ian T. Lim, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The modular commutator is a recently discovered multipartite entanglement measure that quantifies the chirality of the underlying many-body quantum state. In this Letter, we derive a universal expression for the modular commutator in conformal field theories in $1+1$ dimensions and discuss its salient features. We show that the modular commutator depends only on the chiral central charge and the conformal cross ratio. We test this formula for a gapped $(2+1)$-dimensional system with a chiral edge, i.e., the quantum Hall state, and observe excellent agreement with numerical simulations. Furthermore, we propose a geometric dual for the modular commutator in certain preferred states of the AdS/CFT correspondence. For these states, we argue that the modular commutator can be obtained from a set of crossing angles between intersecting Ryu-Takayanagi surfaces.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random tensor networks with nontrivial links</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.10482</link>
    <author>Newton Cheng, Cécilia Lancien, Geoff Penington, Michael Walter, Freek Witteveen</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Random tensor networks are a powerful toy model for understanding the entanglement structure of holographic quantum gravity. However, unlike holographic quantum gravity, their entanglement spectra are flat. It has therefore been argued that a better model consists of random tensor networks with link states that are not maximally entangled, i.e., have nontrivial spectra. In this work, we initiate a systematic study of the entanglement properties of these networks. We employ tools from free probability, random matrix theory, and one-shot quantum information theory to study random tensor networks with bounded and unbounded variation in link spectra, and in cases where a subsystem has one or multiple minimal cuts. If the link states have bounded spectral variation, the limiting entanglement spectrum of a subsystem with two minimal cuts can be expressed as a free product of the entanglement spectra of each cut, along with a Marchenko-Pastur distribution. For a class of states with unbounded spectral variation, analogous to semiclassical states in quantum gravity, we relate the limiting entanglement spectrum of a subsystem with two minimal cuts to the distribution of the minimal entanglement across the two cuts. In doing so, we draw connections to previous work on split transfer protocols, entanglement negativity in random tensor networks, and Euclidean path integrals in quantum gravity.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>