
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>How to simulate quantum measurement without computing marginals</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.08499</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, David Gosset, Yinchen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 17 2021</pubDate>
    <description>We describe and analyze algorithms for classically simulating measurement of an $n$-qubit quantum state $\psi$ in the standard basis, that is, sampling a bit string $x$ from the probability distribution $|\langle x|\psi\rangle|^2$. Our algorithms reduce the sampling task to computing poly$(n)$ amplitudes of $n$-qubit states; unlike previously known techniques they do not require computation of marginal probabilities. First we consider the case where $|\psi\rangle=U|0^n\rangle$ is the output state of an $m$-gate quantum circuit $U$. We propose an exact sampling algorithm which involves computing $O(m)$ amplitudes of $n$-qubit states generated by subcircuits of $U$ spanned by the first $t=1,2,\ldots,m$ gates. We show that our algorithm can significantly accelerate quantum circuit simulations based on tensor network contraction methods or low-rank stabilizer decompositions. As another striking consequence we obtain an efficient classical simulation algorithm for measurement-based quantum computation with the surface code resource state on any planar graph, generalizing a previous algorithm which was known to be efficient only under restrictive topological constraints on the ordering of single-qubit measurements. Second, we consider the case in which $\psi$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian with a spectral gap that is lower bounded by an inverse polynomial function of $n$. We prove that a simple Metropolis-Hastings Markov Chain mixes rapidly to the desired probability distribution provided that $\psi$ obeys a certain technical condition, which we show is satisfied for all sign-problem free Hamiltonians. This gives a sampling algorithm which involves computing $\mathrm{poly}(n)$ amplitudes of $\psi$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Five Starter Pieces: Quantum Information Science via Semi-definite Programs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.08276</link>
    <author>Vikesh Siddhu, Sridhar Tayur</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 16 2021</pubDate>
    <description>As the title indicates, this manuscript presents a brief, self-contained introduction to five fundamental problems in Quantum Information Science (QIS) that are especially well-suited to be formulated as Semi-definite Programs (SDP). We have in mind two audiences. The primary audience comprises of Operations Research (and Computer Science) graduate students who have familiarity with SDPs, but have found it daunting to become even minimally conversant with pre-requisites of QIS. The second audience consists of Physicists (and Electrical Engineers) already knowledgeable with modeling of QIS via SDP but interested in computational tools that are applicable more generally. For both audiences, we strive for rapid access to the unfamiliar material. For the first, we provide just enough required background material (from Quantum Mechanics, treated via matrices, and mapping them in Dirac notation) and simultaneously for the second audience we recreate, computationally in Jupyter notebooks, known closed-form solutions. We hope you will enjoy this little manuscript and gain understanding of the marvelous connection between SDP and QIS by self-study, or as a short seminar course. Ultimately, we hope this disciplinary outreach will fuel advances in QIS through their fruitful study via SDPs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast Thermalization from the Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.07646</link>
    <author>Chi-Fang Chen, Fernando G.S.L. Brandão</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 15 2021</pubDate>
    <description>The Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis (ETH) has played a major role in explaining thermodynamic phenomena in quantum systems. However, so far, no connection has been known between ETH and the timescale of thermalization. In this paper, we rigorously show that ETH indeed implies fast thermalization to the global Gibbs state. We show fast convergence for two models of thermalization. In the first, the system is weakly coupled to a bath of (quasi)-free Fermions that we control. We derive a finitely-resolved version of Davies' generator, with explicit error bounds and resource estimates, that describes the joint evolution at finite times. The second is Quantum Metropolis Sampling, a quantum algorithm for preparing Gibbs states on a quantum computer. In both cases, no guarantee for fast convergence was previously known for non-commuting Hamiltonians, partly due to technical issues with a finite energy resolution. The critical feature of ETH we exploit is that the Hamiltonian can be modeled by random matrix theory below a sufficiently small energy scale. We show this gives quantum expander at nearby eigenstates of the Hamiltonian. This then implies fast convergence to the global Gibbs state by mapping the problem to a one-dimensional classical random walk on the spectrum of the Hamiltonian. Our results explain finite-time thermalization in chaotic open quantum systems and suggest an alternative formulation of ETH in terms of quantum expanders, which we confirm numerically for small systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Logical blocks for fault-tolerant topological quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.12160</link>
    <author>Hector Bombin, Chris Dawson, Ryan V. Mishmash, Naomi Nickerson, Fernando Pastawski, Sam Roberts</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 24 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Logical gates are the building blocks of fault-tolerant quantum computation. While quantum error-corrected memories have been extensively studied in the literature, detailed analyses of thresholds and resource overheads of universal logical gate sets have so far been limited. In this paper, we present a comprehensive framework for universal fault-tolerant logic motivated by the combined need for (i) platform-independent logical gate definitions, (ii) flexible and scalable tools for numerical analysis, and (iii) exploration of novel schemes for universal logic that improve resource overheads. We first introduce the theory of fault-tolerant channels for describing logical gates holistically in space-time. Focusing on channels based on surface codes, we introduce explicit, platform-independent representations of topological logic gates -- called logical blocks -- and generate new, overhead-efficient methods for universal quantum computation. As a specific example, we propose fault-tolerant schemes based on surface codes concatenated with more general low-density parity check (LDPC) codes. The logical blocks framework enables a convenient mapping from an abstract description of the logical gate to a precise set of physical instructions for both circuit-based and fusion-based quantum computation (FBQC). Using this, we numerically simulate a surface-code-based universal gate set implemented with FBQC, and verify that the threshold for fault-tolerant gates is consistent with the bulk memory threshold. We find that boundaries, defects, and twists, can significantly impact the logical error rate scaling, with periodic boundary conditions potentially halving the memory resource requirements. Motivated by the favorable logical error rate suppression for boundaryless computation, we introduce a novel computational scheme based on the teleportation of twists that may offer further resource reductions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Compressive gate set tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.05176</link>
    <author>Raphael Brieger, Ingo Roth, Martin Kliesch</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 13 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Flexible characterization techniques that identify and quantify experimental imperfections under realistic assumptions are crucial for the development of quantum computers. Gate set tomography is a characterization approach that simultaneously and self-consistently extracts a tomographic description of the implementation of an entire set of quantum gates, as well as the initial state and measurement, from experimental data. Obtaining such a detailed picture of the experimental implementation is associated with high requirements on the number of sequences and their design, making gate set tomography a challenging task even for only two qubits. In this work, we show that low-rank approximations of gate sets can be obtained from significantly fewer gate sequences and that it is sufficient to draw them randomly. Such tomographic information is needed for the crucial task of dealing with coherent noise. To this end, we formulate the data processing problem of gate set tomography as a rank-constrained tensor completion problem. We provide an algorithm to solve this problem while respecting the usual positivity and normalization constraints of quantum mechanics by using second-order geometrical optimization methods on the complex Stiefel manifold. Besides the reduction in sequences, we demonstrate numerically that the algorithm does not rely on structured gate sets or an elaborate circuit design to robustly perform gate set tomography and is therefore more broadly applicable than traditional approaches.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Interactive Protocols for Classically-Verifiable Quantum Advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.05156</link>
    <author>Daiwei Zhu, Gregory D. Kahanamoku-Meyer, Laura Lewis, Crystal Noel, Or Katz, Bahaa Harraz, Qingfeng Wang, Andrew Risinger, Lei Feng, Debopriyo Biswas, Laird Egan, Alexandru Gheorghiu, Yunseong Nam, Thomas Vidick, Umesh Vazirani, Norman Y. Yao, Marko Cetina, Christopher Monroe</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 13 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Achieving quantum computational advantage requires solving a classically intractable problem on a quantum device. Natural proposals rely upon the intrinsic hardness of classically simulating quantum mechanics; however, verifying the output is itself classically intractable. On the other hand, certain quantum algorithms (e.g. prime factorization via Shor's algorithm) are efficiently verifiable, but require more resources than what is available on near-term devices. One way to bridge the gap between verifiability and implementation is to use "interactions" between a prover and a verifier. By leveraging cryptographic functions, such protocols enable the classical verifier to enforce consistency in a quantum prover's responses across multiple rounds of interaction. In this work, we demonstrate the first implementation of an interactive quantum advantage protocol, using an ion trap quantum computer. We execute two complementary protocols -- one based upon the learning with errors problem and another where the cryptographic construction implements a computational Bell test. To perform multiple rounds of interaction, we implement mid-circuit measurements on a subset of trapped ion qubits, with subsequent coherent evolution. For both protocols, the performance exceeds the asymptotic bound for classical behavior; maintaining this fidelity at scale would conclusively demonstrate verifiable quantum advantage.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A smallest computable entanglement monotone</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00835</link>
    <author>J. Eisert, M. M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Rains relative entropy of a bipartite quantum state is the tightest known upper bound on its distillable entanglement - which has a crisp physical interpretation of entanglement as a resource - and it is efficiently computable by convex programming. It has not been known to be a selective entanglement monotone in its own right. In this work, we strengthen the interpretation of the Rains relative entropy by showing that it is monotone under the action of selective operations that completely preserve the positivity of the partial transpose, reasonably quantifying entanglement. That is, we prove that Rains relative entropy of an ensemble generated by such an operation does not exceed the Rains relative entropy of the initial state in expectation, giving rise to the smallest, most conservative known computable selective entanglement monotone. Additionally, we show that this is true not only for the original Rains relative entropy, but also for Rains relative entropies derived from various Renyi relative entropies. As an application of these findings, we prove, in both the non-asymptotic and asymptotic settings, that the probabilistic approximate distillable entanglement of a state is bounded from above by various Rains relative entropies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement between superconducting qubits and a tardigrade</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.07978</link>
    <author>K. S. Lee, Y. P. Tan, L. H. Nguyen, R. P. Budoyo, K. H. Park, C. Hufnagel, Y. S. Yap, N. Møbjerg, V. Vedral, T. Paterek, R. Dumke</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 16 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum and biological systems are seldom discussed together as they seemingly demand opposing conditions. Life is complex, "hot and wet" whereas quantum objects are small, cold and well controlled. Here, we overcome this barrier with a tardigrade -- a microscopic multicellular organism known to tolerate extreme physiochemical conditions via a latent state of life known as cryptobiosis. We observe coupling between the animal in cryptobiosis and a superconducting quantum bit and prepare a highly entangled state between this combined system and another qubit. The tardigrade itself is shown to be entangled with the remaining subsystems. The animal is then observed to return to its active form after 420 hours at sub 10 mK temperatures and pressure of $6\times 10^{-6}$ mbar, setting a new record for the conditions that a complex form of life can survive.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational Quantum Algorithms for Semidefinite Programming</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.08859</link>
    <author>Dhrumil Patel, Patrick J. Coles, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 17 2021</pubDate>
    <description>A semidefinite program (SDP) is a particular kind of convex optimization problem with applications in operations research, combinatorial optimization, quantum information science, and beyond. In this work, we propose variational quantum algorithms for approximately solving SDPs. For one class of SDPs, we provide a rigorous analysis of their convergence to approximate locally optimal solutions, under the assumption that they are weakly constrained (i.e., $N\gg M$, where $N$ is the dimension of the input matrices and $M$ is the number of constraints). We also provide algorithms for a more general class of SDPs that requires fewer assumptions. Finally, we numerically simulate our quantum algorithms for applications such as MaxCut, and the results of these simulations provide evidence that convergence still occurs in noisy settings.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Algorithms for Gibbs state preparation on noiseless and noisy random quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14688</link>
    <author>Oles Shtanko, Ramis Movassagh</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 30 2021</pubDate>
    <description>The most promising and practical candidate to demonstrate a drastic advantage of quantum computers over classical ones is the simulation of quantum matter. Despite the advances in simulation of the time evolution, preparing thermal states of quantum many-body systems remains notoriously a difficult yet important task. The existing algorithms either require quantum phase estimation rendering them impractical for current noisy hardware, or are variational which face obstacles such as initialization, barren plateaus, and a general lack of provable convergence. We propose two quantum algorithms with provable guarantees to prepare thermal states on current noisy quantum hardware. The first algorithm requires postselection on intermediate measurements and runs on a quantum circuit with $poly(n)$ depth, where $n$ is the number of qubits. This algorithm requires a significantly smaller number of gates than previous such algorithms. The second algorithm is tailored to ergodic interacting systems which are a vast subset of physical Hamiltonians. This algorithm can potentially sample thermal distributions in polynomial time. In addition, both of our algorithms have free parameters that can be optimized or trained to mitigate noise and computational errors. We illustrate our algorithms by running them on the latest IBM quantum hardware and in particular simulate them for the Fermi-Hubbard model.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>
