<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Is quantum advantage the right goal for quantum machine learning?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01340</link>
    <author>Maria Schuld, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Machine learning is frequently listed among the most promising applications for quantum computing. This is in fact a curious choice: Today's machine learning algorithms are notoriously powerful in practice, but remain theoretically difficult to study. Quantum computing, in contrast, does not offer practical benchmarks on realistic scales, and theory is the main tool we have to judge whether it could become relevant for a problem. In this perspective we explain why it is so difficult to say something about the practical power of quantum computers for machine learning with the tools we are currently using. We argue that these challenges call for a critical debate on whether quantum advantage and the narrative of "beating" classical machine learning should continue to dominate the literature the way it does, and provide a few examples for alternative research questions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The XP Stabiliser Formalism: a Generalisation of the Pauli Stabiliser Formalism with Arbitrary Phases</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00103</link>
    <author>Mark A. Webster, Benjamin J. Brown, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose an extension to the Pauli stabiliser formalism that includes fractional $2\pi/N$ rotations around the $Z$ axis for some integer $N$. The resulting generalised stabiliser formalism - denoted the XP stabiliser formalism - allows for a wider range of states and codespaces to be represented. We describe the states which arise in the formalism, and demonstrate an equivalence between XP stabiliser states and 'weighted hypergraph states' - a generalisation of both hypergraph and weighted graph states. Given an arbitrary set of XP operators, we present algorithms for determining the codespace and logical operators for an XP code. Finally, we consider whether measurements of XP operators on XP codes can be classically simulated.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Tanner codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.13641</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tanner codes are long error correcting codes obtained from short codes and a graph, with bits on the edges and parity-check constraints from the short codes enforced at the vertices of the graph. Combining good short codes together with a spectral expander graph yields the celebrated expander codes of Sipser and Spielman, which are asymptotically good classical LDPC codes. In this work we apply this prescription to the left-right Cayley complex that lies at the heart of the recent construction of a $c^3$ locally testable code by Dinur et al. Specifically, we view this complex as two graphs that share the same set of edges. By defining a Tanner code on each of those graphs we obtain two classical codes that together define a quantum code. This construction can be seen as a simplified variant of the Panteleev and Kalachev asymptotically good quantum LDPC code, with improved estimates for its minimum distance. This quantum code is closely related to the Dinur et al. code in more than one sense: indeed, we prove a theorem that simultaneously gives a linearly growing minimum distance for the quantum code and recovers the local testability of the Dinur et al. code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Logical shadow tomography: Efficient estimation of error-mitigated observables</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.07263</link>
    <author>Hong-Ye Hu, Ryan LaRose, Yi-Zhuang You, Eleanor Rieffel, Zhihui Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a technique to estimate error-mitigated expectation values on noisy quantum computers. Our technique performs shadow tomography on a logical state to produce a memory-efficient classical reconstruction of the noisy density matrix. Using efficient classical post-processing, one can mitigate errors by projecting a general nonlinear function of the noisy density matrix into the codespace. The subspace expansion and virtual distillation can be viewed as special cases of the new framekwork. We show our method is favorable in the quantum and classical resources overhead. Relative to subspace expansion which requires $O\left(2^{N} \right)$ samples to estimate a logical Pauli observable with $[[N, k]]$ error correction code, our technique requires only $O\left(4^{k} \right)$ samples. Relative to virtual distillation, our technique can compute powers of the density matrix without additional copies of quantum states or quantum memory. We present numerical evidence using logical states encoded with up to sixty physical qubits and show fast convergence to error-free expectation values with only $10^5$ samples under 1% depolarizing noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking the Planar Honeycomb Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11845</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney, Michael Newman</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We improve the planar honeycomb code by describing boundaries that need no additional physical connectivity, and by optimizing the shape of the qubit patch. We then benchmark the code using Monte Carlo sampling to estimate logical error rates and derive metrics including thresholds, lambdas, and teraquop qubit counts. We determine that the planar honeycomb code can create a logical qubit with one-in-a-trillion logical error rates using 7000 physical qubits at a 0.1% gate-level error rate (or 900 physical qubits given native two-qubit parity measurements). Our results cement the honeycomb code as a promising candidate for two-dimensional qubit architectures with sparse connectivity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical Verification of Quantum Computations in Linear Time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.13997</link>
    <author>Jiayu Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the quantum computation verification problem, a quantum server wants to convince a client that the output of evaluating a quantum circuit $C$ is some result that it claims. This problem is considered very important both theoretically and practically in quantum computation [arXiv:1709.06984], [arXiv:1704.04487], [arXiv:1209.0449]. The client is considered to be limited in computational power, and one desirable property is that the client can be completely classical, which leads to the classical verification of quantum computation (CVQC) problem. In terms of total time complexity of both the client and the server, the fastest single-server CVQC protocol so far has complexity $O(poly(\kappa)|C|^3)$ where $|C|$ is the size of the circuit to be verified, given by Mahadev [arXiv:1804.01082]. In this work, by developing new techniques, we give a new CVQC protocol with complexity $O(poly(\kappa)|C|)$, which is significantly faster than existing protocols. Our protocol is secure in the quantum random oracle model [arXiv:1008.0931] assuming the existence of noisy trapdoor claw-free functions [arXiv:1804.00640], which are both extensively used assumptions in quantum cryptography. Along the way, we also give a new classical channel remote state preparation protocol for states in $\{|+_\theta\rangle=\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}(|0\rangle+e^{i\theta\pi/4}|1\rangle):\theta\in \{0,1\cdots 7\}\}$, another basic primitive in quantum cryptography. Our protocol allows for parallel verifiable preparation of $L$ independently random states in this form (up to a constant overall error and a possibly unbounded server-side isometry), and runs in only $O(poly(\kappa)L)$ time and constant rounds; for comparison, existing works (even for possibly simpler state families) all require very large or unestimated time and round complexities [arXiv:1904.06320][arXiv:1904.06303][arXiv:2201.13445][arXiv:2201.13430].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>All quantum measurements are asymptotically equivalent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.02593</link>
    <author>Noah Linden, Paul Skrzypczyk</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of reproducing one quantum measurement given the ability to perform another. In particular, given the availability of a -- possibly imperfect -- quantum measurement which can be performed multiple times, we study to what extent it can reproduce the measurement statistics and post-measurement state of a second target measurement, in the most general setting where both the available and target measurements are arbitrary generalised quantum measurements. We show that this general problem in fact reduces to the ability to reproduce the statistics of von Neumann measurements, and that in the asymptotic limit of infinitely many uses of the available measurement, a simple protocol based upon `classical cloning' is able to perfectly achieve this task. This shows that asymptotically all (non-trivial) quantum measurements are equivalent. We also study optimal protocols for a fixed number of uses of the available measurement, and show that better protocols than classical cloning can be found in general. Our protocols show that the average error in reproducing a target measurement drops off exponentially fast, and that one can, for example, rapidly improve imperfect measurements by performing them a small number of times. This includes, but is not limited to, improving both noisy and lossy quantum measurements. Finally, we show that in a setting where we perform multiple measurements in parallel, we can moreover achieve finite-rate measurement reproduction, by using block-coding techniques from classical information theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Shadow Distillation: Quantum Error Mitigation with Classical Shadows for Near-Term Quantum Processors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.07309</link>
    <author>Alireza Seif, Ze-Pei Cian, Sisi Zhou, Senrui Chen, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Mitigating errors in quantum information processing devices is especially important in the absence of fault tolerance. An effective method in suppressing state-preparation errors is using multiple copies to distill the ideal component from a noisy quantum state. Here, we use classical shadows and randomized measurements to circumvent the need for coherent access to multiple copies at an exponential cost. We study the scaling of resources using numerical simulations and find that the overhead is still favorable compared to full state tomography. We optimize measurement resources under realistic experimental constraints and apply our method to an experiment preparing Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) state with trapped ions. In addition to improving stabilizer measurements, the analysis of the improved results reveals the nature of errors affecting the experiment. Hence, our results provide a directly applicable method for mitigating errors in near-term quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fragile boundaries of tailored surface codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04948</link>
    <author>Oscar Higgott, Thomas C. Bohdanowicz, Aleksander Kubica, Steven T. Flammia, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Biased noise is common in physical qubits, and tailoring a quantum code to the bias by locally modifying stabilizers or changing boundary conditions has been shown to greatly increase error correction thresholds. In this work, we explore the challenges of using a specific tailored code, the XY surface code, for fault-tolerant quantum computation. We introduce an efficient and fault-tolerant decoder, belief-matching, which we show has good performance for biased circuit-level noise. Using this decoder, we find that for moderately biased noise, the XY surface code has a higher threshold and lower overhead than the square CSS surface code, however it performs worse when below threshold than the rectangular CSS surface code. We identify a contributor to the reduced performance that we call fragile boundary errors. These are string-like errors that can occur along spatial or temporal boundaries in planar architectures or during logical state preparation and measurement. While we make partial progress towards mitigating these errors by deforming the boundaries of the XY surface code, our work suggests that fragility could remain a significant obstacle, even for other tailored codes. We expect belief-matching will have other uses, and find that it increases the threshold of the surface code to 0.940(3)% in the presence of circuit-level depolarising noise, compared to 0.817(5)% for a minimum-weight perfect matching decoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Differential Privacy: An Information Theory Perspective</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10717</link>
    <author>Christoph Hirche, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Differential privacy has been an exceptionally successful concept when it comes to providing provable security guarantees for classical computations. More recently, the concept was generalized to quantum computations. While classical computations are essentially noiseless and differential privacy is often achieved by artificially adding noise, near-term quantum computers are inherently noisy and it was observed that this leads to natural differential privacy as a feature. In this work we discuss quantum differential privacy in an information theoretic framework by casting it as a quantum divergence. A main advantage of this approach is that differential privacy becomes a property solely based on the output states of the computation, without the need to check it for every measurement. This leads to simpler proofs and generalized statements of its properties as well as several new bounds for both, general and specific, noise models. In particular, these include common representations of quantum circuits and quantum machine learning concepts. Here, we focus on the difference in the amount of noise required to achieve certain levels of differential privacy versus the amount that would make any computation useless. Finally, we also generalize the classical concepts of local differential privacy, Rényi differential privacy and the hypothesis testing interpretation to the quantum setting, providing several new properties and insights.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Circuit Extraction for ZX-diagrams can be #P-hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09194</link>
    <author>Niel de Beaudrap, Aleks Kissinger, John van de Wetering</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ZX-calculus is a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computation using ZX-diagrams, a certain flexible generalisation of quantum circuits that can be used to represent linear maps from $m$ to $n$ qubits for any $m,n \geq 0$. Some applications for the ZX-calculus, such as quantum circuit optimisation and synthesis, rely on being able to efficiently translate a ZX-diagram back into a quantum circuit of comparable size. While several sufficient conditions are known for describing families of ZX-diagrams that can be efficiently transformed back into circuits, it has previously been conjectured that the general problem of circuit extraction is hard. That is, that it should not be possible to efficiently convert an arbitrary ZX-diagram describing a unitary linear map into an equivalent quantum circuit. In this paper we prove this conjecture by showing that the circuit extraction problem is #P-hard, and so is itself at least as hard as strong simulation of quantum circuits. In addition to our main hardness result, which relies specifically on the circuit representation, we give a representation-agnostic hardness result. Namely, we show that any oracle that takes as input a ZX-diagram description of a unitary and produces samples of the output of the associated quantum computation enables efficient probabilistic solutions to NP-complete problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Parameterized Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08002</link>
    <author>Michael J. Bremner, Zhengfeng Ji, Ryan L. Mann, Luke Mathieson, Mauro E.S. Morales, Alexis T.E. Shaw</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Parameterized complexity theory was developed in the 1990s to enrich the complexity-theoretic analysis of problems that depend on a range of parameters. In this paper we establish a quantum equivalent of classical parameterized complexity theory, motivated by the need for new tools for the classifications of the complexity of real-world problems. We introduce the quantum analogues of a range of parameterized complexity classes and examine the relationship between these classes, their classical counterparts, and well-studied problems. This framework exposes a rich classification of the complexity of parameterized versions of QMA-hard problems, demonstrating, for example, a clear separation between the Quantum Circuit Satisfiability problem and the Local Hamiltonian problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Influence in Completely Bounded Block-multilinear Forms and Classical Simulation of Quantum Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00212</link>
    <author>Nikhil Bansal, Makrand Sinha, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Aaronson-Ambainis conjecture (Theory of Computing '14) says that every low-degree bounded polynomial on the Boolean hypercube has an influential variable. This conjecture, if true, would imply that the acceptance probability of every $d$-query quantum algorithm can be well-approximated almost everywhere (i.e., on almost all inputs) by a $\mathrm{poly}(d)$-query classical algorithm. We prove a special case of the conjecture: in every completely bounded degree-$d$ block-multilinear form with constant variance, there always exists a variable with influence at least $1/\mathrm{poly}(d)$. In a certain sense, such polynomials characterize the acceptance probability of quantum query algorithms, as shown by Arunachalam, Briët and Palazuelos (SICOMP '19). As a corollary we obtain efficient classical almost-everywhere simulation for a particular class of quantum algorithms that includes for instance $k$-fold Forrelation. Our main technical result relies on connections to free probability theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Quantum Polynomial-Time Solution to The Dihedral Hidden Subgroup Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09697</link>
    <author>Matthew Moore, Grace Young</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a polynomial-time quantum algorithm for the Hidden Subgroup Problem over $\mathbb{D}_{2^n}$. The usual approach to the Hidden Subgroup Problem relies on harmonic analysis in the domain of the problem, and the best known algorithm using this approach has time complexity in $2^{\mathcal{O}(\sqrt{n})}$. By focusing on structure encoded in the codomain of the problem, we develop a polynomial-time algorithm which uses this structure to direct a "walk" down the subgroup lattice of $\mathbb{D}_{2^n}$ terminating at the hidden subgroup.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hierarchies of resources for measurement-based quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.09965</link>
    <author>Markus Frembs, Sam Roberts, Earl T. Campbell, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For certain restricted computational tasks, quantum mechanics provides a provable advantage over any possible classical implementation. Several of these results have been proven using the framework of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), where non-locality and more generally contextuality have been identified as necessary resources for certain quantum computations. Here, we consider the computational power of MBQC in more detail by refining its resource requirements, both on the allowed operations and the number of accessible qubits. More precisely, we identify which Boolean functions can be computed in non-adaptive MBQC, with local operations contained within a finite level in the Clifford hierarchy. Moreover, for non-adaptive MBQC restricted to certain subtheories such as stabiliser MBQC, we compute the minimal number of qubits required to compute a given Boolean function. Our results point towards hierarchies of resources that more sharply characterise the power of MBQC beyond the binary of contextuality vs non-contextuality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Performance of planar Floquet codes with Majorana-based qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11829</link>
    <author>Adam Paetznick, Christina Knapp, Nicolas Delfosse, Bela Bauer, Jeongwan Haah, Matthew B. Hastings, Marcus P. da Silva</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction is crucial for any quantum computing platform to achieve truly scalable quantum computation. The surface code and its variants have been considered the most promising quantum error correction scheme due to their high threshold, low overhead, and relatively simple structure that can naturally be implemented in many existing qubit architectures, such as superconducting qubits. The recent development of Floquet codes offers another promising approach. By going beyond the usual paradigm of stabilizer codes, Floquet codes achieve similar performance while being constructed entirely from two-qubit measurements. This makes them particularly suitable for platforms where two-qubit measurements can be implemented directly, such as measurement-only topological qubits based on Majorana zero modes (MZMs). Here, we explain how two variants of Floquet codes can be implemented on MZM-based architectures without any auxiliary qubits for syndrome measurement and with shallow syndrome extraction sequences. We then numerically demonstrate their favorable performance. In particular, we show that they improve the threshold for scalable quantum computation in MZM-based systems by an order of magnitude, and significantly reduce space and time overheads below threshold.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Good quantum LDPC codes with linear time decoder from lossless expanders</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.03581</link>
    <author>Ting-Chun Lin, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum low-density parity-check (qLDPC) codes are quantum stabilizer codes where each stabilizer acts on a constant number of qubits and each qubit is acted on by a constant number of stabilizers. We study qLDPC codes constructed from balanced products and lossless expanders. We found that assuming the existence of 2-sided lossless expander graphs with free group action, the resulting qLDPC codes have constant rate, linear distance, and linear time decoders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of nearest-neighbour quantum networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10886</link>
    <author>Frederik Hahn, Axel Dahlberg, Jens Eisert, Anna Pappa</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum communication research has in recent years shifted to include multi-partite networks for which questions of quantum network routing naturally emerge. To understand the potential for multi-partite routing, we focus on the most promising architectures for future quantum networks - those connecting nodes close to each other. Nearest-neighbour networks such as rings, lines, and grids, have been studied under different communication scenarios to facilitate the sharing of quantum resources, especially in the presence of bottlenecks. We here analyze the potential of nearest-neighbour quantum networks and identify some serious limitations, by demonstrating that rings and lines cannot overcome common bottleneck communication problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The quantum low-rank approximation problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00811</link>
    <author>Nic Ezzell, Zoë Holmes, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a quantum version of the famous low-rank approximation problem. Specifically, we consider the distance $D(\rho,\sigma)$ between two normalized quantum states, $\rho$ and $\sigma$, where the rank of $\sigma$ is constrained to be at most $R$. For both the trace distance and Hilbert-Schmidt distance, we analytically solve for the optimal state $\sigma$ that minimizes this distance. For the Hilbert-Schmidt distance, the unique optimal state is $\sigma = \tau_R +N_R$, where $\tau_R = \Pi_R \rho \Pi_R$ is given by projecting $\rho$ onto its $R$ principal components with projector $\Pi_R$, and $N_R$ is a normalization factor given by $N_R = \frac{1- \text{Tr}(\tau_R)}{R}\Pi_R$. For the trace distance, this state is also optimal but not uniquely optimal, and we provide the full set of states that are optimal. We briefly discuss how our results have application for performing principal component analysis (PCA) via variational optimization on quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Optimization of Maximum Independent Set using Rydberg Atom Arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09372</link>
    <author>Sepehr Ebadi, Alexander Keesling, Madelyn Cain, Tout T. Wang, Harry Levine, Dolev Bluvstein, Giulia Semeghini, Ahmed Omran, Jinguo Liu, Rhine Samajdar, Xiu-Zhe Luo, Beatrice Nash, Xun Gao, Boaz Barak, Edward Farhi, Subir Sachdev, Nathan Gemelke, Leo Zhou, Soonwon Choi, Hannes Pichler, et al (4)</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Realizing quantum speedup for practically relevant, computationally hard problems is a central challenge in quantum information science. Using Rydberg atom arrays with up to 289 qubits in two spatial dimensions, we experimentally investigate quantum algorithms for solving the Maximum Independent Set problem. We use a hardware-efficient encoding associated with Rydberg blockade, realize closed-loop optimization to test several variational algorithms, and subsequently apply them to systematically explore a class of graphs with programmable connectivity. We find the problem hardness is controlled by the solution degeneracy and number of local minima, and experimentally benchmark the quantum algorithm's performance against classical simulated annealing. On the hardest graphs, we observe a superlinear quantum speedup in finding exact solutions in the deep circuit regime and analyze its origins.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matching and maximum likelihood decoding of a multi-round subsystem quantum error correction experiment</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.07205</link>
    <author>Neereja Sundaresan, Theodore J. Yoder, Youngseok Kim, Muyuan Li, Edward H. Chen, Grace Harper, Ted Thorbeck, Andrew W. Cross, Antonio D. Córcoles, Maika Takita</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction offers a promising path for performing quantum computations with low errors. Although a fully fault-tolerant execution of a quantum algorithm remains unrealized, recent experimental developments, along with improvements in control electronics, are enabling increasingly advanced demonstrations of the necessary operations for applying quantum error correction. Here, we perform quantum error correction on superconducting qubits connected in a heavy-hexagon lattice. The full processor can encode a logical qubit with distance three and perform several rounds of fault-tolerant syndrome measurements that allow the correction of any single fault in the circuitry. Furthermore, by using dynamic circuits and classical computation as part of our syndrome extraction protocols, we can exploit real-time feedback to reduce the impact of energy relaxation error in the syndrome and flag qubits. We show that the logical error varies depending on the use of a perfect matching decoder compared to a maximum likelihood decoder. We observe a logical error per syndrome measurement round as low as $\sim0.04$ for the matching decoder and as low as $\sim0.03$ for the maximum likelihood decoder. Our results suggest that more significant improvements to decoders are likely on the horizon as quantum hardware has reached a new stage of development towards fully fault-tolerant operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying the barren plateau phenomenon for a model of unstructured variational ansätze</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.06174</link>
    <author>John Napp</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantifying the flatness of the objective-function landscape associated with unstructured parameterized quantum circuits is important for understanding the performance of variational algorithms utilizing a "hardware-efficient ansatz", particularly for ensuring that a prohibitively flat landscape -- a so-called "barren plateau" -- is avoided. For a model of such ansätze, we relate the typical landscape flatness to a certain family of random walks, enabling us to derive a Monte Carlo algorithm for efficiently, classically estimating the landscape flatness for any architecture. The statistical picture additionally allows us to prove new analytic bounds on the barren plateau phenomenon, and more generally provides novel insights into the phenomenon's dependence on the ansatz depth, architecture, qudit dimension, and Hamiltonian combinatorial and spatial locality. Our analysis utilizes techniques originally developed by Dalzell et al. to study anti-concentration in random circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Limitations in Broadband Sensing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.05520</link>
    <author>Anthony M. Polloreno, Jacob L. Beckey, Joshua Levin, Ariel Shlosberg, James K. Thompson, Michael Foss-Feig, David Hayes, Graeme Smith</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider estimating the magnitude of a monochromatic AC signal that couples to a two-level sensor. For any detection protocol, the precision achieved depends on the signal's frequency and can be quantified by the quantum Fisher information. To study limitations in broadband sensing, we introduce the integrated quantum Fisher information and derive inequality bounds that embody fundamental tradeoffs in any sensing protocol. These inequalities show that sensitivity in one frequency range must come at a cost of reduced sensitivity elsewhere. For many protocols, including those with small phase accumulation and those consisting of $\pi$-pulses, we find the integrated Fisher information scales linearly with $T$. We also find protocols with substantial phase accumulation can have integrated QFI that grows quadratically with $T$, which is optimal. These protocols may allow the very rapid detection of a signal with unknown frequency over a very wide bandwidth.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Algorithms for Testing Hamiltonian Symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.10017</link>
    <author>Margarite L. LaBorde, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Symmetries in a Hamiltonian play an important role in quantum physics because they correspond directly with conserved quantities of the related system. In this paper, we propose quantum algorithms capable of testing whether a Hamiltonian exhibits symmetry with respect to a group. We demonstrate that familiar expressions of Hamiltonian symmetry in quantum mechanics correspond directly with the acceptance probabilities of our algorithms. We execute one of our symmetry-testing algorithms on existing quantum computers for simple examples of both symmetric and asymmetric cases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying Grover speed-ups beyond asymptotic analysis</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.04975</link>
    <author>Chris Cade, Marten Folkertsma, Ido Niesen, Jordi Weggemans</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The usual method for studying run-times of quantum algorithms is via an asymptotic, worst-case analysis. Whilst useful, such a comparison can often fall short: it is not uncommon for algorithms with a large worst-case run-time to end up performing well on instances of practical interest. To remedy this it is necessary to resort to run-time analyses of a more empirical nature, which for sufficiently small input sizes can be performed on a quantum device or a simulation thereof. For larger input sizes, alternative approaches are required. In this paper we consider an approach that combines classical emulation with rigorous complexity bounds: simulating quantum algorithms by running classical versions of the sub-routines, whilst simultaneously collecting information about what the run-time of the quantum routine would have been if it were run instead. To do this accurately and efficiently for very large input sizes, we describe an estimation procedure that provides provable guarantees on the estimates that it obtains. A nice feature of this approach is that it allows one to compare the performance of quantum and classical algorithms on particular inputs of interest, rather than only on those that allow for an easier mathematical analysis. We apply our method to some simple quantum speedups of classical heuristic algorithms for solving the well-studied MAX-k-SAT optimization problem. To do this we first obtain some rigorous bounds (including all constants) on the expected- and worst-case complexities of two important quantum sub-routines, which improve upon existing results and might be of broader interest: Grover search with an unknown number of marked items, and quantum maximum-finding. Our results suggest that such an approach can provide insightful and meaningful information, in particular when the speedup is of a small polynomial nature.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical simulation of quantum circuits with partial and graphical stabiliser decompositions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09202</link>
    <author>Aleks Kissinger, John van de Wetering, Renaud Vilmart</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent developments in classical simulation of quantum circuits make use of clever decompositions of chunks of magic states into sums of efficiently simulable stabiliser states. We show here how, by considering certain non-stabiliser entangled states which have more favourable decompositions, we can speed up these simulations. This is made possible by using the ZX-calculus, which allows us to easily find instances of these entangled states in the simplified diagram representing the quantum circuit to be simulated. We additionally find a new technique of partial stabiliser decompositions that allow us to trade magic states for stabiliser terms. With this technique we require only $2^{\alpha t}$ stabiliser terms, where $\alpha\approx 0.396$, to simulate a circuit with T-count $t$. This matches the $\alpha$ found by Qassim et al., but whereas they only get this scaling in the asymptotic limit, ours applies for a circuit of any size. Our method builds upon a recently proposed scheme for simulation combining stabiliser decompositions and optimisation strategies implemented in the software QuiZX. With our techniques we manage to reliably simulate 50-qubit 1400 T-count hidden shift circuits in a couple of minutes on a consumer laptop.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum circuit compilation and hybrid computation using Pauli-based computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01789</link>
    <author>F.C.R. Peres, Ernesto F. Galvão</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Pauli-based computation (PBC) is driven by a sequence of adaptively chosen, non-destructive measurements of Pauli observables. Any quantum circuit written in terms of the Clifford+$T$ gate set and having $t$ $T$ gates can be compiled into a PBC on $t$ qubits. Here we propose practical ways of implementing PBC as adaptive quantum circuits, and provide code to do the required classical side-processing. Our first scheme reduces the number of quantum gates to $O(t^2)$ (from a previous $O(t^3 / \log t)$ scaling) at the cost of one extra auxiliary qubit, with a possible reduction of the depth to $O(t \log t$), at the cost of $t$ additional auxiliary qubits (second scheme). We compile examples of random and hidden-shift quantum circuits into adaptive PBC circuits. We also simulate hybrid quantum computation, where a classical computer effectively extends the working memory of a small quantum computer by $k$ virtual qubits, at a cost exponential in $k$. Our results demonstrate the practical advantage of PBC techniques for circuit compilation and hybrid computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms for estimating quantum entropies</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.02386</link>
    <author>Youle Wang, Benchi Zhao, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The von Neumann and quantum Rényi entropies characterize fundamental properties of quantum systems and lead to theoretical and practical applications in many fields. Quantum algorithms for estimating quantum entropies, using a quantum query model that prepares the purification of the input state, have been established in the literature. However, constructing such a model is almost as hard as state tomography. In this paper, we propose quantum algorithms to estimate the von Neumann and quantum $\alpha$-Rényi entropies of an $n$-qubit quantum state $\rho$ using independent copies of the input state. We also show how to efficiently construct the quantum circuits for quantum entropy estimation using primitive single/two-qubit gates. We prove that the number of required copies scales polynomially in $1/\epsilon$ and $1/\Lambda$, where $\epsilon$ denotes the additive precision and $\Lambda$ denotes the lower bound on all non-zero eigenvalues. Notably, our method outperforms previous methods in the aspect of practicality since it does not require any quantum query oracles, which are usually necessary for previous methods. Furthermore, we conduct experiments to show the efficacy of our algorithms to single-qubit states and study the noise robustness. We also discuss the applications to some quantum states of practical interest as well as some meaningful tasks such as quantum Gibbs state preparation and entanglement estimation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms from fluctuation theorems: Thermal-state preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08882</link>
    <author>Zoe Holmes, Gopikrishnan Muraleedharan, Rolando D. Somma, Yigit Subasi, Burak Şahinoğlu</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fluctuation theorems provide a correspondence between properties of quantum systems in thermal equilibrium and a work distribution arising in a non-equilibrium process that connects two quantum systems with Hamiltonians $H_0$ and $H_1=H_0+V$. Building upon these theorems, we present a quantum algorithm to prepare a purification of the thermal state of $H_1$ at inverse temperature $\beta \ge 0$ starting from a purification of the thermal state of $H_0$. The complexity of the quantum algorithm, given by the number of uses of certain unitaries, is $\tilde {\cal O}(e^{\beta (\Delta \! A- w_l)/2})$, where $\Delta \! A$ is the free-energy difference between $H_1$ and $H_0,$ and $w_l$ is a work cutoff that depends on the properties of the work distribution and the approximation error $\epsilon>0$. If the non-equilibrium process is trivial, this complexity is exponential in $\beta \|V\|$, where $\|V\|$ is the spectral norm of $V$. This represents a significant improvement of prior quantum algorithms that have complexity exponential in $\beta \|H_1\|$ in the regime where $\|V\|\ll \|H_1\|$. The dependence of the complexity in $\epsilon$ varies according to the structure of the quantum systems. It can be exponential in $1/\epsilon$ in general, but we show it to be sublinear in $1/\epsilon$ if $H_0$ and $H_1$ commute, or polynomial in $1/\epsilon$ if $H_0$ and $H_1$ are local spin systems. The possibility of applying a unitary that drives the system out of equilibrium allows one to increase the value of $w_l$ and improve the complexity even further. To this end, we analyze the complexity for preparing the thermal state of the transverse field Ising model using different non-equilibrium unitary processes and see significant complexity improvements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Memory Compression with Quantum Random-Access Gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.05599</link>
    <author>Harry Buhrman, Bruno Loff, Subhasree Patro, Florian Speelman</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the classical RAM, we have the following useful property. If we have an algorithm that uses $M$ memory cells throughout its execution, and in addition is sparse, in the sense that, at any point in time, only $m$ out of $M$ cells will be non-zero, then we may "compress" it into another algorithm which uses only $m \log M$ memory and runs in almost the same time. We may do so by simulating the memory using either a hash table, or a self-balancing tree. We show an analogous result for quantum algorithms equipped with quantum random-access gates. If we have a quantum algorithm that runs in time $T$ and uses $M$ qubits, such that the state of the memory, at any time step, is supported on computational-basis vectors of Hamming weight at most $m$, then it can be simulated by another algorithm which uses only $O(m \log M)$ memory, and runs in time $\tilde O(T)$. We show how this theorem can be used, in a black-box way, to simplify the presentation in several papers. Broadly speaking, when there exists a need for a space-efficient history-independent quantum data-structure, it is often possible to construct a space-inefficient, yet sparse, quantum data structure, and then appeal to our main theorem. This results in simpler and shorter arguments.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>