<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A lower bound on the space overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00119</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Alexander Müller-Hermes, Ala Shayeghi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The threshold theorem is a fundamental result in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation stating that arbitrarily long quantum computations can be performed with a polylogarithmic overhead provided the noise level is below a constant level. A recent work by Fawzi, Grospellier and Leverrier (FOCS 2018) building on a result by Gottesman (QIC 2013) has shown that the space overhead can be asymptotically reduced to a constant independent of the circuit provided we only consider circuits with a length bounded by a polynomial in the width. In this work, using a minimal model for quantum fault tolerance, we establish a general lower bound on the space overhead required to achieve fault tolerance. For any non-unitary qubit channel $\mathcal{N}$ and any quantum fault tolerance schemes against $\mathrm{i.i.d.}$ noise modeled by $\mathcal{N}$, we prove a lower bound of $\max\left\{\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})^{-1}n,\alpha_\mathcal{N} \log T\right\}$ on the number of physical qubits, for circuits of length $T$ and width $n$. Here, $\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})$ denotes the quantum capacity of $\mathcal{N}$ and $\alpha_\mathcal{N}>0$ is a constant only depending on the channel $\mathcal{N}$. In our model, we allow for qubits to be replaced by fresh ones during the execution of the circuit and we allow classical computation to be free and perfect. This improves upon results that assumed classical computations to be also affected by noise, and that sometimes did not allow for fresh qubits to be added. Along the way, we prove an exponential upper bound on the maximal length of fault-tolerant quantum computation with amplitude damping noise resolving a conjecture by Ben-Or, Gottesman, and Hassidim (2013).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bias-tailored quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01702</link>
    <author>Joschka Roffe, Lawrence Z. Cohen, Armanda O. Quintivalle, Daryus Chandra, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bias-tailoring allows quantum error correction codes to exploit qubit noise asymmetry. Recently, it was shown that a modified form of the surface code, the XZZX code, exhibits considerably improved performance under biased noise. In this work, we demonstrate that quantum low density parity check codes can be similarly bias-tailored. We introduce a bias-tailored lifted product code construction that provides the framework to expand bias-tailoring methods beyond the family of 2D topological codes. We present examples of bias-tailored lifted product codes based on classical quasi-cyclic codes and numerically assess their performance using a belief propagation plus ordered statistics decoder. Our Monte Carlo simulations, performed under asymmetric noise, show that bias-tailored codes achieve several orders of magnitude improvement in their error suppression relative to depolarising noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The platypus of the quantum channel zoo</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08380</link>
    <author>Felix Leditzky, Debbie Leung, Vikesh Siddhu, Graeme Smith, John A. Smolin</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding quantum channels and the strange behavior of their capacities is a key objective of quantum information theory. Here we study a remarkably simple, low-dimensional, single-parameter family of quantum channels with exotic quantum information-theoretic features. As the simplest example from this family, we focus on a qutrit-to-qutrit channel that is intuitively obtained by hybridizing together a simple degradable channel and a completely useless qubit channel. Such hybridizing makes this channel's capacities behave in a variety of interesting ways. For instance, the private and classical capacity of this channel coincide and can be explicitly calculated, even though the channel does not belong to any class for which the underlying information quantities are known to be additive. Moreover, the quantum capacity of the channel can be computed explicitly, given a clear and compelling conjecture is true. This "spin alignment conjecture", which may be of independent interest, is proved in certain special cases and additional numerical evidence for its validity is provided. Finally, we generalize the qutrit channel in two ways, and the resulting channels and their capacities display similarly rich behavior. In a companion paper, we further show that the qutrit channel demonstrates superadditivity when transmitting quantum information jointly with a variety of assisting channels, in a manner unknown before.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Parameterized Complexity of Quantum Verification</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08119</link>
    <author>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Sergey Bravyi, Chinmay Nirkhe, Bryan O'Gorman</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We initiate the study of parameterized complexity of $\textsf{QMA}$ problems in terms of the number of non-Clifford gates in the problem description. We show that for the problem of parameterized quantum circuit satisfiability, there exists a classical algorithm solving the problem with a runtime scaling exponentially in the number of non-Clifford gates but only polynomially with the system size. This result follows from our main result, that for any Clifford + $t$ $T$-gate quantum circuit satisfiability problem, the search space of optimal witnesses can be reduced to a stabilizer subspace isomorphic to at most $t$ qubits (independent of the system size). Furthermore, we derive new lower bounds on the $T$-count of circuit satisfiability instances and the $T$-count of the $W$-state assuming the classical exponential time hypothesis ($\textsf{ETH}$). Lastly, we explore the parameterized complexity of the quantum non-identity check problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Practical Guide to the Numerical Implementation of Tensor Networks I: Contractions, Decompositions and Gauge Freedom</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02138</link>
    <author>Glen Evenbly</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an overview of the key ideas and skills necessary to begin implementing tensor network methods numerically, which is intended to facilitate the practical application of tensor network methods for researchers that are already versed with their theoretical foundations. These skills include an introduction to the contraction of tensor networks, to optimal tensor decompositions, and to the manipulation of gauge degrees of freedom in tensor networks. The topics presented are of key importance to many common tensor network algorithms such as DMRG, TEBD, TRG, PEPS and MERA.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mitigating the quantum hype</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01925</link>
    <author>Olivier Ezratty</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We are in the midst of quantum hype with some excessive claims of quantum computing potential, many vendors' and even some research organizations' exaggerations, and a funding frenzy for very low technology readiness level startups. Governments are contributing to this hype with their large quantum initiatives and their technology sovereignty aspirations. Technology hypes are not bad per se since they create emulation, drive innovations and also contribute to attracting new talents. It works as scientists and vendors deliver progress and innovation on a continuous basis after a so-called peak of expectations. It fails with exaggerated overpromises and underdeliveries that last too long. It could cut short research and innovation funding, creating some sort of quantum winter. After looking at the shape and form of technology and science hypes and driving some lessons from past hypes, we investigate the current quantum hype and its specifics. We find that, although there is some significant uncertainty on the potential to create real scalable quantum computers, the scientific and vendor fields are relatively sane and solid compared to other technology hypes. The vendors hype has some profound and disruptive impact on the organization of fundamental research. Also, quantum technologies comprise other fields like quantum telecommunications and quantum sensing with a higher technology readiness level, which are less prone to hype. We then make some proposals to mitigate the potential negative effects of the current quantum hype including recommendations on scientific communication to strengthen the trust in quantum science, vendor behavior improvements, benchmarking methodologies, public education and putting in place a responsible research and innovation approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking the Planar Honeycomb Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11845</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney, Michael Newman</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We improve the planar honeycomb code by describing boundaries that need no additional physical connectivity, and by optimizing the shape of the qubit patch. We then benchmark the code using Monte Carlo sampling to estimate logical error rates and derive metrics including thresholds, lambdas, and teraquop qubit counts. We determine that the planar honeycomb code can create a logical qubit with one-in-a-trillion logical error rates using 7000 physical qubits at a 0.1% gate-level error rate (or 900 physical qubits given native two-qubit parity measurements). Our results cement the honeycomb code as a promising candidate for two-dimensional qubit architectures with sparse connectivity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-Pauli Errors in the Three-Dimensional Surface Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05746</link>
    <author>Thomas R. Scruby, Michael Vasmer, Dan E. Browne</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A powerful feature of stabiliser error correcting codes is the fact that stabiliser measurement projects arbitrary errors to Pauli errors, greatly simplifying the physical error correction process as well as classical simulations of code performance. However, logical non-Clifford operations can map Pauli errors to non-Pauli (Clifford) errors, and while subsequent stabiliser measurements will project the Clifford errors back to Pauli errors the resulting distributions will possess additional correlations that depend on both the nature of the logical operation and the structure of the code. Previous work has studied these effects when applying a transversal $T$ gate to the three-dimensional colour code and shown the existence of a non-local "linking charge" phenomenon between membranes of intersecting errors. In this work we generalise these results to the case of a $CCZ$ gate in the three-dimensional surface code and find that many aspects of the problem are much more easily understood in this setting. In particular, the emergence of linking charge is a local effect rather than a non-local one. We use the relative simplicity of Clifford errors in this setting to simulate their effect on the performance of a single-shot magic state preparation process (the first such simulation to account for the full effect of these errors) and find that while they lead to an increase in the logical error rate their effect on the threshold is minimal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scrambling Dynamics and Out-of-Time Ordered Correlators in Quantum Many-Body Systems: a Tutorial</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.07060</link>
    <author>Shenglong Xu, Brian Swingle</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This tutorial article introduces the physics of quantum information scrambling in quantum many-body systems. The goals are to understand how to quantify the spreading of quantum information precisely and how causality emerges in complex quantum systems. We introduce the general framework to study the dynamics of quantum information, including detection and decoding. We show that the dynamics of quantum information is closely related to operator dynamics in the Heisenberg picture, and, in certain circumstances, can be precisely quantified by the so-called out-the-time ordered correlator (OTOC). The general behavior of OTOC is discussed based on several toy models, including the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model, random circuit models, and Brownian models, in which OTOC is analytically tractable. We introduce numerical methods, both exact diagonalization and tensor network methods, to calculate OTOC for generic quantum many-body systems. We also survey current experiment schemes to measure OTOC in various quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Circuit Extraction for ZX-diagrams can be #P-hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09194</link>
    <author>Niel de Beaudrap, Aleks Kissinger, John van de Wetering</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ZX-calculus is a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computation using ZX-diagrams, a certain flexible generalisation of quantum circuits that can be used to represent linear maps from $m$ to $n$ qubits for any $m,n \geq 0$. Some applications for the ZX-calculus, such as quantum circuit optimisation and synthesis, rely on being able to efficiently translate a ZX-diagram back into a quantum circuit of comparable size. While several sufficient conditions are known for describing families of ZX-diagrams that can be efficiently transformed back into circuits, it has previously been conjectured that the general problem of circuit extraction is hard. That is, that it should not be possible to efficiently convert an arbitrary ZX-diagram describing a unitary linear map into an equivalent quantum circuit. In this paper we prove this conjecture by showing that the circuit extraction problem is #P-hard, and so is itself at least as hard as strong simulation of quantum circuits. In addition to our main hardness result, which relies specifically on the circuit representation, we give a representation-agnostic hardness result. Namely, we show that any oracle that takes as input a ZX-diagram description of a unitary and produces samples of the output of the associated quantum computation enables efficient probabilistic solutions to NP-complete problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Differential Privacy: An Information Theory Perspective</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10717</link>
    <author>Christoph Hirche, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Differential privacy has been an exceptionally successful concept when it comes to providing provable security guarantees for classical computations. More recently, the concept was generalized to quantum computations. While classical computations are essentially noiseless and differential privacy is often achieved by artificially adding noise, near-term quantum computers are inherently noisy and it was observed that this leads to natural differential privacy as a feature. In this work we discuss quantum differential privacy in an information theoretic framework by casting it as a quantum divergence. A main advantage of this approach is that differential privacy becomes a property solely based on the output states of the computation, without the need to check it for every measurement. This leads to simpler proofs and generalized statements of its properties as well as several new bounds for both, general and specific, noise models. In particular, these include common representations of quantum circuits and quantum machine learning concepts. Here, we focus on the difference in the amount of noise required to achieve certain levels of differential privacy versus the amount that would make any computation useless. Finally, we also generalize the classical concepts of local differential privacy, Rényi differential privacy and the hypothesis testing interpretation to the quantum setting, providing several new properties and insights.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Quantum Polynomial-Time Solution to The Dihedral Hidden Subgroup Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09697</link>
    <author>Matthew Moore, Grace Young</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a polynomial-time quantum algorithm for the Hidden Subgroup Problem over $\mathbb{D}_{2^n}$. The usual approach to the Hidden Subgroup Problem relies on harmonic analysis in the domain of the problem, and the best known algorithm using this approach has time complexity in $2^{\mathcal{O}(\sqrt{n})}$. By focusing on structure encoded in the codomain of the problem, we develop a polynomial-time algorithm which uses this structure to direct a "walk" down the subgroup lattice of $\mathbb{D}_{2^n}$ terminating at the hidden subgroup.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generic nonadditivity of quantum capacity in simple channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08377</link>
    <author>Felix Leditzky, Debbie Leung, Vikesh Siddhu, Graeme Smith, John A. Smolin</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Determining capacities of quantum channels is a fundamental question in quantum information theory. Despite having rigorous coding theorems quantifying the flow of information across quantum channels, their capacities are poorly understood due to super-additivity effects. Studying these phenomena is important for deepening our understanding of quantum information, yet simple and clean examples of super-additive channels are scarce. Here we study a simple family of qutrit channels called the platypus channel, and show that it exhibits super-additivity of coherent information when used jointly with a variety of qubit channels. A higher-dimensional variant of the platypus channel displays super-additivity of quantum capacity together with an erasure channel. Subject to the "spin-alignment conjecture" introduced in a companion paper, our results on super-additivity of quantum capacity extend to lower-dimensional channels as well as larger parameter ranges. In particular, super-additivity occurs between two weakly additive channels each with large capacity on their own, in stark contrast to previous results. Remarkably, a single, novel transmission strategy achieves super-additivity in all examples. Our results show that super-additivity is much more prevalent than previously thought. It can occur across a wide variety of channels, even when both participating channels have large quantum capacity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum machine learning with subspace states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00054</link>
    <author>Iordanis Kerenidis, Anupam Prakash</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new approach for quantum linear algebra based on quantum subspace states and present three new quantum machine learning algorithms. The first is a quantum determinant sampling algorithm that samples from the distribution $\Pr[S]= det(X_{S}X_{S}^{T})$ for $|S|=d$ using $O(nd)$ gates and with circuit depth $O(d\log n)$. The state of art classical algorithm for the task requires $O(d^{3})$ operations \citederezinski2019minimax. The second is a quantum singular value estimation algorithm for compound matrices $\mathcal{A}^{k}$, the speedup for this algorithm is potentially exponential. It decomposes a $\binom{n}{k}$ dimensional vector of order-$k$ correlations into a linear combination of subspace states corresponding to $k$-tuples of singular vectors of $A$. The third algorithm reduces exponentially the depth of circuits used in quantum topological data analysis from $O(n)$ to $O(\log n)$. Our basic tool are quantum subspace states, defined as $|Col(X)\rangle = \sum_{S\subset [n], |S|=d} det(X_{S}) |S\rangle$ for matrices $X \in \mathbb{R}^{n \times d}$ such that $X^{T} X = I_{d}$, that encode $d$-dimensional subspaces of $\mathbb{R}^{n}$. We develop two efficient state preparation techniques, the first using Givens circuits uses the representation of a subspace as a sequence of Givens rotations, while the second uses efficient implementations of unitaries $\Gamma(x) = \sum_{i} x_{i} Z^{\otimes (i-1)} \otimes X \otimes I^{n-i}$ with $O(\log n)$ depth circuits that we term Clifford loaders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Finding fault-tolerant Clifford circuits using SMT solvers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12450</link>
    <author>Noah Shutty, Christopher Chamberland</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Universal fault-tolerant quantum computers will require the use of efficient protocols to implement encoded operations necessary in the execution of algorithms. In this work, we show how satisfiability modulo theories (SMT) solvers can be used to automate the construction of Clifford circuits with certain fault-tolerance properties and apply our techniques to a fault-tolerant magic state preparation protocol. Part of the protocol requires converting magic states encoded in the color code to magic states encoded in the surface code. Since the teleportation step involves decoding a color code merged with a surface code, we develop a new decoding algorithm applicable to such codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fold-Transversal Clifford Gates for Quantum Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06647</link>
    <author>Nikolas P. Breuckmann, Simon Burton</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We generalize the concept of folding from surface codes to CSS codes by considering certain dualities within them. In particular, this gives a general method to implement logical operations in suitable LDPC quantum codes using transversal gates and qubit permutations only. To demonstrate our approach, we specifically consider a [[30, 8, 3]] hyperbolic quantum code called Bring's code. Further, we show that by restricting the logical subspace of Bring's code to four qubits, we can obtain the full Clifford group on that subspace.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Correction with Quantum Autoencoders</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00555</link>
    <author>David F. Locher, Lorenzo Cardarelli, Markus Müller</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Active quantum error correction is a central ingredient to achieve robust quantum processors. In this paper we investigate the potential of quantum machine learning for quantum error correction. Specifically, we demonstrate how quantum neural networks, in the form of quantum autoencoders, can be trained to learn optimal strategies for active detection and correction of errors, including spatially correlated computational errors as well as qubit losses. We highlight that the denoising capabilities of quantum autoencoders are not limited to the protection of specific states but extend to the entire logical codespace. We also show that quantum neural networks can be used to discover new logical encodings that are optimally adapted to the underlying noise. Moreover, we find that, even in the presence of moderate noise in the quantum autoencoders themselves, they may still be successfully used to perform beneficial quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of nearest-neighbour quantum networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10886</link>
    <author>Frederik Hahn, Axel Dahlberg, Jens Eisert, Anna Pappa</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum communication research has in recent years shifted to include multi-partite networks for which questions of quantum network routing naturally emerge. To understand the potential for multi-partite routing, we focus on the most promising architectures for future quantum networks - those connecting nodes close to each other. Nearest-neighbour networks such as rings, lines, and grids, have been studied under different communication scenarios to facilitate the sharing of quantum resources, especially in the presence of bottlenecks. We here analyze the potential of nearest-neighbour quantum networks and identify some serious limitations, by demonstrating that rings and lines cannot overcome common bottleneck communication problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Performance of planar Floquet codes with Majorana-based qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11829</link>
    <author>Adam Paetznick, Christina Knapp, Nicolas Delfosse, Bela Bauer, Jeongwan Haah, Matthew B. Hastings, Marcus P. da Silva</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction is crucial for any quantum computing platform to achieve truly scalable quantum computation. The surface code and its variants have been considered the most promising quantum error correction scheme due to their high threshold, low overhead, and relatively simple structure that can naturally be implemented in many existing qubit architectures, such as superconducting qubits. The recent development of Floquet codes offers another promising approach. By going beyond the usual paradigm of stabilizer codes, Floquet codes achieve similar performance while being constructed entirely from two-qubit measurements. This makes them particularly suitable for platforms where two-qubit measurements can be implemented directly, such as measurement-only topological qubits based on Majorana zero modes (MZMs). Here, we explain how two variants of Floquet codes can be implemented on MZM-based architectures without any auxiliary qubits for syndrome measurement and with shallow syndrome extraction sequences. We then numerically demonstrate their favorable performance. In particular, we show that they improve the threshold for scalable quantum computation in MZM-based systems by an order of magnitude, and significantly reduce space and time overheads below threshold.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An exact quantum hidden subgroup algorithm and applications to solvable groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04047</link>
    <author>Muhammad Imran, Gabor Ivanyos</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a polynomial time exact quantum algorithm for the hidden subgroup problem in $Z_{m^k}^n$. The algorithm uses the quantum Fourier transform modulo m and does not require factorization of m. For smooth m, i.e., when the prime factors of m are of size poly(log m), the quantum Fourier transform can be exactly computed using the method discovered independently by Cleve and Coppersmith, while for general m, the algorithm of Mosca and Zalka is available. Even for m=3 and k=1 our result appears to be new. We also present applications to compute the structure of abelian and solvable groups whose order has the same (but possibly unknown) prime factors as m. The applications for solvable groups also rely on an exact version of a technique proposed by Watrous for computing the uniform superposition of elements of subgroups.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An efficient quantum algorithm for lattice problems achieving subexponential approximation factor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.13450</link>
    <author>Lior Eldar, Sean Hallgren</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum algorithm for solving the Bounded Distance Decoding (BDD) problem with a subexponential approximation factor on a class of integer lattices. The quantum algorithm uses a well-known but challenging-to-use quantum state on lattices as a type of approximate quantum eigenvector to randomly self-reduce the BDD instance to a random BDD instance which is solvable classically. The running time of the quantum algorithm is polynomial for one range of approximation factors and subexponential time for a second range of approximation factors. The subclass of lattices we study has a natural description in terms of the lattice's periodicity and finite abelian group rank. This view makes for a clean quantum algorithm in terms of finite abelian groups, uses very relatively little from lattice theory, and suggests exploring approximation algorithms for lattice problems in parameters other than dimension alone. A talk on this paper sparked many lively discussions and resulted in a new classical algorithm matching part of our result. We leave it as a challenge to give a classcial algorithm matching the general case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Optimization of Maximum Independent Set using Rydberg Atom Arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09372</link>
    <author>Sepehr Ebadi, Alexander Keesling, Madelyn Cain, Tout T. Wang, Harry Levine, Dolev Bluvstein, Giulia Semeghini, Ahmed Omran, Jinguo Liu, Rhine Samajdar, Xiu-Zhe Luo, Beatrice Nash, Xun Gao, Boaz Barak, Edward Farhi, Subir Sachdev, Nathan Gemelke, Leo Zhou, Soonwon Choi, Hannes Pichler, et al (4)</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Realizing quantum speedup for practically relevant, computationally hard problems is a central challenge in quantum information science. Using Rydberg atom arrays with up to 289 qubits in two spatial dimensions, we experimentally investigate quantum algorithms for solving the Maximum Independent Set problem. We use a hardware-efficient encoding associated with Rydberg blockade, realize closed-loop optimization to test several variational algorithms, and subsequently apply them to systematically explore a class of graphs with programmable connectivity. We find the problem hardness is controlled by the solution degeneracy and number of local minima, and experimentally benchmark the quantum algorithm's performance against classical simulated annealing. On the hardest graphs, we observe a superlinear quantum speedup in finding exact solutions in the deep circuit regime and analyze its origins.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved quantum algorithms for linear and nonlinear differential equations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01054</link>
    <author>Hari Krovi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present substantially generalized and improved quantum algorithms over prior work for inhomogeneous linear and nonlinear ordinary differential equations (ODE). In Berry et al., (2017), a quantum algorithm for a certain class of linear ODEs is given, where the matrix involved needs to be diagonalizable. The quantum algorithm for linear ODEs presented here extends to many classes of non-diagonalizable matrices. The algorithm here can also be exponentially faster for certain classes of diagonalizable matrices. Our linear ODE algorithm is then applied to nonlinear differential equations using Carleman linearization (an approach taken recently by us in Liu et al., (2021)). The improvement over that result is two-fold. First, we obtain an exponentially better dependence on error. This kind of logarithmic dependence on error has also been achieved by Xue et al., (2021), but only for homogeneous nonlinear equations. Second, the present algorithm can handle any sparse, invertible matrix (that models dissipation) if it has a negative log-norm (including non-diagonalizable matrices), whereas Liu et al., (2021) and Xue et al., (2021) additionally require normality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>High-temperature thermalization implies the emergence of quantum state designs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01669</link>
    <author>Henrik Wilming, Ingo Roth</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It was recently observed that in certain thermalizing many-body systems, measuring the complement of a subsystem that thermalized to infinite temperature in a suitable orthonormal basis gives rise to approximate quantum state k-designs as post-measurement states on the subsystem. We prove that this emergence of approximate k-designs holds true in every large system where some small subsystem is close to being maximally mixed. On a technical level we show that any high-dimensional purification of an approximately maximally mixed state induces an approximate quantum state k-design when measured in a suitable orthonormal basis. Moreover, we show that this is true with overwhelming probability for measurement bases chosen uniformly at random from the Haar measure.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical simulation of quantum circuits with partial and graphical stabiliser decompositions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.09202</link>
    <author>Aleks Kissinger, John van de Wetering, Renaud Vilmart</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent developments in classical simulation of quantum circuits make use of clever decompositions of chunks of magic states into sums of efficiently simulable stabiliser states. We show here how, by considering certain non-stabiliser entangled states which have more favourable decompositions, we can speed up these simulations. This is made possible by using the ZX-calculus, which allows us to easily find instances of these entangled states in the simplified diagram representing the quantum circuit to be simulated. We additionally find a new technique of partial stabiliser decompositions that allow us to trade magic states for stabiliser terms. With this technique we require only $2^{\alpha t}$ stabiliser terms, where $\alpha\approx 0.396$, to simulate a circuit with T-count $t$. This matches the $\alpha$ found by Qassim et al., but whereas they only get this scaling in the asymptotic limit, ours applies for a circuit of any size. Our method builds upon a recently proposed scheme for simulation combining stabiliser decompositions and optimisation strategies implemented in the software QuiZX. With our techniques we manage to reliably simulate 50-qubit 1400 T-count hidden shift circuits in a couple of minutes on a consumer laptop.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing quantum circuits with Riemannian gradient-flow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06976</link>
    <author>Roeland Wiersema, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms are a promising class of algorithms that can be performed on currently available quantum computers. In most settings, the free parameters of a variational circuit are optimized using a classical optimizer that updates parameters in Euclidean geometry. Since quantum circuits are elements of the special unitary group, we can consider an alternative optimization perspective that depends on the structure of this group. In this work, we investigate a Riemannian optimization scheme over the special unitary group and we discuss its implementation on a quantum computer. We illustrate that the resulting Riemannian gradient-flow algorithm has favorable optimization properties for deep circuits and that an approximate version of this algorithm can be performed on near-term hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement estimation in tensor network states via sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04089</link>
    <author>Noa Feldman, Augustine Kshetrimayum, Jens Eisert, Moshe Goldstein</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a method for extracting meaningful entanglement measures of tensor network states in general dimensions. Current methods require the explicit reconstruction of the density matrix, which is highly demanding, or the contraction of replicas, which requires an effort exponential in the number of replicas and which is costly in terms of memory. In contrast, our method requires the stochastic sampling of matrix elements of the classically represented reduced states with respect to random states drawn from simple product probability measures constituting frames. Even though not corresponding to physical operations, such matrix elements are straightforward to calculate for tensor network states, and their moments provide the Rényi entropies and negativities as well as their symmetry-resolved components. We test our method on the one-dimensional critical XX chain and the two-dimensional toric code. Although the cost is exponential in the subsystem size, it is sufficiently moderate so that - in contrast with other approaches - accurate results can be obtained on a personal computer for relatively large subsystem sizes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Approximating Output Probabilities of Shallow Quantum Circuits which are Geometrically-local in any Fixed Dimension</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08349</link>
    <author>Suchetan Dontha, Shi Jie Samuel Tan, Stephen Smith, Sangheon Choi, Matthew Coudron</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a classical algorithm that, for any $D$-dimensional geometrically-local, quantum circuit $C$ of polylogarithmic-depth, and any bit string $x \in {0,1}^n$, can compute the quantity $|<x|C|0^{\otimes n}>|^2$ to within any inverse-polynomial additive error in quasi-polynomial time, for any fixed dimension $D$. This is an extension of the result [CC21], which originally proved this result for $D = 3$. To see why this is interesting, note that, while the $D = 1$ case of this result follows from standard use of Matrix Product States, known for decades, the $D = 2$ case required novel and interesting techniques introduced in [BGM19]. Extending to the case $D = 3$ was even more laborious and required further new techniques introduced in [CC21]. Our work here shows that, while handling each new dimension has historically required a new insight, and fixed algorithmic primitive, based on known techniques for $D \leq 3$, we can now handle any fixed dimension $D > 3$. Our algorithm uses the Divide-and-Conquer framework of [CC21] to approximate the desired quantity via several instantiations of the same problem type, each involving $D$-dimensional circuits on about half the number of qubits as the original. This division step is then applied recursively, until the width of the recursively decomposed circuits in the $D^{th}$ dimension is so small that they can effectively be regarded as $(D-1)$-dimensional problems by absorbing the small width in the $D^{th}$ dimension into the qudit structure at the cost of a moderate increase in runtime. The main technical challenge lies in ensuring that the more involved portions of the recursive circuit decomposition and error analysis from [CC21] still hold in higher dimensions, which requires small modifications to the analysis in some places.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Counting unitaries of T-depth one</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04163</link>
    <author>Vadym Kliuchnikov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits is $ \sum_{m=1}^{n}\tfrac{1}{m!}\prod_{k=0}^{m-1}(4^n/2^k - 2^k) \times \# \mathcal{C}_n, $ where $\#\mathcal{C}_n$ is the size of the $n$-qubit Clifford group, that is the number of unitaries of T-depth zero. The number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits grows as $2^{\Omega(n^2)} \cdot \# \mathcal{C}_n$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-inspired classical algorithm for molecular vibronic spectra</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01861</link>
    <author>Changhun Oh, Youngrong Lim, Yat Wong, Bill Fefferman, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Molecular vibronic spectra is an essential property of molecules, which is an important tool to analyze chemical components and study molecular structures. Computing molecular vibronic spectra has been a challenging task, and its best-known classical algorithm scales combinatorially in the system size. Recently, a quantum simulator, specifically Gaussian boson sampling, has been proposed to generate the spectra efficiently. Thus, molecular vibronic spectra is a candidate of tasks for which a quantum device provides a computational advantage. In this work, we propose a quantum-inspired classical algorithm for molecular vibronic spectra. We find an exact solution of the Fourier components of molecular vibronic spectra at zero temperature using the positive $P$-representation method. Thus, we can obtain the molecular vibronic spectra exactly by the inverse Fourier transformation for the solution for a given resolution. We also show that the same method applies to a finite temperature case. Therefore, computing molecular vibronic spectra, which can be mapped to a Gaussian boson sampling, does not require a quantum device. We then generalize the method beyond the Gaussian framework and find that the Fourier components are written as a loop hafnian, the exact computation of which is known to be \#P-hard. It presents an interesting theoretical separation between non-Gaussian boson sampling and Gaussian boson sampling. Meanwhile, since running an actual boson sampling circuit would incur an $1/\text{poly}(N)$ additive error for $N$ samples, we also study the possibility of achieving the same accuracy using a classical algorithm. Interestingly, when there is no squeezing in the process, one may use Gurvits's algorithm to compute the Fourier components within an additive error. We finally provide possible approaches to approximate the Fourier components and discuss their limitations.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>