<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Lecture Notes on Quantum Algorithms for Scientific Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08309</link>
    <author>Lin Lin</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This is a set of lecture notes used in a graduate topic class in applied mathematics called ``Quantum Algorithms for Scientific Computation'' at the Department of Mathematics, UC Berkeley during the fall semester of 2021. These lecture notes focus only on quantum algorithms closely related to scientific computation, and in particular, matrix computation. The main purpose of the lecture notes is to introduce quantum phase estimation (QPE) and ``post-QPE'' methods such as block encoding, quantum signal processing, and quantum singular value transformation, and to demonstrate their applications in solving eigenvalue problems, linear systems of equations, and differential equations. The intended audience is the broad computational science and engineering (CSE) community interested in using fault-tolerant quantum computers to solve challenging scientific computing problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Clifford-deformed Surface Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07802</link>
    <author>Arpit Dua, Aleksander Kubica, Liang Jiang, Steven T. Flammia, Michael J. Gullans</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Various realizations of Kitaev's surface code perform surprisingly well for biased Pauli noise. Attracted by these potential gains, we study the performance of Clifford-deformed surface codes (CDSCs) obtained from the surface code by the application of single-qubit Clifford operators. We first analyze CDSCs on the $3\times 3$ square lattice and find that depending on the noise bias, their logical error rates can differ by orders of magnitude. To explain the observed behavior, we introduce the effective distance $d'$, which reduces to the standard distance for unbiased noise. To study CDSC performance in the thermodynamic limit, we focus on random CDSCs. Using the statistical mechanical mapping for quantum codes, we uncover a phase diagram that describes random CDSCs with $50\%$ threshold at infinite bias. In the high-threshold region, we further demonstrate that typical code realizations at finite bias outperform the thresholds and subthreshold logical error rates of the best known translationally invariant codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficiently improving the performance of noisy quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10672</link>
    <author>Samuele Ferracin, Akel Hashim, Jean-Loup Ville, Ravi Naik, Arnaud Carignan-Dugas, Hammam Qassim, Alexis Morvan, David I. Santiago, Irfan Siddiqi, Joel J. Wallman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Using near-term quantum computers to achieve a quantum advantage requires efficient strategies to improve the performance of the noisy quantum devices presently available. We develop and experimentally validate two efficient error mitigation protocols named "Noiseless Output Extrapolation" and "Pauli Error Cancellation" that can drastically enhance the performance of quantum circuits composed of noisy cycles of gates. By combining popular mitigation strategies such as probabilistic error cancellation and noise amplification with efficient noise reconstruction methods, our protocols can mitigate a wide range of noise processes that do not satisfy the assumptions underlying existing mitigation protocols, including non-local and gate-dependent processes. We test our protocols on a four-qubit superconducting processor at the Advanced Quantum Testbed. We observe significant improvements in the performance of both structured and random circuits, with up to $86\%$ improvement in variation distance over the unmitigated outputs. Our experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our protocols, as well as their practicality for current hardware platforms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Low-overhead quantum computing with the color code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07806</link>
    <author>Felix Thomsen, Markus S. Kesselring, Stephen D. Bartlett, Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fault-tolerant quantum computation demands significant resources: large numbers of physical qubits must be checked for errors repeatedly to protect quantum data as logic gates are implemented in the presence of noise. We demonstrate that an approach based on the color code can lead to considerable reductions in the resource overheads compared with conventional methods, while remaining compatible with a two-dimensional layout. We propose a lattice surgery scheme that exploits the color code's rich structure to perform arbitrary pairs of commuting logical Pauli measurements in parallel while keeping the space cost low. Compared to lattice surgery schemes based on the surface code with the same code distance, our approach yields about a $3\times$ improvement in the space-time overhead. Even when taking into account the color code's lower error threshold using current decoders, the overhead is reduced by $10\%$ at a physical error rate of $10^{-3}$ and by $50\%$ at $10^{-4}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing matrix product states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01824</link>
    <author>Mehdi Soleimanifar, John Wright</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Devising schemes for testing the amount of entanglement in quantum systems has played a crucial role in quantum computing and information theory. Here, we study the problem of testing whether an unknown state $|\psi\rangle$ is a matrix product state (MPS) in the property testing model. MPS are a class of physically-relevant quantum states which arise in the study of quantum many-body systems. A quantum state $|\psi_{1,...,n}\rangle$ comprised of $n$ qudits is said to be an MPS of bond dimension $r$ if the reduced density matrix $\psi_{1,...,k}$ has rank $r$ for each $k \in \{1,...,n\}$. When $r=1$, this corresponds to the set of product states. For larger values of $r$, this yields a more expressive class of quantum states, which are allowed to possess limited amounts of entanglement. In the property testing model, one is given $m$ identical copies of $|\psi\rangle$, and the goal is to determine whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ or whether $|\psi\rangle$ is far from all such states. For the case of product states, we study the product test, a simple two-copy test previously analyzed by Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010), and a key ingredient in their proof that $\mathsf{QMA(2)}=\mathsf{QMA}(k)$ for $k \geq 2$. We give a new and simpler analysis of the product test which achieves an optimal bound for a wide range of parameters, answering open problems of Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010) and Montanaro and de Wolf (2016). For the case of $r\geq 2$, we give an efficient algorithm for testing whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ using $m = O(n r^2)$ copies, independent of the dimensions of the qudits, and we show that $\Omega(n^{1/2})$ copies are necessary for this task. This lower bound shows that a dependence on the number of qudits $n$ is necessary, in sharp contrast to the case of product states where a constant number of copies suffices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A lower bound on the space overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00119</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Alexander Müller-Hermes, Ala Shayeghi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The threshold theorem is a fundamental result in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation stating that arbitrarily long quantum computations can be performed with a polylogarithmic overhead provided the noise level is below a constant level. A recent work by Fawzi, Grospellier and Leverrier (FOCS 2018) building on a result by Gottesman (QIC 2013) has shown that the space overhead can be asymptotically reduced to a constant independent of the circuit provided we only consider circuits with a length bounded by a polynomial in the width. In this work, using a minimal model for quantum fault tolerance, we establish a general lower bound on the space overhead required to achieve fault tolerance. For any non-unitary qubit channel $\mathcal{N}$ and any quantum fault tolerance schemes against $\mathrm{i.i.d.}$ noise modeled by $\mathcal{N}$, we prove a lower bound of $\max\left\{\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})^{-1}n,\alpha_\mathcal{N} \log T\right\}$ on the number of physical qubits, for circuits of length $T$ and width $n$. Here, $\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})$ denotes the quantum capacity of $\mathcal{N}$ and $\alpha_\mathcal{N}>0$ is a constant only depending on the channel $\mathcal{N}$. In our model, we allow for qubits to be replaced by fresh ones during the execution of the circuit and we allow classical computation to be free and perfect. This improves upon results that assumed classical computations to be also affected by noise, and that sometimes did not allow for fresh qubits to be added. Along the way, we prove an exponential upper bound on the maximal length of fault-tolerant quantum computation with amplitude damping noise resolving a conjecture by Ben-Or, Gottesman, and Hassidim (2013).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Free-Fermion Subsystem Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07254</link>
    <author>Adrian Chapman, Steven T. Flammia, Alicia J. Kollár</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider quantum error-correcting subsystem codes whose gauge generators realize a translation-invariant, free-fermion-solvable spin model. In this setting, errors are suppressed by a Hamiltonian whose terms are the gauge generators of the code and whose exact spectrum and eigenstates can be found via a generalized Jordan-Wigner transformation. Such solutions are characterized by the frustration graph of the Hamiltonian: the graph whose vertices are Hamiltonian terms, which are neighboring if the terms anticommute. We provide methods for embedding a given frustration graph in the anticommutation relations of a spin model and present the first known example of an exactly solvable spin model with a two-dimensional free-fermion description and exact topological qubits. This model can be viewed as a free-fermionized version of the two-dimensional Bacon-Shor code. Using graph-theoretic tools to study the unit cell, we give an efficient algorithm for deciding if a given translation-invariant spin model is solvable, and explicitly construct the solution. Further, we examine the energetics of these exactly solvable models from the graph-theoretic perspective and show that the relevant gaps of the spin model correspond to known graph-theoretic quantities: the skew energy and the median eigenvalue of an oriented graph. Finally, we numerically search for models which have large spectral gaps above the ground state spin configuration and thus exhibit particularly robust thermal suppression of errors. These results suggest that optimal models will have low dimensionality and odd coordination numbers, and that the primary limit to energetic error suppression is the skew energy difference between different symmetry sectors rather than single-particle excitations of the free fermions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Probabilistic error cancellation with sparse Pauli-Lindblad models on noisy quantum processors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.09866</link>
    <author>Ewout van den Berg, Zlatko K. Minev, Abhinav Kandala, Kristan Temme</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Error-mitigation techniques can enable access to accurate estimates of physical observables that are otherwise biased by noise in pre-fault-tolerant quantum computers. One particularly general error-mitigation technique is probabilistic error cancellation (PEC), which effectively inverts a well-characterized noise channel to produce noise-free estimates of observables. Experimental realizations of this technique, however, have been impeded by the challenge of learning correlated noise in large quantum circuits. In this work, we present a practical protocol for learning a sparse noise model that scales to large quantum devices and is efficient to learn and invert. These advances enable us to demonstrate PEC on a superconducting quantum processor with crosstalk errors, thereby revealing a path to error-mitigated quantum computation with noise-free observables at larger circuit volumes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction with fractal topological codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03568</link>
    <author>Arpit Dua, Tomas Jochym-O'Connor, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, a class of fractal surface codes (FSCs), has been constructed on fractal lattices with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$, which admits a fault-tolerant non-Clifford CCZ gate. We investigate the performance of such FSCs as fault-tolerant quantum memories. We prove that there exist decoding strategies with non-zero thresholds for bit-flip and phase-flip errors in the FSCs with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$. For the bit-flip errors, we adapt the sweep decoder, developed for string-like syndromes in the regular 3D surface code, to the FSCs by designing suitable modifications on the boundaries of the holes in the fractal lattice. Moreover, our adaptation of the sweep decoder for the FSCs maintains its self-correcting and single-shot nature. For the phase-flip errors, we employ the minimum-weight-perfect-matching (MWPM) decoder for the point-like syndromes. We report a sustainable fault-tolerant threshold ($\sim 1.7\%$) under phenomenological noise for the sweep decoder and the code capacity threshold (lower bounded by $2.95\%$) for the MWPM decoder for a particular FSC with Hausdorff dimension $D_H\approx2.966$. The latter can be mapped to the critical point of a zero-temperature confinement-Higgs transition on the fractal lattice, which is tunable via the Hausdorff dimension.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A smallest computable entanglement monotone</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00835</link>
    <author>J. Eisert, M. M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Rains relative entropy of a bipartite quantum state is the tightest known upper bound on its distillable entanglement - which has a crisp physical interpretation of entanglement as a resource - and it is efficiently computable by convex programming. It has not been known to be a selective entanglement monotone in its own right. In this work, we strengthen the interpretation of the Rains relative entropy by showing that it is monotone under the action of selective operations that completely preserve the positivity of the partial transpose, reasonably quantifying entanglement. That is, we prove that Rains relative entropy of an ensemble generated by such an operation does not exceed the Rains relative entropy of the initial state in expectation, giving rise to the smallest, most conservative known computable selective entanglement monotone. Additionally, we show that this is true not only for the original Rains relative entropy, but also for Rains relative entropies derived from various Renyi relative entropies. As an application of these findings, we prove, in both the non-asymptotic and asymptotic settings, that the probabilistic approximate distillable entanglement of a state is bounded from above by various Rains relative entropies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum State Preparation with Optimal Circuit Depth: Implementations and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11495</link>
    <author>Xiao-Ming Zhang, Tongyang Li, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum state preparation is an important subroutine for quantum computing. We show that any $n$-qubit quantum state can be prepared with a $\Theta(n)$-depth circuit using only single- and two-qubit gates, although with a cost of an exponential amount of ancillary qubits. On the other hand, for sparse quantum states with $d\geqslant2$ non-zero entries, we can reduce the circuit depth to $\Theta(\log(nd))$ with $O(nd\log d)$ ancillary qubits. The algorithm for sparse states is exponentially faster than best-known results and the number of ancillary qubits is nearly optimal and only increases polynomially with the system size. We discuss applications of the results in different quantum computing tasks, such as Hamiltonian simulation, solving linear systems of equations, and realizing quantum random access memories, and find cases with exponential reductions of the circuit depth for all these three tasks. In particular, using our algorithm, we find a family of linear system solving problems enjoying exponential speedups, even compared to the best-known quantum and classical dequantization algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence between fermion-to-qubit mappings in two spatial dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05153</link>
    <author>Yu-An Chen, Yijia Xu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We argue that all locality-preserving mappings between fermionic observables and Pauli matrices on a two-dimensional lattice can be generated from the exact bosonization in Ref. [1], whose gauge constraints project onto the subspace of the toric code with emergent fermions. Starting from the exact bosonization and applying Clifford finite-depth generalized local unitary (gLU) transformation, we can achieve all possible fermion-to-qubit mappings (up to the re-pairing of Majorana fermions). In particular, we discover a new super-compact encoding using 1.25 qubits per fermion on the square lattice, which is lower than any method in the literature. We prove the existence of fermion-to-qubit mappings with qubit-fermion ratios $r=1+ \frac{1}{2k}$ for positive integers $k$, where the proof utilizes the trivialness of quantum cellular automata (QCA) in two spatial dimensions. When the ratio approaches 1, the fermion-to-qubit mapping reduces to the 1d Jordan-Wigner transformation along a certain path in the two-dimensional lattice. Finally, we explicitly demonstrate that the Bravyi-Kitaev superfast simulation, the Verstraete-Cirac auxiliary method, Kitaev's exactly solved model, the Majorana loop stabilizer codes, and the compact fermion-to-qubit mapping can all be obtained from the exact bosonization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A circuit-level protocol and analysis for twist-based lattice surgery</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05678</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Lattice surgery is a measurement-based technique for performing fault-tolerant quantum computation in two dimensions. When using the surface code, the most general lattice surgery operations require lattice irregularities called twist defects. However, implementing twist-based lattice surgery may require additional resources, such as extra device connectivity, and could lower the threshold and overall performance for the surface code. Here we provide an explicit twist-based lattice surgery protocol and its requisite connectivity layout. We also provide new stabilizer measurement circuits for measuring twist defects which are compatible with our chosen gate scheduling. We undertake the first circuit-level error correction simulations during twist-based lattice surgery using a biased depolarizing noise model. Our results indicate a slight decrease in the threshold for timelike logical failures compared to lattice surgery protocols with no twist defects in the bulk. However, comfortably below threshold (i.e. with CNOT infidelities below $5 \times 10^{-3}$), the performance degradation is mild and in fact preferable over proposed alternative twist-free schemes. Lastly, we provide an efficient scheme for measuring $Y$ operators along boundaries of surface codes which bypasses certain steps that were required in previous schemes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Avoiding barren plateaus using classical shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08194</link>
    <author>Stefan H. Sack, Raimel A. Medina, Alexios A. Michailidis, Richard Kueng, Maksym Serbyn</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms are promising algorithms for achieving quantum advantage on near-term devices. The quantum hardware is used to implement a variational wave function and measure observables, whereas the classical computer is used to store and update the variational parameters. The optimization landscape of expressive variational ansätze is however dominated by large regions in parameter space, known as barren plateaus, with vanishing gradients which prevents efficient optimization. In this work we propose a general algorithm to avoid barren plateaus in the initialization and throughout the optimization. To this end we define a notion of weak barren plateaus (WBP) based on the entropies of local reduced density matrices. The presence of WBPs can be efficiently quantified using recently introduced shadow tomography of the quantum state with a classical computer. We demonstrate that avoidance of WBPs suffices to ensure sizable gradients in the initialization. In addition, we demonstrate that decreasing the gradient step size, guided by the entropies allows to avoid WBPs during the optimization process. This paves the way for efficient barren plateau free optimization on near-term devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Oracle separations of hybrid quantum-classical circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01904</link>
    <author>Atul Singh Arora, Alexandru Gheorghiu, Uttam Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An important theoretical problem in the study of quantum computation, that is also practically relevant in the context of near-term quantum devices, is to understand the computational power of hybrid models, that combine poly-time classical computation with short-depth quantum computation. Here, we consider two such models: CQ_d which captures the scenario of a polynomial-time classical algorithm that queries a d-depth quantum computer many times; and QC_d which is more analogous to measurement-based quantum computation and captures the scenario of a d-depth quantum computer with the ability to change the sequence of gates being applied depending on measurement outcomes processed by a classical computation. Chia, Chung & Lai (STOC 2020) and Coudron & Menda (STOC 2020) showed that these models (with d=log^O(1) (n)) are strictly weaker than BQP (the class of problems solvable by poly-time quantum computation), relative to an oracle, disproving a conjecture of Jozsa in the relativised world. We show that, despite the similarities between CQ_d and QC_d, the two models are incomparable, i.e. CQ_d $\nsubseteq$ QC_d and QC_d $\nsubseteq$ CQ_d relative to an oracle. In other words, there exist problems that one model can solve but not the other and vice versa. We do this by considering new oracle problems that capture the distinctions between the two models and by introducing the notion of an intrinsically stochastic oracle, an oracle whose responses are inherently randomised, which is used for our second result. While we leave showing the second separation relative to a standard oracle as an open problem, we believe the notion of stochastic oracles could be of independent interest for studying complexity classes which have resisted separation in the standard oracle model. Our constructions also yield simpler oracle separations between the hybrid models and BQP, compared to earlier works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Finding fault-tolerant Clifford circuits using SMT solvers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12450</link>
    <author>Noah Shutty, Christopher Chamberland</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Universal fault-tolerant quantum computers will require the use of efficient protocols to implement encoded operations necessary in the execution of algorithms. In this work, we show how SMT solvers can be used to automate the construction of Clifford circuits with certain fault-tolerance properties and apply our techniques to a fault-tolerant magic state preparation protocol. Part of the protocol requires converting magic states encoded in the color code to magic states encoded in the surface code. Since the teleportation step involves decoding a color code merged with a surface code, we develop a new decoding algorithm applicable to such codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limits on Parameter Estimation of Quantum Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01738</link>
    <author>Vishal Katariya</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The aim of this thesis is to develop a theoretical framework to study parameter estimation of quantum channels. We study the task of estimating unknown parameters encoded in a channel in the sequential setting. A sequential strategy is the most general way to use a channel multiple times. Our goal is to establish lower bounds (called Cramer-Rao bounds) on the estimation error. The bounds we develop are universally applicable; i.e., they apply to all permissible quantum dynamics. We consider the use of catalysts to enhance the power of a channel estimation strategy. This is termed amortization. The power of a channel for a parameter estimation is determined by its Fisher information. Thus, we study how much a catalyst quantum state can enhance the Fisher information of a channel by defining the amortized Fisher information. We establish our bounds by proving that for certain Fisher information quantities, catalyst states do not improve the performance of a sequential estimation protocol compared to a parallel one. The technical term for this is an amortization collapse. We use this to establish bounds when estimating one parameter, or multiple parameters simultaneously. Our bounds apply universally and we also cast them as optimization problems. For the single parameter case, we establish bounds for general quantum channels using both the symmetric logarithmic derivative (SLD) Fisher information and the right logarithmic derivative (RLD) Fisher information. The task of estimating multiple parameters simultaneously is more involved than the single parameter case, because the Cramer-Rao bounds take the form of matrix inequalities. We establish a scalar Cramer-Rao bound for multiparameter channel estimation using the RLD Fisher information. For both single and multiparameter estimation, we provide a no-go condition for the so-called Heisenberg scaling using our RLD-based bound.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Algorithms for Approximating Quantum Partition Functions at Low Temperature</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06533</link>
    <author>Tyler Helmuth, Ryan L. Mann</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish an efficient approximation algorithm for the partition functions of a class of quantum spin systems at low temperature, which can be viewed as stable quantum perturbations of classical spin systems. Our algorithm is based on combining the contour representation of quantum spin systems of this type due to Borgs, Kotecký, and Ueltschi with the algorithmic framework developed by Helmuth, Perkins, and Regts, and Borgs et al.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum machine learning with subspace states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00054</link>
    <author>Iordanis Kerenidis, Anupam Prakash</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new approach for quantum linear algebra based on quantum subspace states and present three new quantum machine learning algorithms. The first is a quantum determinant sampling algorithm that samples from the distribution $\Pr[S]= det(X_{S}X_{S}^{T})$ for $|S|=d$ using $O(nd)$ gates and with circuit depth $O(d\log n)$. The state of art classical algorithm for the task requires $O(d^{3})$ operations \citederezinski2019minimax. The second is a quantum singular value estimation algorithm for compound matrices $\mathcal{A}^{k}$, the speedup for this algorithm is potentially exponential. It decomposes a $\binom{n}{k}$ dimensional vector of order-$k$ correlations into a linear combination of subspace states corresponding to $k$-tuples of singular vectors of $A$. The third algorithm reduces exponentially the depth of circuits used in quantum topological data analysis from $O(n)$ to $O(\log n)$. Our basic tool are quantum subspace states, defined as $|Col(X)\rangle = \sum_{S\subset [n], |S|=d} det(X_{S}) |S\rangle$ for matrices $X \in \mathbb{R}^{n \times d}$ such that $X^{T} X = I_{d}$, that encode $d$-dimensional subspaces of $\mathbb{R}^{n}$. We develop two efficient state preparation techniques, the first using Givens circuits uses the representation of a subspace as a sequence of Givens rotations, while the second uses efficient implementations of unitaries $\Gamma(x) = \sum_{i} x_{i} Z^{\otimes (i-1)} \otimes X \otimes I^{n-i}$ with $O(\log n)$ depth circuits that we term Clifford loaders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simultaneous Measurement and Entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10667</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Peter Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study scenarios which arise when two spatially-separated observers, Alice and Bob, are try to identify a quantum state sampled from several possibilities. In particular, we examine their strategies for maximizing both the probability of guessing their state correctly as well as their information gain about it. It is known that there are scenarios where allowing Alice and Bob to use LOCC offers an improvement over the case where they must make their measurements simultaneously. Similarly, Alice and Bob can sometimes improve their outcomes if they have access to a Bell pair. We show how LOCC allows Alice and Bob to distinguish between two product states optimally and find that a LOCC is almost always more helpful than a Bell pair for distinguishing product states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking Characterization Methods for Noisy Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02243</link>
    <author>Megan L. Dahlhauser, Travis S. Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Effective methods for characterizing the noise in quantum computing devices are essential for programming and debugging circuit performance. Existing approaches vary in the information obtained as well as the amount of quantum and classical resources required, with more information generally requiring more resources. Here we benchmark the characterization methods of gate set tomography, Pauli channel noise reconstruction, and empirical direct characterization for developing models that describe noisy quantum circuit performance on a 27-qubit superconducting transmon device. We evaluate these models by comparing the accuracy of noisy circuit simulations with the corresponding experimental observations. We find that the agreement of noise model to experiment does not correlate with the information gained by characterization and that the underlying circuit strongly influences the best choice of characterization approach. Empirical direct characterization scales best of the methods we tested and produced the most accurate characterizations across our benchmarks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure conversion for fault-tolerant quantum computing in alkaline earth Rydberg atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03540</link>
    <author>Yue Wu, Shimon Kolkowitz, Shruti Puri, Jeff D Thompson</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Executing quantum algorithms on error-corrected logical qubits is a critical step for scalable quantum computing, but the requisite numbers of qubits and physical error rates are demanding for current experimental hardware. Recently, the development of error correcting codes tailored to particular physical noise models has helped relax these requirements. In this work, we propose a qubit encoding and gate protocol for ${}^{171}$Yb neutral atom qubits that converts the dominant physical errors into erasures, that is, errors in known locations. The key idea is to encode qubits in a metastable electronic level, such that gate errors predominantly result in transitions to disjoint subspaces whose populations can be continuously monitored via fluorescence. We estimate that 98% of errors can be converted into erasures. We quantify the benefit of this approach via circuit-level simulations of the surface code, finding a threshold increase from 0.937% to 4.15%. We also observe a larger code distance near the threshold, leading to a faster decrease in the logical error rate for the same number of physical qubits, which is important for near-term implementations. Erasure conversion should benefit any error correcting code, and may also be applied to design new gates and encodings in other qubit platforms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailored cluster states with high threshold under biased noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10566</link>
    <author>Jahan Claes, J. Eli Bourassa, Shruti Puri</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fault-tolerant cluster states form the basis for scalable measurement-based quantum computation. Recently, new stabilizer codes for scalable circuit-based quantum computation have been introduced that have very high thresholds under biased noise where the qubit predominantly suffers from one type of error, e.g. dephasing. However, extending these advances in stabilizer codes to generate high-threshold cluster states for biased noise has been a challenge, as the standard method for foliating stabilizer codes to generate fault-tolerant cluster states does not preserve the noise bias. In this work, we overcome this barrier by introducing a generalization of the cluster state that allows us to foliate stabilizer codes in a bias-preserving way. As an example of our approach, we construct a foliated version of the XZZX code which we call the XZZX cluster state. We demonstrate that under a circuit-level noise model, our XZZX cluster state has a threshold more than double the usual cluster state when dephasing errors are more likely than errors which cause bit flips by a factor of $O(100)$ or more.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Correction with Quantum Autoencoders</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00555</link>
    <author>David F. Locher, Lorenzo Cardarelli, Markus Müller</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Active quantum error correction is a central ingredient to achieve robust quantum processors. In this paper we investigate the potential of quantum machine learning for quantum error correction. Specifically, we demonstrate how quantum neural networks, in the form of quantum autoencoders, can be trained to learn optimal strategies for active detection and correction of errors, including spatially correlated computational errors as well as qubit losses. We highlight that the denoising capabilities of quantum autoencoders are not limited to the protection of specific states but extend to the entire logical codespace. We also show that quantum neural networks can be used to discover new logical encodings that are optimally adapted to the underlying noise. Moreover, we find that, even in the presence of moderate noise in the quantum autoencoders themselves, they may still be successfully used to perform beneficial quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Analytical calculation formulas for capacities of classical and classical-quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02450</link>
    <author>Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive an analytical calculation formula for the channel capacity of a classical channel without any iteration while its existing algorithms require iterations and the number of iteration depends on the required precision level. Hence, our formula is its first analytical formula without any iteration. We apply the obtained formula to examples and see how the obtained formula works in these examples. Then, we extend it to the channel capacity of a classical-quantum (cq-) channel. Many existing studies proposed algorithms for a cq-channel and all of them require iterations. Our extended analytical algorithm have also no iteration and output the exactly optimum values.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An efficient quantum algorithm for lattice problems achieving subexponential approximation factor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.13450</link>
    <author>Lior Eldar, Sean Hallgren</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum algorithm for solving the Bounded Distance Decoding (BDD) problem with a subexponential approximation factor on a class of integer lattices. The quantum algorithm uses a well-known but challenging-to-use quantum state on lattices as a type of approximate quantum eigenvector to randomly self-reduce the BDD instance to a random BDD instance which is solvable classically. The running time of the quantum algorithm is polynomial for one range of approximation factors and subexponential time for a second range of approximation factors. The subclass of lattices we study has a natural description in terms of the lattice's periodicity and finite abelian group rank. This view makes for a clean quantum algorithm in terms of finite abelian groups, uses very relatively little from lattice theory, and suggests exploring approximation algorithms for lattice problems in parameters other than dimension alone. A talk on this paper sparked many lively discussions and resulted in a new classical algorithm matching part of our result. We leave it as a challenge to give a classcial algorithm matching the general case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Depth optimization of CZ, CNOT, and Clifford circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05215</link>
    <author>Dmitri Maslov, Ben Zindorf</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We seek to develop better upper bound guarantees on the depth of quantum CZ gate, CNOT gate, and Clifford circuits than those reported previously. We focus on the number of qubits $n\,{\leq}\,$1,345,000 [1], which represents the most practical use case. Our upper bound on the depth of CZ circuits is $\lfloor n/2 + 0.4993{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.0191{\cdot}\log(n) - 10.9139\rfloor$, improving best known depth by a factor of roughly 2. We extend the constructions used to prove this upper bound to obtain depth upper bound of $\lfloor n + 1.9496{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.5075{\cdot}\log(n) - 23.4269 \rfloor$ for CNOT gate circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $4/3$ over state of the art, and depth upper bound of $\lfloor 2n + 2.9487{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 8.4909{\cdot}\log(n) - 44.4798\rfloor$ for Clifford circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $5/3$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum cryptography with classical communication: parallel remote state preparation for copy-protection, verification, and more</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.13445</link>
    <author>Alexandru Gheorghiu, Tony Metger, Alexander Poremba</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum mechanical effects have enabled the construction of cryptographic primitives that are impossible classically. For example, quantum copy-protection allows for a program to be encoded in a quantum state in such a way that the program can be evaluated, but not copied. Many of these cryptographic primitives are two-party protocols, where one party, Bob, has full quantum computational capabilities, and the other party, Alice, is only required to send random BB84 states to Bob. In this work, we show how such protocols can generically be converted to ones where Alice is fully classical, assuming that Bob cannot efficiently solve the LWE problem. In particular, this means that all communication between (classical) Alice and (quantum) Bob is classical, yet they can still make use of cryptographic primitives that would be impossible if both parties were classical. We apply this conversion procedure to obtain quantum cryptographic protocols with classical communication for unclonable encryption, copy-protection, computing on encrypted data, and verifiable blind delegated computation. The key technical ingredient for our result is a protocol for classically-instructed parallel remote state preparation of BB84 states. This is a multi-round protocol between (classical) Alice and (quantum polynomial-time) Bob that allows Alice to certify that Bob must have prepared $n$ uniformly random BB84 states (up to a change of basis on his space). Furthermore, Alice knows which specific BB84 states Bob has prepared, while Bob himself does not. Hence, the situation at the end of this protocol is (almost) equivalent to one where Alice sent $n$ random BB84 states to Bob. This allows us to replace the step of preparing and sending BB84 states in existing protocols by our remote-state preparation protocol in a generic and modular way.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reducing the impact of time-correlated noise on zero-noise extrapolation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11792</link>
    <author>Kevin Schultz, Ryan LaRose, Andrea Mari, Gregory Quiroz, Nathan Shammah, B. David Clader, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Zero-noise extrapolation is a quantum error mitigation technique that has typically been studied under the ideal approximation that the noise acting on a quantum device is not time-correlated. In this work, we investigate the feasibility and performance of zero-noise extrapolation in the presence of time-correlated noise. We show that, in contrast to white noise, time-correlated noise is harder to mitigate via zero-noise extrapolation because it is difficult to scale the noise level without also modifying its spectral distribution. This limitation is particularly strong if "local" gate-level methods are applied for noise scaling. However, we find that "global" noise scaling methods, e.g., global unitary folding, can be sufficiently reliable even in the presence of time-correlated noise. We also introduce gate Trotterization as a new noise scaling technique that may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable High-Performance Fluxonium Quantum Processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.09374</link>
    <author>Long B. Nguyen, Gerwin Koolstra, Yosep Kim, Alexis Morvan, Trevor Chistolini, Shraddha Singh, Konstantin N. Nesterov, Christian Jünger, Larry Chen, Zahra Pedramrazi, Bradley K. Mitchell, John Mark Kreikebaum, Shruti Puri, David I. Santiago, Irfan Siddiqi Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The technological development of hardware heading toward universal fault-tolerant quantum computation requires a large-scale processing unit with high performance. While fluxonium qubits are promising with high coherence and large anharmonicity, their scalability has not been systematically explored. In this work, we propose a superconducting quantum information processor based on compact high-coherence fluxoniums with suppressed crosstalk, reduced design complexity, improved operational efficiency, high-fidelity gates, and resistance to parameter fluctuations. In this architecture, the qubits are readout dispersively using individual resonators connected to a common bus and manipulated via combined on-chip RF and DC control lines, both of which can be designed to have low crosstalk. A multi-path coupling approach enables exchange interactions between the high-coherence computational states and at the same time suppresses the spurious static ZZ rate, leading to fast and high-fidelity entangling gates. We numerically investigate the cross resonance controlled-NOT and the differential AC-Stark controlled-Z operations, revealing low gate error for qubit-qubit detuning bandwidth of up to 1 GHz. Our study on frequency crowding indicates high fabrication yield for quantum processors consisting of over thousands of qubits. In addition, we estimate low resource overhead to suppress logical error rate using the XZZX surface code. These results promise a scalable quantum architecture with high performance for the pursuit of universal quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>