<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms and the power of forgetting</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.12447</link>
    <author>Andrew M. Childs, Matthew Coudron, Amin Shiraz Gilani</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The so-called welded tree problem provides an example of a black-box problem that can be solved exponentially faster by a quantum walk than by any classical algorithm. Given the name of a special ENTRANCE vertex, a quantum walk can find another distinguished EXIT vertex using polynomially many queries, though without finding any particular path from ENTRANCE to EXIT. It has been an open problem for twenty years whether there is an efficient quantum algorithm for finding such a path, or if the path-finding problem is hard even for quantum computers. We show that a natural class of efficient quantum algorithms provably cannot find a path from ENTRANCE to EXIT. Specifically, we consider algorithms that, within each branch of their superposition, always store a set of vertex labels that form a connected subgraph including the ENTRANCE, and that only provide these vertex labels as inputs to the oracle. While this does not rule out the possibility of a quantum algorithm that efficiently finds a path, it is unclear how an algorithm could benefit by deviating from this behavior. Our no-go result suggests that, for some problems, quantum algorithms must necessarily forget the path they take to reach a solution in order to outperform classical computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum majority vote</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.11729</link>
    <author>Harry Buhrman, Noah Linden, Laura Mančinska, Ashley Montanaro, Maris Ozols</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Majority vote is a basic method for amplifying correct outcomes that is widely used in computer science and beyond. While it can amplify the correctness of a quantum device with classical output, the analogous procedure for quantum output is not known. We introduce quantum majority vote as the following task: given a product state $|\psi_1\rangle \otimes \dots \otimes |\psi_n\rangle$ where each qubit is in one of two orthogonal states $|\psi\rangle$ or $|\psi^\perp\rangle$, output the majority state. We show that an optimal algorithm for this problem achieves worst-case fidelity of $1/2 + \Theta(1/\sqrt{n})$. Under the promise that at least $2/3$ of the input qubits are in the majority state, the fidelity increases to $1 - \Theta(1/n)$ and approaches $1$ as $n$ increases. We also consider the more general problem of computing any symmetric and equivariant Boolean function $f: \{0,1\}^n \to \{0,1\}$ in an unknown quantum basis, and show that a generalization of our quantum majority vote algorithm is optimal for this task. The optimal parameters for the generalized algorithm and its worst-case fidelity can be determined by a simple linear program of size $O(n)$. The time complexity of the algorithm is $O(n^4 \log n)$ where $n$ is the number of input qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mind the gap: Achieving a super-Grover quantum speedup by jumping to the end</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.01513</link>
    <author>Alexander M. Dalzell, Nicola Pancotti, Earl T. Campbell, Fernando G. S. L. Brandão</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a quantum algorithm that has rigorous runtime guarantees for several families of binary optimization problems, including Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO), Ising spin glasses ($p$-spin model), and $k$-local constraint satisfaction problems ($k$-CSP). We show that either (a) the algorithm finds the optimal solution in time $O^*(2^{(0.5-c)n})$ for an $n$-independent constant $c$, a $2^{cn}$ advantage over Grover's algorithm; or (b) there are sufficiently many low-cost solutions such that classical random guessing produces a $(1-\eta)$ approximation to the optimal cost value in sub-exponential time for arbitrarily small choice of $\eta$. Additionally, we show that for a large fraction of random instances from the $k$-spin model and for any fully satisfiable or slightly frustrated $k$-CSP formula, statement (a) is the case. The algorithm and its analysis is largely inspired by Hastings' short-path algorithm [$\textit{Quantum}$ $\textbf{2}$ (2018) 78].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Anyon condensation and the color code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.00042</link>
    <author>Markus S. Kesselring, Julio C. Magdalena de la Fuente, Felix Thomsen, Jens Eisert, Stephen D. Bartlett, Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The manipulation of topologically-ordered phases of matter to encode and process quantum information forms the cornerstone of many approaches to fault-tolerant quantum computing. Here, we demonstrate that fault-tolerant logical operations in these approaches, essential for scalable quantum computing, can be usefully interpreted as instances of anyon condensation. We present a constructive theory for anyon condensation and, in tandem, illustrate our theory explicitly with examples of fault-tolerant logical operations for the color-code model. We show that different condensation processes are associated with a general class of domain walls, which can exist in both space- and time-like directions. This class includes semi-transparent domain walls that condense certain bosonic subsets of anyons. We use our theory to classify topological objects and design novel fault-tolerant logic gates for the color code. As a final example, we also argue that dynamical `Floquet codes' can be viewed as a series of condensation operations. We propose a general construction for realising planar dynamically driven codes based on condensation operations on the color code. We use our construction to introduce a new Calderbank-Shor Steane-type Floquet code that we call the Floquet color code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A super-polynomial quantum advantage for combinatorial optimization problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08678</link>
    <author>Niklas Pirnay, Vincent Ulitzsch, Frederik Wilde, Jens Eisert, Jean-Pierre Seifert</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Combinatorial optimization - a field of research addressing problems that feature strongly in a wealth of practical and industrial contexts - has been identified as one of the core potential fields of applicability of near-term quantum computers. It is still unclear, however, to what extent variational quantum algorithms can actually outperform classical algorithms for this type of problems. In this work, by resorting to computational learning theory and cryptographic notions, we prove that fault-tolerant quantum computers feature a super-polynomial advantage over classical computers in approximating solutions to combinatorial optimization problems. Specifically, building on seminal work of Kearns and Valiant, we construct special instances of the integer programming problem (which in its most general form is NP-complete) that we prove to be hard-to-approximate classically but give an efficient quantum algorithm to approximate the optimal solution of those instances, hence showing a super-polynomial quantum advantage. This result shows that quantum devices have the power to approximate combinatorial optimization solutions beyond the reach of classical efficient algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sample-optimal classical shadows for pure states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.11810</link>
    <author>Daniel Grier, Hakop Pashayan, Luke Schaeffer</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the classical shadows task for pure states in the setting of both joint and independent measurements. The task is to measure few copies of an unknown pure state $\rho$ in order to learn a classical description which suffices to later estimate expectation values of observables. Specifically, the goal is to approximate $\mathrm{Tr}(O \rho)$ for any Hermitian observable $O$ to within additive error $\epsilon$ provided $\mathrm{Tr}(O^2)\leq B$ and $\lVert O \rVert = 1$. Our main result applies to the joint measurement setting, where we show $\tilde{\Theta}(\sqrt{B}\epsilon^{-1} + \epsilon^{-2})$ samples of $\rho$ are necessary and sufficient to succeed with high probability. The upper bound is a quadratic improvement on the previous best sample complexity known for this problem. For the lower bound, we see that the bottleneck is not how fast we can learn the state but rather how much any classical description of $\rho$ can be compressed for observable estimation. In the independent measurement setting, we show that $\mathcal O(\sqrt{Bd} \epsilon^{-1} + \epsilon^{-2})$ samples suffice. Notably, this implies that the random Clifford measurements algorithm of Huang, Kueng, and Preskill, which is sample-optimal for mixed states, is not optimal for pure states. Interestingly, our result also uses the same random Clifford measurements but employs a different estimator.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient classical algorithms for simulating symmetric quantum systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.16998</link>
    <author>Eric R. Anschuetz, Andreas Bauer, Bobak T. Kiani, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The presence of symmetries can convert an otherwise computationally hard task into an efficient one. In light of recently proposed quantum algorithms that incorporate symmetries in the hope of quantum advantage, we show that with symmetries that are restrictive enough, classical algorithms can efficiently emulate their quantum counterparts. As an example, we show that simulating and finding the ground state of permutation invariant Hamiltonians can be efficiently performed in polynomial classical time, further restricting the possible set of symmetries that provide quantum advantage.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing the depth of variational quantum algorithms is strongly QCMA-hard to approximate</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.12519</link>
    <author>Lennart Bittel, Sevag Gharibian, Martin Kliesch</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational Quantum Algorithms (VQAs), such as the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) of [Farhi, Goldstone, Gutmann, 2014], have seen intense study towards near-term applications on quantum hardware. A crucial parameter for VQAs is the depth of the variational ansatz used - the smaller the depth, the more amenable the ansatz is to near-term quantum hardware in that it gives the circuit a chance to be fully executed before the system decoheres. This potential for depth reduction has made VQAs a staple of Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ)-era research. In this work, we show that approximating the optimal depth for a given VQA ansatz is intractable. Formally, we show that for any constant $\epsilon>0$, it is QCMA-hard to approximate the optimal depth of a VQA ansatz within multiplicative factor $N^{1-\epsilon}$, for $N$ denoting the encoding size of the VQA instance. (Here, Quantum Classical Merlin-Arthur (QCMA) is a quantum generalization of NP.) We then show that this hardness persists even in the "simpler" setting of QAOAs. To our knowledge, this yields the first natural QCMA-hard-to-approximate problems. To achieve these results, we bypass the need for a PCP theorem for QCMA by appealing to the disperser-based NP-hardness of approximation construction of [Umans, FOCS 1999].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An operator extension of weak monotonicity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.13372</link>
    <author>Ting-Chun Lin, Isaac H. Kim, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Let $S(\rho)$ be the von Neumann entropy of a density matrix $\rho$. Weak monotonicity asserts that $S(\rho_{AB}) - S(\rho_A) + S(\rho_{BC}) - S(\rho_C)\geq 0$ for any tripartite density matrix $\rho_{ABC}$, a fact that is equivalent to the strong subadditivity of entropy. We prove an operator inequality, which, upon taking an expectation value with respect to the state $\rho_{ABC}$, reduces to the weak monotonicity inequality. Generalizations of this inequality to the one involving two independent density matrices, as well as their Rényi-generalizations, are also presented.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning Quantum Processes and Hamiltonians via the Pauli Transfer Matrix</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.04471</link>
    <author>Matthias C. Caro</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Learning about physical systems from quantum-enhanced experiments, relying on a quantum memory and quantum processing, can outperform learning from experiments in which only classical memory and processing are available. Whereas quantum advantages have been established for a variety of state learning tasks, quantum process learning allows for comparable advantages only with a careful problem formulation and is less understood. We establish an exponential quantum advantage for learning an unknown $n$-qubit quantum process $\mathcal{N}$. We show that a quantum memory allows to efficiently solve the following tasks: (a) learning the Pauli transfer matrix of an arbitrary $\mathcal{N}$, (b) predicting expectation values of bounded Pauli-sparse observables measured on the output of an arbitrary $\mathcal{N}$ upon input of a Pauli-sparse state, and (c) predicting expectation values of arbitrary bounded observables measured on the output of an unknown $\mathcal{N}$ with sparse Pauli transfer matrix upon input of an arbitrary state. With quantum memory, these tasks can be solved using linearly-in-$n$ many copies of the Choi state of $\mathcal{N}$, and even time-efficiently in the case of (b). In contrast, any learner without quantum memory requires exponentially-in-$n$ many queries, even when querying $\mathcal{N}$ on subsystems of adaptively chosen states and performing adaptively chosen measurements. In proving this separation, we extend existing shadow tomography upper and lower bounds from states to channels via the Choi-Jamiolkowski isomorphism. Moreover, we combine Pauli transfer matrix learning with polynomial interpolation techniques to develop a procedure for learning arbitrary Hamiltonians, which may have non-local all-to-all interactions, from short-time dynamics. Our results highlight the power of quantum-enhanced experiments for learning highly complex quantum dynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Active volume: An architecture for efficient fault-tolerant quantum computers with limited non-local connections</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.15465</link>
    <author>Daniel Litinski, Naomi Nickerson</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In existing general-purpose architectures for surface-code-based fault-tolerant quantum computers, the cost of a quantum computation is determined by the circuit volume, i.e., the number of qubits multiplied by the number of non-Clifford gates. We introduce an architecture using non-2D-local connections in which the cost does not scale with the number of qubits, and instead only with the number of logical operations. Each logical operation has an associated active volume, such that the cost of a quantum computation can be quantified as a sum of active volumes of all operations. For quantum computations with thousands of logical qubits, the active volume can be orders of magnitude lower than the circuit volume. Importantly, the architecture does not require all-to-all connectivity between N logical qubits. Instead, each logical qubit is connected to O(log N) other sites. As an example, we show that, using the same number of logical qubits, a 2048-bit factoring algorithm can be executed 44 times faster than on a general-purpose architecture without non-local connections. With photonic qubits, long-range connections are available and we show how photonic components can be used to construct a fusion-based active-volume quantum computer.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Thrifty shadow estimation: re-using quantum circuits and bounding tails</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06240</link>
    <author>Jonas Helsen, Michael Walter</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Randomized shadow estimation is a recent protocol that allows estimating exponentially many expectation values of a quantum state from ``classical shadows'', obtained by applying random quantum circuits and computational basis measurements. In this paper we study the statistical efficiency of this approach in light of near-term quantum computing. In particular, we propose and analyze a more practically-implementable variant of the protocol, thrifty shadow estimation, in which quantum circuits are reused many times instead of having to be freshly generated for each measurement (as in the original protocol). We show that the effect of this reuse strongly depends on the family of quantum circuits that is chosen. In particular, it is maximally effective when sampling Haar random unitaries, and maximally ineffective when sampling Clifford circuits (even though the Clifford group forms a three-design). To interpolate between these two extremes, we provide an efficiently simulable family of quantum circuits inspired by a recent construction of approximate t-designs. Finally we consider tail bounds for shadow estimation and discuss when median-of-means estimation can be replaced with standard mean estimation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Even shorter quantum circuit for phase estimation on early fault-tolerant quantum computers with applications to ground-state energy estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.11973</link>
    <author>Zhiyan Ding, Lin Lin</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop a phase estimation method with a distinct feature: its maximal runtime (which determines the circuit depth) is $\delta/\epsilon$, where $\epsilon$ is the target precision, and the preconstant $\delta$ can be arbitrarily close to $0$ as the initial state approaches the target eigenstate. The total cost of the algorithm satisfies the Heisenberg-limited scaling $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(\epsilon^{-1})$. This is different from all previous proposals, where $\delta \gtrsim \pi$ is required even if the initial state is an exact eigenstate. As a result, our algorithm may significantly reduce the circuit depth for performing phase estimation tasks on early fault-tolerant quantum computers. The key technique is a simple subroutine called quantum complex exponential least squares (QCELS). Our algorithm can be readily applied to reduce the circuit depth for estimating the ground-state energy of a quantum Hamiltonian, when the overlap between the initial state and the ground state is large. If this initial overlap is small, we can combine our method with the Fourier filtering method developed in [Lin, Tong, PRX Quantum 3, 010318, 2022], and the resulting algorithm provably reduces the circuit depth in the presence of a large relative overlap compared to $\epsilon$. The relative overlap condition is similar to a spectral gap assumption, but it is aware of the information in the initial state and is therefore applicable to certain Hamiltonians with small spectral gaps. We observe that the circuit depth can be reduced by around two orders of magnitude in numerical experiments under various settings.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Worst-Case to Average-Case Reductions for All Linear Problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.03348</link>
    <author>Vahid R. Asadi, Alexander Golovnev, Tom Gur, Igor Shinkar, Sathyawageeswar Subramanian</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of designing worst-case to average-case reductions for quantum algorithms. For all linear problems, we provide an explicit and efficient transformation of quantum algorithms that are only correct on a small (even sub-constant) fraction of their inputs into ones that are correct on all inputs. This stands in contrast to the classical setting, where such results are only known for a small number of specific problems or restricted computational models. En route, we obtain a tight $\Omega(n^2)$ lower bound on the average-case quantum query complexity of the Matrix-Vector Multiplication problem. Our techniques strengthen and generalise the recently introduced additive combinatorics framework for classical worst-case to average-case reductions (STOC 2022) to the quantum setting. We rely on quantum singular value transformations to construct quantum algorithms for linear verification in superposition and learning Bogolyubov subspaces from noisy quantum oracles. We use these tools to prove a quantum local correction lemma, which lies at the heart of our reductions, based on a noise-robust probabilistic generalisation of Bogolyubov's lemma from additive combinatorics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing sparse fermionic Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.16518</link>
    <author>Yaroslav Herasymenko, Maarten Stroeks, Jonas Helsen, Barbara Terhal</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of approximating the ground state energy of a fermionic Hamiltonian using a Gaussian state. In sharp contrast to the dense case (Hastings & O'Donnell, 2022), we prove that strictly $q$-local $\rm{\textit{sparse}}$ fermionic Hamiltonians have a constant Gaussian approximation ratio; the result holds for any connectivity and interaction strengths. Sparsity means that each fermion participates in a bounded number of interactions, and strictly $q$-local means that each term involves exactly $q$ fermionic (Majorana) operators. We extend our proof to give a constant Gaussian approximation ratio for sparse fermionic Hamiltonians with both quartic and quadratic terms. With additional work, we also prove a constant Gaussian approximation ratio for the so-called sparse SYK model with strictly $4$-local interactions (sparse SYK-4 model). In each setting we show that the Gaussian state can be efficiently determined. Finally, we prove that the $O(n^{-1/2})$ Gaussian approximation ratio for the normal (dense) SYK-$4$ model extends to SYK-$q$ for even $q>4$, with an approximation ratio of $O(n^{1/2 - q/4})$. Our results identify non-sparseness as the prime reason that the SYK-4 model can fail to have a constant approximation ratio.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New additivity properties of the relative entropy of entanglement and its generalizations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.12804</link>
    <author>Roberto Rubboli, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove that the relative entropy of entanglement is additive when at least one of the two states belongs to some specific class. We show that these classes include bipartite pure, maximally correlated, GHZ, Bell diagonal, isotropic, and generalized Dicke states. Previously, additivity was established only if both states belong to the same class. Moreover, we extend these results to entanglement monotones based on the $\alpha$-$z$ Rényi relative entropy. Notably, this family of monotones includes also the generalized robustness of entanglement and the geometric measure of entanglement. In addition, we prove that any monotone based on a quantum relative entropy is not additive for general states. Finally, we compute the value of the monotones based on the $\alpha$-$z$ Rényi relative entropy for bipartite pure, Bell diagonal, isotropic, generalized Werner, generalized Dicke, and maximally correlated Bell diagonal states. Our results rely on proving new necessary and sufficient conditions for the optimizer of the monotones based on the $\alpha$-$z$ Rényi relative entropy which allow us to reduce the original optimization problem to a simpler linear one. Even though we focus mostly on entanglement theory, we formulate some of our technical results in a general resource theory framework and we expect that they could be used to investigate other resource theories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum advantage and stability to errors in analogue quantum simulators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.04924</link>
    <author>Rahul Trivedi, Adrian Franco Rubio, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Several quantum hardware platforms, while being unable to perform fully fault-tolerant quantum computation, can still be operated as analogue quantum simulators for addressing many-body problems. However, due to the presence of errors, it is not clear to what extent those devices can provide us with an advantage with respect to classical computers. In this work we consider the use of noisy analogue quantum simulators for computing physically relevant properties of many-body systems both in equilibrium and undergoing dynamics. We first formulate a system-size independent notion of stability against extensive errors, which we prove for Gaussian fermion models, as well as for a restricted class of spin systems. Remarkably, for the Gaussian fermion models, our analysis shows the stability of critical (gapless) models at zero temperature which have long-range correlations. Furthermore, we analyze how this stability may lead to a quantum advantage, for the problem of computing the thermodynamic limits of many-body models, in the presence of a constant error rate and without any explicit error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Many bounded versions of undecidable problems are NP-hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.13532</link>
    <author>Andreas Klingler, Mirte van der Eyden, Sebastian Stengele, Tobias Reinhart, Gemma De las Cuevas</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Several physically inspired problems have been proven undecidable; examples are the spectral gap problem and the membership problem for quantum correlations. Most of these results rely on reductions from a handful of undecidable problems, such as the halting problem, the tiling problem, the Post correspondence problem or the matrix mortality problem. All these problems have a common property: they have an NP-hard bounded version. This work establishes a relation between undecidable unbounded problems and their bounded NP-hard versions. Specifically, we show that NP-hardness of a bounded version follows easily from the reduction of the unbounded problems. This leads to new and simpler proofs of the NP-hardness of bounded version of the Post correspondence problem, the matrix mortality problem, the positivity of matrix product operators, the reachability problem, the tiling problem, and the ground state energy problem. This work sheds light on the intractability of problems in theoretical physics and on the computational consequences of bounding a parameter.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Transversal Injection: A method for direct encoding of ancilla states for non-Clifford gates using stabiliser codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.10046</link>
    <author>Jason Gavriel, Daniel Herr, Alexis Shaw, Michael J. Bremner, Alexandru Paler, Simon J. Devitt</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fault-tolerant, error-corrected quantum computation is commonly acknowledged to be crucial to the realisation of large-scale quantum algorithms that could lead to extremely impactful scientific or commercial results. Achieving a universal set of quantum gate operations in a fault-tolerant error-corrected framework suffers from a `conservation of unpleasantness'. In general, no matter what error correction technique is employed, there is always one element of a universal gate set that carries a significant resource overhead - either in physical qubits, computational time, or both. Specifically, this is due to the application of non-Clifford gates. A common method for realising these gates for stabiliser codes such as the surface code is a combination of three protocols: state injection, distillation and gate teleportation. These protocols contribute to the resource overhead compared to logical operations such as a CNOT gate and contributes to the qubit resources for any error-corrected quantum algorithm. In this paper, we introduce a very simple protocol to potentially reduce this overhead for non-Clifford gates: Transversal Injection. Transversal injection modifies the initial physical states of all data qubits in a stabiliser code before standard encoding and results in the direct preparation of a large class of single qubit states, including resource states for non-Clifford logic gates. Preliminary results hint at high quality fidelities at larger distances and motivate further research on this technique.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hardware-efficient learning of quantum many-body states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06084</link>
    <author>Katherine Van Kirk, Jordan Cotler, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Mikhail D. Lukin</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Efficient characterization of highly entangled multi-particle systems is an outstanding challenge in quantum science. Recent developments have shown that a modest number of randomized measurements suffices to learn many properties of a quantum many-body system. However, implementing such measurements requires complete control over individual particles, which is unavailable in many experimental platforms. In this work, we present rigorous and efficient algorithms for learning quantum many-body states in systems with any degree of control over individual particles, including when every particle is subject to the same global field and no additional ancilla particles are available. We numerically demonstrate the effectiveness of our algorithms for estimating energy densities in a U(1) lattice gauge theory and classifying topological order using very limited measurement capabilities.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Single-shot error mitigation by coherent Pauli checks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.03937</link>
    <author>Ewout van den Berg, Sergey Bravyi, Jay M. Gambetta, Petar Jurcevic, Dmitri Maslov, Kristan Temme</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Generating samples from the output distribution of a quantum circuit is a ubiquitous task used as a building block of many quantum algorithms. Here we show how to accomplish this task on a noisy quantum processor lacking full-blown error correction for a special class of quantum circuits dominated by Clifford gates. Our approach is based on Coherent Pauli Checks (CPCs) that detect errors in a Clifford circuit by verifying commutation rules between random Pauli-type check operators and the considered circuit. Our main contributions are as follows. First, we derive a simple formula for the probability that a Clifford circuit protected by CPCs contains a logical error. In the limit of a large number of checks, the logical error probability is shown to approach the value ${\approx}7\epsilon n/5$, where $n$ is the number of qubits and $\epsilon$ is the depolarizing error rate. Our formula agrees nearly perfectly with the numerical simulation results. Second, we show that CPCs are well-suited for quantum processors with a limited qubit connectivity. For example, the difference between all-to-all and linear qubit connectivity is only a 3X increase in the number of CNOT gates required to implement CPCs. Third, we describe simplified one-sided CPCs which are well-suited for mitigating measurement errors in the single-shot settings. Finally, we report an experimental demonstration of CPCs with up to 10 logical qubits and more than 100 logical CNOT gates. Our experimental results show that CPCs provide a marked improvement in the logical error probability for the considered task of sampling the output distribution of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Cryptography in Algorithmica</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.00879</link>
    <author>William Kretschmer, Luowen Qian, Makrand Sinha, Avishay Tal</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We construct a classical oracle relative to which $\mathsf{P} = \mathsf{NP}$ yet single-copy secure pseudorandom quantum states exist. In the language of Impagliazzo's five worlds, this is a construction of pseudorandom states in "Algorithmica," and hence shows that in a black-box setting, quantum cryptography based on pseudorandom states is possible even if one-way functions do not exist. As a consequence, we demonstrate that there exists a property of a cryptographic hash function that simultaneously (1) suffices to construct pseudorandom states, (2) holds for a random oracle, and (3) is independent of $\mathsf{P}$ vs. $\mathsf{NP}$ in the black-box setting. We also introduce a conjecture that would generalize our results to multi-copy secure pseudorandom states. We build on the recent construction by Aaronson, Ingram, and Kretschmer (CCC 2022) of an oracle relative to which $\mathsf{P} = \mathsf{NP}$ but $\mathsf{BQP} \neq \mathsf{QCMA}$, based on hardness of the OR $\circ$ Forrelation problem. Our proof also introduces a new discretely-defined variant of the Forrelation distribution, for which we prove pseudorandomness against $\mathsf{AC^0}$ circuits. This variant may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variations on the Choi-Jamiolkowski isomorphism</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.16533</link>
    <author>Markus Frembs, Eric G. Cavalcanti</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We address various aspects of a widely used tool in quantum information theory: the Choi-Jamiolkowski isomorphism [A. Jamiolkowski, Rep. Math. Phys., 3, 275 (1972)]. We review different versions of the isomorphism, their properties and propose a unified description that combines them all. To this end, we identify the physical reason for the appearance of the (basis-dependent) operation of transposition in the isomorphism as used in Choi's theorem [M.-D. Choi, Lin. Alg. Appl., 10, 285 (1975)]. This requires a careful distinction between Jordan algebras and the different C*-algebras they arise from, which are distinguished by their order of composition. Physically, the latter encodes a choice of time orientation in the respective algebras, which relates to a number of recent results, including a characterisation of quantum from more general non-signalling bipartite correlations [M. Frembs and A. Döring, arXiv:2204.11471] and a classification of bipartite entanglement [M. Frembs, arXiv:2207.00024].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lower Bounding Ground-State Energies of Local Hamiltonians Through the Renormalization Group</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.03014</link>
    <author>Ilya Kull, Norbert Schuch, Ben Dive, Miguel Navascués</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a renormalization scheme, we show how to formulate a tractable convex relaxation of the set of feasible local density matrices of a many-body quantum system. The relaxation is obtained by introducing a hierarchy of constraints between the reduced states of ever-growing sets of lattice sites. The coarse-graining maps of the underlying renormalization procedure serve to eliminate a vast number of those constraints, such that the remaining ones can be enforced with reasonable computational means. This can be used to obtain rigorous lower bounds on the ground state energy of arbitrary local Hamiltonians, by performing a linear optimization over the resulting convex relaxation of reduced quantum states. The quality of the bounds crucially depends on the particular renormalization scheme, which must be tailored to the target Hamiltonian. We apply our method to 1D translation-invariant spin models, obtaining energy bounds comparable to those attained by optimizing over locally translation-invariant states of $n\gtrsim 100$ spins. Beyond this demonstration, the general method can be applied to a wide range of other problems, such as spin systems in higher spatial dimensions, electronic structure problems, and various other many-body optimization problems, such as entanglement and nonlocality detection.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>High-threshold quantum computing by fusing one-dimensional cluster states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06775</link>
    <author>Stefano Paesani, Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a measurement-based model for fault-tolerant quantum computation that can be realised with one-dimensional cluster states and fusion measurements only; basic resources that are readily available with scalable photonic hardware. Our simulations demonstrate high thresholds compared with other measurement-based models realized with basic entangled resources and two-qubit fusion measurements. Its high tolerance to noise indicates that our practical construction offers a promising route to scalable quantum computing with quantum emitters and linear-optical elements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Unified Quantum Algorithm Framework for Estimating Properties of Discrete Probability Distributions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.01571</link>
    <author>Tongyang Li, Xinzhao Wang, Shengyu Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Estimating statistical properties is fundamental in statistics and computer science. In this paper, we propose a unified quantum algorithm framework for estimating properties of discrete probability distributions, with estimating Rényi entropies as specific examples. In particular, given a quantum oracle that prepares an $n$-dimensional quantum state $\sum_{i=1}^{n}\sqrt{p_{i}}|i\rangle$, for $\alpha>1$ and $0<\alpha<1$, our algorithm framework estimates $\alpha$-Rényi entropy $H_{\alpha}(p)$ to within additive error $\epsilon$ with probability at least $2/3$ using $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(n^{1-\frac{1}{2\alpha}}/\epsilon + \sqrt{n}/\epsilon^{1+\frac{1}{2\alpha}})$ and $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(n^{\frac{1}{2\alpha}}/\epsilon^{1+\frac{1}{2\alpha}})$ queries, respectively. This improves the best known dependence in $\epsilon$ as well as the joint dependence between $n$ and $1/\epsilon$. Technically, our quantum algorithms combine quantum singular value transformation, quantum annealing, and variable-time amplitude estimation. We believe that our algorithm framework is of general interest and has wide applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-tolerant Post-Selection for Low Overhead Magic State Preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.00813</link>
    <author>Héctor Bombín, Mihir Pant, Sam Roberts, Karthik I. Seetharam</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a framework for fault-tolerant post-selection (FTPS) of fault-tolerant codes and channels -- such as those based on surface-codes -- using soft-information metrics based on visible syndrome and erasure information. We introduce several metrics for ranking configurations of syndromes and erasures. In particular, we introduce the \emphlogical gap (and variants thereof) as a powerful soft-information metric for predicting logical error rates of fault-tolerant channels based on topological error-correcting codes. The logical gap is roughly the unsigned weight difference between inequivalent logical corrections and is adaptable to any tailored noise model or decoder. We deploy this framework to prepare high-quality surface code magic states with low overhead under a model of independent and identically distributed (\emphi.i.d.) Pauli and erasure errors. Post-selection strategies based on the logical gap can suppress the encoding error rate of a magic state preparation channel to the level of the physical error rate with low overhead. For example, when operating at $60\%$ the bulk threshold of the corresponding surface code, an overall reduction of the encoding error rate by a factor of $15$ is achievable with a relative overhead factor of ${< 2}$ (approximately $23$ times less than that of simple syndrome-counting rules). We analyze a schematic buffer architecture for implementing post-selection rules on magic state factories in the context of magic state distillation. The FTPS framework can be utilized for mitigating errors in more general fault-tolerant logical channels.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complementarity and the unitarity of the black hole $S$-matrix</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.00194</link>
    <author>Isaac H. Kim, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, Akers et al. proposed a non-isometric holographic map from the interior of a black hole to its exterior. Within this model, we study properties of the black hole $S$-matrix, which are in principle accessible to observers who stay outside the black hole. Specifically, we investigate a scenario in which an infalling agent interacts with radiation both outside and inside the black hole. Because the holographic map involves postselection, the unitarity of the $S$-matrix is not guaranteed in this scenario, but we find that unitarity is satisfied to very high precision if suitable conditions are met. If the internal black hole dynamics is described by a pseudorandom unitary transformation, and if the operations performed by the infaller have computational complexity scaling polynomially with the black hole entropy, then the $S$-matrix is unitary up to corrections that are superpolynomially small in the black hole entropy. Furthermore, while in principle quantum computation assisted by postselection can be very powerful, we find under similar assumptions that the $S$-matrix of an evaporating black hole has polynomial computational complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Functional analytic insights into irreversibility of quantum resources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.15678</link>
    <author>Bartosz Regula, Ludovico Lami</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose an approach to the study of quantum resource manipulation based on the basic observation that quantum channels which preserve certain sets of states are contractive with respect to the base norms induced by those sets. We forgo the usual physical assumptions on quantum dynamics: instead of enforcing complete positivity, trace preservation, or resource-theoretic considerations, we study transformation protocols as norm-contractive maps. This allows us to apply to this problem a technical toolset from functional analysis, unifying previous approaches and introducing new families of bounds for the distillable resources and the resource cost, both one-shot and asymptotic. Since our expressions lend themselves naturally to single-letter forms, they can often be calculated in practice; by doing so, we demonstrate with examples that they can yield the best known bounds on quantities such as the entanglement cost. As applications, we not only give an alternative derivation of the recent result of [arXiv:2111.02438] which showed that entanglement theory is asymptotically irreversible, but also provide the quantities introduced in that work with explicit operational meaning in the context of entanglement distillation through a novel generalised form of hypothesis testing relative entropy. Besides entanglement, we reveal a new irreversible quantum resource: through improved bounds for state transformations in the resource theory of magic-state quantum computation, we show that there exist qutrit magic states that cannot be reversibly interconverted under stabiliser protocols.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring Arbitrary Physical Properties in Analog Quantum Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.02517</link>
    <author>Minh C. Tran, Daniel K. Mark, Wen Wei Ho, Soonwon Choi</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A central challenge in analog quantum simulation is to characterize desirable physical properties of quantum states produced in experiments. However, in conventional approaches, the extraction of arbitrary information requires performing measurements in many different bases, which necessitates a high level of control that present-day quantum devices may not have. Here, we propose and analyze a scalable protocol that leverages the ergodic nature of generic quantum dynamics, enabling the efficient extraction of many physical properties. The protocol does not require sophisticated controls and can be generically implemented in analog quantum simulation platforms today. Our protocol involves introducing ancillary degrees of freedom in a predetermined state to a system of interest, quenching the joint system under Hamiltonian dynamics native to the particular experimental platform, and then measuring globally in a single, fixed basis. We show that arbitrary information of the original quantum state is contained within such measurement data, and can be extracted using a classical data-processing procedure. We numerically demonstrate our approach with a number of examples, including the measurements of entanglement entropy, many-body Chern number, and various superconducting orders in systems of neutral atom arrays, bosonic and fermionic particles on optical lattices, respectively, only assuming existing technological capabilities. Our protocol excitingly promises to overcome limited controllability and, thus, enhance the versatility and utility of near-term quantum technologies.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>