
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A chain rule for the quantum relative entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05826</link>
    <author>Kun Fang, Omar Fawzi, Renato Renner, David Sutter</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 13 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The chain rule for the classical relative entropy ensures that the relative entropy between probability distributions on multipartite systems can be decomposed into a sum of relative entropies of suitably chosen conditional distributions on the individual systems. Here, we prove a similar chain rule inequality for the quantum relative entropy in terms of channel relative entropies. The new chain rule allows us to solve an open problem in the context of asymptotic quantum channel discrimination: surprisingly, adaptive protocols cannot improve the error rate for asymmetric channel discrimination compared to non-adaptive strategies. In addition, we give examples of quantum channels showing that the channel relative entropy is not additive under the tensor product.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Topological wormholes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.07419</link>
    <author>Anirudh Krishna, David Poulin</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 18 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Locality plays a fundamental role in quantum computation but also severely restricts our ability to store and process quantum information. We argue that this restriction may be unwarranted and re-examine quantum error correcting codes. We proceed to introduce new defects on the surface code called wormholes. These novel defects entangle two spatially separated sectors of the lattice. When anyonic excitations enter the mouth of a wormhole, they emerge through the other mouth. Wormholes thus serve to connect two spatially separated sectors of a flat, $2$D lattice. We show that these defects are capable of encoding logical qubits and can be used to perform all gates in the Clifford group.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cayley path and quantum computational supremacy: A proof of average-case $\#P-$hardness of Random Circuit Sampling with quantified robustness</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.06210</link>
    <author>Ramis Movassagh</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 16 2019</pubDate>
    <description>A one-parameter unitary-valued interpolation between any two unitary matrices (e.g., quantum gates) is constructed based on the Cayley transformation, which extends our previous work [15]. We prove that this path provides scrambled unitaries with probability distributions arbitrarily close to the Haar measure. We then prove the simplest known average-case #$P$-hardness of random circuit sampling (RCS), which is the task of sampling from the output distribution of a quantum circuit whose local gates are random Haar unitaries, and is the lead candidate for demonstrating quantum supremacy in the NISQ era. We show that previous work based on the truncations of the power series representation of the exponential function does not provide practical robustness. Explicit bound on noise resilience is proved, which for an $n-$qubit device with the near term experimental parameters is $2^{-\Theta(n^{3.51})}$ robustness with respect to additive error. Improving this to $\mathcal{O}(2^{-n}/\text{poly}(n))$ would prove the quantum supremacy conjecture; and proving our construction optimal would disprove it</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-tolerant gates on hypergraph product codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.07424</link>
    <author>Anirudh Krishna, David Poulin</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 18 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Hypergraph product codes are a class of quantum low density parity check (LDPC) codes discovered by Tillich and Zémor. These codes have a constant encoding rate and were recently shown to have a constant fault-tolerant error threshold. With these features, they asymptotically offer a smaller overhead compared to topological codes. However, existing techniques to perform logical gates in hypergraph product codes require many separate code blocks, so only becomes effective with a very large number of logical qubits. Here, we demonstrate how to perform Clifford gates on this class of codes using code deformation. To this end, we generalize punctures and wormhole defects, the latter introduced in a companion paper. Together with state injection, we can perform a universal set of gates within a single block of the class of hypergraph product codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Near-term quantum algorithms for linear systems of equations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.07344</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Kishor Bharti, Patrick Rebentrost</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 17 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Solving linear systems of equations is an essential component in science and technology, including in many machine learning algorithms. Existing quantum algorithms have demonstrated large speedup in solving linear systems, but the required quantum resources are not available on near-term quantum devices. In this work, we study potential near-term quantum algorithms for linear systems of equations. We investigate the use of variational algorithms for solving $Ax = b$ and analyze the optimization landscape for variational algorithms. We found that a wide range of variational algorithms designed to avoid barren plateaus, such as properly-initialized imaginary time evolution and adiabatic-inspired optimization, still suffer from a fundamentally different plateau problem. To circumvent this issue, we design a potentially near-term adaptive alternating algorithm based on a core idea: the classical combination of variational quantum states. We have conducted numerical experiments solving linear systems as large as $2^{300} \times 2^{300}$ by considering special systems that can be simulated efficiently on a classical computer. These experiments demonstrate the algorithm's ability to scale to system sizes within reach in near-term quantum devices of about $100$-$300$ qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational Quantum Linear Solver: A Hybrid Algorithm for Linear Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05820</link>
    <author>Carlos Bravo-Prieto, Ryan LaRose, M. Cerezo, Yigit Subasi, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 13 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Solving linear systems of equations is central to many engineering and scientific fields. Several quantum algorithms have been proposed for linear systems, where the goal is to prepare $|x\rangle$ such that $A|x\rangle \propto |b\rangle$. While these algorithms are promising, the time horizon for their implementation is long due to the required quantum circuit depth. In this work, we propose a variational hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for solving linear systems, with the aim of reducing the circuit depth and doing much of the computation classically. We propose a cost function based on the overlap between $|b\rangle$ and $A|x\rangle$, and we derive an operational meaning for this cost in terms of the solution precision $\epsilon$. We also introduce a quantum circuit to estimate this cost, while showing that this cost cannot be efficiently estimated classically. Using Rigetti's quantum computer, we successfully implement our algorithm up to a problem size of $32 \times 32$. Furthermore, we numerically find that the complexity of our algorithm scales efficiently in both $1/\epsilon$ and $\kappa$, with $\kappa$ the condition number of $A$. Our algorithm provides a heuristic for quantum linear systems that could make this application more near term.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-tolerant Quantum Error Correction on Near-term Quantum Processors using Flag and Bridge Qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.07628</link>
    <author>Lingling Lao, Carmen G. Almudever</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 18 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Fault-tolerant (FT) computation by using quantum error correction (QEC) is essential for realizing large-scale quantum algorithms. Devices are expected to have enough qubits to demonstrate aspects of fault tolerance in the near future. However, these near-term quantum processors will only contain a small amount of noisy qubits and allow limited qubit connectivity. Fault-tolerant schemes that not only have low qubit overhead but also comply with geometrical interaction constraints are therefore necessary. In this work, we combine flag fault tolerance with quantum circuit mapping, to enable an efficient flag-bridge approach to implement FT QEC on near-term devices. We further show an example of performing the Steane code error correction on two current superconducting processors and numerically analyze their performance with circuit level noise. The simulation results show that the QEC circuits that measure more stabilisers in parallel have lower logical error rates. We also observe that the Steane code can outperform the distance-3 surface code using flag-bridge error correction. In addition, we foresee potential applications of the flag-bridge approach such as FT computation using lattice surgery and code deformation techniques.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Oracle complexity classes and local measurements on physical Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05981</link>
    <author>Sevag Gharibian, Stephen Piddock, Justin Yirka</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 16 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The canonical problem for the class Quantum Merlin-Arthur (QMA) is that of estimating ground state energies of local Hamiltonians. Perhaps surprisingly, [Ambainis, CCC 2014] showed that the related, but arguably more natural, problem of simulating local measurements on ground states of local Hamiltonians (APX-SIM) is likely harder than QMA. Indeed, [Ambainis, CCC 2014] showed that APX-SIM is P^QMA[log]-complete, for P^QMA[log] the class of languages decidable by a P machine making a logarithmic number of adaptive queries to a QMA oracle. In this work, we show that APX-SIM is P^QMA[log]-complete even when restricted to more physical Hamiltonians, obtaining as intermediate steps a variety of related complexity-theoretic results. We first give a sequence of results which together yield P^QMA[log]-hardness for APX-SIM on well-motivated Hamiltonians: (1) We show that for NP, StoqMA, and QMA oracles, a logarithmic number of adaptive queries is equivalent to polynomially many parallel queries. These equalities simplify the proofs of our subsequent results. (2) Next, we show that the hardness of APX-SIM is preserved under Hamiltonian simulations (a la [Cubitt, Montanaro, Piddock, 2017]). As a byproduct, we obtain a full complexity classification of APX-SIM, showing it is complete for P, P^||NP, P^||StoqMA, or P^||QMA depending on the Hamiltonians employed. (3) Leveraging the above, we show that APX-SIM is P^QMA[log]-complete for any family of Hamiltonians which can efficiently simulate spatially sparse Hamiltonians, including physically motivated models such as the 2D Heisenberg model. Our second focus considers 1D systems: We show that APX-SIM remains P^QMA[log]-complete even for local Hamiltonians on a 1D line of 8-dimensional qudits. This uses a number of ideas from above, along with replacing the "query Hamiltonian" of [Ambainis, CCC 2014] with a new "sifter" construction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Geometric Rényi Divergence and its Applications in Quantum Channel Capacities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05758</link>
    <author>Kun Fang, Hamza Fawzi</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 13 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We present a systematic study of the geometric Rényi divergence (GRD), also known as the maximal Rényi divergence, from the point of view of quantum information theory. We show that this divergence, together with its extension to channels, has many appealing structural properties. For example we prove a chain rule inequality that immediately implies the "amortization collapse" for the geometric Rényi divergence, addressing an open question by Berta et al. [arXiv:1808.01498, Equation (55)] in the area of quantum channel discrimination. As applications, we explore various channel capacity problems and construct new channel information measures based on the geometric Rényi divergence, sharpening the previously best-known bounds based on the max-relative entropy while still keeping the new bounds single-letter efficiently computable. A plethora of examples are investigated and the improvements are evident for almost all cases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On sets of commuting and anticommuting Paulis</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.08123</link>
    <author>Rahul Sarkar, Ewout van den Berg</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 19 2019</pubDate>
    <description>In this work we study the structure and cardinality of maximal sets of commuting and anticommuting Paulis in the setting of the abelian Pauli group. We provide necessary and sufficient conditions for anticommuting sets to be maximal, and present an efficient algorithm for generating anticommuting sets of maximum size. As a theoretical tool, we introduce commutativity maps, and study properties of maps associated with elements in the cosets with respect to anticommuting minimal generating sets. We also derive expressions for the number of distinct sets of commuting and anticommuting abelian Paulis of a given size.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On maximum-likelihood decoding with circuit-level errors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.06732</link>
    <author>Leonid P. Pryadko</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 17 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Error probability distribution associated with a given Clifford measurement circuit is described exactly in terms of the circuit subsystem code previously introduced by Bacon, Flammia, Harrow, and Shi. In particular, this gives a prescription for maximum-likelihood decoding with a given measurement circuit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-inspired algorithms for multivariate analysis: from interpolation to partial differential equations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.06619</link>
    <author>Juan José García-Ripoll</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 17 2019</pubDate>
    <description>In this work we study the encoding of smooth, differentiable multivariate functions distributions in quantum registers, using quantum computers or tensor-network representations. We show that a large family of distributions can be encoded as low-entanglement states of the quantum register. These states can be efficiently created in a quantum computer, but they are also efficiently stored, manipulated and probed using Matrix-Product States techniques. Inspired by this idea, we present eight quantum-inspired numerical analysis algorithms, that include Fourier sampling, interpolation, differentiation and integration of partial derivative equations. These algorithms combine classical ideas---finite-differences, spectral methods---with the efficient encoding of quantum registers, and well known algorithms, such as the Quantum Fourier Transform. When these heuristic methods work, they provide an exponential speed-up over other classical algorithms, such as Monte Carlo integration, finite-difference and fast Fourier transforms (FFT). But even when they don't, some of these algorithms can be translated back to a quantum computer to implement a similar task.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum simulations of excited states with active-space downfolded Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.06404</link>
    <author>Nicholas P. Bauman, Guang Hao Low, Karol Kowalski</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 17 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Many-body techniques based on the double unitary coupled cluster ansatz (DUCC) can be used to downfold electronic Hamiltonians into low-dimensional active spaces. It can be shown that the resulting dimensionality reduced Hamiltonians are amenable for quantum computing. Recent studies performed for several benchmark systems using quantum phase estimation (QPE) algorithms demonstrated that these formulations can recover a significant portion of ground-state dynamical correlation effects that stem from the electron excitations outside of the active space. These results have also been confirmed in studies of ground-state potential energy surfaces using quantum simulators. In this letter, we study the effectiveness of the DUCC formalism in describing excited states. We also emphasize the role of the QPE formalism and its stochastic nature in discovering/identifying excited states or excited-state processes in situations when the knowledge about the true configurational structure of a sought after excited state is limited or postulated (due to the specific physics driving excited-state processes of interest). In this context, we can view the QPE algorithm as an engine for verifying various hypotheses for excited-state processes and providing statistically meaningful results that correspond to the electronic state(s) with the largest overlap with a postulated configurational structure. We illustrate these ideas on examples of strongly correlated molecular systems, characterized by small energy gaps and high density of quasi-degenerate states around the Fermi level.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Local Matrix Product Operators: Canonical Form, Compression, & Control Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.06341</link>
    <author>Daniel E. Parker, Xiangyu Cao, Michael P. Zaletel</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 16 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We present a new method for compressing matrix product operators (MPOs) which represent sums of local terms, such as Hamiltonians. Just as with area law states, such local operators may be fully specified with a small amount of information per site. Standard matrix product state (MPS) tools are ill-suited to this case, due to extensive Schmidt values that coexist with intensive ones, and Jordan blocks in the transfer matrix. We ameliorate these issues by introducing an "almost Schmidt decomposition" that respects locality. Our method is "$\varepsilon$-close" to the accuracy of MPS-based methods for finite MPOs, and extends seamlessly to the thermodynamic limit, where MPS techniques are inapplicable. In the framework of control theory, our method generalizes Kung's algorithm for model order reduction. Several examples are provided, including an all-MPO version of the operator recursion method (Lanczos algorithm) directly in the thermodynamic limit. All results are accompanied by practical algorithms, well-suited for the large MPOs that arise in DMRG for long-range or quasi-2D models.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>
