<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A polynomial-time classical algorithm for noisy random circuit sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03999</link>
    <author>Dorit Aharonov, Xun Gao, Zeph Landau, Yunchao Liu, Umesh Vazirani</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a polynomial time classical algorithm for sampling from the output distribution of a noisy random quantum circuit in the regime of anti-concentration to within inverse polynomial total variation distance. This gives strong evidence that, in the presence of a constant rate of noise per gate, random circuit sampling (RCS) cannot be the basis of a scalable experimental violation of the extended Church-Turing thesis. Our algorithm is not practical in its current form, and does not address finite-size RCS based quantum supremacy experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exponentially tighter bounds on limitations of quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11505</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Daniel Stilck França, Sumeet Khatri, Johannes Jakob Meyer, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation has been proposed as a means to combat unavoidable errors in near-term quantum computing by classically post-processing outcomes of multiple quantum circuits. It does so in a fashion that requires no or few additional quantum resources, in contrast to fault-tolerant schemes that come along with heavy overheads. Error mitigation leads to noise reduction in small systems. In this work, however, we identify strong limitations to the degree to which quantum noise can be effectively `undone' for larger system sizes. We start out by presenting a formal framework that rigorously encapsulates large classes of meaningful and practically applied schemes for quantum error mitigation, including virtual distillation, Clifford data regression, zero-noise extrapolation and probabilistic error cancellation. With the framework in place, our technical contribution is to construct families of random circuits that are highly sensitive to noise, in the sense that even at log log(n) depth, a whisker beyond constant, quantum noise is seen to super-exponentially rapidly scramble their output into the maximally-mixed state. Our results exponentially tighten known arguments for error mitigation, but they go beyond that: Our arguments can be applied to kernel estimation or to compute the depth at which barren plateaus emerge, implying that the scrambling kicks in at exponentially smaller depths than previously thought. Our results also say that a noisy device must be sampled exponentially many times to estimate expectation values. There are classical algorithms that exhibit the same scaling in complexity. While improvements in quantum hardware will push noise levels down, if error mitigation is used, ultimately this can only lead to an exponential time quantum algorithm with a better exponent, putting up a strong obstruction to the hope for exponential quantum speedups in this setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning to predict arbitrary quantum processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14894</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Sitan Chen, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an efficient machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting any unknown quantum process $\mathcal{E}$ over $n$ qubits. For a wide range of distributions $\mathcal{D}$ on arbitrary $n$-qubit states, we show that this ML algorithm can learn to predict any local property of the output from the unknown process $\mathcal{E}$, with a small average error over input states drawn from $\mathcal{D}$. The ML algorithm is computationally efficient even when the unknown process is a quantum circuit with exponentially many gates. Our algorithm combines efficient procedures for learning properties of an unknown state and for learning a low-degree approximation to an unknown observable. The analysis hinges on proving new norm inequalities, including a quantum analogue of the classical Bohnenblust-Hille inequality, which we derive by giving an improved algorithm for optimizing local Hamiltonians. Overall, our results highlight the potential for ML models to predict the output of complex quantum dynamics much faster than the time needed to run the process itself.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Challenges in Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15844</link>
    <author>Daniel Gottesman</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I will give an overview of what I see as some of the most important future directions in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation. In particular, I will give a brief summary of the major problems that need to be solved in fault tolerance based on low-density parity check codes and in hardware-specific fault tolerance. I will then conclude with a discussion of a possible new paradigm for designing fault-tolerant protocols based on a space-time picture of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Pseudoentanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.00747</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Bill Fefferman, Soumik Ghosh, Umesh Vazirani, Zixin Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum pseudorandom states are efficiently constructable states which nevertheless masquerade as Haar-random states to poly-time observers. First defined by Ji, Liu and Song, such states have found a number of applications ranging from cryptography to the AdS/CFT correspondence. A fundamental question is exactly how much entanglement is required to create such states. Haar-random states, as well as $t$-designs for $t\geq 2$, exhibit near-maximal entanglement. Here we provide the first construction of pseudorandom states with only polylogarithmic entanglement entropy across an equipartition of the qubits, which is the minimum possible. Our construction can be based on any one-way function secure against quantum attack. We additionally show that the entanglement in our construction is fully "tunable", in the sense that one can have pseudorandom states with entanglement $\Theta(f(n))$ for any desired function $\omega(\log n) \leq f(n) \leq O(n)$. More fundamentally, our work calls into question to what extent entanglement is a "feelable" quantity of quantum systems. Inspired by recent work of Gheorghiu and Hoban, we define a new notion which we call "pseudoentanglement", which are ensembles of efficiently constructable quantum states which hide their entanglement entropy. We show such states exist in the strongest form possible while simultaneously being pseudorandom states. We also describe diverse applications of our result from entanglement distillation to property testing to quantum gravity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A classical oracle separation between QMA and QCMA</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15380</link>
    <author>Anand Natarajan, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It is a long-standing open question in quantum complexity theory whether the definition of $\textit{non-deterministic}$ quantum computation requires quantum witnesses $(\textsf{QMA})$ or if classical witnesses suffice $(\textsf{QCMA})$. We make progress on this question by constructing a randomized classical oracle separating the respective computational complexity classes. Previous separations [Aaronson-Kuperberg (CCC'07), Fefferman-Kimmel (MFCS'18)] required a quantum unitary oracle. The separating problem is deciding whether a distribution supported on regular un-directed graphs either consists of multiple connected components (yes instances) or consists of one expanding connected component (no instances) where the graph is given in an adjacency-list format by the oracle. Therefore, the oracle is a distribution over $n$-bit boolean functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bosonic coding: introduction and use cases</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05714</link>
    <author>Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bosonic or continuous-variable coding is a field concerned with robust quantum information processing and communication with electromagnetic signals or mechanical modes. I review bosonic quantum memories, characterizing them as either bosonic stabilizer or bosonic Fock-state codes. I then enumerate various applications of bosonic encodings, four of which circumvent no-go theorems due to the intrinsic infinite-dimensionality of bosonic systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Real-time quantum error correction beyond break-even</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09116</link>
    <author>V. V. Sivak, A. Eickbusch, B. Royer, S. Singh, I. Tsioutsios, S. Ganjam, A. Miano, B. L. Brock, A. Z. Ding, L. Frunzio, S. M. Girvin, R. J. Schoelkopf, M. H. Devoret</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ambition of harnessing the quantum for computation is at odds with the fundamental phenomenon of decoherence. The purpose of quantum error correction (QEC) is to counteract the natural tendency of a complex system to decohere. This cooperative process, which requires participation of multiple quantum and classical components, creates a special type of dissipation that removes the entropy caused by the errors faster than the rate at which these errors corrupt the stored quantum information. Previous experimental attempts to engineer such a process faced an excessive generation of errors that overwhelmed the error-correcting capability of the process itself. Whether it is practically possible to utilize QEC for extending quantum coherence thus remains an open question. We answer it by demonstrating a fully stabilized and error-corrected logical qubit whose quantum coherence is significantly longer than that of all the imperfect quantum components involved in the QEC process, beating the best of them with a coherence gain of $G = 2.27 \pm 0.07$. We achieve this performance by combining innovations in several domains including the fabrication of superconducting quantum circuits and model-free reinforcement learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailoring three-dimensional topological codes for biased noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02116</link>
    <author>Eric Huang, Arthur Pesah, Christopher T. Chubb, Michael Vasmer, Arpit Dua</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tailored topological stabilizer codes in two dimensions have been shown to exhibit high storage threshold error rates and improved subthreshold performance under biased Pauli noise. Three-dimensional (3D) topological codes can allow for several advantages including a transversal implementation of non-Clifford logical gates, single-shot decoding strategies, parallelized decoding in the case of fracton codes as well as construction of fractal lattice codes. Motivated by this, we tailor 3D topological codes for enhanced storage performance under biased Pauli noise. We present Clifford deformations of various 3D topological codes, such that they exhibit a threshold error rate of $50\%$ under infinitely biased Pauli noise. Our examples include the 3D surface code on the cubic lattice, the 3D surface code on a checkerboard lattice that lends itself to a subsystem code with a single-shot decoder, the 3D color code, as well as fracton models such as the X-cube model, the Sierpinski model and the Haah code. We use the belief propagation with ordered statistics decoder (BP-OSD) to study threshold error rates at finite bias. We also present a rotated layout for the 3D surface code, which uses roughly half the number of physical qubits for the same code distance under appropriate boundary conditions. Imposing coprime periodic dimensions on this rotated layout leads to logical operators of weight $O(n)$ at infinite bias and a corresponding $\exp[-O(n)]$ subthreshold scaling of the logical failure rate, where $n$ is the number of physical qubits in the code. Even though this scaling is unstable due to the existence of logical representations with $O(1)$ low-rate Pauli errors, the number of such representations scales only polynomially for the Clifford-deformed code, leading to an enhanced effective distance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum state preparation without coherent arithmetic</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14892</link>
    <author>Sam McArdle, András Gilyén, Mario Berta</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a versatile method for preparing a quantum state whose amplitudes are given by some known function. Unlike existing approaches, our method does not require handcrafted reversible arithmetic circuits, or quantum memory loads, to encode the function values. Instead, we use a template quantum eigenvalue transformation circuit to convert a low cost block encoding of the sine function into the desired function. Our method uses only 4 ancilla qubits (3 if the approximating polynomial has definite parity), providing order-of-magnitude qubit count reductions compared to state-of-the-art approaches, while using a similar number of Toffoli gates if the function can be well represented by a polynomial or Fourier approximation. Like black-box methods, the complexity of our approach depends on the 'L2-norm filling-fraction' of the function. We demonstrate the efficiency of our method for preparing states commonly used in quantum algorithms, such as Gaussian and Kaiser window states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Continuous-variable quantum state designs: theory and applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05127</link>
    <author>Joseph T. Iosue, Kunal Sharma, Michael J. Gullans, Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We generalize the notion of quantum state designs to infinite-dimensional spaces. We first prove that, under the definition of continuous-variable (CV) state $t$-designs from Comm. Math. Phys. 326, 755 (2014), no state designs exist for $t\geq2$. Similarly, we prove that no CV unitary $t$-designs exist for $t\geq 2$. We propose an alternative definition for CV state designs, which we call rigged $t$-designs, and provide explicit constructions for $t=2$. As an application of rigged designs, we develop a design-based shadow-tomography protocol for CV states. Using energy-constrained versions of rigged designs, we define an average fidelity for CV quantum channels and relate this fidelity to the CV entanglement fidelity. As an additional result of independent interest, we establish a connection between torus $2$-designs and complete sets of mutually unbiased bases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the complexity of implementing Trotter steps</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09133</link>
    <author>Guang Hao Low, Yuan Su, Yu Tong, Minh C. Tran</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum dynamics can be simulated on a quantum computer by exponentiating elementary terms from the Hamiltonian in a sequential manner. However, such an implementation of Trotter steps has gate complexity depending on the total Hamiltonian term number, comparing unfavorably to algorithms using more advanced techniques. We develop methods to perform faster Trotter steps with complexity sublinear in the number of terms. We achieve this for a class of Hamiltonians whose interaction strength decays with distance according to power law. Our methods include one based on a recursive block encoding and one based on an average-cost simulation, overcoming the normalization-factor barrier of these advanced quantum simulation techniques. We also realize faster Trotter steps when certain blocks of Hamiltonian coefficients have low rank. Combining with a tighter error analysis, we show that it suffices to use $\left(\eta^{1/3}n^{1/3}+\frac{n^{2/3}}{\eta^{2/3}}\right)n^{1+o(1)}$ gates to simulate uniform electron gas with $n$ spin orbitals and $\eta$ electrons in second quantization in real space, asymptotically improving over the best previous work. We obtain an analogous result when the external potential of nuclei is introduced under the Born-Oppenheimer approximation. We prove a circuit lower bound when the Hamiltonian coefficients take a continuum range of values, showing that generic $n$-qubit $2$-local Hamiltonians with commuting terms require at least $\Omega(n^2)$ gates to evolve with accuracy $\epsilon=\Omega(1/poly(n))$ for time $t=\Omega(\epsilon)$. Our proof is based on a gate-efficient reduction from the approximate synthesis of diagonal unitaries within the Hamming weight-$2$ subspace, which may be of independent interest. Our result thus suggests the use of Hamiltonian structural properties as both necessary and sufficient to implement Trotter steps with lower gate complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Assessing requirements to scale to practical quantum advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07629</link>
    <author>Michael E. Beverland, Prakash Murali, Matthias Troyer, Krysta M. Svore, Torsten Hoeffler, Vadym Kliuchnikov, Guang Hao Low, Mathias Soeken, Aarthi Sundaram, Alexander Vaschillo</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While quantum computers promise to solve some scientifically and commercially valuable problems thought intractable for classical machines, delivering on this promise will require a large-scale quantum machine. Understanding the impact of architecture design choices for a scaled quantum stack for specific applications, prior to full realization of the quantum system, is an important open challenge. To this end, we develop a framework for quantum resource estimation, abstracting the layers of the stack, to estimate resources required across these layers for large-scale quantum applications. Using a tool that implements this framework, we assess three scaled quantum applications and find that hundreds of thousands to millions of physical qubits are needed to achieve practical quantum advantage. We identify three qubit parameters, namely size, speed, and controllability, that are critical at scale to rendering these applications practical. A goal of our work is to accelerate progress towards practical quantum advantage by enabling the broader community to explore design choices across the stack, from algorithms to qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical simulation of short-time quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11490</link>
    <author>Dominik S. Wild, Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Locality is a key simplifying feature of many physical systems. Cluster expansion techniques provide one particular way of exploiting it. They have historically appeared in statistical physics to prove the uniqueness of Gibbs states and the decay of correlations at high temperature, among many other results. Here, we apply these techniques to quantum many-body systems evolving under local Hamiltonians. We consider the evolution of both local observables and non-local quantities such as the Loschmidt echo. We show that for a product initial state, the cluster expansion enables efficient classical computation of the dynamics up to a fixed evolution time, independent of the system size. The computational cost scales polynomially with the system size and the inverse of the approximation error. In the case of local observables, we can extend the evolution time to any constant value using analytic continuation. In more than one dimension, the resulting algorithm has a better dependence on the approximation error than algorithms based on the Lieb-Robinson bound. Our algorithms rely on the convergence of the cluster expansion, which also has important physical consequences. In particular, we establish a novel quantum speed limit, a bound on dynamical phase transitions, and a concentration bound for product states evolved for short times.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Homomorphic Logical Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03625</link>
    <author>Shilin Huang, Tomas Jochym-O'Connor, Theodore J. Yoder</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shor and Steane ancilla are two well-known methods for fault-tolerant logical measurements, which are successful on small codes and their concatenations. On large quantum low-density-parity-check (LDPC) codes, however, Shor and Steane measurements have impractical time and space overhead respectively. In this work, we widen the choice of ancilla codes by unifying Shor and Steane measurements into a single framework, called homomorphic measurements. For any Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) code with the appropriate ancilla code, one can avoid repetitive measurements or complicated ancilla state preparation procedures such as distillation, which overcomes the difficulties of both Shor and Steane methods. As an example, we utilize the theory of covering spaces to construct homomorphic measurement protocols for arbitrary $X$- or $Z$-type logical Pauli operators on surface codes in general, including the toric code and hyperbolic surface codes. Conventional surface code decoders, such as minimum-weight perfect matching, can be directly applied to our constructions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Greatly improved higher-order product formulae for quantum simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15817</link>
    <author>Mauro E.S. Morales, Pedro C.S. Costa, Daniel K. Burgarth, Yuval R. Sanders, Dominic W. Berry</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for simulation of Hamiltonian evolution are often based on product formulae like Trotter. The fractal method of Suzuki gives a systematic way to find arbitrarily high-order product formulae, but results in a large number of exponentials. On the other hand, an alternative way, with a minimum number of exponentials, for 6th and 8th order product formulae is given by Yoshida. In this work, we not only extended Yoshida's method to 10th order, but we also found hundreds of new 8th order product formulae. Moreover, we found an 8th order product formula that is over $1000$ times more accurate than the best product formula of Yoshida.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning quantum processes without input control</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05005</link>
    <author>Marco Fanizza, Yihui Quek, Matteo Rosati</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a general statistical learning theory for processes that take as input a classical random variable and output a quantum state. This is a practically motivated setting where the learner wants to find an approximate representation of an unknown quantum process, without having control on the classical inputs that govern the process itself, e.g., in learning astronomical processes, studying disordered systems and biological processes not controlled by the observer. We provide an algorithm for learning with high probability in this setting with a finite amount of samples, even if the concept class is infinite. To do this, we review and adapt existing algorithms for shadow tomography and hypothesis selection, and combine their guarantees with the uniform convergence on the data of the loss functions of interest. As a by-product we obtain sufficient conditions for performing shadow tomography of classical-quantum states with a number of copies which depend only on the dimension of the quantum register. We give concrete examples of processes that can be learned in this manner, based on quantum circuits or physically motivated scenarios like systems subject to Hamiltonians with random perturbations or data-dependent phase-shifts.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generating $k$ EPR-pairs from an n-party resource state</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06497</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Yash Sharma, Mario Szegedy, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Motivated by quantum network applications over classical channels, we initiate the study of $n$-party resource states from which LOCC protocols can create EPR-pairs between any $k$ disjoint pairs of parties. We give constructions of such states where $k$ is not too far from the optimal $n/2$ while the individual parties need to hold only a constant number of qubits. In the special case when each party holds only one qubit, we describe a family of $n$-qubit states with $k$ proportional to $\log n$ based on Reed-Muller codes, as well as small numerically found examples for $k=2$ and $k=3$. We also prove some lower bounds, for example showing that if $k=n/2$ then the parties must have at least $\Omega(\log\log n)$ qubits each.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Invertible subalgebras</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02086</link>
    <author>Jeongwan Haah</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce invertible subalgebras of local operator algebras on lattices. An invertible subalgebra is defined to be one such that every local operator can be locally expressed by elements of the inveritible subalgebra and those of the commutant. On a two-dimensional lattice, an invertible subalgebra hosts a chiral anyon theory by a commuting Hamiltonian, which is believed not to be possible on a full local operator algebra. We prove that the stable equivalence classes of $D$-dimensional invertible subalgebras form an abelian group under tensor product, isomorphic to the group of all $D+1$ dimensional QCA modulo blending equivalence and shifts. In an appendix, we consider a metric on the group of all QCA on infinite lattices and prove that the metric completion contains the time evolution by local Hamiltonians, which is only approximately locality-preserving. Our metric topology is strictly finer than the strong topology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Black-Hole Radiation Decoding is Quantum Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05491</link>
    <author>Zvika Brakerski</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose to study equivalence relations between phenomena in high-energy physics and the existence of standard cryptographic primitives, and show the first example where such an equivalence holds. A small number of prior works showed that high-energy phenomena can be explained by cryptographic hardness. Examples include using the existence of one-way functions to explain the hardness of decoding black-hole Hawking radiation (Harlow and Hayden 2013, Aaronson 2016), and using pseudorandom quantum states to explain the hardness of computing AdS/CFT dictionary (Bouland, Fefferman and Vazirani, 2020). In this work we show, for the former example of black-hole radiation decoding, that it also implies the existence of secure quantum cryptography. In fact, we show an existential equivalence between the hardness of black-hole radiation decoding and a variety of cryptographic primitives, including bit-commitment schemes and oblivious transfer protocols (using quantum communication). This can be viewed (with proper disclaimers, as we discuss) as providing a physical justification for the existence of secure cryptography. We conjecture that such connections may be found in other high-energy physics phenomena.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Autonomous quantum error correction and fault-tolerant quantum computation with squeezed cat qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.13406</link>
    <author>Qian Xu, Guo Zheng, Yu-Xin Wang, Peter Zoller, Aashish A. Clerk, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose an autonomous quantum error correction scheme using squeezed cat (SC) code against the dominant error source, excitation loss, in continuous-variable systems. Through reservoir engineering, we show that a structured dissipation can stabilize a two-component SC while autonomously correcting the errors. The implementation of such dissipation only requires low-order nonlinear couplings among three bosonic modes or between a bosonic mode and a qutrit. While our proposed scheme is device independent, it is readily implementable with current experimental platforms such as superconducting circuits and trapped-ion systems. Compared to the stabilized cat, the stabilized SC has a much lower dominant error rate and a significantly enhanced noise bias. Furthermore, the bias-preserving operations for the SC have much lower error rates. In combination, the stabilized SC leads to substantially better logical performance when concatenating with an outer discrete-variable code. The surface-SC scheme achieves more than one order of magnitude increase in the threshold ratio between the loss rate $\kappa_1$ and the engineered dissipation rate $\kappa_2$. Under a practical noise ratio $\kappa_1/\kappa_2 = 10^{-3}$, the repetition-SC scheme can reach a $10^{-15}$ logical error rate even with a small mean excitation number of 4, which already suffices for practically useful quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Pseudorandom (Function-Like) Quantum State Generators: New Definitions and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01444</link>
    <author>Prabhanjan Ananth, Aditya Gulati, Luowen Qian, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Pseudorandom quantum states (PRS) are efficiently constructible states that are computationally indistinguishable from being Haar-random, and have recently found cryptographic applications. We explore new definitions, new properties and applications of pseudorandom states, and present the following contributions: 1. New Definitions: We study variants of pseudorandom function-like state (PRFS) generators, introduced by Ananth, Qian, and Yuen (CRYPTO'22), where the pseudorandomness property holds even when the generator can be queried adaptively or in superposition. We show feasibility of these variants assuming the existence of post-quantum one-way functions. 2. Classical Communication: We show that PRS generators with logarithmic output length imply commitment and encryption schemes with classical communication. Previous constructions of such schemes from PRS generators required quantum communication. 3. Simplified Proof: We give a simpler proof of the Brakerski--Shmueli (TCC'19) result that polynomially-many copies of uniform superposition states with random binary phases are indistinguishable from Haar-random states. 4. Necessity of Computational Assumptions: We also show that a secure PRS with output length logarithmic, or larger, in the key length necessarily requires computational assumptions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Deterministic constant-depth preparation of the AKLT state on a quantum processor using fusion measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.17548</link>
    <author>Kevin C. Smith, Eleanor Crane, Nathan Wiebe, S. M. Girvin</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ground state of the spin-1 Affleck, Kennedy, Lieb and Tasaki (AKLT) model is a paradigmatic example of both a matrix product state and a symmetry-protected topological phase, and additionally holds promise as a resource state for measurement-based quantum computation. Having a nonzero correlation length, the AKLT state cannot be exactly prepared by a constant-depth unitary circuit composed of local gates. In this work, we demonstrate that this no-go limit can be evaded by augmenting a constant-depth circuit with fusion measurements, such that the total preparation time is independent of system size and entirely deterministic. We elucidate our preparation scheme using the language of tensor networks, and furthermore show that the $\mathbb{Z}_2\times\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry of the AKLT state directly affords this speed-up over previously known preparation methods. To demonstrate the practical advantage of measurement-assisted preparation on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices, we carry out our protocol on an IBM Quantum processor. We measure both the string order and entanglement spectrum of prepared AKLT chains and, employing these as metrics, find improved results over the known (purely unitary) sequential preparation approach. We conclude with a demonstration of quantum teleportation using the AKLT state prepared by our measurement-assisted scheme. This work thus serves to provide an efficient strategy to prepare a specific resource in the form of the AKLT state and, more broadly, experimentally demonstrates the possibility for realizable improvement in state preparation afforded by measurement-based circuit depth reduction strategies on NISQ-era devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A (simple) classical algorithm for estimating Betti numbers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09618</link>
    <author>Simon Apers, Sayantan Sen, Dániel Szabó</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a simple algorithm for estimating the $k$-th normalized Betti number of a simplicial complex over $n$ elements using the path integral Monte Carlo method. For a general simplicial complex, the running time of our algorithm is $n^{O(\frac{1}{\gamma}\log\frac{1}{\varepsilon})}$ with $\gamma$ measuring the spectral gap of the combinatorial Laplacian and $\varepsilon \in (0,1)$ the additive precision. In the case of a clique complex, the running time of our algorithm improves to $(n/\lambda_{\max})^{O(\frac{1}{\gamma}\log\frac{1}{\varepsilon})}$ with $\lambda_{\max} \geq k$ the maximum eigenvalue of the combinatorial Laplacian. Our algorithm provides a classical benchmark for a line of quantum algorithms for estimating Betti numbers, and it matches their running time on clique complexes when the spectral gap is constant and $k \in \Omega(n)$ or $\lambda_{\max} \in \Omega(n)$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Invertible bimodule categories and generalized Schur orthogonality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01947</link>
    <author>Jacob C. Bridgeman, Laurens Lootens, Frank Verstraete</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Schur orthogonality relations are a cornerstone in the representation theory of groups. We utilize a generalization to weak Hopf algebras to provide a new, readily verifiable condition on the skeletal data for deciding whether a given bimodule category is invertible and therefore defines a Morita equivalence. As a first application, we provide an algorithm for the construction of the full skeletal data of the invertible bimodule category associated to a given module category, which is obtained in a unitary gauge when the underlying categories are unitary. As a second application, we show that our condition for invertibility is equivalent to the notion of MPO-injectivity, thereby closing an open question concerning tensor network representations of string-net models exhibiting topological order. We discuss applications to generalized symmetries, including a generalized Wigner-Eckart theorem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The $2T$-qutrit, a two-mode bosonic qutrit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16188</link>
    <author>Aurélie Denys, Anthony Leverrier</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Building on the observation that bosonic cat codes live in the span of coherent states indexed by a finite subgroup of the complex numbers, we consider a two-mode bosonic code where the coherent states now form a finite subgroup of the quaternions. We focus on the binary tetrahedral group, denoted $2T$, which admits 24 elements forming the vertices of the 24-cell, a regular four-dimensional polytope, and define a bosonic qutrit that appears to be quite robust in the regime of low loss. We initiate a study of the properties of this qutrit and identify stabilisers as well as logical operators for this bosonic code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hunting for quantum-classical crossover in condensed matter problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14109</link>
    <author>Nobuyuki Yoshioka, Tsuyoshi Okubo, Yasunari Suzuki, Yuki Koizumi, Wataru Mizukami</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The intensive pursuit for quantum algorithms with speedup in terms of computational complexity has further led to this modernized crucial question: \it When and how will quantum computers outperform classical computers?. The next milestone in the context of this quantum transcendence is undoubtedly the realization of quantum acceleration in practical problems. Here we provide a clear evidence and arguments that the primary target is likely to be condensed matter physics. Our primary contributions are summarized as follows: 1) Proposal of systematic error/runtime analysis on state-of-the-art classical algorithm based on tensor networks; 2) Dedicated and high-resolution analysis on quantum resource performed at the level of executable logical instructions; 3) Clarification of quantum-classical crosspoint for ground-state simulation to be within runtime of hours using only a few hundreds of thousand physical qubits for 2d Heisenberg and 2d Fermi-Hubbard models. To our knowledge, we argue that condensed matter problems offer the earliest platform for demonstration of practical quantum advantage that is order-of-magnitude more feasible than ever known candidates, in terms of both qubit counts and total runtime.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Overcoming leakage in scalable quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.04728</link>
    <author>Kevin C. Miao, Matt McEwen, Juan Atalaya, Dvir Kafri, Leonid P. Pryadko, Andreas Bengtsson, Alex Opremcak, Kevin J. Satzinger, Zijun Chen, Paul V. Klimov, Chris Quintana, Rajeev Acharya, Kyle Anderson, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Joseph C. Bardin, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, et al (97)</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Leakage of quantum information out of computational states into higher energy states represents a major challenge in the pursuit of quantum error correction (QEC). In a QEC circuit, leakage builds over time and spreads through multi-qubit interactions. This leads to correlated errors that degrade the exponential suppression of logical error with scale, challenging the feasibility of QEC as a path towards fault-tolerant quantum computation. Here, we demonstrate the execution of a distance-3 surface code and distance-21 bit-flip code on a Sycamore quantum processor where leakage is removed from all qubits in each cycle. This shortens the lifetime of leakage and curtails its ability to spread and induce correlated errors. We report a ten-fold reduction in steady-state leakage population on the data qubits encoding the logical state and an average leakage population of less than $1 \times 10^{-3}$ throughout the entire device. The leakage removal process itself efficiently returns leakage population back to the computational basis, and adding it to a code circuit prevents leakage from inducing correlated error across cycles, restoring a fundamental assumption of QEC. With this demonstration that leakage can be contained, we resolve a key challenge for practical QEC at scale.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A super-polynomial quantum-classical separation for density modelling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14936</link>
    <author>Niklas Pirnay, Ryan Sweke, Jens Eisert, Jean-Pierre Seifert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Density modelling is the task of learning an unknown probability density function from samples, and is one of the central problems of unsupervised machine learning. In this work, we show that there exists a density modelling problem for which fault-tolerant quantum computers can offer a super-polynomial advantage over classical learning algorithms, given standard cryptographic assumptions. Along the way, we provide a variety of additional results and insights, of potential interest for proving future distribution learning separations between quantum and classical learning algorithms. Specifically, we (a) provide an overview of the relationships between hardness results in supervised learning and distribution learning, and (b) show that any weak pseudo-random function can be used to construct a classically hard density modelling problem. The latter result opens up the possibility of proving quantum-classical separations for density modelling based on weaker assumptions than those necessary for pseudo-random functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Pauli topological subsystem codes from Abelian anyon theories</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03798</link>
    <author>Tyler D. Ellison, Yu-An Chen, Arpit Dua, Wilbur Shirley, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Dominic J. Williamson</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We construct Pauli topological subsystem codes characterized by arbitrary two-dimensional Abelian anyon theories--this includes anyon theories with degenerate braiding relations and those without a gapped boundary to the vacuum. Our work both extends the classification of two-dimensional Pauli topological subsystem codes to systems of composite-dimensional qudits and establishes that the classification is at least as rich as that of Abelian anyon theories. We exemplify the construction with topological subsystem codes defined on four-dimensional qudits based on the $\mathbb{Z}_4^{(1)}$ anyon theory with degenerate braiding relations and the chiral semion theory--both of which cannot be captured by topological stabilizer codes. The construction proceeds by "gauging out" certain anyon types of a topological stabilizer code. This amounts to defining a gauge group generated by the stabilizer group of the topological stabilizer code and a set of anyonic string operators for the anyon types that are gauged out. The resulting topological subsystem code is characterized by an anyon theory containing a proper subset of the anyons of the topological stabilizer code. We thereby show that every Abelian anyon theory is a subtheory of a stack of toric codes and a certain family of twisted quantum doubles that generalize the double semion anyon theory. We further prove a number of general statements about the logical operators of translation invariant topological subsystem codes and define their associated anyon theories in terms of higher-form symmetries.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>