
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Faster quantum and classical SDP approximations for quadratic binary optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.04613</link>
    <author>Fernando G.S L. Brandão, Richard Kueng, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 11 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum speedup for solving the canonical semidefinite programming relaxation for binary quadratic optimization. The class of relaxations for combinatorial optimization has so far eluded quantum speedups. Our methods combine ideas from quantum Gibbs sampling and matrix exponent updates. A de-quantization of the algorithm also leads to a faster classical solver. For generic instances, our quantum solver gives a nearly quadratic speedup over state-of-the-art algorithms. We also provide an efficient randomized rounding procedure that converts approximately optimal SDP solutions into constant factor approximations of the original quadratic optimization problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A chain rule for the quantum relative entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05826</link>
    <author>Kun Fang, Omar Fawzi, Renato Renner, David Sutter</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 13 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The chain rule for the classical relative entropy ensures that the relative entropy between probability distributions on multipartite systems can be decomposed into a sum of relative entropies of suitably chosen conditional distributions on the individual systems. Here, we prove a similar chain rule inequality for the quantum relative entropy in terms of channel relative entropies. The new chain rule allows us to solve an open problem in the context of asymptotic quantum channel discrimination: surprisingly, adaptive protocols cannot improve the error rate for asymmetric channel discrimination compared to non-adaptive strategies. In addition, we give examples of quantum channels showing that the channel relative entropy is not additive under the tensor product.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise-robust exploration of quantum matter on near-term quantum devices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.04786</link>
    <author>Johannes Borregaard, Matthias Christandl, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a resource-efficient approach to studying many-body quantum states on noisy, intermediate-scale quantum devices. We employ a sequential generation model that allows to bound the range of correlations in the resulting many-body quantum states. From this, we characterize situations where the estimation of local observables does not require the preparation of the entire state. Instead smaller patches of the state can be generated from which the observables can be estimated. This reduces the required circuit size and number of qubits for the computation of physical properties of quantum matter. Moreover, we show that the effect of noise decreases along the computation. Our results apply to a broad class of widely studied tensor network states and can be directly applied to near-term implementations of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational algorithms for linear algebra</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03898</link>
    <author>Xiaosi Xu, Jinzhao Sun, Suguru Endo, Ying Li, Simon C. Benjamin, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 10 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms have been developed for efficiently solving linear algebra tasks. However they generally require deep circuits and therefore universal fault-tolerant quantum computers. In this work, we propose variational algorithms for linear algebra tasks that are compatible with Noisy Intermediate Scaled Quantum devices. We show that the solutions of linear systems of equations and matrix-vector multiplications can be translated as the ground states of the constructed Hamiltonians. Based on recently proposed variational quantum algorithms, we introduce Hamiltonian morphing together with an adaptive ansatz for efficiently finding the ground state. As the ground state always has zero energy, it also enables us to verify the solution. Our algorithms have wide applications in machine learning and optimisation problems, and the algorithm for matrix multiplications can be also used for variational Hamiltonian simulation. Finally, we conduct numerical simulations of the algorithm for solving linear systems of equations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational Quantum Linear Solver: A Hybrid Algorithm for Linear Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05820</link>
    <author>Carlos Bravo-Prieto, Ryan LaRose, M. Cerezo, Yigit Subasi, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 13 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Solving linear systems of equations is central to many engineering and scientific fields. Several quantum algorithms have been proposed for linear systems, where the goal is to prepare $|x\rangle$ such that $A|x\rangle \propto |b\rangle$. While these algorithms are promising, the time horizon for their implementation is long due to the required quantum circuit depth. In this work, we propose a variational hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for solving linear systems, with the aim of reducing the circuit depth and doing much of the computation classically. We propose a cost function based on the overlap between $|b\rangle$ and $A|x\rangle$, and we derive an operational meaning for this cost in terms of the solution precision $\epsilon$. We also introduce a quantum circuit to estimate this cost, while showing that this cost cannot be efficiently estimated classically. Using Rigetti's quantum computer, we successfully implement our algorithm up to a problem size of $32 \times 32$. Furthermore, we numerically find that the complexity of our algorithm scales efficiently in both $1/\epsilon$ and $\kappa$, with $\kappa$ the condition number of $A$. Our algorithm provides a heuristic for quantum linear systems that could make this application more near term.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Correlation measures and distillable entanglement in AdS/CFT</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.04727</link>
    <author>Joshua Levin, Oliver DeWolfe, Graeme Smith</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Recent developments have exposed close connections between quantum information and holography. In this paper, we explore the geometrical interpretations of the recently introduced $Q$-correlation and $R$-correlation, $E_Q$ and $E_R$. We find that $E_Q$ admits a natural geometric interpretation via the surface-state correspondence: it is a minimal mutual information between a surface region $A$ and a cross-section of $A$'s entanglement wedge with $B$. We note a strict trade-off between this minimal mutual information and the symmetric side-channel assisted distillable entanglement from the environment $E$ to $A$, $I^{ss}(E\rangle A)$. We also show that the $R$-correlation, $E_R$, coincides holographically with the entanglement wedge cross-section. This further elucidates the intricate relationship between entanglement, correlations, and geometry in holographic field theories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Quantum Search Decoder for Natural Language Processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05023</link>
    <author>Johannes Bausch, Sathyawageeswar Subramanian, Stephen Piddock</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Probabilistic language models, e.g. those based on an LSTM, often face the problem of finding a high probability prediction from a sequence of random variables over a set of words. This is commonly addressed using a form of greedy decoding such as beam search, where a limited number of highest-likelihood paths (the beam width) of the decoder are kept, and at the end the maximum-likelihood path is chosen. The resulting algorithm has linear runtime in the beam width. However, the input is not necessarily distributed such that a high-likelihood input symbol at any given time step also leads to the global optimum. Limiting the beam width can thus result in a failure to recognise long-range dependencies. In practice, only an exponentially large beam width can guarantee that the global optimum is found: for an input of length $n$ and average parser branching ratio $R$, the baseline classical algorithm needs to query the input on average $R^n$ times. In this work, we construct a quantum algorithm to find the globally optimal parse with high constant success probability. Given the input to the decoder is distributed like a power-law with exponent $k>0$, our algorithm yields a runtime $R^{n f(R,k)}$, where $f\le 1/2$, and $f\rightarrow 0$ exponentially quickly for growing $k$. This implies that our algorithm always yields a super-Grover type speedup, i.e. it is more than quadratically faster than its classical counterpart. We further modify our procedure to recover a quantum beam search variant, which enables an even stronger empirical speedup, while sacrificing accuracy. Finally, we apply this quantum beam search decoder to Mozilla's implementation of Baidu's DeepSpeech neural net, which we show to exhibit such a power law word rank frequency, underpinning the applicability of our model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Universality of the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03123</link>
    <author>Mauro E. S. Morales, Jacob Biamonte, Zoltán Zimborás</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 10 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) is considered to be one of the most promising approaches towards using near-term quantum computers for practical application. In its original form, the algorithm applies two different Hamiltonians, called the mixer and the cost Hamiltonian, in alternation with the goal being to approach the ground state of the cost Hamiltonian. Recently, it has been suggested that one might use such a set-up as a parametric quantum circuit with possibly some other goal than reaching ground states. From this perspective, a recent work [S. Lloyd, arXiv:1812.11075] argued that for one-dimensional local cost Hamiltonians, composed of nearest neighbor ZZ terms, this set-up is quantum computationally universal, i.e., all unitaries can be reached up to arbitrary precision. In the present paper, we give the complete proof of this statement and the precise conditions under which such a one-dimensional QAOA might be considered universal. We further generalize this type of universality for certain cost Hamiltonians with ZZ and ZZZ terms arranged according to the adjacency structure of certain graphs and hypergraphs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Geometric Rényi Divergence and its Applications in Quantum Channel Capacities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05758</link>
    <author>Kun Fang, Hamza Fawzi</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 13 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We present a systematic study of the geometric Rényi divergence (GRD), also known as the maximal Rényi divergence, from the point of view of quantum information theory. We show that this divergence, together with its extension to channels, has many appealing structural properties. For example we prove a chain rule inequality that immediately implies the "amortization collapse" for the geometric Rényi divergence, addressing an open question by Berta et al. [arXiv:1808.01498, Equation (55)] in the area of quantum channel discrimination. As applications, we explore various channel capacity problems and construct new channel information measures based on the geometric Rényi divergence, sharpening the previously best-known bounds based on the max-relative entropy while still keeping the new bounds single-letter efficiently computable. A plethora of examples are investigated and the improvements are evident for almost all cases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying LOSR nonclassicality across arbitrary resource types</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.04065</link>
    <author>David Schmid, Denis Rosset, Francesco Buscemi</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 11 2019</pubDate>
    <description>In space-like separated experiments and other scenarios where multiple parties share a classical common cause but no cause-effect relations, quantum theory allows a variety of nonsignaling resources which are useful for distributed quantum information processing. These include quantum states, nonlocal boxes, steering assemblages, teleportages, channel steering assemblages, and so on. Such resources are often studied using nonlocal games, semiquantum games, entanglement-witnesses, teleportation experiments, and similar tasks. We introduce a unifying framework which subsumes the full range of nonsignaling resources, as well as the games and experiments which probe them, into a common resource theory: that of local operations and shared randomness (LOSR). Crucially, we allow these LOSR operations to locally change the type of a resource, so that players can convert resources of any type into resources of any other type, and in particular into strategies for the specific type of game they are playing. We then prove several theorems relating resources and games of different types. These theorems generalize a number of seminal results from the literature, and can be applied to lessen the assumptions and technological requirements needed to characterize the nonclassicality of certain types of resources. As just one example, we prove that semiquantum games are able to perfectly characterize the LOSR nonclassicality of every resource of any type (not just quantum states, as was previously shown). As a consequence, we show that any resource can be characterized in a measurement-device-independent manner.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the natural gradient for variational quantum eigensolver</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05074</link>
    <author>Naoki Yamamoto</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The variational quantum eigensolver is a hybrid algorithm composed of quantum state driving and classical parameter optimization, for finding the ground state of a given Hamiltonian. The natural gradient method is an optimization method taking into account the geometric structure of the parameter space. Very recently, Stokes et al. developed the general method for employing the natural gradient for the variational quantum eigensolver. This paper gives some simple case-studies of this optimization method, to see in detail how the natural gradient optimizer makes use of the geometric property to change and improve the ordinary gradient method.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing Clifford gate generation for measurement-only topological quantum computation with Majorana zero modes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03002</link>
    <author>Alan Tran, Alex Bocharov, Bela Bauer, Parsa Bonderson</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 09 2019</pubDate>
    <description>One of the main challenges for quantum computation is that while the number of gates required to perform a non-trivial quantum computation may be very large, decoherence and errors in realistic quantum architectures limits the number of physical gate operations that can be performed coherently. Therefore, an optimal mapping of the quantum algorithm into the physically available set of operations is of crucial importance. We examine this problem for a measurement-only topological quantum computer based on Majorana zero modes, where gates are performed through sequences of measurements. Such a scheme has been proposed as a practical, scalable approach to process quantum information in an array of topological qubits built using Majorana zero modes. Building on previous work that has shown that multi-qubit Clifford gates can be enacted in a topologically protected fashion in such qubit networks, we discuss methods to obtain the optimal measurement sequence for a given Clifford gate under the constraints imposed by the physical architecture, such as layout and the relative difficulty of implementing different types of measurements. Our methods also provide tools for comparative analysis of different architectures and strategies, given experimental characterizations of particular aspects of the systems under consideration.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Robustness-optimized quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.05156</link>
    <author>David Layden, Louisa Ruixue Huang, Paola Cappellaro</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction codes are usually designed to correct errors regardless of their physical origins. In large-scale devices, this is an essential feature. In smaller-scale devices, however, the main error sources are often understood, and this knowledge could be exploited for more efficient error correction. Optimizing the quantum error correction protocol is therefore a promising strategy in smaller devices. Typically, this involves tailoring the protocol to a given decoherence channel by solving an appropriate optimization problem. Here we introduce a new optimization-based approach, which maximizes the robustness to faults in the recovery. Our approach is inspired by recent experiments, where such faults have been a significant source of logical errors. We illustrate this approach with a three-qubit model, and show how near-term experiments could benefit from more robust quantum error correction protocols.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generalized topological state-sum constructions and their universality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03031</link>
    <author>Andreas Bauer</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 09 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We formalize and generalize the concept of a topological state-sum construction using the language of tensor networks. We give examples for constructions that are possibly more general than all state-sum constructions in the literature that we are aware of. In particular we propose a state-sum construction that is universal in the sense that it can emulate every other state-sum construction. Physically, state-sum models in $n$ dimensions correspond to fixed point models for topological phases of matter in $n$ space-time dimensions. We conjecture that our universal state-sum construction contains fixed point models for topological phases that are not captured by known constructions. In particular we demonstrate that, unlike common state-sum constructions, the construction is compatible with the absence of gapped boundaries and commuting-projector Hamiltonians in $2+1$-dimensional chiral topological phases.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>
