<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Sparse random Hamiltonians are quantumly easy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03394</link>
    <author>Chi-Fang Chen, Alexander M. Dalzell, Mario Berta, Fernando G.S.L. Brandão, Joel A. Tropp</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A candidate application for quantum computers is to simulate the low-temperature properties of quantum systems. For this task, there is a well-studied quantum algorithm that performs quantum phase estimation on an initial trial state that has a nonnegligible overlap with a low-energy state. However, it is notoriously hard to give theoretical guarantees that such a trial state can be prepared efficiently. Moreover, the heuristic proposals that are currently available, such as with adiabatic state preparation, appear insufficient in practical cases. This paper shows that, for most random sparse Hamiltonians, the maximally mixed state is a sufficiently good trial state, and phase estimation efficiently prepares states with energy arbitrarily close to the ground energy. Furthermore, any low-energy state must have nonnegligible quantum circuit complexity, suggesting that low-energy states are classically nontrivial and phase estimation is the optimal method for preparing such states (up to polynomial factors). These statements hold for two models of random Hamiltonians: (i) a sum of random signed Pauli strings and (ii) a random signed $d$-sparse Hamiltonian. The main technical argument is based on some new results in nonasymptotic random matrix theory. In particular, a refined concentration bound for the spectral density is required to obtain complexity guarantees for these random Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient learning of ground & thermal states within phases of matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.12946</link>
    <author>Emilio Onorati, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França, James D. Watson</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We consider two related tasks: (a) estimating a parameterisation of a given Gibbs state and expectation values of Lipschitz observables on this state; and (b) learning the expectation values of local observables within a thermal or quantum phase of matter. In both cases, we wish to minimise the number of samples we use to learn these properties to a given precision. For the first task, we develop new techniques to learn parameterisations of classes of systems, including quantum Gibbs states of non-commuting Hamiltonians with exponential decay of correlations and the approximate Markov property. We show it is possible to infer the expectation values of all extensive properties of the state from a number of copies that not only scales polylogarithmically with the system size, but polynomially in the observable's locality -- an exponential improvement. This set of properties includes expected values of quasi-local observables and entropies. For the second task, we develop efficient algorithms for learning observables in a phase of matter of a quantum system. By exploiting the locality of the Hamiltonian, we show that $M$ local observables can be learned with probability $1-\delta$ to precision $\epsilon$ with using only $N=O\big(\log\big(\frac{M}{\delta}\big)e^{polylog(\epsilon^{-1})}\big)$ samples -- an exponential improvement on the precision over previous bounds. Our results apply to both families of ground states of Hamiltonians displaying local topological quantum order, and thermal phases of matter with exponential decay of correlations. In addition, our sample complexity applies to the worse case setting whereas previous results only applied on average. Furthermore, we develop tools of independent interest, such as robust shadow tomography algorithms, Gibbs approximations to ground states, and generalisations of transportation cost inequalities for Gibbs states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved machine learning algorithm for predicting ground state properties</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.13169</link>
    <author>Laura Lewis, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Viet T. Tran, Sebastian Lehner, Richard Kueng, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Finding the ground state of a quantum many-body system is a fundamental problem in quantum physics. In this work, we give a classical machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting ground state properties with an inductive bias encoding geometric locality. The proposed ML model can efficiently predict ground state properties of an $n$-qubit gapped local Hamiltonian after learning from only $\mathcal{O}(\log(n))$ data about other Hamiltonians in the same quantum phase of matter. This improves substantially upon previous results that require $\mathcal{O}(n^c)$ data for a large constant $c$. Furthermore, the training and prediction time of the proposed ML model scale as $\mathcal{O}(n \log n)$ in the number of qubits $n$. Numerical experiments on physical systems with up to 45 qubits confirm the favorable scaling in predicting ground state properties using a small training dataset.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A note on quantum expanders</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.07772</link>
    <author>Cécilia Lancien, Pierre Youssef</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We prove that a wide class of random quantum channels with few Kraus operators, sampled as random matrices with some moment assumptions, exhibit a large spectral gap, and are therefore optimal quantum expanders. In particular, our result provides a recipe to construct random quantum expanders from their classical (random or deterministic) counterparts. This considerably enlarges the list of known constructions of optimal quantum expanders, which was previously limited to few examples. Our proofs rely on recent progress in the study of the operator norm of random matrices with dependence and non-homogeneity, which we expect to have further applications in several areas of quantum information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A lower bound on the overhead of quantum error correction in low dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.04317</link>
    <author>Nouédyn Baspin, Omar Fawzi, Ala Shayeghi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We show that a quantum architecture with an error correction procedure limited to geometrically local operations incurs an overhead that grows with the system size, even if arbitrary error-free classical computation is allowed. In particular, we prove that in order to operate a quantum error correcting code in 2D at a logical error rate of $\delta$, a space overhead of $\Omega(\sqrt{\log(1/\delta)})$ is needed for any constant depolarizing noise $p > 0$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum complexity of the Kronecker coefficients</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11454</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Anirban Chowdhury, David Gosset, Vojtech Havlicek, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Whether or not the Kronecker coefficients of the symmetric group count some set of combinatorial objects is a longstanding open question. In this work we show that a given Kronecker coefficient is proportional to the rank of a projector that can be measured efficiently using a quantum computer. In other words a Kronecker coefficient counts the dimension of the vector space spanned by the accepting witnesses of a QMA verifier, where QMA is the quantum analogue of NP. This implies that approximating the Kronecker coefficients to within a given relative error is not harder than a certain natural class of quantum approximate counting problems that captures the complexity of estimating thermal properties of quantum many-body systems. A second consequence is that deciding positivity of Kronecker coefficients is contained in QMA, complementing a recent NP-hardness result of Ikenmeyer, Mulmuley and Walter. We obtain similar results for the related problem of approximating row sums of the character table of the symmetric group. Finally, we discuss an efficient quantum algorithm that approximates normalized Kronecker coefficients to inverse-polynomial additive error.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Qubit, a Coin, and an Advice String Walk Into a Relational Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10332</link>
    <author>Scott Aaronson, Harry Buhrman, William Kretschmer</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Relational problems (those with many possible valid outputs) are different from decision problems, but it is easy to forget just how different. This paper initiates the study of FBQP/qpoly, the class of relational problems solvable in quantum polynomial-time with the help of polynomial-sized quantum advice, along with its analogues for deterministic and randomized computation (FP, FBPP) and advice (/poly, /rpoly). Our first result is that FBQP/qpoly != FBQP/poly, unconditionally, with no oracle -- a striking contrast with what we know about the analogous decision classes. The proof repurposes the separation between quantum and classical one-way communication complexities due to Bar-Yossef, Jayram, and Kerenidis. We discuss how this separation raises the prospect of near-term experiments to demonstrate "quantum information supremacy," a form of quantum supremacy that would not depend on unproved complexity assumptions. Our second result is that FBPP is not contained in FP/poly -- that is, Adleman's Theorem fails for relational problems -- unless PSPACE is contained in NP/poly. Our proof uses IP=PSPACE and time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity. On the other hand, we show that proving FBPP not in FP/poly will be hard, as it implies a superpolynomial circuit lower bound for PromiseBPEXP. We prove the following further results: * Unconditionally, FP != FBPP and FP/poly != FBPP/poly (even when these classes are carefully defined). * FBPP/poly = FBPP/rpoly (and likewise for FBQP). For sampling problems, by contrast, SampBPP/poly != SampBPP/rpoly (and likewise for SampBQP).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-Tolerant Connection of Error-Corrected Qubits with Noisy Links</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01296</link>
    <author>Joshua Ramette, Josiah Sinclair, Nikolas P. Breuckmann, Vladan Vuletić</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>One of the most promising routes towards scalable quantum computing is a modular approach. We show that distinct surface code patches can be connected in a fault-tolerant manner even in the presence of substantial noise along their connecting interface. We quantify analytically and numerically the combined effect of errors across the interface and bulk. We show that the system can tolerate 14 times higher noise at the interface compared to the bulk, with only a small effect on the code's threshold and sub-threshold behavior, reaching threshold with $\sim 1 \%$ bulk errors and $\sim 10 \%$ interface errors. This implies that fault-tolerant scaling of error-corrected modular devices is within reach using existing technology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Qubit-Efficient Randomized Quantum Algorithms for Linear Algebra</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01873</link>
    <author>Samson Wang, Sam McArdle, Mario Berta</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a class of randomized quantum algorithms for the task of sampling from matrix functions, without the use of quantum block encodings or any other coherent oracle access to the matrix elements. As such, our use of qubits is purely algorithmic, and no additional qubits are required for quantum data structures. For $N\times N$ Hermitian matrices, the space cost is $\log(N)+1$ qubits and depending on the structure of the matrices, the gate complexity can be comparable to state-of-the-art methods that use quantum data structures of up to size $O(N^2)$, when considering equivalent end-to-end problems. Within our framework, we present a quantum linear system solver that allows one to sample properties of the solution vector, as well as an algorithm for sampling properties of ground states of Hamiltonians. As a concrete application, we combine these two sub-routines to present a scheme for calculating Green's functions of quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Relaxing Hardware Requirements for Surface Code Circuits using Time-dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.02192</link>
    <author>Matt McEwen, Dave Bacon, Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The typical time-independent view of quantum error correction (QEC) codes hides significant freedom in the decomposition into circuits that are executable on hardware. Using the concept of detecting regions, we design time-dynamic QEC circuits directly instead of designing static QEC codes to decompose into circuits. In particular, we improve on the standard circuit constructions for the surface code, presenting new circuits that can embed on a hexagonal grid instead of a square grid, that can use ISWAP gates instead of CNOT or CZ gates, that can exchange qubit data and measure roles, and that move logical patches around the physical qubit grid while executing. All these constructions use no additional entangling gate layers and display essentially the same logical performance, having teraquop footprints within 25% of the standard surface code circuit. We expect these circuits to be of great interest to quantum hardware engineers, because they achieve essentially the same logical performance as standard surface code circuits while relaxing demands on hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On classical simulation algorithms for noisy Boson Sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11532</link>
    <author>Changhun Oh, Liang Jiang, Bill Fefferman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present a classical algorithm that approximately samples from the output distribution of certain noisy Boson Sampling experiments. This algorithm is inspired by a recent result of Aharonov, Gao, Landau, Liu and Vazirani and makes use of an observation originally due to Kalai and Kindler that the output probability of Boson Sampling experiments with a Gaussian noise model can be approximated by sparse low-degree polynomials. This observation alone does not suffice for classical sampling, because its marginal probabilities might not be approximated by sparse low-degree polynomials, and furthermore, the approximated probabilities might be negative. We solve this problem by employing the first quantization representation to give an algorithm for computing the marginal probabilities of these experiments. We prove that when the overall noise rate is constant, the algorithm runs in time quasi-polynomial in the number of input photons $N$ and accuracy. When the overall noise rate scales as $1-x_1^\gamma$ for constant $x_1$ and $\gamma=\Omega(\log N)$, the running time becomes polynomial. Furthermore, we study noisy Boson Sampling with practically relevant noise models such as partial distinguishability and photon loss. We show that the same technique does not immediately apply in these settings, leaving open the possibility of a scalable demonstration of noisy quantum advantage for these noise models in certain parameter regimes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Computational Separation Between Quantum No-cloning and No-teleportation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01858</link>
    <author>Barak Nehoran, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Two of the fundamental no-go theorems of quantum information are the no-cloning theorem (that it is impossible to make copies of general quantum states) and the no-teleportation theorem (the prohibition on sending quantum states over classical channels without pre-shared entanglement). They are known to be equivalent, in the sense that a collection of quantum states is clonable if and only if it is teleportable. Our main result suggests that this is not the case when computational efficiency is considered. We give a collection of quantum states and oracles relative to which these states are efficiently clonable but not efficiently teleportable. Given that the opposite scenario is impossible (states that can be teleported can always trivially be cloned), this gives the most complete oracle separation possible between these two important no-go properties. In doing so, we introduce a related quantum no-go property, reconstructibility, which refers to the ability to construct a quantum state from a uniquely identifying classical description. We show the stronger result of a collection of quantum states that are efficiently clonable but not efficiently reconstructible. This novel no-go property only exists in relation to computational efficiency, as it is trivial for unbounded computation. It thus opens up the possibility of further computational no-go properties that have not yet been studied because they do not exist outside the computational context.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The qudit Pauli group: non-commuting pairs, non-commuting sets, and structure theorems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.07966</link>
    <author>Rahul Sarkar, Theodore J. Yoder</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Qudits with local dimension $d>2$ can have unique structure and uses that qubits ($d=2$) cannot. Qudit Pauli operators provide a very useful basis of the space of qudit states and operators. We study the structure of the qudit Pauli group for any, including composite, $d$ in several ways. For any specified set of commutation relations, we construct a set of qudit Paulis satisfying those relations. We also study the maximum size of sets of Paulis that mutually non-commute and sets that non-commute in pairs. Finally, we give methods to find near minimal generating sets of Pauli subgroups, calculate the sizes of Pauli subgroups, and find bases of logical operators for qudit stabilizer codes. Useful tools in this study are normal forms from linear algebra over commutative rings, including the Smith normal form, alternating Smith normal form, and Howell normal form of matrices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Everything is a quantum Ising model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11917</link>
    <author>Ruben Verresen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>This work shows that any $k$-local Hamiltonian of qubits can be obtained from a 4-state 'Ising' model with $k$-local diagonal interactions and a single-site transverse field -- giving a new theoretical and experimental handle on quantum matter. In particular, the classical Ising interactions can be determined by replacing each Pauli operator with a $4 \times 4$ diagonal matrix. Subsequently tuning a large transverse field projects out two of the four states, recovering the original qubit model, with qudit generalizations. This leads to striking correspondences, such as the spin-1/2 XY and Heisenberg models arising from the large-field limit of 3-state and 4-state Potts models, respectively. Similarly, the Kitaev honeycomb model emerges from classical interactions which enforce loop states on the honeycomb lattice. These generalized Ising models also display rich physics for smaller fields, including quantum criticality and topological phases of matter. This work expands what is experimentally achievable by showing how to realize any quantum spin model using only diagonal interactions and a tuneable field -- ingredients found in, e.g., tweezer arrays of Rydberg atoms or polar molecules. More broadly, 4-state spins can also be encoded in the positions of itinerant particles, exemplified by a Bose-Hubbard model realizing the Kitaev honeycomb model -- giving an experimental path to its $\mathbb Z_2$ and non-Abelian topological quantum liquids.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal lower bound on topological entanglement entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.00689</link>
    <author>Isaac H. Kim, Michael Levin, Ting-Chun Lin, Daniel Ranard, Bowen Shi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement entropies of two-dimensional gapped ground states are expected to satisfy an area law, with a constant correction term known as the topological entanglement entropy (TEE). In many models, the TEE takes a universal value that characterizes the underlying topological phase. However, the TEE is not truly universal: it can differ even for two states related by constant-depth circuits, which are necessarily in the same phase. The difference between the TEE and the value predicted by the anyon theory is often called the spurious topological entanglement entropy. We show that this spurious contribution is always nonnegative, thus the value predicted by the anyon theory provides a universal lower bound. This observation also leads to a definition of TEE which is invariant under constant-depth quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Elementary Proof of QAOA Convergence</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.04968</link>
    <author>Lennart Binkowski, Gereon Koßmann, Timo Ziegler, René Schwonnek</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 13 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Alternating Operator Ansatz (QAOA) and its predecessor, the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm, are one of the most widely used quantum algorithms for solving combinatorial optimization problems. However, as there is yet no rigorous proof of convergence for the QAOA, we provide one in this paper. The proof involves retracing the connection between the Quantum Adiabatic Algorithm and the QAOA, and naturally suggests a refined definition of the `phase separator' and `mixer' keywords.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental demonstration of the advantage of adaptive quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03029</link>
    <author>Michael Foss-Feig, Arkin Tikku, Tsung-Cheng Lu, Karl Mayer, Mohsin Iqbal, Thomas M. Gatterman, Justin A. Gerber, Kevin Gilmore, Dan Gresh, Aaron Hankin, Nathan Hewitt, Chandler V. Horst, Mitchell Matheny, Tanner Mengle, Brian Neyenhuis, Henrik Dreyer, David Hayes, Timothy H. Hsieh, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Adaptive quantum circuits employ unitary gates assisted by mid-circuit measurement, classical computation on the measurement outcome, and the conditional application of future unitary gates based on the result of the classical computation. In this paper, we experimentally demonstrate that even a noisy adaptive quantum circuit of constant depth can achieve a task that is impossible for any purely unitary quantum circuit of identical depth: the preparation of long-range entangled topological states with high fidelity. We prepare a particular toric code ground state with fidelity of at least $76.9\pm 1.3\%$ using a constant depth ($d=4$) adaptive circuit, and rigorously show that no unitary circuit of the same depth and connectivity could prepare this state with fidelity greater than $50\%$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Theory of Direct Randomized Benchmarking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.13853</link>
    <author>Anthony M. Polloreno, Arnaud Carignan-Dugas, Jordan Hines, Robin Blume-Kohout, Kevin Young, Timothy Proctor</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Randomized benchmarking (RB) protocols are widely used to measure an average error rate for a set of quantum logic gates. However, the standard version of RB is limited because it only benchmarks a processor's native gates indirectly, by using them in composite $n$-qubit Clifford gates. Standard RB's reliance on $n$-qubit Clifford gates restricts it to the few-qubit regime, because the fidelity of a typical composite $n$-qubit Clifford gate decreases rapidly with increasing $n$. Furthermore, although standard RB is often used to infer the error rate of native gates, by rescaling standard RB's error per Clifford to an error per native gate, this is an unreliable extrapolation. Direct RB is a method that addresses these limitations of standard RB, by directly benchmarking a customizable gate set, such as a processor's native gates. Here we provide a detailed introduction to direct RB, we discuss how to design direct RB experiments, and we present two complementary theories for direct RB. The first of these theories uses the concept of error propagation or scrambling in random circuits to show that direct RB is reliable for gates that experience stochastic Pauli errors. We prove that the direct RB decay is a single exponential, and that the decay rate is equal to the average infidelity of the benchmarked gates, under broad circumstances. This theory shows that group twirling is not required for reliable RB. Our second theory proves that direct RB is reliable for gates that experience general gate-dependent Markovian errors, using similar techniques to contemporary theories for standard RB. Our two theories for direct RB have complementary regimes of applicability, and they provide complementary perspectives on why direct RB works. Together these theories provide comprehensive guarantees on the reliability of direct RB.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Herculean task: Classical simulation of quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.08880</link>
    <author>Xiaosi Xu, Simon Benjamin, Jinzhao Sun, Xiao Yuan, Pan Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In the effort to develop useful quantum computers simulating quantum machines with conventional computing resources is a key capability. Such simulations will always face limits preventing the emulation of quantum computers of substantial scale but by pushing the envelope as far as possible through optimal choices of algorithms and hardware the value of the simulator tool is maximized. This work reviews the state-of-the-art numerical simulation methods i.e. the classical algorithms that emulate quantum computer evolution under specific operations. We focus on the mainstream state-vector and tensor-network paradigms while briefly mentioning alternative methods. Moreover we review the diverse applications of simulation across different facets of quantum computer development such as understanding the fundamental difference between quantum and classical computations exploring algorithm design spaces for quantum advantage predicting quantum processor performance at the design stage and characterizing fabricated devices efficiently for fast iterations. This review complements recent surveys on today's tools and implementations here we seek to acquaint the reader with an essential understanding of the theoretical basis of classical simulations detailed discussions on the advantages and limitations of different methods and the demands and challenges arising from practical use cases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Comment on "Traversable wormhole dynamics on a quantum processor"</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.07897</link>
    <author>Bryce Kobrin, Thomas Schuster, Norman Y. Yao</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A recent article [Nature 612, 51-55 (2022)] claims to observe traversable wormhole dynamics in an experiment. This claim is based upon performing a teleportation protocol using a Hamiltonian that consists of seven Majorana fermions with five fully-commuting terms. The Hamiltonian is generated via a machine-learning procedure designed to replicate the teleportation behavior of the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model. The authors claim that the learned Hamiltonian reproduces gravitational dynamics of the SYK model and demonstrates gravitational teleportation through an emergent wormhole. We find: (i) in contrast to these claims, the learned Hamiltonian does not exhibit thermalization; (ii) the teleportation signal only resembles the SYK model for operators that were used in the machine-learning training; (iii) the observed perfect size winding is in fact a generic feature of small-size, fully-commuting models, and does not appear to persist in larger-size fully-commuting models or in non-commuting models at equivalent system sizes</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Basic quantum subroutines: finding multiple marked elements and summing numbers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10244</link>
    <author>Joran van Apeldoorn, Sander Gribling, Harold Nieuwboer</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We show how to find all $k$ marked elements in a list of size $N$ using the optimal number $O(\sqrt{N k})$ of quantum queries and only a polylogarithmic overhead in the gate complexity, in the setting where one has a small quantum memory. Previous algorithms either incurred a factor $k$ overhead in the gate complexity, or had an extra factor $\log(k)$ in the query complexity. We then consider the problem of finding a multiplicative $\delta$-approximation of $s = \sum_{i=1}^N v_i$ where $v=(v_i) \in [0,1]^N$, given quantum query access to a binary description of $v$. We give an algorithm that does so, with probability at least $1-\rho$, using $O(\sqrt{N \log(1/\rho) / \delta})$ queries (under mild assumptions on $\rho$). This quadratically improves the dependence on $1/\delta$ and $\log(1/\rho)$ compared to a straightforward application of amplitude estimation. To obtain the improved $\log(1/\rho)$ dependence we use the first result.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum entropy thermalization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10165</link>
    <author>Yichen Huang, Aram W. Harrow</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In an isolated quantum many-body system undergoing unitary evolution, the entropy of a subsystem (smaller than half the system size) thermalizes if at long times, it is to leading order equal to the thermodynamic entropy of the subsystem at the same energy. In this paper, we prove entropy thermalization for a nearly integrable Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model initialized in a pure product state. The model is obtained by adding random all-to-all $4$-body interactions as a perturbation to a random free-fermion model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>CSS code surgery as a universal construction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.13738</link>
    <author>Alexander Cowtan, Simon Burton</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We define code maps between Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) codes using maps between chain complexes, and describe code surgery between such codes using a specific colimit in the category of chain complexes. As well as describing a surgery operation, this gives a general recipe for new codes. As an application we describe how to `merge' and `split' along a shared $\overline{X}$ or $\overline{Z}$ operator between arbitrary CSS codes in a fault-tolerant manner, so long as certain technical conditions concerning gauge fixing and code distance are satisfied. We prove that such merges and splits on LDPC codes yield codes which are themselves LDPC.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Block-encoding structured matrices for data input in quantum computing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10949</link>
    <author>Christoph Sünderhauf, Earl Campbell, Joan Camps</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The cost of data input can dominate the run-time of quantum algorithms. Here, we consider data input of arithmetically structured matrices via block encoding circuits, the input model for the quantum singular value transform and related algorithms. We demonstrate how to construct block encoding circuits based on an arithmetic description of the sparsity and pattern of repeated values of a matrix. We present schemes yielding different subnormalisations of the block encoding; a comparison shows that the best choice depends on the specific matrix. The resulting circuits reduce flag qubit number according to sparsity, and data loading cost according to repeated values, leading to an exponential improvement for certain matrices. We give examples of applying our block encoding schemes to a few families of matrices, including Toeplitz and tridiagonal matrices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum free games</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.04322</link>
    <author>Anand Natarajan, Tina Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The complexity of free games with two or more classical players was essentially settled by Aaronson, Impagliazzo, and Moshkovitz (CCC'14). There are two complexity classes that can be considered quantum analogues of classical free games: (1) AM*, the multiprover interactive proof class corresponding to free games with entangled players, and, somewhat less obviously, (2) BellQMA(2), the class of quantum Merlin-Arthur proof systems with two unentangled Merlins, whose proof states are separately measured by Arthur. In this work, we make significant progress towards a tight characterization of both of these classes. 1. We show a BellQMA(2) protocol for 3SAT on $n$ variables, where the total amount of communication is $\tilde{O}(\sqrt{n})$. This answers an open question of Chen and Drucker (2010) and also shows, conditional on ETH, that the algorithm of Brandão, Christandl and Yard (STOC'11) is tight up to logarithmic factors. 2. We show that $\mathsf{AM}^*[n_{\text{provers}} = 2, q = O(1), a =\mathrm{poly}\log(n)] = \mathsf{RE}$, i.e. that free entangled games with constant-sized questions are as powerful as general entangled games. Our result is a significant improvement over the headline result of Ji et al. (2020), whose MIP* protocol for the halting problem has $\mathrm{poly}(n)$-sized questions and answers. 3. We obtain a zero-gap AM* protocol for a $\Pi_2$ complete language with constant-size questions and almost logarithmically large answers, improving on the headline result of Mousavi, Nezhadi and Yuen (STOC'22). 4. Using a connection to the nonuniform complexity of the halting problem we show that any MIP* protocol for RE requires $\Omega(\log n)$ bits of communication. It follows that our results in item 3 are optimal up to an $O(\log^* n)$ factor, and that the gapless compression theorems of MNY'22 are asymptotically optimal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum trapdoor functions from classical one-way functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.12821</link>
    <author>Andrea Coladangelo</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce the notion of a quantum trapdoor function. This is an efficiently computable unitary that takes as input a "public" quantum state and a classical string $x$, and outputs a quantum state. This map is such that (i) it is hard to invert, in the sense that it is hard to recover $x$ given the output state (and many copies of the public state), and (ii) there is a classical trapdoor that allows efficient inversion. We show that a quantum trapdoor function can be constructed from any quantum-secure one-way function. A direct consequence of this result is that, assuming just the existence of quantum-secure one-way functions, there exist: (i) a public-key encryption scheme with a quantum public key, and (ii) a two-message key-exchange protocol, assuming an appropriate notion of a quantum authenticated channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum spherical codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11593</link>
    <author>Shubham P. Jain, Joseph T. Iosue, Alexander Barg, Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a framework for constructing quantum codes defined on spheres by recasting such codes as quantum analogues of the classical spherical codes. We apply this framework to bosonic coding, obtaining multimode extensions of the cat codes that can outperform previous constructions while requiring a similar type of overhead. Our polytope-based cat codes consist of sets of points with large separation that at the same time form averaging sets known as spherical designs. We also recast concatenations of qubit CSS codes with cat codes as quantum spherical codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error Mitigation Thresholds in Noisy Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.04278</link>
    <author>Pradeep Niroula, Sarang Gopalakrishnan, Michael J. Gullans</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Extracting useful information from noisy near-term quantum simulations requires error mitigation strategies. A broad class of these strategies rely on precise characterization of the noise source. We study the performance of such strategies when the noise is imperfectly characterized. We adapt an Imry-Ma argument to predict the existence of an error mitigation threshold for random spatially local circuits in spatial dimensions $D \geq 2$: characterization disorder below the threshold rate allows for error mitigation up to times that scale with the number of qubits. For one-dimensional circuits, by contrast, mitigation fails at an $\mathcal{O}(1)$ time for any imperfection in the characterization of disorder. We discuss implications for tests of quantum computational advantage, fault-tolerant probes of measurement-induced phase transitions, and quantum algorithms in near-term devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Can shallow quantum circuits scramble local noise into global white noise?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.00881</link>
    <author>Jonathan Foldager, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Shallow quantum circuits are believed to be the most promising candidates for achieving early practical quantum advantage - this has motivated the development of a broad range of error mitigation techniques whose performance generally improves when the quantum state is well approximated by a global depolarising (white) noise model. While it has been crucial for demonstrating quantum supremacy that random circuits scramble local noise into global white noise - a property that has been proved rigorously - we investigate to what degree practical shallow quantum circuits scramble local noise into global white noise. We define two key metrics as (a) density matrix eigenvalue uniformity and (b) commutator norm. While the former determines the distance from white noise, the latter determines the performance of purification based error mitigation. We derive analytical approximate bounds on their scaling and find in most cases they nicely match numerical results. On the other hand, we simulate a broad class of practical quantum circuits and find that white noise is in certain cases a bad approximation posing significant limitations on the performance of some of the simpler error mitigation schemes. On a positive note, we find in all cases that the commutator norm is sufficiently small guaranteeing a very good performance of purification-based error mitigation. Lastly, we identify techniques that may decrease both metrics, such as increasing the dimensionality of the dynamical Lie algebra by gate insertions or randomised compiling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Guidable Local Hamiltonian Problems with Implications to Heuristic Ansätze State Preparation and the Quantum PCP Conjecture</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11578</link>
    <author>Jordi Weggemans, Marten Folkertsma, Chris Cade</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce 'Merlinized' versions of the recently defined Guided Local Hamiltonian problem, which we call 'Guidable Local Hamiltonian' problems. Unlike their guided counterparts, these problems do not have a guiding state provided as a part of the input, but merely come with the promise that one exists and that it satisfies certain constraints. We consider in particular two classes of guiding states: those that can be prepared efficiently by a quantum circuit; and those belonging to a class of quantum states we call classically evaluatable, which have a short classical description from which it is possible to efficiently compute expectation values of local observables classically. We show that guidable local Hamiltonian problems for both classes of guiding states are $\mathsf{QCMA}$-complete in the inverse-polynomial precision setting, but lie within $\mathsf{NP}$ (or $\mathsf{NqP}$) in certain parameter regimes when the guiding state is classically evaluatable. We discuss the implications of these results to heuristic ansätze state preparation and the quantum PCP conjecture. Our completeness results show that, from a complexity-theoretic perspective, classical ansätze prepared by classical heuristics are just as powerful as quantum ansätze prepared by quantum heuristics, so long as one has access to quantum phase estimation. In relation to the quantum PCP conjecture, we (i) define a PCP for $\mathsf{QCMA}$ and show that it is equal to $\mathsf{NP}$ under quantum reductions; (ii) show several no-go results for the existence of quantum gap amplification procedures that preserve certain ground state properties; and (iii) propose two conjectures that can be viewed as stronger versions of the NLTS theorem. Finally, we show that many of our results can be directly modified to obtain similar results for the class $\mathsf{MA}$.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>