<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Unconditional Quantum Advantage for Sampling with Shallow Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.00995</link>
    <author>Adam Bene Watts, Natalie Parham</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 04 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Recent work by Bravyi, Gosset, and Koenig showed that there exists a search problem that a constant-depth quantum circuit can solve, but that any constant-depth classical circuit with bounded fan-in cannot. They also pose the question: can we achieve a similar proof of separation for an input-independent sampling task? In this paper, we show that the answer to this question is yes. We introduce a distribution $D_{n}$ and give a constant-depth, $n$ qubit, quantum circuit that samples from a distribution close to $D_{n}$ in total variation distance. For any $\delta < 1$ we also prove, unconditionally, that any classical circuit with bounded fan-in gates that takes as input $n + n^\delta$ uniformly random bits and produces output close to $D_{n}$ in total variation distance has depth $\Omega(\log \log n)$. This gives an unconditional proof that constant-depth quantum circuits can sample from distributions which can't be reproduced by constant-depth bounded fan-in classical circuits, even up to additive error. The distribution $D_n$ and classical circuit lower bounds are based on work of Viola, in which he shows a different (but related) distribution cannot be sampled from approximately by constant-depth bounded fan-in classical circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>stateQIP = statePSPACE</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07730</link>
    <author>Tony Metger, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Complexity theory traditionally studies the hardness of solving classical computational problems. In the quantum setting, it is also natural to consider a different notion of complexity, namely the complexity of physically preparing a certain quantum state. We study the relation between two such state complexity classes: statePSPACE, which contains states that can be generated by space-uniform polynomial-space quantum circuits, and stateQIP, which contains states that a polynomial-time quantum verifier can generate by interacting with an all-powerful untrusted quantum prover. The latter class was recently introduced by Rosenthal and Yuen (ITCS 2022), who proved that statePSPACE $\subseteq$ stateQIP. Our main result is the reverse inclusion, stateQIP $\subseteq$ statePSPACE, thereby establishing equality of the two classes and providing a natural state-complexity analogue to the celebrated QIP = PSPACE theorem of Jain, et al. (J. ACM 2011). To prove this, we develop a polynomial-space quantum algorithm for solving exponentially large "PSPACE-computable" semidefinite programs (SDPs), which also prepares an optimiser encoded in a quantum state. Our SDP solver relies on recent block-encoding techniques from quantum algorithms, demonstrating that these techniques are also useful for complexity theory. Using similar techniques, we also show that optimal prover strategies for general quantum interactive protocols can be implemented in quantum polynomial space. We prove this by studying an algorithmic version of Uhlmann's theorem and establishing an upper bound on the complexity of implementing Uhlmann transformations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lower Bounds on Learning Pauli Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09192</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Aadil Oufkir, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding the noise affecting a quantum device is of fundamental importance for scaling quantum technologies. A particularly important class of noise models is that of Pauli channels, as randomized compiling techniques can effectively bring any quantum channel to this form and are significantly more structured than general quantum channels. In this paper, we show fundamental lower bounds on the sample complexity for learning Pauli channels in diamond norm with unentangled measurements. We consider both adaptive and non-adaptive strategies. In the non-adaptive setting, we show a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{3n}\epsilon^{-2})$ to learn an $n$-qubit Pauli channel. In particular, this shows that the recently introduced learning procedure by Flammia and Wallman is essentially optimal. In the adaptive setting, we show a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{2.5n}\epsilon^{-2})$ for $\epsilon=\mathcal{O}(2^{-n})$, and a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{2n}\epsilon^{-2} )$ for any $\epsilon > 0$. This last lower bound even applies for arbitrarily many sequential uses of the channel, as long as they are only interspersed with other unital operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A note on lower bounds to variational problems with guarantees</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06142</link>
    <author>J. Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods play an important role in the study of quantum many body problems, both in the flavour of classical variational principles based on tensor networks as well as of quantum variational principles in near-term quantum computing. This brief pedagogical note stresses that for translationally invariant lattice Hamiltonians, one can easily derive efficiently computable lower bounds to ground state energies that can and should be compared with variational principles providing upper bounds. As small technical results, it is shown that (i) the Anderson bound and a (ii) common hierarchy of semi-definite relaxations both provide approximations with performance guarantees that scale like a constant in the energy density for cubic lattices. (iii) Also, the Anderson bound is systematically improved as a hierarchy of semi-definite relaxations inspired by the marginal problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal lower bounds for Quantum Learning via Information Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02227</link>
    <author>Shima Bab Hadiashar, Ashwin Nayak, Pulkit Sinha</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Although a concept class may be learnt more efficiently using quantum samples as compared with classical samples in certain scenarios, Arunachalam and de Wolf (JMLR, 2018) proved that quantum learners are asymptotically no more efficient than classical ones in the quantum PAC and Agnostic learning models. They established lower bounds on sample complexity via quantum state identification and Fourier analysis. In this paper, we derive optimal lower bounds for quantum sample complexity in both the PAC and agnostic models via an information-theoretic approach. The proofs are arguably simpler, and the same ideas can potentially be used to derive optimal bounds for other problems in quantum learning theory. We then turn to a quantum analogue of the Coupon Collector problem, a classic problem from probability theory also of importance in the study of PAC learning. Arunachalam, Belovs, Childs, Kothari, Rosmanis, and de Wolf (TQC, 2020) characterized the quantum sample complexity of this problem up to constant factors. First, we show that the information-theoretic approach mentioned above provably does not yield the optimal lower bound. As a by-product, we get a natural ensemble of pure states in arbitrarily high dimensions which are not easily (simultaneously) distinguishable, while the ensemble has close to maximal Holevo information. Second, we discover that the information-theoretic approach yields an asymptotically optimal bound for an approximation variant of the problem. Finally, we derive a sharp lower bound for the Quantum Coupon Collector problem, with the exact leading order term, via the Holevo-Curlander bounds on the distinguishability of an ensemble. All the aspects of the Quantum Coupon Collector problem we study rest on properties of the spectrum of the associated Gram matrix, which may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error Correction of Quantum Algorithms: Arbitrarily Accurate Recovery Of Noisy Quantum Signal Processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08542</link>
    <author>Andrew K. Tan, Yuan Liu, Minh C. Tran, Isaac L. Chuang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The intrinsic probabilistic nature of quantum systems makes error correction or mitigation indispensable for quantum computation. While current error-correcting strategies focus on correcting errors in quantum states or quantum gates, these fine-grained error-correction methods can incur significant overhead for quantum algorithms of increasing complexity. We present a first step in achieving error correction at the level of quantum algorithms by combining a unified perspective on modern quantum algorithms via quantum signal processing (QSP). An error model of under- or over-rotation of the signal processing operator parameterized by $\epsilon < 1$ is introduced. It is shown that while Pauli $Z$-errors are not recoverable without additional resources, Pauli $X$ and $Y$ errors can be arbitrarily suppressed by coherently appending a noisy `recovery QSP.' Furthermore, it is found that a recovery QSP of length $O(2^k c^{k^2} d)$ is sufficient to correct any length-$d$ QSP with $c$ unique phases to $k^{th}$-order in error $\epsilon$. Allowing an additional assumption, a lower bound of $\Omega(cd)$ is shown, which is tight for $k = 1$, on the length of the recovery sequence. Our algorithmic-level error correction method is applied to Grover's fixed-point search algorithm as a demonstration.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Exponential Separation Between Quantum Query Complexity and the Polynomial Degree</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09218</link>
    <author>Andris Ambainis, Aleksandrs Belovs</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>While it is known that there is at most a polynomial separation between quantum query complexity and the polynomial degree for total functions, the precise relationship between the two is not clear for partial functions. In this paper, we demonstrate an exponential separation between exact polynomial degree and approximate quantum query complexity for a partial Boolean function. For an unbounded alphabet size, we have a constant versus polynomial separation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailoring fusion-based error correction for high thresholds to biased fusion failures</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.00019</link>
    <author>Kaavya Sahay, Jahan Claes, Shruti Puri</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce fault-tolerant (FT) architectures for error correction with the XZZX cluster state based on performing measurements of two-qubit Pauli operators $Z\otimes Z$ and $X\otimes X$, or fusions, on a collection of few-body entangled resource states. Our construction is tailored to be effective against noise that predominantly causes faulty $X\otimes X$ measurements during fusions. This feature offers practical advantage in linear optical quantum computing with dual-rail photonic qubits, where failed fusions only erase $X\otimes X$ measurement outcomes. By applying our construction to this platform, we find a record high FT threshold to fusion failures exceeding $25\%$ in the experimentally relevant regime of non-zero loss rate per photon, considerably simplifying hardware requirements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Mass Production Theorems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.14399</link>
    <author>William Kretschmer</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 02 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We prove that for any $n$-qubit unitary transformation $U$ and for any $r = 2^{o(n / \log n)}$, there exists a quantum circuit to implement $U^{\otimes r}$ with at most $O(4^n)$ gates. This asymptotically equals the number of gates needed to implement just a single copy of a worst-case $U$. We also establish analogous results for quantum states and diagonal unitary transformations. Our techniques are based on the work of Uhlig [Math. Notes 1974], who proved a similar mass production theorem for Boolean functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Graphical quantum Clifford-encoder compilers from the ZX calculus</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02356</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu, Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 09 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present a quantum compilation algorithm that maps Clifford encoders, an equivalence class of quantum circuits that arise universally in quantum error correction, into a representation in the ZX calculus. In particular, we develop a canonical form in the ZX calculus and prove canonicity as well as efficient reducibility of any Clifford encoder into the canonical form. The diagrams produced by our compiler explicitly visualize information propagation and entanglement structure of the encoder, revealing properties that may be obscured in the circuit or stabilizer-tableau representation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum simulation of exact electron dynamics can be more efficient than classical mean-field methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.01203</link>
    <author>Ryan Babbush, William J. Huggins, Dominic W. Berry, Shu Fay Ung, Andrew Zhao, David R. Reichman, Hartmut Neven, Andrew D. Baczewski, Joonho Lee</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 04 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for simulating electronic ground states are slower than popular classical mean-field algorithms such as Hartree-Fock and density functional theory, but offer higher accuracy. Accordingly, quantum computers have been predominantly regarded as competitors to only the most accurate and costly classical methods for treating electron correlation. However, here we tighten bounds showing that certain first quantized quantum algorithms enable exact time evolution of electronic systems with exponentially less space and polynomially fewer operations in basis set size than conventional real-time time-dependent Hartree-Fock and density functional theory. Although the need to sample observables in the quantum algorithm reduces the speedup, we show that one can estimate all elements of the $k$-particle reduced density matrix with a number of samples scaling only polylogarithmically in basis set size. We also introduce a more efficient quantum algorithm for first quantized mean-field state preparation that is likely cheaper than the cost of time evolution. We conclude that quantum speedup is most pronounced for finite temperature simulations and suggest several practically important electron dynamics problems with potential quantum advantage.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Asymptotic Equipartition Theorems in von Neumann algebras</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.14700</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Li Gao, Mizanur Rahaman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 02 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The Asymptotic Equipartition Property (AEP) in information theory establishes that independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) states behave in a way that is similar to uniform states. In particular, with appropriate smoothing, for such states both the min and the max relative entropy asymptotically coincide with the relative entropy. In this paper, we generalize several such equipartition properties to states on general von Neumann algebras. First, we show that the smooth max relative entropy of i.i.d. states on a von Neumann algebra has an asymptotic rate given by the quantum relative entropy. In fact, our AEP not only applies to states, but also to quantum channels with appropriate restrictions. In addition, going beyond the i.i.d. assumption, we show that for states that are produced by a sequential process of quantum channels, the smooth max relative entropy can be upper bounded by the sum of appropriate channel relative entropies. Our main technical contributions are to extend to the context of general von Neumann algebras a chain rule for quantum channels, as well as an additivity result for the channel relative entropy with a replacer channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From Kraus Operators to the Stinespring Form of Quantum Maps: An Alternative Construction for Infinite Dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05488</link>
    <author>Frederik vom Ende</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 16 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present an alternative (constructive) proof of the statement that for every completely positive, trace-preserving map $\Phi$ there exists an ancilla Hilbert space $\mathcal K$ in a pure state $|\psi\rangle\langle\psi|$ as well as a unitary operator $U$ on system plus ancilla such that $\Phi$ equals $\operatorname{tr}_{\mathcal K}(U((\cdot)\otimes|\psi\rangle\langle\psi|)U^*)$. The main tool of our proof is Sz.-Nagy's dilation theorem applied to isometries defined on a subspace. In our construction, the ancilla consists of a system of dimension the Kraus rank of $\Phi$ together with a qubit which, however, only acts as a catalyst. In contrast, the original proof of Hellwig & Kraus given in the 70s yields an ancilla of dimension "Kraus rank plus one". We conclude by providing an example which illustrates how the constructions differ from each other.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Speedups for Zero-Sum Games via Improved Dynamic Gibbs Sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03763</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Yosheb Getachew, Yujia Jin, Aaron Sidford, Kevin Tian</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum algorithm for computing an $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium of a zero-sum game in a $m \times n$ payoff matrix with bounded entries. Given a standard quantum oracle for accessing the payoff matrix our algorithm runs in time $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{m + n}\cdot \epsilon^{-2.5} + \epsilon^{-3})$ and outputs a classical representation of the $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium. This improves upon the best prior quantum runtime of $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{m + n} \cdot \epsilon^{-3})$ obtained by [vAG19] and the classic $\widetilde{O}((m + n) \cdot \epsilon^{-2})$ runtime due to [GK95] whenever $\epsilon = \Omega((m +n)^{-1})$. We obtain this result by designing new quantum data structures for efficiently sampling from a slowly-changing Gibbs distribution.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Randomized adaptive quantum state preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.04201</link>
    <author>Alicia B. Magann, Sophia E. Economou, Christian Arenz</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We develop an adaptive method for quantum state preparation that utilizes randomness as an essential component and that does not require classical optimization. Instead, a cost function is minimized to prepare a desired quantum state through an adaptively constructed quantum circuit, where each adaptive step is informed by feedback from gradient measurements in which the associated tangent space directions are randomized. We provide theoretical arguments and numerical evidence that convergence to the target state can be achieved for almost all initial states. We investigate different randomization procedures and develop lower bounds on the expected cost function change, which allows for drawing connections to barren plateaus and for assessing the applicability of the algorithm to large-scale problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-tolerant error correction for a universal non-Abelian topological quantum computer at finite temperature</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.00054</link>
    <author>Alexis Schotte, Lander Burgelman, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We study fault-tolerant error correction in a quantum memory constructed as a two-dimensional model of Fibonacci anyons on a torus, in the presence of thermal noise represented by pair-creation processes and measurement errors. The correction procedure is based on the cellular automaton decoders originating in the works of Gács and Harrington. Through numerical simulations, we observe that this code behaves fault-tolerantly and that threshold behavior is likely present. Hence, we provide strong evidence for the existence of a fault-tolerant universal non-Abelian topological quantum computer.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Guaranteed efficient energy estimation of quantum many-body Hamiltonians using ShadowGrouping</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03385</link>
    <author>Alexander Gresch, Martin Kliesch</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Energy estimation in quantum many-body Hamiltonians is a paradigmatic task in various research fields. In particular, efficient energy estimation may be crucial in achieving a quantum advantage for a practically relevant problem. For instance, the measurement effort poses a crucial bottleneck in variational quantum algorithms. We aim to find the optimal strategy with single-qubit measurements that yields the highest provable accuracy given a total measurement budget. As a central tool, we establish new tail bounds for empirical estimators of the energy. They are useful for identifying measurement settings that improve the energy estimate the most. This task constitutes an NP-hard problem. However, we are able to circumvent this bottleneck and use the tail bounds to develop a practical efficient estimation strategy which we call ShadowGrouping. As the name suggests, it combines shadow estimation methods with grouping strategies for Pauli strings. In numerical experiments, we demonstrate that ShadowGrouping outperforms state-of-the-art methods in estimating the electronic ground-state energies of various small molecules, both in provable and effective accuracy benchmarks. Hence, this work provides a promising way, e.g., to tackle the measurement bottleneck of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>One-Way Ticket to Las Vegas and the Quantum Adversary</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02003</link>
    <author>Aleksandrs Belovs, Duyal Yolcu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a new definition of quantum Las Vegas query complexity. We show that it is exactly equal to the quantum adversary bound. This is achieved by a new and very simple way of transforming a feasible solution to the adversary optimisation problem into a quantum query algorithm. This allows us to generalise the bound to include unidirectional access, multiple input oracles, and input oracles that are not unitary. As an application, we demonstrate a separation between unidirectional and bidirectional access to an input oracle for a rather natural unitary permutation inversion problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hypothesis Testing for Error Mitigation: How to Evaluate Error Mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02690</link>
    <author>Abdullah Ash Saki, Amara Katabarwa, Salonik Resch, George Umbrarescu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In the noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era, quantum error mitigation will be a necessary tool to extract useful performance out of quantum devices. However, there is a big gap between the noise models often assumed by error mitigation techniques and the actual noise on quantum devices. As a consequence, there arises a gap between the theoretical expectations of the techniques and their everyday performance. Cloud users of quantum devices in particular, who often take the devices as they are, feel this gap the most. How should they parametrize their uncertainty in the usefulness of these techniques and be able to make judgement calls between resources required to implement error mitigation and the accuracy required at the algorithmic level? To answer the first question, we introduce hypothesis testing within the framework of quantum error mitigation and for the second question, we propose an inclusive figure of merit that accounts for both resource requirement and mitigation efficiency of an error mitigation implementation. The figure of merit is useful to weigh the trade-offs between the scalability and accuracy of various error mitigation methods. Finally, using the hypothesis testing and the figure of merit, we experimentally evaluate $16$ error mitigation pipelines composed of singular methods such as zero noise extrapolation, randomized compilation, measurement error mitigation, dynamical decoupling, and mitigation with estimation circuits. In total our data involved running $275,640$ circuits on two IBM quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Direct Reduction from the Polynomial to the Adversary Method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10317</link>
    <author>Aleksandrs Belovs</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The polynomial and the adversary methods are the two main tools for proving lower bounds on query complexity of quantum algorithms. Both methods have found a large number of applications, some problems more suitable for one method, some for the other. It is known though that the adversary method, in its general negative-weighted version, is tight for bounded-error quantum algorithms, whereas the polynomial method is not. By the tightness of the former, for any polynomial lower bound, there ought to exist a corresponding adversary lower bound. However, direct reduction was not known. In this paper, we give a simple and direct reduction from the polynomial method (in the form of a dual polynomial) to the adversary method. This shows that any lower bound in the form of a dual polynomial is actually an adversary lower bound of a specific form.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A generic quantum Wielandt's inequality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08241</link>
    <author>Yifan Jia, Angela Capel</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we provide a generic version of quantum Wielandt's inequality, which gives an optimal upper bound on the minimal length $k$ such that length-$k$ products of elements in a generating system span $M_n(\mathbb{C})$ with probability one. We show that $k$ generically is of order $\Theta(\log n)$, as opposed to the general case, in which the best bound to the date is $O(n^2 \log n)$. Our result implies a new bound on the primitivity index of a random quantum channel. Furthermore, we conclude that almost any translation-invariant (with periodic boundary conditions) matrix product state with length of order $\Omega( \log n )$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian. We observe similar characteristics for matrix Lie algebras and provide numerical results for random Lie-generating systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast Quantum Algorithms for Trace Distance Estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06783</link>
    <author>Qisheng Wang, Zhicheng Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In quantum information processing, trace distance is a basic metric of distinguishability between quantum states. However, there is no known efficient approach to estimate the value of trace distance in general. In this paper, we propose efficient quantum algorithms for estimating the trace distance within additive error $\varepsilon$ between mixed quantum states of rank $r$. Specifically, we first provide a quantum algorithm using $r \cdot \widetilde O(1/\varepsilon^2)$ queries to the quantum circuits that prepare the purifications of quantum states, which achieves a linear time dependence on the rank $r$. Then, we modify this quantum algorithm to obtain another algorithm using $\widetilde O(r^2/\varepsilon^5)$ samples of quantum states, which can be applied to quantum state certification. Both algorithms have the same quantum time complexities as their query/sample complexities up to a logarithmic factor.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing quantum satisfiability</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10699</link>
    <author>Ashley Montanaro, Changpeng Shao, Dominic Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum k-SAT (the problem of determining whether a k-local Hamiltonian is frustration-free) is known to be QMA_1-complete for k >= 3, and hence likely hard for quantum computers to solve. Building on a classical result of Alon and Shapira, we show that quantum k-SAT can be solved in randomised polynomial time given the `property testing' promise that the instance is either satisfiable (by any state) or far from satisfiable by a product state; by `far from satisfiable by a product state' we mean that \epsilon n^k constraints must be removed before a product state solution exists, for some fixed \epsilon > 0. The proof has two steps: we first show that for a satisfiable instance of quantum k-SAT, most subproblems on a constant number of qubits are satisfiable by a product state. We then show that for an instance of quantum k-SAT which is far from satisfiable by a product state, most subproblems are unsatisfiable by a product state. Given the promise, quantum k-SAT may therefore be solved by checking satisfiability by a product state on randomly chosen subsystems of constant size.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entropy Uncertainty Relations and Strong Sub-additivity of Quantum Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08402</link>
    <author>Li Gao, Marius Junge, Nicholas LaRacuente</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We prove an entropic uncertainty relation for two quantum channels, extending the work of Frank and Lieb for quantum measurements. This is obtained via a generalized strong super-additivity (SSA) of quantum entropy. Motivated by Petz's algebraic SSA inequality, we also obtain a generalized SSA for quantum relative entropy. As a special case, it gives an improved data processing inequality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Path integrals for classical-quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.04677</link>
    <author>Jonathan Oppenheim, Zachary Weller-Davies</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Consistent dynamics which couples classical and quantum degrees of freedom exists. This dynamics is linear in the hybrid state, completely positive and trace preserving. Starting from completely positive classical-quantum master equations, we derive a general path integral representation for such dynamics in terms of a classical-quantum action, which includes the necessary and sufficient conditions for complete positivity and trace preservation. The path integral we study is a generalization of the Feynman path integral for quantum systems, and the stochastic path integral used to study classical stochastic processes, allowing for interaction between the classical and quantum systems. When the classical-quantum Hamiltonian is at most quadratic in the momenta we are able to derive a configuration space path integral, providing a map between master equations and covariant classical-quantum path integrals.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Discrete holography in dual-unitary circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02825</link>
    <author>Lluis Masanes</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a family of dual-unitary circuits in 1+1 dimensions which constitute a discrete analog of conformal field theories. These circuits are quantum cellular automata which are invariant under the joint action of Lorentz and scale transformations. Dual unitaries are four-legged tensors which satisfy the unitarity condition across the time as well as the space direction, a property that makes the model mathematically tractable. Using dual unitaries too, we construct tensor-network states for our 1+1 model, which are interpreted as spatial slices of curved 2+1 discrete geometries, where the metric distance is defined by the entanglement structure of the state, following Ryu-Takayanagi's prescription. The dynamics of the circuit induces a natural dynamics on these geometries, which we study for flat and anti-de Sitter spaces, and in the presence or absence of matter. We observe that the dynamics of spaces with two or more particles differs from that of zero or one, suggesting the presence of black holes. But this contrasts with the fact that the family of models appears to be non-chaotic. We observe that the dynamics of a particle in such spaces strongly depends on the presence of other particles, suggesting gravitational back-reaction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring out quasi-local integrals of motion from entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.01787</link>
    <author>B. Lu, C. Bertoni, S. J. Thomson, J. Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quasi-local integrals of motion are a key concept underpinning the modern understanding of many-body localisation, an intriguing phenomenon in which interactions and disorder come together. Despite the existence of several numerical ways to compute them - and astoundingly in the light of the observation that much of the phenomenology of many properties can be derived from them - it is not obvious how to directly measure aspects of them in real quantum simulations; in fact, the smoking gun of their experimental observation is arguably still missing. In this work, we propose a way to extract the real-space properties of such quasi-local integrals of motion based on a spatially-resolved entanglement probe able to distinguish Anderson from many-body localisation from non-equilibrium dynamics. We complement these findings with a new rigorous entanglement bound and compute the relevant quantities using tensor networks. We demonstrate that the entanglement gives rise to a well-defined length scale that can be measured in experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable Quantum Error Correction for Surface Codes using FPGA</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08419</link>
    <author>Namitha Liyanage, Yue Wu, Alexander Deters, Lin Zhong</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A fault-tolerant quantum computer must decode and correct errors faster than they appear. The faster errors can be corrected, the more time the computer can do useful work. The Union-Find (UF) decoder is promising with an average time complexity slightly higher than $O(d^3)$. We report a distributed version of the UF decoder that exploits parallel computing resources for further speedup. Using an FPGA-based implementation, we empirically show that this distributed UF decoder has a sublinear average time complexity with regard to $d$, given $O(d^3)$ parallel computing resources. The decoding time per measurement round decreases as $d$ increases, a first time for a quantum error decoder. The implementation employs a scalable architecture called Helios that organizes parallel computing resources into a hybrid tree-grid structure. Using Xilinx's cycle-accurate simulator, we present cycle-accurate decoding time for $d$ up to 15, with the phenomenological noise model with $p=0.1\%$. We are able to implement $d$ up to 7 with a Xilinx ZC106 FPGA, for which an average decoding time is 120 ns per measurement round. Since the decoding time per measurement round of Helios decreases with $d$, Helios can decode a surface code of arbitrarily large $d$ without a growing backlog.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Diagnostics of mixed-state topological order and breakdown of quantum memory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05689</link>
    <author>Ruihua Fan, Yimu Bao, Ehud Altman, Ashvin Vishwanath</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 16 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Topological quantum memory can protect information against local errors up to finite error thresholds. Such thresholds are usually determined based on the success of decoding algorithms rather than the intrinsic properties of the mixed states describing corrupted memories. Here we provide an intrinsic characterization of the breakdown of topological quantum memory, which both gives a bound on the performance of decoding algorithms and provides examples of topologically distinct mixed states. We employ three information-theoretical quantities that can be regarded as generalizations of the diagnostics of ground-state topological order, and serve as a definition for topological order in error-corrupted mixed states. We consider the topological contribution to entanglement negativity and two other metrics based on quantum relative entropy and coherent information. In the concrete example of the 2D Toric code with local bit-flip and phase errors, we map three quantities to observables in 2D classical spin models and analytically show they all undergo a transition at the same error threshold. This threshold is an upper bound on that achieved in any decoding algorithm and is indeed saturated by that in the optimal decoding algorithm for the Toric code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simultaneous superadditivity of the direct and complementary channel capacities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05142</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Sergii Strelchuk</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum communication channels differ from their classical counterparts because their capacities can be superadditive. The principle of monogamy of entanglement suggests that superadditive improvements in the transmission capacity of a channel should reduce the amount of information loss to the environment. We challenge this intuition by demonstrating that the coherent and private information of a channel and its complement can be simultaneously superadditive for arbitrarily many channel uses. To quantify the limits of this effect, we consider the notion of max (resp. total) private information of a channel, which represents the maximum (resp. sum) of the private information of the channel itself and its complement, and study its relationship with the coherent information of the individual direct and complementary channels. For a varying number of channel uses, we show that these quantities can obey different interleaving sequences of inequalities.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>