
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>No-Go Theorems for Quantum Resource Distillation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.02540</link>
    <author>Kun Fang, Zi-Wen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 06 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Distillation, which generally means converting noisy states into better approximations of some valuable pure states by low-cost operations, is a fundamental type of resource trading protocol that plays major roles in quantum computation and information processing. In this work, we establish a series of fundamental limits to the efficiency of distillation with finite resources which apply to any reasonable resource theory, using an information-theoretic tool called the quantum hypothesis testing relative entropy. We show that, for highly generic noisy inputs, there is an insuperable limitation to the accuracy (or lower bound on the error) of any distillation protocol, even probabilistic ones. More explicitly, our bounds indicate a forbidden regime of the accuracy and success probability that no protocol with the corresponding parameters can exist. We use these no-go theorems to derive bounds which imply that the total overhead i.e. the number of noisy inputs needed to distill a pure resource state with small error $\epsilon$ must scale at least as $\Omega(\log(1/\epsilon))$. This allows us to establish specific lower bounds on the cost of magic state distillation, a task crucial to fault-tolerant quantum computation, which in particular address an open problem raised by Hastings and Haah [PRL 120, 050504 (2018)]. Finally, we showcase a basic no-go result for simulating unitary resource channels to demonstrate that the analogous understandings may extend to channel resource theories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Faster quantum and classical SDP approximations for quadratic binary optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.04613</link>
    <author>Fernando G.S L. Brandão, Richard Kueng, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 11 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum speedup for solving the canonical semidefinite programming relaxation for binary quadratic optimization. The class of relaxations for combinatorial optimization has so far eluded quantum speedups. Our methods combine ideas from quantum Gibbs sampling and matrix exponent updates. A de-quantization of the algorithm also leads to a faster classical solver. For generic instances, our quantum solver gives a nearly quadratic speedup over state-of-the-art algorithms. We also provide an efficient randomized rounding procedure that converts approximately optimal SDP solutions into constant factor approximations of the original quadratic optimization problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Brascamp-Lieb Dualities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.02383</link>
    <author>Mario Berta, David Sutter, Michael Walter</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 06 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Brascamp-Lieb inequalities are entropy inequalities which have a dual formulation as generalized Young inequalities. In this work, we introduce a fully quantum version of this duality, relating quantum relative entropy inequalities to matrix exponential inequalities of Young type. We demonstrate this novel duality by means of examples from quantum information theory - including entropic uncertainty relations, strong data-processing inequalities, super-additivity inequalities, and many more. As an application we find novel uncertainty relations for Gaussian quantum operations that can be interpreted as quantum duals of the well-known family of geometric Brascamp-Lieb inequalities.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational algorithms for linear algebra</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03898</link>
    <author>Xiaosi Xu, Jinzhao Sun, Suguru Endo, Ying Li, Simon C. Benjamin, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 10 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms have been developed for efficiently solving linear algebra tasks. However they generally require deep circuits and therefore universal fault-tolerant quantum computers. In this work, we propose variational algorithms for linear algebra tasks that are compatible with Noisy Intermediate Scaled Quantum devices. We show that the solutions of linear systems of equations and matrix-vector multiplications can be translated as the ground states of the constructed Hamiltonians. Based on recently proposed variational quantum algorithms, we introduce Hamiltonian morphing together with an adaptive ansatz for efficiently finding the ground state. As the ground state always has zero energy, it also enables us to verify the solution. Our algorithms have wide applications in machine learning and optimisation problems, and the algorithm for matrix multiplications can be also used for variational Hamiltonian simulation. Finally, we conduct numerical simulations of the algorithm for solving linear systems of equations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved local spectral gap thresholds for lattices of finite dimension</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.01516</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Knabe's theorem lower bounds the spectral gap of a one dimensional frustration-free local hamiltonian in terms of the local spectral gaps of finite regions. It also provides a local spectral gap threshold for hamiltonians that are gapless in the thermodynamic limit, showing that the local spectral gap much scale inverse linearly with the length of the region for such systems. Recent works have further improved upon this threshold, tightening it in the one dimensional case and extending it to higher dimensions. Here, we show a local spectral gap threshold for frustration-free hamiltonians on a finite dimensional lattice, that is optimal up to a constant factor that depends on the dimension of the lattice. Our proof is based on the detectability lemma framework and uses the notion of coarse-grained hamiltonian (introduced in [Phys. Rev. B 93, 205142]) as a link connecting the (global) spectral gap and the local spectral gap.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Natural Gradient</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.02108</link>
    <author>James Stokes, Josh Izaac, Nathan Killoran, Giuseppe Carleo</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 06 2019</pubDate>
    <description>A quantum generalization of Natural Gradient Descent is presented as part of a general-purpose optimization framework for variational quantum circuits. The optimization dynamics is interpreted as moving in the steepest descent direction with respect to the Quantum Information Geometry, corresponding to the real part of the Quantum Geometric Tensor (QGT), also known as the Fubini-Study metric tensor. An efficient algorithm is presented for computing a block-diagonal approximation to the Fubini-Study metric tensor for parametrized quantum circuits, which may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Universality of the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03123</link>
    <author>Mauro E. S. Morales, Jacob Biamonte, Zoltán Zimborás</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 10 2019</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) is considered to be one of the most promising approaches towards using near-term quantum computers for practical application. In its original form, the algorithm applies two different Hamiltonians, called the mixer and the cost Hamiltonian, in alternation with the goal being to approach the ground state of the cost Hamiltonian. Recently, it has been suggested that one might use such a set-up as a parametric quantum circuit with possibly some other goal than reaching ground states. From this perspective, a recent work [S. Lloyd, arXiv:1812.11075] argued that for one-dimensional local cost Hamiltonians, composed of nearest neighbor ZZ terms, this set-up is quantum computationally universal, i.e., all unitaries can be reached up to arbitrary precision. In the present paper, we give the complete proof of this statement and the precise conditions under which such a one-dimensional QAOA might be considered universal. We further generalize this type of universality for certain cost Hamiltonians with ZZ and ZZZ terms arranged according to the adjacency structure of certain graphs and hypergraphs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Playing Games with Multiple Access Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.02479</link>
    <author>Felix Leditzky, Mohammad A. Alhejji, Joshua Levin, Graeme Smith</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 06 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Communication networks have multiple users, each sending and receiving messages. A multiple access channel (MAC) models multiple senders transmitting to a single receiver, such as the uplink from many mobile phones to a single base station. The optimal performance of a MAC is quantified by a capacity region of simultaneously achievable communication rates. We study the two-sender classical MAC, the simplest and best-understood network, and find a surprising richness in both a classical and quantum context. First, we find that quantum entanglement shared between senders can substantially boost the capacity of a classical MAC. Second, we find that optimal performance of a MAC with bounded-size inputs may require unbounded amounts of entanglement. Third, determining whether a perfect communication rate is achievable using finite-dimensional entanglement is undecidable. Finally, we show that evaluating the capacity region of a two-sender classical MAC is in fact NP-hard.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Alibaba Cloud Quantum Development Platform: Applications to Quantum Algorithm Design</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.02559</link>
    <author>Cupjin Huang, Mario Szegedy, Fang Zhang, Xun Gao, Jianxin Chen, Yaoyun Shi</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 06 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We report our work on the Alibaba Cloud Quantum Development Platform (AC-QDP). The capability of AC-QDP's computational engine was already reported in \citeCZH+18, ZHN+19.In this follow-up article, we demonstrate with figures how AC-QDP helps in testing large-scale quantum algorithms (currently within the QAOA framework). We give new benchmark results on regular graphs. AC-QDP's QAOA framework can simulate thousands of qubits for up to $4$ layers. Then we discuss two interesting use cases we have implemented on the platform: 1. Optimal QAOA sequences for small-cycle free graphs; 2. Graph structure discovery.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal limitations on implementing resourceful unitary evolutions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.01336</link>
    <author>Ryuji Takagi, Hiroyasu Tajima</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We derive a fundamental trade-off relation between accuracy of implementing a desired unitary evolution using a restricted set of free unitaries and the size of the assisting system, in terms of the resource generating/losing capacity of the target unitary. In particular, this relation implies that, for any theory that is equipped with a resource measure satisfying lenient conditions, any resource changing unitary cannot be perfectly implemented by a free unitary applied to system and environment if the environment has finite dimensions. Our results are applicable to a wide class of resources including energy, asymmetry, coherence, entanglement, and magic, imposing ultimate limitations inherent in those important physical settings, as well as providing new insights into operational restrictions in general resource theories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing Clifford gate generation for measurement-only topological quantum computation with Majorana zero modes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03002</link>
    <author>Alan Tran, Alex Bocharov, Bela Bauer, Parsa Bonderson</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 09 2019</pubDate>
    <description>One of the main challenges for quantum computation is that while the number of gates required to perform a non-trivial quantum computation may be very large, decoherence and errors in realistic quantum architectures limits the number of physical gate operations that can be performed coherently. Therefore, an optimal mapping of the quantum algorithm into the physically available set of operations is of crucial importance. We examine this problem for a measurement-only topological quantum computer based on Majorana zero modes, where gates are performed through sequences of measurements. Such a scheme has been proposed as a practical, scalable approach to process quantum information in an array of topological qubits built using Majorana zero modes. Building on previous work that has shown that multi-qubit Clifford gates can be enacted in a topologically protected fashion in such qubit networks, we discuss methods to obtain the optimal measurement sequence for a given Clifford gate under the constraints imposed by the physical architecture, such as layout and the relative difficulty of implementing different types of measurements. Our methods also provide tools for comparative analysis of different architectures and strategies, given experimental characterizations of particular aspects of the systems under consideration.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generalized topological state-sum constructions and their universality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03031</link>
    <author>Andreas Bauer</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 09 2019</pubDate>
    <description>We formalize and generalize the concept of a topological state-sum construction using the language of tensor networks. We give examples for constructions that are possibly more general than all state-sum constructions in the literature that we are aware of. In particular we propose a state-sum construction that is universal in the sense that it can emulate every other state-sum construction. Physically, state-sum models in $n$ dimensions correspond to fixed point models for topological phases of matter in $n$ space-time dimensions. We conjecture that our universal state-sum construction contains fixed point models for topological phases that are not captured by known constructions. In particular we demonstrate that, unlike common state-sum constructions, the construction is compatible with the absence of gapped boundaries and commuting-projector Hamiltonians in $2+1$-dimensional chiral topological phases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>General framework for verifying pure quantum states in the adversarial scenario</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.01943</link>
    <author>Huangjun Zhu, Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2019</pubDate>
    <description>Bipartite and multipartite entangled states are of central interest in quantum information processing and foundational studies. Efficient verification of these states, especially in the adversarial scenario, is a key to various applications, including quantum computation, quantum simulation, and quantum networks. However, little is know about this topic in the adversarial scenario. Here we initiate a systematic study of pure-state verification in the adversarial scenario. In particular, we introduce a general method for determining the minimal number of tests required by a given strategy to achieve a given precision. In the case of homogeneous strategies, we can even derive an analytical formula. Furthermore, we propose a general recipe to verifying pure quantum states in the adversarial scenario by virtue of protocols for the nonadversarial scenario. Thanks to this recipe, the resource cost for verifying an arbitrary pure state in the adversarial scenario is comparable to the counterpart for the nonadversarial scenario, and the overhead is at most three times for high-precision verification. Our recipe can readily be applied to efficiently verify bipartite pure states, stabilizer states, hypergraph states, weighted graph states, and Dicke states in the adversarial scenario.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>
