<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Suppressing quantum errors by scaling a surface code logical qubit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.06431</link>
    <author>Rajeev Acharya, Igor Aleiner, Richard Allen, Trond I. Andersen, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Joao Basso, Andreas Bengtsson, Sergio Boixo, Gina Bortoli, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, Leon Brill, Michael Broughton, et al (137)</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Practical quantum computing will require error rates that are well below what is achievable with physical qubits. Quantum error correction offers a path to algorithmically-relevant error rates by encoding logical qubits within many physical qubits, where increasing the number of physical qubits enhances protection against physical errors. However, introducing more qubits also increases the number of error sources, so the density of errors must be sufficiently low in order for logical performance to improve with increasing code size. Here, we report the measurement of logical qubit performance scaling across multiple code sizes, and demonstrate that our system of superconducting qubits has sufficient performance to overcome the additional errors from increasing qubit number. We find our distance-5 surface code logical qubit modestly outperforms an ensemble of distance-3 logical qubits on average, both in terms of logical error probability over 25 cycles and logical error per cycle ($2.914\%\pm 0.016\%$ compared to $3.028\%\pm 0.023\%$). To investigate damaging, low-probability error sources, we run a distance-25 repetition code and observe a $1.7\times10^{-6}$ logical error per round floor set by a single high-energy event ($1.6\times10^{-7}$ when excluding this event). We are able to accurately model our experiment, and from this model we can extract error budgets that highlight the biggest challenges for future systems. These results mark the first experimental demonstration where quantum error correction begins to improve performance with increasing qubit number, illuminating the path to reaching the logical error rates required for computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A single $T$-gate makes distribution learning hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03140</link>
    <author>Marcel Hinsche, Marios Ioannou, Alexander Nietner, Jonas Haferkamp, Yihui Quek, Dominik Hangleiter, Jean-Pierre Seifert, Jens Eisert, Ryan Sweke</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The task of learning a probability distribution from samples is ubiquitous across the natural sciences. The output distributions of local quantum circuits form a particularly interesting class of distributions, of key importance both to quantum advantage proposals and a variety of quantum machine learning algorithms. In this work, we provide an extensive characterization of the learnability of the output distributions of local quantum circuits. Our first result yields insight into the relationship between the efficient learnability and the efficient simulatability of these distributions. Specifically, we prove that the density modelling problem associated with Clifford circuits can be efficiently solved, while for depth $d=n^{\Omega(1)}$ circuits the injection of a single $T$-gate into the circuit renders this problem hard. This result shows that efficient simulatability does not imply efficient learnability. Our second set of results provides insight into the potential and limitations of quantum generative modelling algorithms. We first show that the generative modelling problem associated with depth $d=n^{\Omega(1)}$ local quantum circuits is hard for any learning algorithm, classical or quantum. As a consequence, one cannot use a quantum algorithm to gain a practical advantage for this task. We then show that, for a wide variety of the most practically relevant learning algorithms -- including hybrid-quantum classical algorithms -- even the generative modelling problem associated with depth $d=\omega(\log(n))$ Clifford circuits is hard. This result places limitations on the applicability of near-term hybrid quantum-classical generative modelling algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A rapidly mixing Markov chain from any gapped quantum many-body system</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07044</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Giuseppe Carleo, David Gosset, Yinchen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the computational task of sampling a bit string $x$ from a distribution $\pi(x)=|\langle x|\psi\rangle|^2$, where $\psi$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian $H$. Our main result describes a direct link between the inverse spectral gap of $H$ and the mixing time of an associated continuous-time Markov Chain with steady state $\pi$. The Markov Chain can be implemented efficiently whenever ratios of ground state amplitudes $\langle y|\psi\rangle/\langle x|\psi\rangle$ are efficiently computable and the starting state of the chain satisfies a mild technical condition that can be efficiently checked. This extends a previously known relationship between sign-problem free Hamiltonians and Markov chains. The tool which enables this generalization is the so-called fixed-node Hamiltonian construction, previously used in Quantum Monte Carlo simulations to address the fermionic sign problem. We implement the proposed sampling algorithm numerically and use it to sample from the ground state of Haldane-Shastry Hamiltonian with up to 56 qubits. We observe empirically that our Markov chain based on the fixed-node Hamiltonian mixes more rapidly than the standard Metropolis-Hastings Markov chain.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time-energy uncertainty relation for noisy quantum metrology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13707</link>
    <author>Philippe Faist, Mischa P. Woods, Victor V. Albert, Joseph M. Renes, Jens Eisert, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Detection of weak forces and precise measurement of time are two of the many applications of quantum metrology to science and technology. We consider a quantum system initialized in a pure state and whose evolution is goverened by a Hamiltonian $H$; a measurement can later estimate the time $t$ for which the system has evolved. In this work, we introduce and study a fundamental trade-off which relates the amount by which noise reduces the accuracy of a quantum clock to the amount of information about the energy of the clock that leaks to the environment. Specifically, we consider an idealized scenario in which Alice prepares an initial pure state of the clock, allows the clock to evolve for a time $t$ that is not precisely known, and then transmits the clock through a noisy channel to Bob. The environment (Eve) receives any information that is lost. We prove that Bob's loss of quantum Fisher information (QFI) about $t$ is equal to Eve's gain of QFI about a complementary energy parameter. We also prove a more general trade-off that applies when Bob and Eve wish to estimate the values of parameters associated with two non-commuting observables. We derive the necessary and sufficient conditions for the accuracy of the clock to be unaffected by the noise. These are a subset of the Knill-Laflamme error-correction conditions; states satisfying these conditions are said to form a metrological code. We provide a scheme to construct metrological codes in the stabilizer formalism. We show that there are metrological codes that cannot be written as a quantum error-correcting code with similar distance in which the Hamiltonian acts as a logical operator, potentially offering new schemes for constructing states that do not lose any sensitivity upon application of a noisy channel. We discuss applications of our results to sensing using a many-body state subject to erasure or amplitude-damping noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved Hardness Results for the Guided Local Hamiltonian Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.10250</link>
    <author>Sevag Gharibian, Ryu Hayakawa, François Le Gall, Tomoyuki Morimae</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Estimating the ground state energy of a local Hamiltonian is a central problem in quantum chemistry. In order to further investigate its complexity and the potential of quantum algorithms for quantum chemistry, Gharibian and Le Gall (STOC 2022) recently introduced the guided local Hamiltonian problem (GLH), which is a variant of the local Hamiltonian problem where an approximation of a ground state is given as an additional input. Gharibian and Le Gall showed quantum advantage (more precisely, BQP-completeness) for GLH with $6$-local Hamiltonians when the guiding vector has overlap (inverse-polynomially) close to 1/2 with a ground state. In this paper, we optimally improve both the locality and the overlap parameters: we show that this quantum advantage (BQP-completeness) persists even with 2-local Hamiltonians, and even when the guiding vector has overlap (inverse-polynomially) close to 1 with a ground state. Moreover, we show that the quantum advantage also holds for 2-local physically motivated Hamiltonians on a 2D square lattice. This makes a further step towards establishing practical quantum advantage in quantum chemistry.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matchgate Shadows for Fermionic Quantum Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13723</link>
    <author>Kianna Wan, William J. Huggins, Joonho Lee, Ryan Babbush</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>"Classical shadows" are estimators of an unknown quantum state, constructed from suitably distributed random measurements on copies of that state [Nature Physics 16, 1050-1057]. Here, we analyze classical shadows obtained using random matchgate circuits, which correspond to fermionic Gaussian unitaries. We prove that the first three moments of the Haar distribution over the continuous group of matchgate circuits are equal to those of the discrete uniform distribution over only the matchgate circuits that are also Clifford unitaries; thus, the latter forms a "matchgate 3-design." This implies that the classical shadows resulting from the two ensembles are functionally equivalent. We show how one can use these matchgate shadows to efficiently estimate inner products between an arbitrary quantum state and fermionic Gaussian states, as well as the expectation values of local fermionic operators and various other quantities, thus surpassing the capabilities of prior work. As a concrete application, this enables us to apply wavefunction constraints that control the fermion sign problem in the quantum-classical auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm (QC-AFQMC) [Nature 603, 416-420], without the exponential post-processing cost incurred by the original approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complexity of the Guided Local Hamiltonian Problem: Improved Parameters and Extension to Excited States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.10097</link>
    <author>Chris Cade, Marten Folkertsma, Jordi Weggemans</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently it was shown that the so-called guided local Hamiltonian problem -- estimating the smallest eigenvalue of a $k$-local Hamiltonian when provided with a description of a quantum state ('guiding state') that is guaranteed to have substantial overlap with the true groundstate -- is BQP-complete for $k \geq 6$ when the required precision is inverse polynomial in the system size $n$, and remains hard even when the overlap of the guiding state with the groundstate is close to a constant $\left(\frac12 - \Omega\left(\frac{1}{\mathop{poly}(n)}\right)\right)$. We improve upon this result in three ways: by showing that it remains BQP-complete when i) the Hamiltonian is 2-local, ii) the overlap between the guiding state and target eigenstate is as large as $1 - \Omega\left(\frac{1}{\mathop{poly}(n)}\right)$, and iii) when one is interested in estimating energies of excited states, rather than just the groundstate. Interestingly, iii) is only made possible by first showing that ii) holds.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Conservation laws and quantum error correction: towards a generalised matching decoder</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.06428</link>
    <author>Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A decoding algorithm is essential to any fault-tolerant quantum-computing architecture. In this perspective we explore decoding algorithms for the surface code; a prototypical quantum low-density parity-check code that underlies many of the leading efforts to demonstrate scalable quantum computing. Central to our discussion is the minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder. The decoder works by exploiting underlying structure that arises due to materialised symmetries among surface-code stabilizer elements. By concentrating on these symmetries, we begin to address the question of how a minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder might be generalised for other types of code. We approach this question first by investigating examples of matching decoders for other codes. These include decoding algorithms that have been specialised to correct for noise models that demonstrate a particular structure or bias with respect to certain types of code. In addition to this, we propose a systematic way of constructing a minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder for codes with certain characteristic properties. The properties we make use of are common among topological codes. We discuss the broader applicability of the proposal, and we suggest some questions we can address that may show us how to design a generalised matching decoder for arbitrary stabilizer codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fully undistillable quantum states are separable</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05193</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Nilanjana Datta</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Assume that Alice, Bob, and Eve share a tripartite pure state $|\psi_{ABE}\rangle$. We prove that if Alice cannot distill entanglement with either Bob or Eve using $|\psi_{ABE}\rangle$ and local operations with any one of the following configurations for classical communication: $(A\to B, A\leftrightarrow E), (A\leftrightarrow B, A\to E),$ and $(A\leftrightarrow B, A\leftrightarrow E)$, then the same is also true for the other two configurations. Moreover, this happens precisely when the state is such that both its reductions $\rho_{AB}$ and $\rho_{AE}$ are separable, which is further equivalent to the reductions being PPT. This, in particular, implies that any NPT bipartite state is such that either the state itself or its complement is 2-way distillable. In proving these results, we first obtain an explicit lower bound on the 2-way distillable entanglement of low rank bipartite states. Furthermore, we show that even though not all low rank states are 1-way distillable, a randomly sampled low rank state will almost surely be 1-way distillable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Emergent Quantum Mechanics at the Boundary of a Local Classical Lattice Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.09465</link>
    <author>Kevin Slagle, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We formulate a conceptually new model in which quantum mechanics emerges from classical mechanics. Given a local Hamiltonian $H$ acting on $n$ qubits, we define a local classical model with an additional spatial dimension whose boundary dynamics is described by Schrodinger's equation and $H$. The bulk consists of a lattice of classical bits that propagate towards the boundary through a circuit of stochastic matrices. The bits reaching the boundary are governed by a probability distribution whose deviation from the uniform distribution can be interpreted as the quantum-mechanical wavefunction. Bell nonlocality is achieved because information can move through the bulk much faster than the boundary speed of light. We analytically estimate how much the model deviates from quantum mechanics, and we validate these estimates using computer simulations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Super-exponential Quantum Speedup of Equivariant Quantum Machine Learning Algorithms with SU($d$) Symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07250</link>
    <author>Han Zheng, Zimu Li, Junyu Liu, Sergii Strelchuk, Risi Kondor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a framework of the equivariant convolutional algorithms which is tailored for a number of machine-learning tasks on physical systems with arbitrary SU($d$) symmetries. It allows us to enhance a natural model of quantum computation--permutational quantum computing (PQC) [Quantum Inf. Comput., 10, 470-497 (2010)] --and defines a more powerful model: PQC+. While PQC was shown to be effectively classically simulatable, we exhibit a problem which can be efficiently solved on PQC+ machine, whereas the best known classical algorithms runs in $O(n!n^2)$ time, thus providing strong evidence against PQC+ being classically simulatable. We further discuss practical quantum machine learning algorithms which can be carried out in the paradigm of PQC+.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Sublinear-Time Quantum Algorithm for Approximating Partition Functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08643</link>
    <author>Arjan Cornelissen, Yassine Hamoudi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a novel quantum algorithm for estimating Gibbs partition functions in sublinear time with respect to the logarithm of the size of the state space. This is the first speed-up of this type to be obtained over the seminal nearly-linear time algorithm of Štefankovič, Vempala and Vigoda [JACM, 2009]. Our result also preserves the quadratic speed-up in precision and spectral gap achieved in previous work by exploiting the properties of quantum Markov chains. As an application, we obtain new polynomial improvements over the best-known algorithms for computing the partition function of the Ising model, and counting the number of $k$-colorings, matchings or independent sets of a graph. Our approach relies on developing new variants of the quantum phase and amplitude estimation algorithms that return nearly unbiased estimates with low variance and without destroying their initial quantum state. We extend these subroutines into a nearly unbiased quantum mean estimator that reduces the variance quadratically faster than the classical empirical mean. No such estimator was known to exist prior to our work. These properties, which are of general interest, lead to better convergence guarantees within the paradigm of simulated annealing for computing partition functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The QAOA gets stuck starting from a good classical string</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05089</link>
    <author>Madelyn Cain, Edward Farhi, Sam Gutmann, Daniel Ranard, Eugene Tang</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) is designed to maximize a cost function over bit strings. While the initial state is traditionally a superposition over all strings, it is natural to try expediting the QAOA: first use a classical algorithm to produce some good string, and then run the ordinary QAOA starting in the computational basis state associated with that string. Here we report numerical experiments that this method of initializing the QAOA fails dramatically, exhibiting little to no improvement of the cost function. We investigate criteria for the rare instances in which there is any improvement at all, and we provide a statistical argument for the more typical case of no improvement. The statistical argument holds for any string that locally mimics the thermal ensemble at the appropriate temperature. Our numerical experiments indicate this property holds for typical good strings. We emphasize that our negative results only apply to our simple incarnation of the warm-start QAOA and may not apply to other approaches in the literature. We hope that our theoretical analysis will inform future algorithm design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Constant-cost implementations of Clifford operations and multiply controlled gates using global interactions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08691</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Dmitri Maslov, Yunseong Nam</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A frequent physical-level requirement for the ability to implement quantum operations simultaneously is their commutativity. In this work, we asked if quantum computation by commuting Ising-type entangling operations and ``free'' single-qubit gates can be advantageous compared to quantum computation by the two-qubit gates and ``free'' single-qubit gates. We focused on the elements of the Clifford group and the multiply controlled gates. It turned out that such circuits and composite gates can be implemented with very little effort -- using constantly or effectively constantly many blocks of commuting sets of gates, in all cases except some with the most severe restrictions on the number of ancillary qubits available. Specifically, we show constant-cost implementations of Clifford operations with and without ancilla, constant-cost implementation of the multiply controlled gates with linearly many ancillae, and an $O(\log^*(n))$ implementation of the $n$-controlled single-target gates using logarithmically many ancillae. This shows significant (asymptotic) improvement of circuits enabled by the global gates vs those over single- and two-qubit gates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>What is nonclassical about uncertainty relations?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11779</link>
    <author>Lorenzo Catani, Matthew Leifer, Giovanni Scala, David Schmid, Robert W. Spekkens</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Uncertainty relations express limits on the extent to which the outcomes of distinct measurements on a single state can be made jointly predictable. The existence of nontrivial uncertainty relations in quantum theory is generally considered to be a way in which it entails a departure from the classical worldview. However, this view is undermined by the fact that there exist operational theories which exhibit nontrivial uncertainty relations but which are consistent with the classical worldview insofar as they admit of a generalized-noncontextual ontological model. This prompts the question of what aspects of uncertainty relations, if any, cannot be realized in this way and so constitute evidence of genuine nonclassicality. We here consider uncertainty relations describing the tradeoff between the predictability of a pair of binary-outcome measurements (e.g., measurements of Pauli X and Pauli Z observables in quantum theory). We show that, for a class of theories satisfying a particular symmetry property, the functional form of this predictability tradeoff is constrained by noncontextuality to be below a linear curve. Because qubit quantum theory has the relevant symmetry property, the fact that it has a quadratic tradeoff between these predictabilities is a violation of this noncontextual bound, and therefore constitutes an example of how the functional form of an uncertainty relation can witness contextuality. We also deduce the implications for a selected group of operational foils to quantum theory and consider the generalization to three measurements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time-Efficient Constant-Space-Overhead Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08826</link>
    <author>Hayata Yamasaki, Masato Koashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Scalable realization of quantum computation to attain substantial speedups over classical computation requires fault tolerance. Conventionally, fault-tolerant quantum computation (FTQC) demands excessive space overhead of physical qubits per logical qubit. A more recent protocol to achieve constant-space-overhead FTQC using quantum low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes thus attracts considerable attention but suffers from another drawback: it incurs polynomially long time overhead. We construct an alternative avenue of FTQC to achieve constant space overhead and only quasi-polylogarithmic time overhead simultaneously via techniques for using concatenations of different quantum Hamming codes rather than quantum LDPC codes. Our protocol achieves FTQC even if a decoder has nonzero runtime, unlike the existing constant-space-overhead protocol. These results establish a foundation for realizing FTQC within feasibly bounded space overhead yet negligibly tiny slowdown.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Gauge Theory of Measurement-Based Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.10098</link>
    <author>Gabriel Wong, Robert Raussendorf, Bartlomiej Czech</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Measurement-Based Quantum Computation (MBQC) is a model of quantum computation, which uses local measurements instead of unitary gates. Here we explain that the MBQC procedure has a fundamental basis in an underlying gauge theory. This perspective provides a theoretical foundation for global aspects of MBQC. The gauge symmetry reflects the freedom of formulating the same MBQC computation in different local reference frames. The main identifications between MBQC and gauge theory concepts are: (i) the computational output of MBQC is a holonomy of the gauge field, (ii) the adaption of measurement basis that remedies the inherent randomness of quantum measurements is effected by gauge transformations. The gauge theory of MBQC also plays a role in characterizing the entanglement structure of symmetry-protected topologically (SPT) ordered states, which are resources for MBQC. Our framework situates MBQC in a broader context of condensed matter and high energy theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The classical cost of transmitting a qubit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02244</link>
    <author>Martin J. Renner, Armin Tavakoli, Marco Túlio Quintino</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider general prepare-and-measure scenarios in which Alice can transmit qubit states to Bob, who can perform general measurements in the form of positive operator-valued measures (POVMs). We show that the statistics obtained in any such quantum protocol can be simulated by the purely classical means of shared randomness and two bits of communication. Furthermore, we prove that two bits of communication is the minimal cost of a perfect classical simulation. In addition, we apply our methods to Bell scenarios, which extends the well-known Toner and Bacon protocol. In particular, two bits of communication are enough to simulate all quantum correlations associated to arbitrary local POVMs applied to any entangled two-qubit state.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum tomography using state-preparation unitaries</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08800</link>
    <author>Joran van Apeldoorn, Arjan Cornelissen, András Gilyén, Giacomo Nannicini</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe algorithms to obtain an approximate classical description of a $d$-dimensional quantum state when given access to a unitary (and its inverse) that prepares it. For pure states we characterize the query complexity for $\ell_q$-norm error up to logarithmic factors. As a special case, we show that it takes $\widetilde{\Theta}(d/\varepsilon)$ applications of the unitaries to obtain an $\varepsilon$-$\ell_2$-approximation of the state. For mixed states we consider a similar model, where the unitary prepares a purification of the state. In this model we give an efficient algorithm for obtaining Schatten $q$-norm estimates of a rank-$r$ mixed state, giving query upper bounds that are close to optimal. In particular, we show that a trace-norm ($q=1$) estimate can be obtained with $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(dr/\varepsilon)$ queries. This improves (assuming our stronger input model) the $\varepsilon$-dependence over the algorithm of Haah et al.\ (2017) that uses a joint measurement on $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(dr/\varepsilon^2)$ copies of the state. To our knowledge, the most sample-efficient results for pure-state tomography come from setting the rank to $1$ in generic mixed-state tomography algorithms, which can be computationally demanding. We describe sample-optimal algorithms for pure states that are easy and fast to implement. Along the way we show that an $\ell_\infty$-norm estimate of a normalized vector induces a (slightly worse) $\ell_q$-norm estimate for that vector, without losing a dimension-dependent factor in the precision. We also develop an unbiased and symmetric version of phase estimation, where the probability distribution of the estimate is centered around the true value. Finally, we give an efficient method for estimating multiple expectation values, improving over the recent result by Huggins et al.\ (2021) when the measurement operators do not fully overlap.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Linear programming with unitary-equivariant constraints</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05713</link>
    <author>Dmitry Grinko, Maris Ozols</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Unitary equivariance is a natural symmetry that occurs in many contexts in physics and mathematics. Optimization problems with such symmetry can often be formulated as semidefinite programs for a $d^{p+q}$-dimensional matrix variable that commutes with $U^{\otimes p} \otimes \bar{U}^{\otimes q}$, for all $U \in \mathrm{U}(d)$. Solving such problems naively can be prohibitively expensive even if $p+q$ is small but the local dimension $d$ is large. We show that, under additional symmetry assumptions, this problem reduces to a linear program that can be solved in time that does not scale in $d$, and we provide a general framework to execute this reduction under different types of symmetries. The key ingredient of our method is a compact parametrization of the solution space by linear combinations of walled Brauer algebra diagrams. This parametrization requires the idempotents of a Gelfand--Tsetlin basis, which we obtain by adapting a general method arXiv:1606.08900 inspired by the Okounkov--Vershik approach. To illustrate potential applications, we use several toy examples from quantum information: deciding the principal eigenvalue of a quantum state, quantum majority vote, and asymmetric cloning. We also outline a possible route for extending our method to general unitary-equivariant semidefinite programs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Amplitude Estimation from Quantum Signal Processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08628</link>
    <author>Patrick Rall, Bryce Fuller</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Amplitude estimation algorithms are based on Grover's algorithm: alternating reflections about the input state and the desired outcome. But what if we are given the ability to perform arbitrary rotations, instead of just reflections? In this situation, we find that quantum signal processing lets us estimate the amplitude in a more flexible way. We leverage this technique to give improved and simplified algorithms for many amplitude estimation tasks: we perform non-destructive estimation without any assumptions on the amplitude, develop an algorithm with improved performance in practice, present a new method for unbiased amplitude estimation, and finally give a simpler method for trading quantum circuit depth for more repetitions of short circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Uncertainty relations from graph theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02197</link>
    <author>Carlos de Gois, Kiara Hansenne, Otfried Gühne</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum measurements are inherently probabilistic. Further defying our classical intuition, quantum theory often forbids us to precisely determine the outcomes of simultaneous measurements. This phenomenon is captured and quantified through uncertainty relations. Although studied since the inception of quantum theory, this problem of determining the possible expectation values of a collection of quantum measurements remains, in general, unsolved. By constructing a close connection between observables and graph theory, we derive uncertainty relations valid for any set of dichotomic observables. These relations are, in many cases, tight, and related to the size of the maximum clique of the associated graph. As applications, they can be straightforwardly used to build entropic uncertainty relations, separability criteria and entanglement witnesses.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying Nonstabilizerness of Matrix Product States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13076</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, Lorenzo Piroli</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Nonstabilizerness, also known as magic, quantifies the number of non-Clifford operations needed in order to prepare a quantum state. As typical measures either involve minimization procedures or a computational cost exponential in the number of qubits $N$, it is notoriously hard to characterize for many-body states. In this work, we show that nonstabilizerness, as quantified by the recently introduced Stabilizer Rényi Entropies (SREs), can be computed efficiently for matrix product states (MPSs). Specifically, given an MPS of bond-dimension $\chi$ and integer Rényi index $n>1$, we show that the SRE can be expressed in terms of the norm of an MPS with bond-dimension $\chi^{2n}$. For translation-invariant states, this allows us to extract magic from a single tensor, the transfer matrix, while for generic MPSs this construction yields a computational cost linear in $N$ and polynomial in $\chi$. We exploit this observation to revisit the study of ground-state magic in the quantum Ising chain, providing accurate numerical results up to large system sizes. We analyze the SRE near criticality and investigate its dependence on the local computational basis. We show that it is in general not maximal at the critical point, and interpret our findings in terms of ``long-range magic''.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Finite-rate sparse quantum codes aplenty</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03562</link>
    <author>Maxime Tremblay, Guillaume Duclos-Cianci, Stefanos Kourtis</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a methodology for generating random multi-qubit stabilizer codes based on solving a constraint satisfaction problem (CSP) on random bipartite graphs. This framework allows us to enforce stabilizer commutation, X/Z balancing, finite rate, sparsity, and maximum-degree constraints simultaneously in a CSP that we can then solve numerically. Using a state-of-the-art CSP solver, we obtain convincing evidence for the existence of a satisfiability threshold. Furthermore, the extent of the satisfiable phase increases with the number of qubits. In that phase, finding sparse codes becomes an easy problem. Moreover, we observe that the sparse codes found in the satisfiable phase practically achieve the channel capacity for erasure noise. Our results show that intermediate-size finite-rate sparse quantum codes are easy to find, while also demonstrating a flexible methodology for generating good codes with custom properties. We therefore establish a complete and customizable pipeline for random quantum code discovery that can be geared towards near to mid-term quantum processor layouts.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Preparing Many Copies of a Quantum State in the Black-Box Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11014</link>
    <author>Yassine Hamoudi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a simple quantum algorithm for preparing $K$ copies of an $N$-dimensional quantum state whose amplitudes are given by a quantum oracle. Our result extends a previous work of Grover, who showed how to prepare one copy in time $O(\sqrt{N})$. In comparison with the naive $O(K\sqrt{N})$ solution obtained by repeating this procedure~$K$ times, our algorithm achieves the optimal running time of $\theta(\sqrt{KN})$. Our technique uses a refinement of the quantum rejection sampling method employed by Grover. As a direct application, we obtain a similar speed-up for obtaining $K$ independent samples from a distribution whose probability vector is given by a quantum oracle.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing and Learning Quantum Juntas Nearly Optimally</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05898</link>
    <author>Thomas Chen, Shivam Nadimpalli, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of testing and learning quantum $k$-juntas: $n$-qubit unitary matrices which act non-trivially on just $k$ of the $n$ qubits and as the identity on the rest. As our main algorithmic results, we give (a) a $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{k})$-query quantum algorithm that can distinguish quantum $k$-juntas from unitary matrices that are "far" from every quantum $k$-junta; and (b) a $O(4^k)$-query algorithm to learn quantum $k$-juntas. We complement our upper bounds for testing quantum $k$-juntas and learning quantum $k$-juntas with near-matching lower bounds of $\Omega(\sqrt{k})$ and $\Omega(\frac{4^k}{k})$, respectively. Our techniques are Fourier-analytic and make use of a notion of influence of qubits on unitaries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Publicly verifiable quantum money from random lattices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13135</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu, Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Publicly verifiable quantum money is a protocol for the preparation of quantum states that can be efficiently verified by any party for authenticity but is computationally infeasible to counterfeit. We develop a cryptographic scheme for publicly verifiable quantum money based on Gaussian superpositions over random lattices. We introduce a verification-of-authenticity procedure based on the lattice discrete Fourier transform, and subsequently prove the unforgeability of our quantum money under the hardness of the short vector problem from lattice-based cryptography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Syndrome-Derived Error Rates as a Benchmark of Quantum Hardware</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00553</link>
    <author>James R. Wootton</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correcting codes are designed to pinpoint exactly when and where errors occur in quantum circuits. This feature is the foundation of their primary task: to support fault-tolerant quantum computation. However, this feature could used as the basis of benchmarking: By analyzing the outputs of even small-scale quantum error correction circuits, a detailed picture can be constructed of error processes across a quantum device. Here we perform an example of such an analysis, using the results of small repetition codes to determine the error rate of each qubit while idle during a syndrome measurement. This provides an idea of the errors experienced by the qubits across a device while they are part of the kind of circuit that we expect to be typical in fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14280</link>
    <author>Matthew P. A. Fisher, Vedika Khemani, Adam Nahum, Sagar Vijay</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum circuits -- built from local unitary gates and local measurements -- are a new playground for quantum many-body physics and a tractable setting to explore universal collective phenomena far-from-equilibrium. These models have shed light on longstanding questions about thermalization and chaos, and on the underlying universal dynamics of quantum information and entanglement. In addition, such models generate new sets of questions and give rise to phenomena with no traditional analog, such as new dynamical phases in quantum systems that are monitored by an external observer. Quantum circuit dynamics is also topical in view of experimental progress in building digital quantum simulators that allow control of precisely these ingredients. Randomness in the circuit elements allows a high level of theoretical control, with a key theme being mappings between real-time quantum dynamics and effective classical lattice models or dynamical processes. Many of the universal phenomena that can be identified in this tractable setting apply to much wider classes of more structured many-body dynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classification of measurement-based quantum wire in stabilizer PEPS</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00616</link>
    <author>Paul Herringer, Robert Raussendorf</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a class of translation-invariant 2D tensor network states with a stabilizer symmetry, which we call stabilizer PEPS. The cluster state, GHZ state, and states in the toric code belong to this class. We investigate the transmission capacity of stabilizer PEPS for measurement-based quantum wire, and arrive at a complete classification of transmission behaviors. The transmission behaviors fall into 13 classes, one of which corresponds to Clifford quantum cellular automata. In addition, we identify 12 other classes.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>