<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Early Days of Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09964</link>
    <author>Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I recount some of my memories of the early development of quantum computation, including the discovery of the factoring algorithm, of error correcting codes, and of fault tolerance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Physics of Quantum Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08064</link>
    <author>John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Rapid ongoing progress in quantum information science makes this an apt time for a Solvay Conference focused on The Physics of Quantum Information. Here I review four intertwined themes encompassed by this topic: Quantum computer science, quantum hardware, quantum matter, and quantum gravity. Though the time scale for broad practical impact of quantum computation is still uncertain, in the near future we can expect noteworthy progress toward scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing, and discoveries enabled by programmable quantum simulators. In the longer term, controlling highly complex quantum matter will open the door to profound scientific advances and powerful new technologies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A mathematical framework for quantum Hamiltonian simulation and duality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11941</link>
    <author>Harriet Apel, Toby Cubitt</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Analogue Hamiltonian simulation is a promising near-term application of quantum computing and has recently been put on a theoretical footing. In Hamiltonian simulation, a physical Hamiltonian is engineered to have identical physics to another - often very different - Hamiltonian. This is qualitatively similar to the notion of duality in physics, whereby two superficially different theories are mathematically equivalent in some precise sense. However, existing characterisations of Hamiltonian simulations are not sufficiently general to extend to all dualities in physics. In particular, they cannot encompass the important cases of strong/weak and high-temperature/low-temperature dualities. In this work, we give three physically motivated axiomatisations of duality, formulated respectively in terms of observables, partition functions and entropies. We prove that these axiomatisations are equivalent, and characterise the mathematical form that any duality satisfying these axioms must take. A building block in one of our results is a strengthening of earlier results on entropy-preserving maps to maps that are entropy-preserving up to an additive constant, which we prove decompose as a direct sum of unitary and anti-unitary components, which may be of independent mathematical interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Wasserstein Complexity of Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06306</link>
    <author>Lu Li, Kaifeng Bu, Dax Enshan Koh, Arthur Jaffe, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a unitary transformation, what is the size of the smallest quantum circuit that implements it? This quantity, known as the quantum circuit complexity, is a fundamental property of quantum evolutions that has widespread applications in many fields, including quantum computation, quantum field theory, and black hole physics. In this letter, we obtain a new lower bound for the quantum circuit complexity in terms of a novel complexity measure that we propose for quantum circuits, which we call the quantum Wasserstein complexity. Our proposed measure is based on the quantum Wasserstein distance of order one (also called the quantum earth mover's distance), a metric on the space of quantum states. We also prove several fundamental and important properties of our new complexity measure, which stand to be of independent interest. Finally, we show that our new measure also provides a lower bound for the experimental cost of implementing quantum circuits, which implies a quantum limit on converting quantum resources to computational resources. Our results provide novel applications of the quantum Wasserstein distance and pave the way for a deeper understanding of the resources needed to implement a quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadows of fermions with particle number symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08964</link>
    <author>Guang Hao Low</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider classical shadows of fermion wavefunctions with $\eta$ particles occupying $n$ modes. We prove that of all $k$-reduced density matrices may be simultaneously estimated to an average variance of $\epsilon^{2}$ using at most $\binom{\eta}{k}\big(1-\frac{\eta-k}{n}\big)^{k}\frac{1+n}{1+n-k}/\epsilon^{2}$ measurements in random single-particle bases that conserve particle number, and provide an estimator that is computationally efficient. This is a super-exponential improvement over the $\binom{n}{k}\sqrt{\pi k}/\epsilon^{2}$ scaling of prior approaches as $n$ can be arbitrarily larger than $\eta$ in natural problems. Our method, in the worst-case of half-filling, still provides a factor of $4^{k}$ advantage in sample complexity, and also estimates all $\eta$-reduced density matrices, applicable to estimating overlaps with all single Slater determinants, with at most $\frac{4}{3}/\epsilon^{2}$ samples, which is additionally independent of $\eta$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal algorithms for learning quantum phase states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07851</link>
    <author>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Sergey Bravyi, Arkopal Dutt, Theodore J. Yoder</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the complexity of learning $n$-qubit quantum phase states. A degree-$d$ phase state is defined as a superposition of all $2^n$ basis vectors $x$ with amplitudes proportional to $(-1)^{f(x)}$, where $f$ is a degree-$d$ Boolean polynomial over $n$ variables. We show that the sample complexity of learning an unknown degree-$d$ phase state is $\Theta(n^d)$ if we allow separable measurements and $\Theta(n^{d-1})$ if we allow entangled measurements. Our learning algorithm based on separable measurements has runtime $\textsf{poly}(n)$ (for constant $d$) and is well-suited for near-term demonstrations as it requires only single-qubit measurements in the Pauli $X$ and $Z$ bases. We show similar bounds on the sample complexity for learning generalized phase states with complex-valued amplitudes. We further consider learning phase states when $f$ has sparsity-$s$, degree-$d$ in its $\mathbb{F}_2$ representation (with sample complexity $O(2^d sn)$), $f$ has Fourier-degree-$t$ (with sample complexity $O(2^{2t})$), and learning quadratic phase states with $\varepsilon$-global depolarizing noise (with sample complexity $O(n^{1+\varepsilon})$). These learning algorithms give us a procedure to learn the diagonal unitaries of the Clifford hierarchy and IQP circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Inevitability of knowing less than nothing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14424</link>
    <author>Gilad Gour, Mark M. Wilde, Sarah Brandsen, Isabelle Jianing Geng</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A colloquial interpretation of entropy is that it is the knowledge gained upon learning the outcome of a random experiment. Conditional entropy is then interpreted as the knowledge gained upon learning the outcome of one random experiment after learning the outcome of another, possibly statistically dependent, random experiment. In the classical world, entropy and conditional entropy take only non-negative values, consistent with the intuition that one has regarding the aforementioned interpretations. However, for certain entangled states, one obtains negative values when evaluating commonly accepted and information-theoretically justified formulas for the quantum conditional entropy, leading to the confounding conclusion that one can know less than nothing in the quantum world. Here, we introduce a physically motivated framework for defining quantum conditional entropy, based on two simple postulates inspired by the second law of thermodynamics (non-decrease of entropy) and extensivity of entropy, and we argue that all plausible definitions of quantum conditional entropy should respect these two postulates. We then prove that all plausible quantum conditional entropies take on negative values for certain entangled states, so that it is inevitable that one can know less than nothing in the quantum world. All of our arguments are based on constructions of physical processes that respect the first postulate, the one inspired by the second law of thermodynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mean estimation when you have the source code; or, quantum Monte Carlo methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07544</link>
    <author>Robin Kothari, Ryan O'Donnell</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Suppose $\boldsymbol{y}$ is a real random variable, and one is given access to ``the code'' that generates it (for example, a randomized or quantum circuit whose output is $\boldsymbol{y}$). We give a quantum procedure that runs the code $O(n)$ times and returns an estimate $\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}}$ for $\mu = \mathrm{E}[\boldsymbol{y}]$ that with high probability satisfies $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/n$, where $\sigma = \mathrm{stddev}[\boldsymbol{y}]$. This dependence on $n$ is optimal for quantum algorithms. One may compare with classical algorithms, which can only achieve the quadratically worse $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/\sqrt{n}$. Our method improves upon previous works, which either made additional assumptions about $\boldsymbol{y}$, and/or assumed the algorithm knew an a priori bound on $\sigma$, and/or used additional logarithmic factors beyond $O(n)$. The central subroutine for our result is essentially Grover's algorithm but with complex phases.ally Grover's algorithm but with complex phases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Solving boolean satisfiability problems with the quantum approximate optimization algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06909</link>
    <author>Sami Boulebnane, Ashley Montanaro</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) is one of the most prominent proposed applications for near-term quantum computing. Here we study the ability of QAOA to solve hard constraint satisfaction problems, as opposed to optimization problems. We focus on the fundamental boolean satisfiability problem, in the form of random $k$-SAT. We develop analytic bounds on the average success probability of QAOA over random boolean formulae at the satisfiability threshold, as the number of variables $n$ goes to infinity. The bounds hold for fixed parameters and when $k$ is a power of 2. We complement these theoretical results with numerical results on the performance of QAOA for small $n$, showing that these match the limiting theoretical bounds closely. We then use these results to compare QAOA with leading classical solvers. In the case of random 8-SAT, we find that for around 14 ansatz layers, QAOA matches the scaling performance of the highest-performance classical solver we tested, WalkSATlm. For larger numbers of layers, QAOA outperforms WalkSATlm, with an ultimate level of advantage that is still to be determined. Our methods provide a framework for analysing the performance of QAOA for hard constraint satisfaction problems and finding further speedups over classical algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure qubits: Overcoming the $T_1$ limit in superconducting circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05461</link>
    <author>Aleksander Kubica, Arbel Haim, Yotam Vaknin, Fernando Brandão, Alex Retzker</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The amplitude damping time, $T_1$, has long stood as the major factor limiting quantum fidelity in superconducting circuits, prompting concerted efforts in the material science and design of qubits aimed at increasing $T_1$. In contrast, the dephasing time, $T_{\phi}$, can usually be extended above $T_1$ (via, e.g., dynamical decoupling), to the point where it does not limit fidelity. In this article we propose a scheme for overcoming the conventional $T_1$ limit on fidelity by designing qubits in a way that amplitude damping errors can be detected and converted into erasure errors. Compared to standard qubit implementations our scheme improves the performance of fault-tolerant protocols, as numerically demonstrated by the circuit-noise simulations of the surface code. We describe two simple qubit implementations with superconducting circuits and discuss procedures for detecting amplitude damping errors, performing entangling gates, and extending $T_\phi$. Our results suggest that engineering efforts should focus on improving $T_\phi$ and the quality of quantum coherent control, as they effectively become the limiting factor on the performance of fault-tolerant protocols.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal sample lower bounds for quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09178</link>
    <author>Ryuji Takagi, Hiroyasu Tajima, Mile Gu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Although numerous quantum error-mitigation protocols have been proposed as means to suppress noise effects on intermediate-scale quantum devices, their general potential and limitations have still been elusive. In particular, to understand the ultimate feasibility of quantum error mitigation, it is crucial to characterize the fundamental sampling cost -- how many times an arbitrary mitigation protocol must run a noisy quantum device. Here, we establish universal lower bounds on the sampling cost for quantum error mitigation to achieve the desired accuracy with high probability. Our bounds apply to general mitigation protocols, including the ones involving nonlinear postprocessing. We further show that the number of samples required for a wide class of protocols to mitigate errors in layered circuits must grow exponentially with the circuit depth for various noise models, revealing the fundamental obstacles in showing useful applications of noisy near-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal cost bound of quantum error mitigation based on quantum estimation theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09385</link>
    <author>Kento Tsubouchi, Takahiro Sagawa, Nobuyuki Yoshioka</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation is an art to combat noise in quantum computers that are not fully fault tolerant. While a wide variety of techniques has been proposed with surging number of experimental applications, little is known concerning the unified understanding on their fundamental aspects. In this paper, we perform a theoretical analysis on the cost of quantum error mitigation using the quantum estimation theory. The applicability of quantum estimation theory is extended so that we can analyze the quantum Fisher information of layered noisy quantum circuits equipped with a wide range of quantum error mitigation methods. By showing that the quantum Fisher information decays exponentially with the circuit depth, we derive for a general class of Markovian noise that unbiased estimation of an observable encounters an exponential growth in the lower bound on the measurement cost, or more precisely the required number of copies of noisy quantum state. As two practical and illustrative examples, we discuss the case when the noise channel is solely the global or local depolarizing noise. We explicitly express the lower bound in terms of their noise rates, and further find that we can asymptotically saturate the bound by a simple mitigation technique for the global depolarizing noise. Our results not only reveal the physical limitations of quantum error mitigation, but may also provide a new criteria for performance evaluation of quantum error mitigation techniques.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Synergy Between Quantum Circuits and Tensor Networks: Short-cutting the Race to Practical Quantum Advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13673</link>
    <author>Manuel S. Rudolph, Jacob Miller, Jing Chen, Atithi Acharya, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While recent breakthroughs have proven the ability of noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices to achieve quantum advantage in classically-intractable sampling tasks, the use of these devices for solving more practically relevant computational problems remains a challenge. Proposals for attaining practical quantum advantage typically involve parametrized quantum circuits (PQCs), whose parameters can be optimized to find solutions to diverse problems throughout quantum simulation and machine learning. However, training PQCs for real-world problems remains a significant practical challenge, largely due to the phenomenon of barren plateaus in the optimization landscapes of randomly-initialized quantum circuits. In this work, we introduce a scalable procedure for harnessing classical computing resources to determine task-specific initializations of PQCs, which we show significantly improves the trainability and performance of PQCs on a variety of problems. Given a specific optimization task, this method first utilizes tensor network (TN) simulations to identify a promising quantum state, which is then converted into gate parameters of a PQC by means of a high-performance decomposition procedure. We show that this task-specific initialization avoids barren plateaus, and effectively translates increases in classical resources to enhanced performance and speed in training quantum circuits. By demonstrating a means of boosting limited quantum resources using classical computers, our approach illustrates the promise of this synergy between quantum and quantum-inspired models in quantum computing, and opens up new avenues to harness the power of modern quantum hardware for realizing practical quantum advantage.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exponential concentration and untrainability in quantum kernel methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11060</link>
    <author>Supanut Thanasilp, Samson Wang, M. Cerezo, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Kernel methods in Quantum Machine Learning (QML) have recently gained significant attention as a potential candidate for achieving a quantum advantage in data analysis. Among other attractive properties, when training a kernel-based model one is guaranteed to find the optimal model's parameters due to the convexity of the training landscape. However, this is based on the assumption that the quantum kernel can be efficiently obtained from a quantum hardware. In this work we study the trainability of quantum kernels from the perspective of the resources needed to accurately estimate kernel values. We show that, under certain conditions, values of quantum kernels over different input data can be exponentially concentrated (in the number of qubits) towards some fixed value, leading to an exponential scaling of the number of measurements required for successful training. We identify four sources that can lead to concentration including: the expressibility of data embedding, global measurements, entanglement and noise. For each source, an associated concentration bound of quantum kernels is analytically derived. Lastly, we show that when dealing with classical data, training a parametrized data embedding with a kernel alignment method is also susceptible to exponential concentration. Our results are verified through numerical simulations for several QML tasks. Altogether, we provide guidelines indicating that certain features should be avoided to ensure the efficient evaluation and the trainability of quantum kernel methods.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Extendibility of Werner States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13743</link>
    <author>Dávid Jakab, Adrián Solymos, Zoltán Zimborás</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the two-sided symmetric extendibility problem of Werner states. The interplay of the unitary symmetry of these states and the inherent bipartite permutation symmetry of the extendibility scenario allows us to map this problem into the ground state problem of a highly symmetric spin-model Hamiltonian. We solve this ground state problem analytically by utilizing the representation theory of SU(d), in particular a result related to the dominance order of Young diagrams in Littlewood-Richarson decompositions. As a result, we obtain necessary and sufficient conditions for the extendibility of Werner states for arbitrary extension size and local dimension. Interestingly, the range of extendible states has a non-trivial trade-off between the extension sizes on the two sides. We compare our result with the two-sided extendibility problem of isotropic states, where there is no such trade-off.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A parallel decoder for good quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05537</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a parallel decoding algorithm for recently discovered families of asymptotically good quantum low-density parity-check codes. This algorithm provably corrects arbitrary errors of weight linear in the code length, with a logarithmic number of steps. This decoder applies directly to the family of quantum Tanner codes, and serves as a subroutine for expander lifted product codes. Along the way, we exploit recently established bounds on the robustness of random tensor codes to give a tight bound on the minimum distance of quantum Tanner codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A local pre-decoder to reduce the bandwidth and latency of quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04660</link>
    <author>Samuel C. Smith, Benjamin J. Brown, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A fault-tolerant quantum computer will be supported by a classical decoding system interfacing with quantum hardware to perform quantum error correction. It is important that the decoder can keep pace with the quantum clock speed, within the limitations on communication that are imposed by the physical architecture. To this end we propose a local `pre-decoder', which makes greedy corrections to reduce the amount of syndrome data sent to a standard matching decoder. We study these classical overheads for the surface code under a phenomenological phase-flip noise model with imperfect measurements. We find substantial improvements in the runtime of the global decoder and the communication bandwidth by using the pre-decoder. For instance, to achieve a logical failure probability of $f = 10^{-15}$ using qubits with physical error rate $p = 10^{-3}$ and a distance $d=22$ code, we find that the bandwidth cost is reduced by a factor of $1000$, and the time taken by a matching decoder is sped up by a factor of $200$. To achieve this target failure probability, the pre-decoding approach requires a $50\%$ increase in the qubit count compared with the optimal decoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multidimensional Quantum Walks, with Application to $k$-Distinctness</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13492</link>
    <author>Stacey Jeffery, Sebastian Zur</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While the quantum query complexity of $k$-distinctness is known to be $O\left(n^{3/4-1/4(2^k-1)}\right)$ for any constant $k \geq 4$, the best previous upper bound on the time complexity was $\widetilde{O}\left(n^{1-1/k}\right)$. We give a new upper bound of $\widetilde{O}\left(n^{3/4-1/4(2^k-1)}\right)$ on the time complexity, matching the query complexity up to polylogarithmic factors. In order to achieve this upper bound, we give a new technique for designing quantum walk search algorithms, which is an extension of the electric network framework. We also show how to solve the welded trees problem in $O(n)$ queries and $O(n^2)$ time using this new technique, showing that the new quantum walk framework can achieve exponential speedups.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Resource theory of quantum scrambling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.10477</link>
    <author>Roy J. Garcia, Kaifeng Bu, Arthur Jaffe</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum scrambling refers to the spread of local quantum information into the many degrees of freedom of a quantum system. In this work, we introduce a resource theory of scrambling which incorporates two mechanisms, "entanglement scrambling" and "magic scrambling". We introduce two resource monotones called the Pauli growth and the OTOC (out-of-time-ordered correlator) magic for these two mechanisms, respectively. Moreover, we show that OTOC fluctuations are bounded by the OTOC magic. This proves that small OTOC fluctuations are an indication of magic in Google's recent experiment (Science 374, 1479 (2021)). We also show that both resource monotones can be used to bound the decoding fidelity in the Hayden-Preskill protocol. These applications provide an operational interpretation of the resource monotones defined in this work.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum supremacy in mechanical tasks: projectiles, rockets and quantum backflow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00725</link>
    <author>David Trillo, Thinh P. Le, Miguel Navascues</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a scenario where a non-relativistic one-dimensional quantum particle is prepared in some bounded region of space and left to propagate freely. After a certain amount of time, we check if the particle has reached some distant target region. We find that there exist "ultrafast" ("ultraslow") quantum states, whose probability of arrival is greater (smaller) than that of any classical system prepared in the same region with the same momentum distribution. We prove that the maximum possible difference between quantum and optimal classical arrival probabilities for projectiles, as well as for self-propelling particles or rockets, is limited by the Bracken-Melloy constant $c_{bm}$, introduced in $1969$ to characterize the maximum expression of the phenomenon known as quantum backflow. This mathematical correspondence extends to other examples of mechanical effects with a quantum advantage, whose study we advance by deriving the first rigorous upper bound $c_{bm} \leq 0.0725$. We also prove that the hard limit given by $c_{bm}$ can be overcome in a variant of the original projectile scenario: if the classical particle is required to possess, not just the same momentum distribution as the quantum particle, but also the same position distribution, then the difference between arrival probabilities can reach $0.1228$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decomposition of Matrix Product States into Shallow Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00595</link>
    <author>Manuel S. Rudolph, Jing Chen, Jacob Miller, Atithi Acharya, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The rapid pace of recent advancements in numerical computation, notably the rise of GPU and TPU hardware accelerators, have allowed tensor network (TN) algorithms to scale to even larger quantum simulation problems, and to be employed more broadly for solving machine learning tasks. The "quantum-inspired" nature of TNs permits them to be mapped to parametrized quantum circuits (PQCs), a fact which has inspired recent proposals for enhancing the performance of TN algorithms using near-term quantum devices, as well as enabling joint quantum-classical training frameworks which benefit from the distinct strengths of TN and PQC models. However, the success of any such methods depends on efficient and accurate methods for approximating TN states using realistic quantum circuits, something which remains an unresolved question. In this work, we compare a range of novel and previously-developed algorithmic protocols for decomposing matrix product states (MPS) of arbitrary bond dimensions into low-depth quantum circuits consisting of stacked linear layers of two-qubit unitaries. These protocols are formed from different combinations of a preexisting analytical decomposition scheme with constrained optimization of circuit unitaries, and all possess efficient classical runtimes. Our experimental results reveal one particular protocol, involving sequential growth and optimization of the quantum circuit, to outperform all other methods, with even greater benefits seen in the setting of limited computational resources. Given these promising results, we expect our proposed decomposition protocol to form a useful ingredient within any joint application of TNs and PQCs, in turn further unlocking the rich and complementary benefits of classical and quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Alternating Layered Variational Quantum Circuits Can Be Classically Optimized Efficiently Using Classical Shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11623</link>
    <author>Afrad Basheer, Yuan Feng, Christopher Ferrie, Sanjiang Li</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms (VQAs) are the quantum analog of classical neural networks (NNs). A VQA consists of a parameterized quantum circuit (PQC) which is composed of multiple layers of ansatzes (simpler PQCs, which are an analogy of NN layers) that differ only in selections of parameters. Previous work has identified the alternating layered ansatz as potentially a new standard ansatz in near-term quantum computing. Indeed, shallow alternating layered VQAs are easy to implement and have been shown to be both trainable and expressive. In this work, we introduce a training algorithm with an exponential reduction in training cost of such VQAs. Moreover, our algorithm uses classical shadows of quantum input data, and can hence be run on a classical computer with rigorous performance guarantees. We demonstrate 2--3 orders of magnitude improvement in the training cost using our algorithm for the example problems of finding state preparation circuits and the quantum autoencoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On establishing learning separations between classical and quantum machine learning with classical data</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06339</link>
    <author>Casper Gyurik, Vedran Dunjko</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Despite years of effort, the quantum machine learning community has only been able to show quantum learning advantages for certain contrived cryptography-inspired datasets in the case of classical data. In this note, we discuss the challenges of finding learning problems that quantum learning algorithms can learn much faster than any classical learning algorithm, and we study how to identify such learning problems. Specifically, we reflect on the main concepts in computational learning theory pertaining to this question, and we discuss how subtle changes in definitions can mean conceptually significantly different tasks, which can either lead to a separation or no separation at all. Moreover, we study existing learning problems with a provable quantum speedup to distill sets of more general and sufficient conditions (i.e., ``checklists'') for a learning problem to exhibit a separation between classical and quantum learners. These checklists are intended to streamline one's approach to proving quantum speedups for learning problems, or to elucidate bottlenecks. Finally, to illustrate its application, we analyze examples of potential separations (i.e., when the learning problem is build from computational separations, or when the data comes from a quantum experiment) through the lens of our approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Putting paradoxes to work: contextuality in measurement-based quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06624</link>
    <author>Robert Raussendorf</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a joint cohomological framework for measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) and the corresponding contextuality proofs. The central object in this framework is an element in the second cohomology group of the chain complex describing a given MBQC. It contains the function computed, up to gauge equivalence, and at the same time is a contextuality witness. The present cohomological description only applies to temporally flat MBQCs, and we outline an approach for extending it to the temporally ordered case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Software Tools for Decoding Quantum Low-Density Parity Check Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01180</link>
    <author>Lucas Berent, Lukas Burgholzer, Robert Wille</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Error Correction (QEC) is an essential field of research towards the realization of large-scale quantum computers. On the theoretical side, a lot of effort is put into designing error-correcting codes that protect quantum data from errors, which inevitably happen due to the noisy nature of quantum hardware and quantum bits (qubits). Protecting data with an error-correcting code necessitates means to recover the original data, given a potentially corrupted data set-a task referred to as decoding. It is vital that decoding algorithms can recover error-free states in an efficient manner. While theoretical properties of recent QEC methods have been extensively studied, good techniques to analyze their performance in practically more relevant settings is still a widely unexplored area. In this work, we propose a set of software tools that allows to numerically experiment with so-called Quantum Low-Density Parity Check codes (QLDPC codes)-a broad class of codes, some of which have recently been shown to be asymptotically good. Based on that, we provide an implementation of a general decoder for QLDPC codes. On top of that, we propose an efficient heuristic decoder that tackles the runtime bottlenecks of the general QLDPC decoder while still maintaining comparable decoding performance. These tools eventually allow to confirm theoretical results around QLDPC codes in a more practical setting and showcase the value of software tools (in addition to theoretical considerations) for investigating codes for practical applications. The resulting tool, which is publicly available at https://github.com/lucasberent/qecc under the MIT license, is meant to provide a playground for the search for "practically good" quantum codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Long-distance transmon coupler with CZ gate fidelity above $99.8\%$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09460</link>
    <author>Fabian Marxer, Antti Vepsäläinen, Shan W. Jolin, Jani Tuorila, Alessandro Landra, Caspar Ockeloen-Korppi, Wei Liu, Olli Ahonen, Adrian Auer, Lucien Belzane, Ville Bergholm, Chun Fai Chan, Kok Wai Chan, Tuukka Hiltunen, Juho Hotari, Eric Hyyppä, Joni Ikonen, David Janzso, Miikka Koistinen, Janne Kotilahti, et al (19)</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tunable coupling of superconducting qubits has been widely studied due to its importance for isolated gate operations in scalable quantum processor architectures. Here, we demonstrate a tunable qubit-qubit coupler based on a floating transmon device which allows us to place qubits at least 2 mm apart from each other while maintaining over 50 MHz coupling between the coupler and the qubits. In the introduced tunable-coupler design, both the qubit-qubit and the qubit-coupler couplings are mediated by two waveguides instead of relying on direct capacitive couplings between the components, reducing the impact of the qubit-qubit distance on the couplings. This leaves space for each qubit to have an individual readout resonator and a Purcell filter needed for fast high-fidelity readout. In addition, the large qubit-qubit distance reduces unwanted non-nearest neighbor coupling and allows multiple control lines to cross over the structure with minimal crosstalk. Using the proposed flexible and scalable architecture, we demonstrate a controlled-$Z$ gate with $(99.81 \pm 0.02)\%$ fidelity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A hybrid framework for estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08416</link>
    <author>You Zhou, Zhenhuan Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states, such as the moment $\tr(\rho^m)$, is of fundamental and practical interest in quantum science and technology. Here we show a quantum-classical hybrid framework to measure them, where the quantum part is constituted by the generalized swap test, and the classical part is realized by postprocessing the result from randomized measurements. This hybrid framework utilizes the partial coherent power of the intermediate-scale quantum processor and, at the same time, dramatically reduces the number of quantum measurements and the cost of classical postprocessing. We demonstrate the advantage of our framework in the tasks of state-moment estimation and quantum error mitigation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sample optimal tomography of quantum Markov chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02240</link>
    <author>Li Gao, Nengkun Yu</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A state on a tripartite quantum system $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C} $ forms a Markov chain, i.e., quantum conditional independence, if it can be reconstructed from its marginal on $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}$ by a quantum operation from $\mathcal{H}_{B}$ to $\mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C}$ via the famous Petz map: a quantum Markov chain $\rho_{ABC}$ satisfies $\rho_{ABC}=\rho_{BC}^{1/2}(\rho_B^{-1/2}\rho_{AB}\rho_B^{-1/2}\otimes id_C)\rho_{BC}^{1/2}$. In this paper, we study the robustness of the Petz map for different metrics, i.e., the closeness of marginals implies the closeness of the Petz map outcomes. The robustness results are dimension-independent for infidelity $\delta$ and trace distance $\epsilon$. The applications of robustness results are The sample complexity of quantum Markov chain tomography, i.e., how many copies of an unknown quantum Markov chain are necessary and sufficient to determine the state, is $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\delta})$, and $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\epsilon^2}) $. The sample complexity of quantum Markov Chain certification, i.e., to certify whether a tripartite state equals a fixed given quantum Markov Chain $\sigma_{ABC}$ or at least $\delta$-far from $\sigma_{ABC}$, is ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\delta})$, and ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\epsilon^2})$. $\tilde{O}(\frac{\min\{d_Ad_B^3d_C^3,d_A^3d_B^3d_C\}}{\epsilon^2})$ copies to test whether $\rho_{ABC}$ is a quantum Markov Chain or $\epsilon$-far from its Petz recovery state. We generalized the tomography results into multipartite quantum system by showing $\tilde{O}(\frac{n^2\max_{i} \{d_i^2d_{i+1}^2\}}{\delta})$ copies for infidelity $\delta$ are enough for $n$-partite quantum Markov chain tomography with $d_i$ being the dimension of the $i$-th subsystem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive syndrome measurements for Shor-style error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05601</link>
    <author>Theerapat Tansuwannont, Kenneth R. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Shor fault-tolerant error correction (FTEC) scheme uses transversal gates and ancilla qubits prepared in the cat state in syndrome extraction circuits to prevent propagation of errors caused by gate faults. For a stabilizer code that can correct up to $t$ errors, the traditional Shor scheme handles ancilla preparation and measurement faults by performing syndrome measurements until the syndromes are repeated $t+1$ times in a row; in the worst-case scenario, $(t+1)^2$ rounds of measurements are required. In this work, we improve the Shor FTEC scheme using an adaptive syndrome measurement technique. In particular, our protocols determine a syndrome for error correction based on information from the differences of syndromes obtained from any two consecutive rounds. Our protocol that satisfies the strong FTEC conditions requires no more than $(t+3)^2/4-1$ rounds of measurements and is applicable to any stabilizer code. Compared to the traditional method, we estimate that our adaptive measurement method could increase the fault-tolerant threshold by a factor of 4 in the large $t$ limit. We also extend our ideas to error correction satisfying the weak FTEC conditions and flag FTEC.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Barren plateaus in quantum tensor network optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00292</link>
    <author>Enrique Cervero Martín, Kirill Plekhanov, Michael Lubasch</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the barren plateau phenomenon in the variational optimization of quantum circuits inspired by matrix product states (qMPS), tree tensor networks (qTTN), and the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (qMERA). We consider as the cost function the expectation value of a Hamiltonian that is a sum of local terms. For randomly chosen variational parameters we show that the variance of the cost function gradient decreases exponentially with the distance of a Hamiltonian term from the canonical centre in the quantum tensor network. Therefore, as a function of qubit count, for qMPS most gradient variances decrease exponentially and for qTTN as well as qMERA they decrease polynomially. We also show that the calculation of these gradients is exponentially more efficient on a classical computer than on a quantum computer.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>