<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient learning of ground & thermal states within phases of matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.12946</link>
    <author>Emilio Onorati, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França, James D. Watson</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We consider two related tasks: (a) estimating a parameterisation of a given Gibbs state and expectation values of Lipschitz observables on this state; and (b) learning the expectation values of local observables within a thermal or quantum phase of matter. In both cases, we wish to minimise the number of samples we use to learn these properties to a given precision. For the first task, we develop new techniques to learn parameterisations of classes of systems, including quantum Gibbs states of non-commuting Hamiltonians with exponential decay of correlations and the approximate Markov property. We show it is possible to infer the expectation values of all extensive properties of the state from a number of copies that not only scales polylogarithmically with the system size, but polynomially in the observable's locality -- an exponential improvement. This set of properties includes expected values of quasi-local observables and entropies. For the second task, we develop efficient algorithms for learning observables in a phase of matter of a quantum system. By exploiting the locality of the Hamiltonian, we show that $M$ local observables can be learned with probability $1-\delta$ to precision $\epsilon$ with using only $N=O\big(\log\big(\frac{M}{\delta}\big)e^{polylog(\epsilon^{-1})}\big)$ samples -- an exponential improvement on the precision over previous bounds. Our results apply to both families of ground states of Hamiltonians displaying local topological quantum order, and thermal phases of matter with exponential decay of correlations. In addition, our sample complexity applies to the worse case setting whereas previous results only applied on average. Furthermore, we develop tools of independent interest, such as robust shadow tomography algorithms, Gibbs approximations to ground states, and generalisations of transportation cost inequalities for Gibbs states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved machine learning algorithm for predicting ground state properties</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.13169</link>
    <author>Laura Lewis, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Viet T. Tran, Sebastian Lehner, Richard Kueng, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Finding the ground state of a quantum many-body system is a fundamental problem in quantum physics. In this work, we give a classical machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting ground state properties with an inductive bias encoding geometric locality. The proposed ML model can efficiently predict ground state properties of an $n$-qubit gapped local Hamiltonian after learning from only $\mathcal{O}(\log(n))$ data about other Hamiltonians in the same quantum phase of matter. This improves substantially upon previous results that require $\mathcal{O}(n^c)$ data for a large constant $c$. Furthermore, the training and prediction time of the proposed ML model scale as $\mathcal{O}(n \log n)$ in the number of qubits $n$. Numerical experiments on physical systems with up to 45 qubits confirm the favorable scaling in predicting ground state properties using a small training dataset.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lower Bounds on Learning Pauli Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09192</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Aadil Oufkir, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding the noise affecting a quantum device is of fundamental importance for scaling quantum technologies. A particularly important class of noise models is that of Pauli channels, as randomized compiling techniques can effectively bring any quantum channel to this form and are significantly more structured than general quantum channels. In this paper, we show fundamental lower bounds on the sample complexity for learning Pauli channels in diamond norm with unentangled measurements. We consider both adaptive and non-adaptive strategies. In the non-adaptive setting, we show a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{3n}\epsilon^{-2})$ to learn an $n$-qubit Pauli channel. In particular, this shows that the recently introduced learning procedure by Flammia and Wallman is essentially optimal. In the adaptive setting, we show a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{2.5n}\epsilon^{-2})$ for $\epsilon=\mathcal{O}(2^{-n})$, and a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{2n}\epsilon^{-2} )$ for any $\epsilon > 0$. This last lower bound even applies for arbitrarily many sequential uses of the channel, as long as they are only interspersed with other unital operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>stateQIP = statePSPACE</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07730</link>
    <author>Tony Metger, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Complexity theory traditionally studies the hardness of solving classical computational problems. In the quantum setting, it is also natural to consider a different notion of complexity, namely the complexity of physically preparing a certain quantum state. We study the relation between two such state complexity classes: statePSPACE, which contains states that can be generated by space-uniform polynomial-space quantum circuits, and stateQIP, which contains states that a polynomial-time quantum verifier can generate by interacting with an all-powerful untrusted quantum prover. The latter class was recently introduced by Rosenthal and Yuen (ITCS 2022), who proved that statePSPACE $\subseteq$ stateQIP. Our main result is the reverse inclusion, stateQIP $\subseteq$ statePSPACE, thereby establishing equality of the two classes and providing a natural state-complexity analogue to the celebrated QIP = PSPACE theorem of Jain, et al. (J. ACM 2011). To prove this, we develop a polynomial-space quantum algorithm for solving exponentially large "PSPACE-computable" semidefinite programs (SDPs), which also prepares an optimiser encoded in a quantum state. Our SDP solver relies on recent block-encoding techniques from quantum algorithms, demonstrating that these techniques are also useful for complexity theory. Using similar techniques, we also show that optimal prover strategies for general quantum interactive protocols can be implemented in quantum polynomial space. We prove this by studying an algorithmic version of Uhlmann's theorem and establishing an upper bound on the complexity of implementing Uhlmann transformations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A note on lower bounds to variational problems with guarantees</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06142</link>
    <author>J. Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods play an important role in the study of quantum many body problems, both in the flavour of classical variational principles based on tensor networks as well as of quantum variational principles in near-term quantum computing. This brief pedagogical note stresses that for translationally invariant lattice Hamiltonians, one can easily derive efficiently computable lower bounds to ground state energies that can and should be compared with variational principles providing upper bounds. As small technical results, it is shown that (i) the Anderson bound and a (ii) common hierarchy of semi-definite relaxations both provide approximations with performance guarantees that scale like a constant in the energy density for cubic lattices. (iii) Also, the Anderson bound is systematically improved as a hierarchy of semi-definite relaxations inspired by the marginal problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error Correction of Quantum Algorithms: Arbitrarily Accurate Recovery Of Noisy Quantum Signal Processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08542</link>
    <author>Andrew K. Tan, Yuan Liu, Minh C. Tran, Isaac L. Chuang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The intrinsic probabilistic nature of quantum systems makes error correction or mitigation indispensable for quantum computation. While current error-correcting strategies focus on correcting errors in quantum states or quantum gates, these fine-grained error-correction methods can incur significant overhead for quantum algorithms of increasing complexity. We present a first step in achieving error correction at the level of quantum algorithms by combining a unified perspective on modern quantum algorithms via quantum signal processing (QSP). An error model of under- or over-rotation of the signal processing operator parameterized by $\epsilon < 1$ is introduced. It is shown that while Pauli $Z$-errors are not recoverable without additional resources, Pauli $X$ and $Y$ errors can be arbitrarily suppressed by coherently appending a noisy `recovery QSP.' Furthermore, it is found that a recovery QSP of length $O(2^k c^{k^2} d)$ is sufficient to correct any length-$d$ QSP with $c$ unique phases to $k^{th}$-order in error $\epsilon$. Allowing an additional assumption, a lower bound of $\Omega(cd)$ is shown, which is tight for $k = 1$, on the length of the recovery sequence. Our algorithmic-level error correction method is applied to Grover's fixed-point search algorithm as a demonstration.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Exponential Separation Between Quantum Query Complexity and the Polynomial Degree</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09218</link>
    <author>Andris Ambainis, Aleksandrs Belovs</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>While it is known that there is at most a polynomial separation between quantum query complexity and the polynomial degree for total functions, the precise relationship between the two is not clear for partial functions. In this paper, we demonstrate an exponential separation between exact polynomial degree and approximate quantum query complexity for a partial Boolean function. For an unbounded alphabet size, we have a constant versus polynomial separation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sparse random Hamiltonians are quantumly easy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03394</link>
    <author>Chi-Fang Chen, Alexander M. Dalzell, Mario Berta, Fernando G.S.L. Brandão, Joel A. Tropp</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A candidate application for quantum computers is to simulate the low-temperature properties of quantum systems. For this task, there is a well-studied quantum algorithm that performs quantum phase estimation on an initial trial state that has a nonnegligible overlap with a low-energy state. However, it is notoriously hard to give theoretical guarantees that such a trial state can be prepared efficiently. Moreover, the heuristic proposals that are currently available, such as with adiabatic state preparation, appear insufficient in practical cases. This paper shows that, for most random sparse Hamiltonians, the maximally mixed state is a sufficiently good trial state, and phase estimation efficiently prepares states with energy arbitrarily close to the ground energy. Furthermore, any low-energy state must have nonnegligible quantum circuit complexity, suggesting that low-energy states are classically nontrivial and phase estimation is the optimal method for preparing such states (up to polynomial factors). These statements hold for two models of random Hamiltonians: (i) a sum of random signed Pauli strings and (ii) a random signed $d$-sparse Hamiltonian. The main technical argument is based on some new results in nonasymptotic random matrix theory. In particular, a refined concentration bound for the spectral density is required to obtain complexity guarantees for these random Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-Tolerant Connection of Error-Corrected Qubits with Noisy Links</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01296</link>
    <author>Joshua Ramette, Josiah Sinclair, Nikolas P. Breuckmann, Vladan Vuletić</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>One of the most promising routes towards scalable quantum computing is a modular approach. We show that distinct surface code patches can be connected in a fault-tolerant manner even in the presence of substantial noise along their connecting interface. We quantify analytically and numerically the combined effect of errors across the interface and bulk. We show that the system can tolerate 14 times higher noise at the interface compared to the bulk, with only a small effect on the code's threshold and sub-threshold behavior, reaching threshold with $\sim 1 \%$ bulk errors and $\sim 10 \%$ interface errors. This implies that fault-tolerant scaling of error-corrected modular devices is within reach using existing technology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On classical simulation algorithms for noisy Boson Sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11532</link>
    <author>Changhun Oh, Liang Jiang, Bill Fefferman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present a classical algorithm that approximately samples from the output distribution of certain noisy Boson Sampling experiments. This algorithm is inspired by a recent result of Aharonov, Gao, Landau, Liu and Vazirani and makes use of an observation originally due to Kalai and Kindler that the output probability of Boson Sampling experiments with a Gaussian noise model can be approximated by sparse low-degree polynomials. This observation alone does not suffice for classical sampling, because its marginal probabilities might not be approximated by sparse low-degree polynomials, and furthermore, the approximated probabilities might be negative. We solve this problem by employing the first quantization representation to give an algorithm for computing the marginal probabilities of these experiments. We prove that when the overall noise rate is constant, the algorithm runs in time quasi-polynomial in the number of input photons $N$ and accuracy. When the overall noise rate scales as $1-x_1^\gamma$ for constant $x_1$ and $\gamma=\Omega(\log N)$, the running time becomes polynomial. Furthermore, we study noisy Boson Sampling with practically relevant noise models such as partial distinguishability and photon loss. We show that the same technique does not immediately apply in these settings, leaving open the possibility of a scalable demonstration of noisy quantum advantage for these noise models in certain parameter regimes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Qubit-Efficient Randomized Quantum Algorithms for Linear Algebra</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01873</link>
    <author>Samson Wang, Sam McArdle, Mario Berta</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a class of randomized quantum algorithms for the task of sampling from matrix functions, without the use of quantum block encodings or any other coherent oracle access to the matrix elements. As such, our use of qubits is purely algorithmic, and no additional qubits are required for quantum data structures. For $N\times N$ Hermitian matrices, the space cost is $\log(N)+1$ qubits and depending on the structure of the matrices, the gate complexity can be comparable to state-of-the-art methods that use quantum data structures of up to size $O(N^2)$, when considering equivalent end-to-end problems. Within our framework, we present a quantum linear system solver that allows one to sample properties of the solution vector, as well as an algorithm for sampling properties of ground states of Hamiltonians. As a concrete application, we combine these two sub-routines to present a scheme for calculating Green's functions of quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal lower bound on topological entanglement entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.00689</link>
    <author>Isaac H. Kim, Michael Levin, Ting-Chun Lin, Daniel Ranard, Bowen Shi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement entropies of two-dimensional gapped ground states are expected to satisfy an area law, with a constant correction term known as the topological entanglement entropy (TEE). In many models, the TEE takes a universal value that characterizes the underlying topological phase. However, the TEE is not truly universal: it can differ even for two states related by constant-depth circuits, which are necessarily in the same phase. The difference between the TEE and the value predicted by the anyon theory is often called the spurious topological entanglement entropy. We show that this spurious contribution is always nonnegative, thus the value predicted by the anyon theory provides a universal lower bound. This observation also leads to a definition of TEE which is invariant under constant-depth quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Relaxing Hardware Requirements for Surface Code Circuits using Time-dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.02192</link>
    <author>Matt McEwen, Dave Bacon, Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The typical time-independent view of quantum error correction (QEC) codes hides significant freedom in the decomposition into circuits that are executable on hardware. Using the concept of detecting regions, we design time-dynamic QEC circuits directly instead of designing static QEC codes to decompose into circuits. In particular, we improve on the standard circuit constructions for the surface code, presenting new circuits that can embed on a hexagonal grid instead of a square grid, that can use ISWAP gates instead of CNOT or CZ gates, that can exchange qubit data and measure roles, and that move logical patches around the physical qubit grid while executing. All these constructions use no additional entangling gate layers and display essentially the same logical performance, having teraquop footprints within 25% of the standard surface code circuit. We expect these circuits to be of great interest to quantum hardware engineers, because they achieve essentially the same logical performance as standard surface code circuits while relaxing demands on hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Everything is a quantum Ising model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11917</link>
    <author>Ruben Verresen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>This work shows that any $k$-local Hamiltonian of qubits can be obtained from a 4-state 'Ising' model with $k$-local diagonal interactions and a single-site transverse field -- giving a new theoretical and experimental handle on quantum matter. In particular, the classical Ising interactions can be determined by replacing each Pauli operator with a $4 \times 4$ diagonal matrix. Subsequently tuning a large transverse field projects out two of the four states, recovering the original qubit model, with qudit generalizations. This leads to striking correspondences, such as the spin-1/2 XY and Heisenberg models arising from the large-field limit of 3-state and 4-state Potts models, respectively. Similarly, the Kitaev honeycomb model emerges from classical interactions which enforce loop states on the honeycomb lattice. These generalized Ising models also display rich physics for smaller fields, including quantum criticality and topological phases of matter. This work expands what is experimentally achievable by showing how to realize any quantum spin model using only diagonal interactions and a tuneable field -- ingredients found in, e.g., tweezer arrays of Rydberg atoms or polar molecules. More broadly, 4-state spins can also be encoded in the positions of itinerant particles, exemplified by a Bose-Hubbard model realizing the Kitaev honeycomb model -- giving an experimental path to its $\mathbb Z_2$ and non-Abelian topological quantum liquids.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Direct Reduction from the Polynomial to the Adversary Method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10317</link>
    <author>Aleksandrs Belovs</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The polynomial and the adversary methods are the two main tools for proving lower bounds on query complexity of quantum algorithms. Both methods have found a large number of applications, some problems more suitable for one method, some for the other. It is known though that the adversary method, in its general negative-weighted version, is tight for bounded-error quantum algorithms, whereas the polynomial method is not. By the tightness of the former, for any polynomial lower bound, there ought to exist a corresponding adversary lower bound. However, direct reduction was not known. In this paper, we give a simple and direct reduction from the polynomial method (in the form of a dual polynomial) to the adversary method. This shows that any lower bound in the form of a dual polynomial is actually an adversary lower bound of a specific form.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Computational Separation Between Quantum No-cloning and No-teleportation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01858</link>
    <author>Barak Nehoran, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Two of the fundamental no-go theorems of quantum information are the no-cloning theorem (that it is impossible to make copies of general quantum states) and the no-teleportation theorem (the prohibition on sending quantum states over classical channels without pre-shared entanglement). They are known to be equivalent, in the sense that a collection of quantum states is clonable if and only if it is teleportable. Our main result suggests that this is not the case when computational efficiency is considered. We give a collection of quantum states and oracles relative to which these states are efficiently clonable but not efficiently teleportable. Given that the opposite scenario is impossible (states that can be teleported can always trivially be cloned), this gives the most complete oracle separation possible between these two important no-go properties. In doing so, we introduce a related quantum no-go property, reconstructibility, which refers to the ability to construct a quantum state from a uniquely identifying classical description. We show the stronger result of a collection of quantum states that are efficiently clonable but not efficiently reconstructible. This novel no-go property only exists in relation to computational efficiency, as it is trivial for unbounded computation. It thus opens up the possibility of further computational no-go properties that have not yet been studied because they do not exist outside the computational context.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From Kraus Operators to the Stinespring Form of Quantum Maps: An Alternative Construction for Infinite Dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05488</link>
    <author>Frederik vom Ende</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 16 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present an alternative (constructive) proof of the statement that for every completely positive, trace-preserving map $\Phi$ there exists an auxiliary Hilbert space $\mathcal K$ in a pure state $|\psi\rangle\langle\psi|$ as well as a unitary operator $U$ on system plus environment such that $\Phi$ equals $\operatorname{tr}_{\mathcal K}(U((\cdot)\otimes|\psi\rangle\langle\psi|)U^*)$. The main tool of our proof is Sz.-Nagy's dilation theorem applied to isometries defined on a subspace. In our construction, the environment consists of a system of dimension "Kraus rank of $\Phi$" together with a qubit, the latter only acting as a catalyst. In contrast, the original proof of Hellwig & Kraus given in the 70s yields an auxiliary system of dimension "Kraus rank plus one". We conclude by providing an example which illustrates how the constructions differ from each other.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Speedups for Zero-Sum Games via Improved Dynamic Gibbs Sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03763</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Yosheb Getachew, Yujia Jin, Aaron Sidford, Kevin Tian</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum algorithm for computing an $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium of a zero-sum game in a $m \times n$ payoff matrix with bounded entries. Given a standard quantum oracle for accessing the payoff matrix our algorithm runs in time $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{m + n}\cdot \epsilon^{-2.5} + \epsilon^{-3})$ and outputs a classical representation of the $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium. This improves upon the best prior quantum runtime of $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{m + n} \cdot \epsilon^{-3})$ obtained by [vAG19] and the classic $\widetilde{O}((m + n) \cdot \epsilon^{-2})$ runtime due to [GK95] whenever $\epsilon = \Omega((m +n)^{-1})$. We obtain this result by designing new quantum data structures for efficiently sampling from a slowly-changing Gibbs distribution.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Randomized adaptive quantum state preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.04201</link>
    <author>Alicia B. Magann, Sophia E. Economou, Christian Arenz</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We develop an adaptive method for quantum state preparation that utilizes randomness as an essential component and that does not require classical optimization. Instead, a cost function is minimized to prepare a desired quantum state through an adaptively constructed quantum circuit, where each adaptive step is informed by feedback from gradient measurements in which the associated tangent space directions are randomized. We provide theoretical arguments and numerical evidence that convergence to the target state can be achieved for almost all initial states. We investigate different randomization procedures and develop lower bounds on the expected cost function change, which allows for drawing connections to barren plateaus and for assessing the applicability of the algorithm to large-scale problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Guaranteed efficient energy estimation of quantum many-body Hamiltonians using ShadowGrouping</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03385</link>
    <author>Alexander Gresch, Martin Kliesch</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Energy estimation in quantum many-body Hamiltonians is a paradigmatic task in various research fields. In particular, efficient energy estimation may be crucial in achieving a quantum advantage for a practically relevant problem. For instance, the measurement effort poses a crucial bottleneck in variational quantum algorithms. We aim to find the optimal strategy with single-qubit measurements that yields the highest provable accuracy given a total measurement budget. As a central tool, we establish new tail bounds for empirical estimators of the energy. They are useful for identifying measurement settings that improve the energy estimate the most. This task constitutes an NP-hard problem. However, we are able to circumvent this bottleneck and use the tail bounds to develop a practical efficient estimation strategy which we call ShadowGrouping. As the name suggests, it combines shadow estimation methods with grouping strategies for Pauli strings. In numerical experiments, we demonstrate that ShadowGrouping outperforms state-of-the-art methods in estimating the electronic ground-state energies of various small molecules, both in provable and effective accuracy benchmarks. Hence, this work provides a promising way, e.g., to tackle the measurement bottleneck of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing quantum satisfiability</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10699</link>
    <author>Ashley Montanaro, Changpeng Shao, Dominic Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum k-SAT (the problem of determining whether a k-local Hamiltonian is frustration-free) is known to be QMA_1-complete for k >= 3, and hence likely hard for quantum computers to solve. Building on a classical result of Alon and Shapira, we show that quantum k-SAT can be solved in randomised polynomial time given the `property testing' promise that the instance is either satisfiable (by any state) or far from satisfiable by a product state; by `far from satisfiable by a product state' we mean that \epsilon n^k constraints must be removed before a product state solution exists, for some fixed \epsilon > 0. The proof has two steps: we first show that for a satisfiable instance of quantum k-SAT, most subproblems on a constant number of qubits are satisfiable by a product state. We then show that for an instance of quantum k-SAT which is far from satisfiable by a product state, most subproblems are unsatisfiable by a product state. Given the promise, quantum k-SAT may therefore be solved by checking satisfiability by a product state on randomly chosen subsystems of constant size.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>CSS code surgery as a universal construction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.13738</link>
    <author>Alexander Cowtan, Simon Burton</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We define code maps between Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) codes using maps between chain complexes, and describe code surgery between such codes using a specific colimit in the category of chain complexes. As well as describing a surgery operation, this gives a general recipe for new codes. As an application we describe how to `merge' and `split' along a shared $\overline{X}$ or $\overline{Z}$ operator between arbitrary CSS codes in a fault-tolerant manner, so long as the participating qubits satisfy a technical condition related to gauge fixing. We prove that such merges and splits on LDPC codes yield codes which are themselves LDPC.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental demonstration of the advantage of adaptive quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03029</link>
    <author>Michael Foss-Feig, Arkin Tikku, Tsung-Cheng Lu, Karl Mayer, Mohsin Iqbal, Thomas M. Gatterman, Justin A. Gerber, Kevin Gilmore, Dan Gresh, Aaron Hankin, Nathan Hewitt, Chandler V. Horst, Mitchell Matheny, Tanner Mengle, Brian Neyenhuis, Henrik Dreyer, David Hayes, Timothy H. Hsieh, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Adaptive quantum circuits employ unitary gates assisted by mid-circuit measurement, classical computation on the measurement outcome, and the conditional application of future unitary gates based on the result of the classical computation. In this paper, we experimentally demonstrate that even a noisy adaptive quantum circuit of constant depth can achieve a task that is impossible for any purely unitary quantum circuit of identical depth: the preparation of long-range entangled topological states with high fidelity. We prepare a particular toric code ground state with fidelity of at least $76.9\pm 1.3\%$ using a constant depth ($d=4$) adaptive circuit, and rigorously show that no unitary circuit of the same depth and connectivity could prepare this state with fidelity greater than $50\%$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Can shallow quantum circuits scramble local noise into global white noise?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.00881</link>
    <author>Jonathan Foldager, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Shallow quantum circuits are believed to be the most promising candidates for achieving early practical quantum advantage - this has motivated the development of a broad range of error mitigation techniques whose performance generally improves when the quantum state is well approximated by a global depolarising (white) noise model. While it has been crucial for demonstrating quantum supremacy that random circuits scramble local noise into global white noise - a property that has been proved rigorously - we investigate to what degree practical shallow quantum circuits scramble local noise into global white noise. We define two key metrics as (a) density matrix eigenvalue uniformity and (b) commutator norm. While the former determines the distance from white noise, the latter determines the performance of purification based error mitigation. We derive analytical approximate bounds on their scaling and find in most cases they nicely match numerical results. On the other hand, we simulate a broad class of practical quantum circuits and find that white noise is in certain cases a bad approximation posing significant limitations on the performance of some of the simpler error mitigation schemes. On a positive note, we find in all cases that the commutator norm is sufficiently small guaranteeing a very good performance of purification-based error mitigation. Lastly, we identify techniques that may decrease both metrics, such as increasing the dimensionality of the dynamical Lie algebra by gate insertions or randomised compiling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A generic quantum Wielandt's inequality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08241</link>
    <author>Yifan Jia, Angela Capel</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we provide a generic version of quantum Wielandt's inequality, which gives an optimal upper bound on the minimal length $k$ such that length-$k$ products of elements in a generating system span $M_n(\mathbb{C})$ with probability one. We show that $k$ generically is of order $\Theta(\log n)$, as opposed to the general case, in which the best bound to the date is $O(n^2 \log n)$. Our result implies a new bound on the primitivity index of a random quantum channel. Furthermore, we conclude that almost any translation-invariant (with periodic boundary conditions) matrix product state with length of order $\Omega( \log n )$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian. We observe similar characteristics for matrix Lie algebras and provide numerical results for random Lie-generating systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast Quantum Algorithms for Trace Distance Estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06783</link>
    <author>Qisheng Wang, Zhicheng Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In quantum information processing, trace distance is a basic metric of distinguishability between quantum states. However, there is no known efficient approach to estimate the value of trace distance in general. In this paper, we propose efficient quantum algorithms for estimating the trace distance within additive error $\varepsilon$ between mixed quantum states of rank $r$. Specifically, we first provide a quantum algorithm using $r \cdot \widetilde O(1/\varepsilon^2)$ queries to the quantum circuits that prepare the purifications of quantum states, which achieves a linear time dependence on the rank $r$. Then, we modify this quantum algorithm to obtain another algorithm using $\widetilde O(r^2/\varepsilon^5)$ samples of quantum states, which can be applied to quantum state certification. Both algorithms have the same quantum time complexities as their query/sample complexities up to a logarithmic factor.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hypothesis Testing for Error Mitigation: How to Evaluate Error Mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02690</link>
    <author>Abdullah Ash Saki, Amara Katabarwa, Salonik Resch, George Umbrarescu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In the noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era, quantum error mitigation will be a necessary tool to extract useful performance out of quantum devices. However, there is a big gap between the noise models often assumed by error mitigation techniques and the actual noise on quantum devices. As a consequence, there arises a gap between the theoretical expectations of the techniques and their everyday performance. Cloud users of quantum devices in particular, who often take the devices as they are, feel this gap the most. How should they parametrize their uncertainty in the usefulness of these techniques and be able to make judgement calls between resources required to implement error mitigation and the accuracy required at the algorithmic level? To answer the first question, we introduce hypothesis testing within the framework of quantum error mitigation and for the second question, we propose an inclusive figure of merit that accounts for both resource requirement and mitigation efficiency of an error mitigation implementation. The figure of merit is useful to weigh the trade-offs between the scalability and accuracy of various error mitigation methods. Finally, using the hypothesis testing and the figure of merit, we experimentally evaluate $16$ error mitigation pipelines composed of singular methods such as zero noise extrapolation, randomized compilation, measurement error mitigation, dynamical decoupling, and mitigation with estimation circuits. In total our data involved running $275,640$ circuits on two IBM quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An operator-algebraic formulation of self-testing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11291</link>
    <author>Connor Paddock, William Slofstra, Yuming Zhao, Yangchen Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We give a new definition of self-testing for correlations in terms of states on $C^*$-algebras. We show that this definition is equivalent to the standard definition for any class of finite-dimensional quantum models which is closed, provided that the correlation is extremal and has a full-rank model in the class. This last condition automatically holds for the class of POVM quantum models, but does not necessarily hold for the class of projective models by a result of Kaniewski and Mančinska. For extremal binary correlations and for extremal synchronous correlations, we show that any self-test for projective models is a self-test for POVM models. The question of whether there is a self-test for projective models which is not a self-test for POVM models remains open. An advantage of our new definition is that it extends naturally to commuting operator models. We show that an extremal correlation is a self-test for finite-dimensional quantum models if and only if it is a self-test for finite-dimensional commuting operator models, and also observe that many known finite-dimensional self-tests are in fact self-tests for infinite-dimensional commuting operator models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bulk-to-boundary anyon fusion from microscopic models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01835</link>
    <author>Julio C. Magdalena de la Fuente, Jens Eisert, Andreas Bauer</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Topological quantum error correction based on the manipulation of the anyonic defects constitutes one of the most promising frameworks towards realizing fault-tolerant quantum devices. Hence, it is crucial to understand how these defects interact with external defects such as boundaries or domain walls. Motivated by this line of thought, in this work, we study the fusion events between anyons in the bulk and at the boundary in fixed-point models of 2+1-dimensional non-chiral topological order defined by arbitrary fusion categories. Our construction uses generalized tube algebra techniques to construct a bi-representation of bulk and boundary defects. We explicitly derive a formula to calculate the fusion multiplicities of a bulk-to-boundary fusion event for twisted quantum double models and calculate some exemplary fusion events for Abelian models and the (twisted) quantum double model of S3, the simplest non-Abelian group-theoretical model. Moreover, we use the folding trick to study the anyonic behavior at non-trivial domain walls between twisted S3 and twisted Z2 as well as Z3 models. A recurring theme in our construction is an isomorphism relating twisted cohomology groups to untwisted ones. The results of this work can directly be applied to study logical operators in two-dimensional topological error correcting codes with boundaries described by a twisted gauge theory of a finite group.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sketching phase diagrams using low-depth variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09369</link>
    <author>Jan Lukas Bosse, Raul Santos, Ashley Montanaro</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Mapping out phase diagrams of quantum systems using classical simulations can be challenging or intractable due to the computational resources required to simulate even small quantum systems far away from the thermodynamic limit. We investigate using quantum computers and the Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) for this task. In contrast to the task of preparing the exact ground state using VQE, sketching phase diagrams might require less quantum resources and accuracy, because low fidelity approximations to the ground state may be enough to correctly identify different phases. We used classical numerical simulations of low-depth VQE circuits to compute order parameters for four well-studied spin and fermion models which represent a mix of 1D and 2D, and exactly-solvable and classically hard systems. We find that it is possible to predict the location of phase transitions up to reasonable accuracy using states produced by VQE even when their overlap with the true ground state is small. Further, we introduce a model-agnostic predictor of phase transitions based on the speed with which the VQE energy improves with respect to the circuit depth, and find that in some cases this is also able to predict phase transitions.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>