<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Time-energy uncertainty relation for noisy quantum metrology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13707</link>
    <author>Philippe Faist, Mischa P. Woods, Victor V. Albert, Joseph M. Renes, Jens Eisert, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Detection of weak forces and precise measurement of time are two of the many applications of quantum metrology to science and technology. We consider a quantum system initialized in a pure state and whose evolution is goverened by a Hamiltonian $H$; a measurement can later estimate the time $t$ for which the system has evolved. In this work, we introduce and study a fundamental trade-off which relates the amount by which noise reduces the accuracy of a quantum clock to the amount of information about the energy of the clock that leaks to the environment. Specifically, we consider an idealized scenario in which Alice prepares an initial pure state of the clock, allows the clock to evolve for a time $t$ that is not precisely known, and then transmits the clock through a noisy channel to Bob. The environment (Eve) receives any information that is lost. We prove that Bob's loss of quantum Fisher information (QFI) about $t$ is equal to Eve's gain of QFI about a complementary energy parameter. We also prove a more general trade-off that applies when Bob and Eve wish to estimate the values of parameters associated with two non-commuting observables. We derive the necessary and sufficient conditions for the accuracy of the clock to be unaffected by the noise. These are a subset of the Knill-Laflamme error-correction conditions; states satisfying these conditions are said to form a metrological code. We provide a scheme to construct metrological codes in the stabilizer formalism. We show that there are metrological codes that cannot be written as a quantum error-correcting code with similar distance in which the Hamiltonian acts as a logical operator, potentially offering new schemes for constructing states that do not lose any sensitivity upon application of a noisy channel. We discuss applications of our results to sensing using a many-body state subject to erasure or amplitude-damping noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Physics of Quantum Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08064</link>
    <author>John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Rapid ongoing progress in quantum information science makes this an apt time for a Solvay Conference focused on The Physics of Quantum Information. Here I review four intertwined themes encompassed by this topic: Quantum computer science, quantum hardware, quantum matter, and quantum gravity. Though the time scale for broad practical impact of quantum computation is still uncertain, in the near future we can expect noteworthy progress toward scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing, and discoveries enabled by programmable quantum simulators. In the longer term, controlling highly complex quantum matter will open the door to profound scientific advances and powerful new technologies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matchgate Shadows for Fermionic Quantum Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13723</link>
    <author>Kianna Wan, William J. Huggins, Joonho Lee, Ryan Babbush</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>"Classical shadows" are estimators of an unknown quantum state, constructed from suitably distributed random measurements on copies of that state [Nature Physics 16, 1050-1057]. Here, we analyze classical shadows obtained using random matchgate circuits, which correspond to fermionic Gaussian unitaries. We prove that the first three moments of the Haar distribution over the continuous group of matchgate circuits are equal to those of the discrete uniform distribution over only the matchgate circuits that are also Clifford unitaries; thus, the latter forms a "matchgate 3-design." This implies that the classical shadows resulting from the two ensembles are functionally equivalent. We show how one can use these matchgate shadows to efficiently estimate inner products between an arbitrary quantum state and fermionic Gaussian states, as well as the expectation values of local fermionic operators and various other quantities, thus surpassing the capabilities of prior work. As a concrete application, this enables us to apply wavefunction constraints that control the fermion sign problem in the quantum-classical auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm (QC-AFQMC) [Nature 603, 416-420], without the exponential post-processing cost incurred by the original approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Implementing Fault-tolerant Entangling Gates on the Five-qubit Code and the Color Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01863</link>
    <author>C. Ryan-Anderson, N. C. Brown, M. S. Allman, B. Arkin, G. Asa-Attuah, C. Baldwin, J. Berg, J. G. Bohnet, S. Braxton, N. Burdick, J. P. Campora, A. Chernoguzov, J. Esposito, B. Evans, D. Francois, J. P. Gaebler, T. M. Gatterman, J. Gerber, K. Gilmore, D. Gresh, et al (17)</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We compare two different implementations of fault-tolerant entangling gates on logical qubits. In one instance, a twelve-qubit trapped-ion quantum computer is used to implement a non-transversal logical CNOT gate between two five qubit codes. The operation is evaluated with varying degrees of fault tolerance, which are provided by including quantum error correction circuit primitives known as flagging and pieceable fault tolerance. In the second instance, a twenty-qubit trapped-ion quantum computer is used to implement a transversal logical CNOT gate on two [[7,1,3]] color codes. The two codes were implemented on different but similar devices, and in both instances, all of the quantum error correction primitives, including the determination of corrections via decoding, are implemented during runtime using a classical compute environment that is tightly integrated with the quantum processor. For different combinations of the primitives, logical state fidelity measurements are made after applying the gate to different input states, providing bounds on the process fidelity. We find the highest fidelity operations with the color code, with the fault-tolerant SPAM operation achieving fidelities of 0.99939(15) and 0.99959(13) when preparing eigenstates of the logical X and Z operators, which is higher than the average physical qubit SPAM fidelities of 0.9968(2) and 0.9970(1) for the physical X and Z bases, respectively. When combined with a logical transversal CNOT gate, we find the color code to perform the sequence--state preparation, CNOT, measure out--with an average fidelity bounded by [0.9957,0.9963]. The logical fidelity bounds are higher than the analogous physical-level fidelity bounds, which we find to be [0.9850,0.9903], reflecting multiple physical noise sources such as SPAM errors for two qubits, several single-qubit gates, a two-qubit gate and some amount of memory error.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simulating quantum circuits using efficient tensor network contraction algorithms with subexponential upper bound</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01498</link>
    <author>Thorsten B. Wahl, Sergii Strelchuk</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive a rigorous upper bound on the classical computation time of finite-ranged tensor network contractions in $d \geq 2$ dimensions. By means of the Sphere Separator Theorem, we are able to take advantage of the structure of quantum circuits to speed up contractions to show that quantum circuits of single-qubit and finite-ranged two-qubit gates can be classically simulated in subexponential time in the number of gates. In many practically relevant cases this beats standard simulation schemes. Moreover, our algorithm leads to speedups of several orders of magnitude over naive contraction schemes for two-dimensional quantum circuits on as little as an $8 \times 8$ lattice. We obtain similarly efficient contraction schemes for Google's Sycamore-type quantum circuits, instantaneous quantum polynomial-time circuits and non-homogeneous (2+1)-dimensional random quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved Hardness Results for the Guided Local Hamiltonian Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.10250</link>
    <author>Sevag Gharibian, Ryu Hayakawa, François Le Gall, Tomoyuki Morimae</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Estimating the ground state energy of a local Hamiltonian is a central problem in quantum chemistry. In order to further investigate its complexity and the potential of quantum algorithms for quantum chemistry, Gharibian and Le Gall (STOC 2022) recently introduced the guided local Hamiltonian problem (GLH), which is a variant of the local Hamiltonian problem where an approximation of a ground state is given as an additional input. Gharibian and Le Gall showed quantum advantage (more precisely, BQP-completeness) for GLH with $6$-local Hamiltonians when the guiding vector has overlap (inverse-polynomially) close to 1/2 with a ground state. In this paper, we optimally improve both the locality and the overlap parameters: we show that this quantum advantage (BQP-completeness) persists even with 2-local Hamiltonians, and even when the guiding vector has overlap (inverse-polynomially) close to 1 with a ground state. Moreover, we show that the quantum advantage also holds for 2-local physically motivated Hamiltonians on a 2D square lattice. This makes a further step towards establishing practical quantum advantage in quantum chemistry.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Wasserstein Complexity of Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06306</link>
    <author>Lu Li, Kaifeng Bu, Dax Enshan Koh, Arthur Jaffe, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a unitary transformation, what is the size of the smallest quantum circuit that implements it? This quantity, known as the quantum circuit complexity, is a fundamental property of quantum evolutions that has widespread applications in many fields, including quantum computation, quantum field theory, and black hole physics. In this letter, we obtain a new lower bound for the quantum circuit complexity in terms of a novel complexity measure that we propose for quantum circuits, which we call the quantum Wasserstein complexity. Our proposed measure is based on the quantum Wasserstein distance of order one (also called the quantum earth mover's distance), a metric on the space of quantum states. We also prove several fundamental and important properties of our new complexity measure, which stand to be of independent interest. Finally, we show that our new measure also provides a lower bound for the experimental cost of implementing quantum circuits, which implies a quantum limit on converting quantum resources to computational resources. Our results provide novel applications of the quantum Wasserstein distance and pave the way for a deeper understanding of the resources needed to implement a quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Emergent Quantum Mechanics at the Boundary of a Local Classical Lattice Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.09465</link>
    <author>Kevin Slagle, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We formulate a conceptually new model in which quantum mechanics emerges from classical mechanics. Given a local Hamiltonian $H$ acting on $n$ qubits, we define a local classical model with an additional spatial dimension whose boundary dynamics is described by Schrodinger's equation and $H$. The bulk consists of a lattice of classical bits that propagate towards the boundary through a circuit of stochastic matrices. The bits reaching the boundary are governed by a probability distribution whose deviation from the uniform distribution can be interpreted as the quantum-mechanical wavefunction. Bell nonlocality is achieved because information can move through the bulk much faster than the boundary speed of light. We analytically estimate how much the model deviates from quantum mechanics, and we validate these estimates using computer simulations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lower bounds for learning quantum states with single-copy measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14438</link>
    <author>Angus Lowe, Ashwin Nayak</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problems of quantum tomography and shadow tomography using measurements performed on individual, identical copies of an unknown $d$-dimensional state. We first revisit a known lower bound due to Haah et al. (2017) on quantum tomography with accuracy $\epsilon$ in trace distance, when the measurements choices are independent of previously observed outcomes (i.e., they are nonadaptive). We give a succinct proof of this result. This leads to stronger lower bounds when the learner uses measurements with a constant number of outcomes. In particular, this rigorously establishes the optimality of the folklore ``Pauli tomography" algorithm in terms of its sample complexity. We also derive novel bounds of $\Omega(r^2 d/\epsilon^2)$ and $\Omega(r^2 d^2/\epsilon^2)$ for learning rank $r$ states using arbitrary and constant-outcome measurements, respectively, in the nonadaptive case. In addition to the sample complexity, a resource of practical significance for learning quantum states is the number of different measurements used by an algorithm. We extend our lower bounds to the case where the learner performs possibly adaptive measurements from a fixed set of $\exp(O(d))$ measurements. This implies in particular that adaptivity does not give us any advantage using single-copy measurements that are efficiently implementable. We also obtain a similar bound in the case where the goal is to predict the expectation values of a given sequence of observables, a task known as shadow tomography. Finally, in the case of adaptive, single-copy measurements implementable with polynomial-size circuits, we prove that a straightforward strategy based on computing sample means of the given observables is optimal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complexity of the Guided Local Hamiltonian Problem: Improved Parameters and Extension to Excited States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.10097</link>
    <author>Chris Cade, Marten Folkertsma, Jordi Weggemans</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently it was shown that the so-called guided local Hamiltonian problem -- estimating the smallest eigenvalue of a $k$-local Hamiltonian when provided with a description of a quantum state ('guiding state') that is guaranteed to have substantial overlap with the true groundstate -- is BQP-complete for $k \geq 6$ when the required precision is inverse polynomial in the system size $n$, and remains hard even when the overlap of the guiding state with the groundstate is close to a constant $\left(\frac12 - \Omega\left(\frac{1}{\mathop{poly}(n)}\right)\right)$. We improve upon this result in three ways: by showing that it remains BQP-complete when i) the Hamiltonian is 2-local, ii) the overlap between the guiding state and target eigenstate is as large as $1 - \Omega\left(\frac{1}{\mathop{poly}(n)}\right)$, and iii) when one is interested in estimating energies of excited states, rather than just the groundstate. Interestingly, iii) is only made possible by first showing that ii) holds.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure qubits: Overcoming the $T_1$ limit in superconducting circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05461</link>
    <author>Aleksander Kubica, Arbel Haim, Yotam Vaknin, Fernando Brandão, Alex Retzker</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The amplitude damping time, $T_1$, has long stood as the major factor limiting quantum fidelity in superconducting circuits, prompting concerted efforts in the material science and design of qubits aimed at increasing $T_1$. In contrast, the dephasing time, $T_{\phi}$, can usually be extended above $T_1$ (via, e.g., dynamical decoupling), to the point where it does not limit fidelity. In this article we propose a scheme for overcoming the conventional $T_1$ limit on fidelity by designing qubits in a way that amplitude damping errors can be detected and converted into erasure errors. Compared to standard qubit implementations our scheme improves the performance of fault-tolerant protocols, as numerically demonstrated by the circuit-noise simulations of the surface code. We describe two simple qubit implementations with superconducting circuits and discuss procedures for detecting amplitude damping errors, performing entangling gates, and extending $T_\phi$. Our results suggest that engineering efforts should focus on improving $T_\phi$ and the quality of quantum coherent control, as they effectively become the limiting factor on the performance of fault-tolerant protocols.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal algorithms for learning quantum phase states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07851</link>
    <author>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Sergey Bravyi, Arkopal Dutt, Theodore J. Yoder</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the complexity of learning $n$-qubit quantum phase states. A degree-$d$ phase state is defined as a superposition of all $2^n$ basis vectors $x$ with amplitudes proportional to $(-1)^{f(x)}$, where $f$ is a degree-$d$ Boolean polynomial over $n$ variables. We show that the sample complexity of learning an unknown degree-$d$ phase state is $\Theta(n^d)$ if we allow separable measurements and $\Theta(n^{d-1})$ if we allow entangled measurements. Our learning algorithm based on separable measurements has runtime $\textsf{poly}(n)$ (for constant $d$) and is well-suited for near-term demonstrations as it requires only single-qubit measurements in the Pauli $X$ and $Z$ bases. We show similar bounds on the sample complexity for learning generalized phase states with complex-valued amplitudes. We further consider learning phase states when $f$ has sparsity-$s$, degree-$d$ in its $\mathbb{F}_2$ representation (with sample complexity $O(2^d sn)$), $f$ has Fourier-degree-$t$ (with sample complexity $O(2^{2t})$), and learning quadratic phase states with $\varepsilon$-global depolarizing noise (with sample complexity $O(n^{1+\varepsilon})$). These learning algorithms give us a procedure to learn the diagonal unitaries of the Clifford hierarchy and IQP circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mean estimation when you have the source code; or, quantum Monte Carlo methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07544</link>
    <author>Robin Kothari, Ryan O'Donnell</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Suppose $\boldsymbol{y}$ is a real random variable, and one is given access to ``the code'' that generates it (for example, a randomized or quantum circuit whose output is $\boldsymbol{y}$). We give a quantum procedure that runs the code $O(n)$ times and returns an estimate $\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}}$ for $\mu = \mathrm{E}[\boldsymbol{y}]$ that with high probability satisfies $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/n$, where $\sigma = \mathrm{stddev}[\boldsymbol{y}]$. This dependence on $n$ is optimal for quantum algorithms. One may compare with classical algorithms, which can only achieve the quadratically worse $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/\sqrt{n}$. Our method improves upon previous works, which either made additional assumptions about $\boldsymbol{y}$, and/or assumed the algorithm knew an a priori bound on $\sigma$, and/or used additional logarithmic factors beyond $O(n)$. The central subroutine for our result is essentially Grover's algorithm but with complex phases.ally Grover's algorithm but with complex phases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast erasure decoder for a class of quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01002</link>
    <author>Nicholas Connolly, Vivien Londe, Anthony Leverrier, Nicolas Delfosse</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a decoder for the correction of erasures with hypergraph product codes, which form one of the most popular families of quantum LDPC codes. Our numerical simulations show that this decoder provides a close approximation of the maximum likelihood decoder that can be implemented in O(N^2) bit operations where N is the length of the quantum code. A probabilistic version of this decoder can be implemented in O(N^1.5) bit operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time-Efficient Constant-Space-Overhead Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08826</link>
    <author>Hayata Yamasaki, Masato Koashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Scalable realization of quantum computation to attain substantial speedups over classical computation requires fault tolerance. Conventionally, fault-tolerant quantum computation (FTQC) demands excessive space overhead of physical qubits per logical qubit. A more recent protocol to achieve constant-space-overhead FTQC using quantum low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes thus attracts considerable attention but suffers from another drawback: it incurs polynomially long time overhead. We construct an alternative avenue of FTQC to achieve constant space overhead and only quasi-polylogarithmic time overhead simultaneously via techniques for using concatenations of different quantum Hamming codes rather than quantum LDPC codes. Our protocol achieves FTQC even if a decoder has nonzero runtime, unlike the existing constant-space-overhead protocol. These results establish a foundation for realizing FTQC within feasibly bounded space overhead yet negligibly tiny slowdown.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Solving boolean satisfiability problems with the quantum approximate optimization algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06909</link>
    <author>Sami Boulebnane, Ashley Montanaro</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) is one of the most prominent proposed applications for near-term quantum computing. Here we study the ability of QAOA to solve hard constraint satisfaction problems, as opposed to optimization problems. We focus on the fundamental boolean satisfiability problem, in the form of random $k$-SAT. We develop analytic bounds on the average success probability of QAOA over random boolean formulae at the satisfiability threshold, as the number of variables $n$ goes to infinity. The bounds hold for fixed parameters and when $k$ is a power of 2. We complement these theoretical results with numerical results on the performance of QAOA for small $n$, showing that these match the limiting theoretical bounds closely. We then use these results to compare QAOA with leading classical solvers. In the case of random 8-SAT, we find that for around 14 ansatz layers, QAOA matches the scaling performance of the highest-performance classical solver we tested, WalkSATlm. For larger numbers of layers, QAOA outperforms WalkSATlm, with an ultimate level of advantage that is still to be determined. Our methods provide a framework for analysing the performance of QAOA for hard constraint satisfaction problems and finding further speedups over classical algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Gauge Theory of Measurement-Based Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.10098</link>
    <author>Gabriel Wong, Robert Raussendorf, Bartlomiej Czech</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Measurement-Based Quantum Computation (MBQC) is a model of quantum computation, which uses local measurements instead of unitary gates. Here we explain that the MBQC procedure has a fundamental basis in an underlying gauge theory. This perspective provides a theoretical foundation for global aspects of MBQC. The gauge symmetry reflects the freedom of formulating the same MBQC computation in different local reference frames. The main identifications between MBQC and gauge theory concepts are: (i) the computational output of MBQC is a holonomy of the gauge field, (ii) the adaption of measurement basis that remedies the inherent randomness of quantum measurements is effected by gauge transformations. The gauge theory of MBQC also plays a role in characterizing the entanglement structure of symmetry-protected topologically (SPT) ordered states, which are resources for MBQC. Our framework situates MBQC in a broader context of condensed matter and high energy theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>What is nonclassical about uncertainty relations?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11779</link>
    <author>Lorenzo Catani, Matthew Leifer, Giovanni Scala, David Schmid, Robert W. Spekkens</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Uncertainty relations express limits on the extent to which the outcomes of distinct measurements on a single state can be made jointly predictable. The existence of nontrivial uncertainty relations in quantum theory is generally considered to be a way in which it entails a departure from the classical worldview. However, this view is undermined by the fact that there exist operational theories which exhibit nontrivial uncertainty relations but which are consistent with the classical worldview insofar as they admit of a generalized-noncontextual ontological model. This prompts the question of what aspects of uncertainty relations, if any, cannot be realized in this way and so constitute evidence of genuine nonclassicality. We here consider uncertainty relations describing the tradeoff between the predictability of a pair of binary-outcome measurements (e.g., measurements of Pauli X and Pauli Z observables in quantum theory). We show that, for a class of theories satisfying a particular symmetry property, the functional form of this predictability tradeoff is constrained by noncontextuality to be below a linear curve. Because qubit quantum theory has the relevant symmetry property, the fact that it has a quadratic tradeoff between these predictabilities is a violation of this noncontextual bound, and therefore constitutes an example of how the functional form of an uncertainty relation can witness contextuality. We also deduce the implications for a selected group of operational foils to quantum theory and consider the generalization to three measurements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Correcting non-independent and non-identically distributed errors with surface codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.02191</link>
    <author>Konstantin Tiurev, Peter-Jan H. S. Derks, Joschka Roffe, Jens Eisert, Jan-Michael Reiner</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A common approach to studying the performance of quantum error correcting codes is to assume independent and identically distributed single-qubit errors. However, realistic errors in experimental multi-qubit devices are typically neither independent nor identical across qubits. In this work, we develop and investigate the properties of topological surface codes tailored to a known noise channel by locally adapted Clifford conjugations. We show that the surface code locally tailored to non-uniform single-qubit noise in conjunction with a scalable matching decoder yields improved error thresholds and exponentially suppressed sub-threshold failure rates when compared to the Calderbank-Shor-Steane surface code. Furthermore, we study the behaviour of the tailored surface code under local two-qubit noise and show the role that code degeneracy plays in correcting such noise. The proposed methods do not require additional overhead in terms of the number of qubits and use a standard matching decoder, hence come at no extra cost compared to the standard surface-code error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A local pre-decoder to reduce the bandwidth and latency of quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04660</link>
    <author>Samuel C. Smith, Benjamin J. Brown, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A fault-tolerant quantum computer will be supported by a classical decoding system interfacing with quantum hardware to perform quantum error correction. It is important that the decoder can keep pace with the quantum clock speed, within the limitations on communication that are imposed by the physical architecture. To this end we propose a local `pre-decoder', which makes greedy corrections to reduce the amount of syndrome data sent to a standard matching decoder. We study these classical overheads for the surface code under a phenomenological phase-flip noise model with imperfect measurements. We find substantial improvements in the runtime of the global decoder and the communication bandwidth by using the pre-decoder. For instance, to achieve a logical failure probability of $f = 10^{-15}$ using qubits with physical error rate $p = 10^{-3}$ and a distance $d=22$ code, we find that the bandwidth cost is reduced by a factor of $1000$, and the time taken by a matching decoder is sped up by a factor of $200$. To achieve this target failure probability, the pre-decoding approach requires a $50\%$ increase in the qubit count compared with the optimal decoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact and efficient Lanczos method on a quantum computer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.00567</link>
    <author>William Kirby, Mario Motta, Antonio Mezzacapo</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an algorithm that uses block encoding on a quantum computer to exactly construct a Krylov space, which can be used as the basis for the Lanczos method to estimate extremal eigenvalues of Hamiltonians. While the classical Lanczos method has exponential cost in the system size to represent the Krylov states for quantum systems, our efficient quantum algorithm achieves this in polynomial time and memory. The construction presented is exact in the sense that the resulting Krylov space is identical to that of the Lanczos method, so the only approximation with respect to the Lanczos method is due to finite sample noise. This is possible because, unlike previous quantum versions of the Lanczos method, our algorithm does not require simulating real or imaginary time evolution. We provide an explicit error bound for the resulting ground state energy estimate in the presence of noise. For this method to be successful, the only requirement on the input problem is that the overlap of the initial state with the true ground state must be $\Omega(1/\text{poly}(n))$ for $n$ qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Publicly verifiable quantum money from random lattices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13135</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu, Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Publicly verifiable quantum money is a protocol for the preparation of quantum states that can be efficiently verified by any party for authenticity but is computationally infeasible to counterfeit. We develop a cryptographic scheme for publicly verifiable quantum money based on Gaussian superpositions over random lattices. We introduce a verification-of-authenticity procedure based on the lattice discrete Fourier transform, and subsequently prove the unforgeability of our quantum money under the hardness of the short vector problem from lattice-based cryptography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A parallel decoder for good quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05537</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a parallel decoding algorithm for recently discovered families of asymptotically good quantum low-density parity-check codes. This algorithm provably corrects arbitrary errors of weight linear in the code length, with a logarithmic number of steps. This decoder applies directly to the family of quantum Tanner codes, and serves as a subroutine for expander lifted product codes. Along the way, we exploit recently established bounds on the robustness of random tensor codes to give a tight bound on the minimum distance of quantum Tanner codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying Nonstabilizerness of Matrix Product States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13076</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, Lorenzo Piroli</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Nonstabilizerness, also known as magic, quantifies the number of non-Clifford operations needed in order to prepare a quantum state. As typical measures either involve minimization procedures or a computational cost exponential in the number of qubits $N$, it is notoriously hard to characterize for many-body states. In this work, we show that nonstabilizerness, as quantified by the recently introduced Stabilizer Rényi Entropies (SREs), can be computed efficiently for matrix product states (MPSs). Specifically, given an MPS of bond-dimension $\chi$ and integer Rényi index $n>1$, we show that the SRE can be expressed in terms of the norm of an MPS with bond-dimension $\chi^{2n}$. For translation-invariant states, this allows us to extract magic from a single tensor, the transfer matrix, while for generic MPSs this construction yields a computational cost linear in $N$ and polynomial in $\chi$. We exploit this observation to revisit the study of ground-state magic in the quantum Ising chain, providing accurate numerical results up to large system sizes. We analyze the SRE near criticality and investigate its dependence on the local computational basis. We show that it is in general not maximal at the critical point, and interpret our findings in terms of "long-range magic".</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Is there evidence for exponential quantum advantage in quantum chemistry?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.02199</link>
    <author>Seunghoon Lee, Joonho Lee, Huanchen Zhai, Yu Tong, Alexander M. Dalzell, Ashutosh Kumar, Phillip Helms, Johnnie Gray, Zhi-Hao Cui, Wenyuan Liu, Michael Kastoryano, Ryan Babbush, John Preskill, David R. Reichman, Earl T. Campbell, Edward F. Valeev, Lin Lin, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The idea to use quantum mechanical devices to simulate other quantum systems is commonly ascribed to Feynman. Since the original suggestion, concrete proposals have appeared for simulating molecular and materials chemistry through quantum computation, as a potential "killer application". Indications of potential exponential quantum advantage in artificial tasks have increased interest in this application, thus, it is critical to understand the basis for potential exponential quantum advantage in quantum chemistry. Here we gather the evidence for this case in the most common task in quantum chemistry, namely, ground-state energy estimation. We conclude that evidence for such an advantage across chemical space has yet to be found. While quantum computers may still prove useful for quantum chemistry, it may be prudent to assume exponential speedups are not generically available for this problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Preparing Many Copies of a Quantum State in the Black-Box Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11014</link>
    <author>Yassine Hamoudi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a simple quantum algorithm for preparing $K$ copies of an $N$-dimensional quantum state whose amplitudes are given by a quantum oracle. Our result extends a previous work of Grover, who showed how to prepare one copy in time $O(\sqrt{N})$. In comparison with the naive $O(K\sqrt{N})$ solution obtained by repeating this procedure~$K$ times, our algorithm achieves the optimal running time of $\theta(\sqrt{KN})$. Our technique uses a refinement of the quantum rejection sampling method employed by Grover. As a direct application, we obtain a similar speed-up for obtaining $K$ independent samples from a distribution whose probability vector is given by a quantum oracle.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fundamental Limitation on the Detectability of Entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.02518</link>
    <author>Pengyu Liu, Zhenhuan Liu, Shu Chen, Xiongfeng Ma</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement detection is essential in quantum information science and quantum many-body physics. It has been proved that entanglement exists almost surely for a random quantum state, while the realizations of effective entanglement criteria usually consume exponential resources, and efficient criteria often perform poorly without prior knowledge. This fact implies a fundamental limitation might exist in the detectability of entanglement. In this work, we formalize this limitation as a fundamental trade-off between the efficiency and effectiveness of entanglement criteria via a systematic method to theoretically evaluate the detection capability of entanglement criteria. For a system coupled to an environment, we prove that any entanglement criterion needs exponentially many observables to detect the entanglement effectively when restricted to single-copy operations. Otherwise, the detection capability of the criterion will decay double-exponentially. Furthermore, if multi-copy joint measurements are allowed, the effectiveness of entanglement detection can be exponentially improved, which implies a quantum advantage in entanglement detection problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14280</link>
    <author>Matthew P. A. Fisher, Vedika Khemani, Adam Nahum, Sagar Vijay</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum circuits -- built from local unitary gates and local measurements -- are a new playground for quantum many-body physics and a tractable setting to explore universal collective phenomena far-from-equilibrium. These models have shed light on longstanding questions about thermalization and chaos, and on the underlying universal dynamics of quantum information and entanglement. In addition, such models generate new sets of questions and give rise to phenomena with no traditional analog, such as new dynamical phases in quantum systems that are monitored by an external observer. Quantum circuit dynamics is also topical in view of experimental progress in building digital quantum simulators that allow control of precisely these ingredients. Randomness in the circuit elements allows a high level of theoretical control, with a key theme being mappings between real-time quantum dynamics and effective classical lattice models or dynamical processes. Many of the universal phenomena that can be identified in this tractable setting apply to much wider classes of more structured many-body dynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Techniques for combining fast local decoders with global decoders under circuit-level noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01178</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Luis Goncalves, Prasahnt Sivarajah, Eric Peterson, Sebastian Grimberg</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Implementing algorithms on a fault-tolerant quantum computer will require fast decoding throughput and latency times to prevent an exponential increase in buffer times between the applications of gates. In this work we begin by quantifying these requirements. We then introduce the construction of local neural network (NN) decoders using three-dimensional convolutions. These local decoders are adapted to circuit-level noise and can be applied to surface code volumes of arbitrary size. Their application removes errors arising from a certain number of faults, which serves to substantially reduce the syndrome density. Remaining errors can then be corrected by a global decoder, such as Blossom or Union Find, with their implementation significantly accelerated due to the reduced syndrome density. However, in the circuit-level setting, the corrections applied by the local decoder introduce many vertical pairs of highlighted vertices. To obtain a low syndrome density in the presence of vertical pairs, we consider a strategy of performing a syndrome collapse which removes many vertical pairs and reduces the size of the decoding graph used by the global decoder. We also consider a strategy of performing a vertical cleanup, which consists of removing all local vertical pairs prior to implementing the global decoder. Lastly, we estimate the cost of implementing our local decoders on Field Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGAs).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Data Center: Theories and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14336</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Connor T. Hann, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we propose the Quantum Data Center (QDC), an architecture combining Quantum Random Access Memory (QRAM) and quantum networks. We give a precise definition of QDC, and discuss its possible realizations and extensions. We discuss applications of QDC in quantum computation, quantum communication, and quantum sensing, with a primary focus on QDC for $T$-gate resources, QDC for multi-party private quantum communication, and QDC for distributed sensing through data compression. We show that QDC will provide efficient, private, and fast services as a future version of data centers.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>