<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Foundations for learning from noisy quantum experiments</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.13691</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Steven T. Flammia, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding what can be learned from experiments is central to scientific progress. In this work, we use a learning-theoretic perspective to study the task of learning physical operations in a quantum machine when all operations (state preparation, dynamics, and measurement) are a priori unknown. We prove that, without any prior knowledge, if one can explore the full quantum state space by composing the operations, then every operation can be learned. When one cannot explore the full state space but all operations are approximately known and noise in Clifford gates is gate-independent, we find an efficient algorithm for learning all operations up to a single unlearnable parameter characterizing the fidelity of the initial state. For learning a noise channel on Clifford gates to a fixed accuracy, our algorithm uses quadratically fewer experiments than previously known protocols. Under more general conditions, the true description of the noise can be unlearnable; for example, we prove that no benchmarking protocol can learn gate-dependent Pauli noise on Clifford+T gates even under perfect state preparation and measurement. Despite not being able to learn the noise, we show that a noisy quantum computer that performs entangled measurements on multiple copies of an unknown state can yield a large advantage in learning properties of the state compared to a noiseless device that measures individual copies and then processes the measurement data using a classical computer. Concretely, we prove that noisy quantum computers with two-qubit gate error rate $\epsilon$ can achieve a learning task using $N$ copies of the state, while $N^{\Omega(1/\epsilon)}$ copies are required classically.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum many-body systems in thermal equilibrium</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08349</link>
    <author>Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The thermal or equilibrium ensemble is one of the most ubiquitous states of matter. For models comprised of many locally interacting quantum particles, it describes a wide range of physical situations, relevant to condensed matter physics, high energy physics, quantum chemistry and quantum computing, among others. We give a pedagogical overview of some of the most important universal features about the physics and complexity of these states, which have the locality of the Hamiltonian at its core. We focus on mathematically rigorous statements, many of them inspired by ideas and tools from quantum information theory. These include bounds on their correlations, the form of the subsystems, various statistical properties, and the performance of classical and quantum algorithms. We also include a summary of a few of the most important technical tools, as well as some self-contained proofs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Modern applications of machine learning in quantum sciences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04198</link>
    <author>Anna Dawid, Julian Arnold, Borja Requena, Alexander Gresch, Marcin Płodzień, Kaelan Donatella, Kim Nicoli, Paolo Stornati, Rouven Koch, Miriam Büttner, Robert Okuła, Gorka Muñoz-Gil, Rodrigo A. Vargas-Hernández, Alba Cervera-Lierta, Juan Carrasquilla, Vedran Dunjko, Marylou Gabrié, Patrick Huembeli, Evert van Nieuwenburg, Filippo Vicentini, et al (9)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In these Lecture Notes, we provide a comprehensive introduction to the most recent advances in the application of machine learning methods in quantum sciences. We cover the use of deep learning and kernel methods in supervised, unsupervised, and reinforcement learning algorithms for phase classification, representation of many-body quantum states, quantum feedback control, and quantum circuits optimization. Moreover, we introduce and discuss more specialized topics such as differentiable programming, generative models, statistical approach to machine learning, and quantum machine learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Verifiable Quantum Advantage without Structure</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02063</link>
    <author>Takashi Yamakawa, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show the following hold, unconditionally unless otherwise stated, relative to a random oracle with probability 1: - There are NP search problems solvable by BQP machines but not BPP machines. - There exist functions that are one-way, and even collision resistant, against classical adversaries but are easily inverted quantumly. Similar separations hold for digital signatures and CPA-secure public key encryption (the latter requiring the assumption of a classically CPA-secure encryption scheme). Interestingly, the separation does not necessarily extend to the case of other cryptographic objects such as PRGs. - There are unconditional publicly verifiable proofs of quantumness with the minimal rounds of interaction: for uniform adversaries, the proofs are non-interactive, whereas for non-uniform adversaries the proofs are two message public coin. - Our results do not appear to contradict the Aaronson-Ambanis conjecture. Assuming this conjecture, there exist publicly verifiable certifiable randomness, again with the minimal rounds of interaction. By replacing the random oracle with a concrete cryptographic hash function such as SHA2, we obtain plausible Minicrypt instantiations of the above results. Previous analogous results all required substantial structure, either in terms of highly structured oracles and/or algebraic assumptions in Cryptomania and beyond.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of variational quantum algorithms: a quantum optimal transport approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03455</link>
    <author>Giacomo De Palma, Milad Marvian, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The impressive progress in quantum hardware of the last years has raised the interest of the quantum computing community in harvesting the computational power of such devices. However, in the absence of error correction, these devices can only reliably implement very shallow circuits or comparatively deeper circuits at the expense of a nontrivial density of errors. In this work, we obtain extremely tight limitation bounds for standard NISQ proposals in both the noisy and noiseless regimes, with or without error-mitigation tools. The bounds limit the performance of both circuit model algorithms, such as QAOA, and also continuous-time algorithms, such as quantum annealing. In the noisy regime with local depolarizing noise $p$, we prove that at depths $L=\cO(p^{-1})$ it is exponentially unlikely that the outcome of a noisy quantum circuit outperforms efficient classical algorithms for combinatorial optimization problems like Max-Cut. Although previous results already showed that classical algorithms outperform noisy quantum circuits at constant depth, these results only held for the expectation value of the output. Our results are based on newly developed quantum entropic and concentration inequalities, which constitute a homogeneous toolkit of theoretical methods from the quantum theory of optimal mass transport whose potential usefulness goes beyond the study of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Chain rules for quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11153</link>
    <author>Mario Berta, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Divergence chain rules for channels relate the divergence of a pair of channel inputs and to the divergence of the corresponding channel outputs. An important special case of such a rule is the data-processing inequality, which tells us that if the same channel is applied to both inputs then the divergence cannot increase. Based on direct matrix analysis methods, we derive several Rényi divergence chain rules for channels in the quantum setting. Our results simplify and in some cases generalise previous derivations in the literature.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Clifford Circuits can be Properly PAC Learned if and only if $\textsf{RP}=\textsf{NP}$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06638</link>
    <author>Daniel Liang</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a dataset of input states, measurements, and probabilities, is it possible to efficiently predict the measurement probabilities associated with a quantum circuit? Recent work of Caro and Datta (2020) studied the problem of PAC learning quantum circuits in an information theoretic sense, leaving open questions of computational efficiency. In particular, one candidate class of circuits for which an efficient learner might have been possible was that of Clifford circuits, since the corresponding set of states generated by such circuits, called stabilizer states, are known to be efficiently PAC learnable (Rocchetto 2018). Here we provide a negative result, showing that proper learning of CNOT circuits is hard for classical learners unless $\textsf{RP} = \textsf{NP}$. As the classical analogue and subset of Clifford circuits, this naturally leads to a hardness result for Clifford circuits as well. Additionally, we show that if $\textsf{RP} = \textsf{NP}$ then there would exist efficient proper learning algorithms for CNOT and Clifford circuits. By similar arguments, we also find that an efficient proper quantum learner for such circuits exists if and only if $\textsf{NP} \subseteq \textsf{RQP}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Out-of-distribution generalization for learning quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10268</link>
    <author>Matthias C. Caro, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Nicholas Ezzell, Joe Gibbs, Andrew T. Sornborger, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Generalization bounds are a critical tool to assess the training data requirements of Quantum Machine Learning (QML). Recent work has established guarantees for in-distribution generalization of quantum neural networks (QNNs), where training and testing data are assumed to be drawn from the same data distribution. However, there are currently no results on out-of-distribution generalization in QML, where we require a trained model to perform well even on data drawn from a distribution different from the training distribution. In this work, we prove out-of-distribution generalization for the task of learning an unknown unitary using a QNN and for a broad class of training and testing distributions. In particular, we show that one can learn the action of a unitary on entangled states using only product state training data. We numerically illustrate this by showing that the evolution of a Heisenberg spin chain can be learned using only product training states. Since product states can be prepared using only single-qubit gates, this advances the prospects of learning quantum dynamics using near term quantum computers and quantum experiments, and further opens up new methods for both the classical and quantum compilation of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Routing with Teleportation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04185</link>
    <author>Dhruv Devulapalli, Eddie Schoute, Aniruddha Bapat, Andrew M. Childs, Alexey V. Gorshkov</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of implementing arbitrary permutations of qubits under interaction constraints in quantum systems that allow for arbitrarily fast local operations and classical communication (LOCC). In particular, we show examples of speedups over swap-based and more general unitary routing methods by distributing entanglement and using LOCC to perform quantum teleportation. We further describe an example of an interaction graph for which teleportation gives a logarithmic speedup in the worst-case routing time over swap-based routing. We also study limits on the speedup afforded by quantum teleportation - showing an $O(\sqrt{N \log N})$ upper bound on the separation in routing time for any interaction graph - and give tighter bounds for some common classes of graphs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Partitioning qubits in hypergraph product codes to implement logical gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10812</link>
    <author>Armanda O. Quintavalle, Paul Webster, Michael Vasmer</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The promise of high-rate low-density parity check (LDPC) codes to substantially reduce the overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation depends on constructing efficient, fault-tolerant implementations of logical gates on such codes. Transversal gates are the simplest type of fault-tolerant gate, but the potential of transversal gates on LDPC codes has hitherto been largely neglected. We investigate the transversal gates that can be implemented in hypergraph product codes, a class of LDPC codes. Our analysis is aided by the construction of a symplectic canonical basis for the logical operators of hypergraph product codes, a result that may be of independent interest. We show that in these codes transversal gates can implement Hadamard (up to logical SWAP gates) and control-Z on all logical qubits. Moreover, we show that sequences of transversal operations, interleaved with error correction, allow implementation of entangling gates between arbitrary pairs of logical qubits in the same code block. We thereby demonstrate that transversal gates can be used as the basis for universal quantum computing on LDPC codes, when supplemented with state injection.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Imaging stars with quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06044</link>
    <author>Zixin Huang, Gavin K. Brennen, Yingkai Ouyang</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The development of high-resolution, large-baseline optical interferometers would revolutionize astronomical imaging. However, classical techniques are hindered by physical limitations including loss, noise, and the fact that the received light is generally quantum in nature. We show how to overcome these issues using quantum communication techniques. We present a general framework for using quantum error correction codes for protecting and imaging starlight received at distant telescope sites. In our scheme, the quantum state of light is coherently captured into a non-radiative atomic state via Stimulated Raman Adiabatic Passage, which is then imprinted into a quantum error correction code. The code protects the signal during subsequent potentially noisy operations necessary to extract the image parameters. We show that even a small quantum error correction code can offer significant protection against noise. For large codes, we find noise thresholds below which the information can be preserved. Our scheme represents an application for near-term quantum devices that can increase imaging resolution beyond what is feasible using classical techniques.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ground state preparation and energy estimation on early fault-tolerant quantum computers via quantum eigenvalue transformation of unitary matrices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.05955</link>
    <author>Yulong Dong, Lin Lin, Yu Tong</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Under suitable assumptions, the algorithms in [Lin, Tong, Quantum 2020] can estimate the ground state energy and prepare the ground state of a quantum Hamiltonian with near-optimal query complexities. However, this is based on a block encoding input model of the Hamiltonian, whose implementation is known to require a large resource overhead. We develop a tool called quantum eigenvalue transformation of unitary matrices with real polynomials (QET-U), which uses a controlled Hamiltonian evolution as the input model, a single ancilla qubit and no multi-qubit control operations, and is thus suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum devices. This leads to a simple quantum algorithm that outperforms all previous algorithms with a comparable circuit structure for estimating the ground state energy. For a class of quantum spin Hamiltonians, we propose a new method that exploits certain anti-commutation relations and further removes the need of implementing the controlled Hamiltonian evolution. Coupled with Trotter based approximation of the Hamiltonian evolution, the resulting algorithm can be very suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum devices. We demonstrate the performance of the algorithm using IBM Qiskit for the transverse field Ising model. If we are further allowed to use multi-qubit Toffoli gates, we can then implement amplitude amplification and a new binary amplitude estimation algorithm, which increases the circuit depth but decreases the total query complexity. The resulting algorithm saturates the near-optimal complexity for ground state preparation and energy estimating using a constant number of ancilla qubits (no more than 3).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Maximal entanglement velocity implies dual unitarity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10341</link>
    <author>Tianci Zhou, Aram W. Harrow</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A global quantum quench can be modeled by a quantum circuit with local unitary gates. In general, entanglement grows linearly at a rate given by entanglement velocity, which is upper bounded by the growth of the light cone. We show that the unitary interactions achieving the maximal rate must remain unitary if we exchange the space and time directions -- a property known as dual unitarity. Our results are robust: approximate maximal entanglement velocity also implies approximate dual unitarity. We further show that maximal entanglement velocity is always accompanied by a specific dynamical pattern of entanglement, which yields simpler analyses of several known exactly solvable models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Establishing trust in quantum computations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07568</link>
    <author>Timothy Proctor, Stefan Seritan, Erik Nielsen, Kenneth Rudinger, Kevin Young, Robin Blume-Kohout, Mohan Sarovar</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Real-world quantum computers have grown sufficiently complex that they can no longer be simulated by classical supercomputers, but their computational power remains limited by errors. These errors corrupt the results of quantum algorithms, and it is no longer always feasible to use classical simulations to directly check the correctness of quantum computations. Without practical methods for quantifying the accuracy with which a quantum algorithm has been executed, it is difficult to establish trust in the results of a quantum computation. Here we solve this problem, by introducing a simple and efficient technique for measuring the fidelity with which an as-built quantum computer can execute an algorithm. Our technique converts the algorithm's quantum circuits into a set of closely related circuits whose success rates can be efficiently measured. It enables measuring the fidelity of quantum algorithm executions both in the near-term, with algorithms run on hundreds or thousands of physical qubits, and into the future, with algorithms run on logical qubits protected by quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum variational learning for quantum error-correcting codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03560</link>
    <author>Chenfeng Cao, Chao Zhang, Zipeng Wu, Markus Grassl, Bei Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error-correcting codes (QECCs) are believed to be a necessity for large-scale fault-tolerant quantum computation. In the past two decades, various methods of QECC constructions have been developed, leading to many good families of codes. However, the majority of these codes are not suitable for near-term quantum devices. Here we present VarQEC, a noise-resilient variational quantum algorithm to search for quantum codes with a hardware-efficient encoding circuit. The cost functions are inspired by the most general and fundamental requirements of a QECC, the Knill-Laflamme conditions. Given the target noise channel (or the target code parameters) and the hardware connectivity graph, we optimize a shallow variational quantum circuit to prepare the basis states of an eligible code. In principle, VarQEC can find quantum codes for any error model, whether additive or non-additive, degenerate or non-degenerate, pure or impure. We have verified its effectiveness by (re)discovering some symmetric and asymmetric codes, e.g., $((n,2^{n-6},3))_2$ for $n$ from 7 to 14. We also found new $((6,2,3))_2$ and $((7,2,3))_2$ codes that are not equivalent to any stabilizer code, and extensive numerical evidence with VarQEC suggests that a $((7,3,3))_2$ code does not exist. Furthermore, we found many new channel-adaptive codes for error models involving nearest-neighbor correlated errors. Our work sheds new light on the understanding of QECC in general, which may also help to enhance near-term device performance with channel-adaptive error-correcting codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Certifiable Randomness from a Single Quantum Device</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11353</link>
    <author>Urmila Mahadev, Umesh Vazirani, Thomas Vidick</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Brakerski et. al [BCM+18] introduced the model of cryptographic testing of a single untrusted quantum device and gave a protocol for certifiable randomness generation. We use the leakage resilience properties of the Learning With Errors problem to address a key issue left open in previous work - the rate of generation of randomness. Our new protocol can certify $\Omega(n)$ fresh bits of randomness in constant rounds, where $n$ is a parameter of the protocol and the total communication is $O(n)$, thus achieving a nearly optimal rate. The proof that the output is statistically random is conceptually simple and technically elementary.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complexity phase transitions in instantaneous quantum polynomial-time circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08898</link>
    <author>Chae-Yeun Park, Michael J. Kastoryano</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study a subclass of the Instantaneous Quantum Polynomial-time (IQP) circuit with a varying density of two-qubit gates. We identify two phase transitions as a function of the gate density. At the first transition, the coherent Gibbs representation of the output state transitions from quasilocal to extended, and becomes completely non-local after the second transition, resembling that of Haar random states. We introduce several new diagnostics to argue that learning the distribution after the first transition already becomes classically intractable, even though its output distribution is far from random. Our work thus opens a novel pathway for exploring quantum advantage in more practical setups whose outcome distributions are more structured than random states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Cleaning Lemma of Quantum Coding Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04699</link>
    <author>Gleb Kalachev, Sergey Sadov</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The term "Cleaning Lemma" refers to a family of similar propositions that have been used in Quantum Coding Theory to estimate the minimum distance of a code in terms of its length and dimension. We show that the mathematical core is a simple fact of linear algebra of inner product spaces; moreover, it admits a further reduction to a combinatorial, lattice-theoretical level. Several concrete variants of the Cleaning Lemma and some additional propositions are derived as corollaries of the proposed approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring magic on a quantum processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.00015</link>
    <author>Salvatore F.E. Oliviero, Lorenzo Leone, Alioscia Hamma, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic states are the resource that allows quantum computers to attain an advantage over classical computers. This resource consists in the deviation from a property called stabilizerness which in turn implies that stabilizer circuits can be efficiently simulated on a classical computer. Without magic, no quantum computer can do anything that a classical computer cannot do. Given the importance of magic for quantum computation, it would be useful to have a method for measuring the amount of magic in a quantum state. In this work, we propose and experimentally demonstrate a protocol for measuring magic based on randomized measurements. Our experiments are carried out on two IBM Quantum Falcon processors. This protocol can provide a characterization of the effectiveness of a quantum hardware in producing states that cannot be effectively simulated on a classical computer. We show how from these measurements one can construct realistic noise models affecting the hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>ADAPT-VQE is insensitive to rough parameter landscapes and barren plateaus</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07179</link>
    <author>Harper R. Grimsley, George S. Barron, Edwin Barnes, Sophia E. Economou, Nicholas J. Mayhall</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum eigensolvers (VQEs) represent a powerful class of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms for computing molecular energies. Various numerical issues exist for these methods, however, including barren plateaus and large numbers of local minima. In this work, we consider Adaptive, Problem-Tailored (ADAPT)-VQE ansätze, and examine how they are impacted by these local minima. We find that while ADAPT-VQE does not remove local minima, the gradient-informed, one-operator-at-a-time circuit construction seems to accomplish two things: First, it provides an initialization strategy that is dramatically better than random initialization, and which is applicable in situations where chemical intuition cannot help with initialization, i.e., when Hartree-Fock is a poor approximation to the ground state. Second, even if an ADAPT-VQE iteration converges to a local trap at one step, it can still "burrow" toward the exact solution by adding more operators, which preferentially deepens the occupied trap. This same mechanism helps highlight a surprising feature of ADAPT-VQE: It should not suffer optimization problems due to "barren plateaus". Even if barren plateaus appear in the parameter landscape, our analysis and simulations reveal that ADAPT-VQE avoids such regions by design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bi-PPT channels are entanglement breaking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01685</link>
    <author>Alexander Müller-Hermes, Satvik Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a recent paper, Hirche and Leditzky introduced the notion of bi-PPT channels which are quantum channels that stay completely positive under composition with a transposition and such that the same property holds for one of their complementary channels. They asked whether there are examples of such channels that are not antidegradable. We show that this is not the case, since bi-PPT channels are always entanglement breaking. We also show that degradable quantum channels staying completely positive under composition with a transposition are entanglement breaking.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dynamical simulation via quantum machine learning with provable generalization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10269</link>
    <author>Joe Gibbs, Zoë Holmes, Matthias C. Caro, Nicholas Ezzell, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Lukasz Cincio, Andrew T. Sornborger, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Much attention has been paid to dynamical simulation and quantum machine learning (QML) independently as applications for quantum advantage, while the possibility of using QML to enhance dynamical simulations has not been thoroughly investigated. Here we develop a framework for using QML methods to simulate quantum dynamics on near-term quantum hardware. We use generalization bounds, which bound the error a machine learning model makes on unseen data, to rigorously analyze the training data requirements of an algorithm within this framework. This provides a guarantee that our algorithm is resource-efficient, both in terms of qubit and data requirements. Our numerics exhibit efficient scaling with problem size, and we simulate 20 times longer than Trotterization on IBMQ-Bogota.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical algorithms for many-body quantum systems at finite energies</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.09439</link>
    <author>Yilun Yang, J. Ignacio Cirac, Mari Carmen Bañuls</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate quantum inspired algorithms to compute physical observables of quantum many-body systems at finite energies. They are based on the quantum algorithms proposed in [Lu et al. PRX Quantum 2, 020321 (2021)], which use the quantum simulation of the dynamics of such systems, as well as classical filtering and sampling techniques. Here, we replace the quantum simulation by standard classical methods based on matrix product states and operators. As a result, we can address significantly larger systems than those reachable by exact diagonalization or by other algorithms. We demonstrate the performance with spin chains up to 80 sites.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Variational Ansatz for the Ground State of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02923</link>
    <author>Paul M. Schindler, Tommaso Guaita, Tao Shi, Eugene Demler, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an ansatz for the ground states of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model, a paradigmatic model for quantum spin glasses. Our ansatz, based on the concept of generalized coherent states, very well captures the fundamental aspects of the model, including the ground state energy and the position of the spin glass phase transition. It further enables us to study some previously unexplored features, such as the non-vanishing longitudinal field regime and the entanglement structure of the ground states. We find that the ground state entanglement can be captured by a simple ensemble of weighted graph states with normally distributed phase gates, leading to a volume law entanglement, contrasting with predictions based on entanglement monogamy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>How to simulate key properties of lithium-ion batteries with a fault-tolerant quantum computer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11890</link>
    <author>Alain Delgado, Pablo A. M. Casares, Roberto dos Reis, Modjtaba Shokrian Zini, Roberto Campos, Norge Cruz-Hernández, Arne-Christian Voigt, Angus Lowe, Soran Jahangiri, M. A. Martin-Delgado, Jonathan E. Mueller, Juan Miguel Arrazola</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>There is a pressing need to develop new rechargeable battery technologies that can offer higher energy storage, faster charging, and lower costs. Despite the success of existing methods for the simulation of battery materials, they can sometimes fall short of delivering accurate and reliable results. Quantum computing has been discussed as an avenue to overcome these issues, but only limited work has been done to outline how they may impact battery simulations. In this work, we provide a detailed answer to the following question: how can a quantum computer be used to simulate key properties of a lithium-ion battery? Based on recently-introduced first-quantization techniques, we lay out an end-to-end quantum algorithm for calculating equilibrium cell voltages, ionic mobility, and thermal stability. These can be obtained from ground-state energies of materials, which is the core calculation executed by the quantum computer using qubitization-based quantum phase estimation. The algorithm includes explicit methods for preparing approximate ground states of periodic materials in first quantization. We bring these insights together to perform the first estimation of the resources required to implement a quantum algorithm for simulating a realistic cathode material, dilithium iron silicate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable measures of magic for quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10061</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, M. S. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic characterizes the degree of non-stabilizerness of quantum states. It is a crucial resource for quantum computing and a necessary condition for quantum advantage. However, quantifying magic beyond a few qubits has been a major challenge. Here, we introduce Bell magic to efficiently measure magic for any number of qubits. Our method can be easily implemented in experiments together with a cost-free error mitigation scheme. We experimentally demonstrate the transition of classically simulable stabilizer states into intractable quantum states on the IonQ quantum computer. For applications, Bell magic distinguishes stabilizer and magical states with a low measurement cost. Further, variational quantum algorithms can maximize the magic of quantum states via the shift-rule. Our results pave the way to benchmark the non-classical power of quantum computers, quantum simulators and quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A general framework for the composition of quantum homomorphic encryption \& quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10471</link>
    <author>Yingkai Ouyang, Peter P. Rohde</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two essential primitives for universal, cloud-based quantum computation with security based on the laws of quantum mechanics, are quantum homomorphic encryption with information-theoretic security and quantum error correction. The former enables information-theoretic security of outsourced quantum computation, while the latter allows reliable and scalable quantum computations in the presence of errors. Previously these ingredients have been considered in isolation from one another. By establishing group-theoretic requirements that these two ingredients must satisfy, we provide a general framework for composing them. Namely, a quantum homomorphic encryption scheme enhanced with quantum error correction can directly inherit its properties from its constituent quantum homomorphic encryption and quantum error correction schemes. We apply our framework to both discrete- and continuous-variable models for quantum computation, such as Pauli-key and permutation-key encryptions in the qubit model, and displacement-key encryptions in a continuous-variable model based on Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tight Bounds for Quantum State Certification with Incoherent Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07155</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Brice Huang, Jerry Li, Allen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of quantum state certification, where we are given the description of a mixed state $\sigma \in \mathbb{C}^{d \times d}$, $n$ copies of a mixed state $\rho \in \mathbb{C}^{d \times d}$, and $\varepsilon > 0$, and we are asked to determine whether $\rho = \sigma$ or whether $\| \rho - \sigma \|_1 > \varepsilon$. When $\sigma$ is the maximally mixed state $\frac{1}{d} I_d$, this is known as mixedness testing. We focus on algorithms which use incoherent measurements, i.e. which only measure one copy of $\rho$ at a time. Unlike those that use entangled, multi-copy measurements, these can be implemented without persistent quantum memory and thus represent a large class of protocols that can be run on current or near-term devices. For mixedness testing, there is a folklore algorithm which uses incoherent measurements and only needs $O(d^{3/2} / \varepsilon^2)$ copies. The algorithm is non-adaptive, that is, its measurements are fixed ahead of time, and is known to be optimal for non-adaptive algorithms. However, when the algorithm can make arbitrary incoherent measurements, the best known lower bound is only $\Omega (d^{4/3} / \varepsilon^2)$ [Bubeck-Chen-Li '20], and it has been an outstanding open problem to close this polynomial gap. In this work, 1) we settle the copy complexity of mixedness testing with incoherent measurements and show that $\Omega (d^{3/2} / \varepsilon^2)$ copies are necessary, and 2) we show the instance-optimal bounds for state certification to general $\sigma$ first derived by [Chen-Li-O'Donnell '21] for non-adaptive measurements also hold for arbitrary incoherent measurements. Qualitatively, our results say that adaptivity does not help at all for these problems. Our results are based on new techniques that allow us to reduce the problem to understanding certain matrix martingales, which we believe may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gaussian matrix product states cannot efficiently describe critical systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02478</link>
    <author>Adrián Franco-Rubio, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gaussian fermionic matrix product states (GfMPS) form a class of ansatz quantum states for 1d systems of noninteracting fermions. We show, for a simple critical model of free hopping fermions, that: (i) any GfMPS approximation to its ground state must have bond dimension scaling superpolynomially with the system size, whereas (ii) there exists a non-Gaussian fermionic MPS approximation to this state with polynomial bond dimension. This proves that, in general, imposing Gaussianity at the level of the tensor network may significantly alter its capability to efficiently approximate critical Gaussian states. We also provide numerical evidence that the required bond dimension is subexponential, and thus can still be simulated with moderate resources.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Diagrammatic Analysis for Parameterized Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01307</link>
    <author>Tobias Stollenwerk, Stuart Hadfield</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Diagrammatic representations of quantum algorithms and circuits offer novel approaches to their design and analysis. In this work, we describe extensions of the ZX-calculus especially suitable for parameterized quantum circuits, in particular for computing observable expectation values as functions of or for fixed parameters, which are important algorithmic quantities in a variety of applications ranging from combinatorial optimization to quantum chemistry. We provide several new ZX-diagram rewrite rules and generalizations for this setting. In particular, we give formal rules for dealing with linear combinations of ZX-diagrams, where the relative complex-valued scale factors of each diagram must be kept track of, in contrast to most previously studied single-diagram realizations where these coefficients can be effectively ignored. This allows us to directly import a number useful relations from the operator analysis to ZX-calculus setting, including causal cone and quantum gate commutation rules. We demonstrate that the diagrammatic approach offers useful insights into algorithm structure and performance by considering several ansätze from the literature including realizations of hardware-efficient ansätze and QAOA. We find that by employing a diagrammatic representation, calculations across different ansätze can become more intuitive and potentially easier approach systematically than by alternative means. Finally, we outline how diagrammatic approaches may aid in the design and study of new and more effective quantum circuit ansätze.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>