<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The randomized measurement toolbox</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11374</link>
    <author>Andreas Elben, Steven T. Flammia, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, John Preskill, Benoît Vermersch, Peter Zoller</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Increasingly sophisticated programmable quantum simulators and quantum computers are opening unprecedented opportunities for exploring and exploiting the properties of highly entangled complex quantum systems. The complexity of large quantum systems is the source of their power, but also makes them difficult to control precisely or characterize accurately using measured classical data. We review recently developed protocols for probing the properties of complex many-qubit systems using measurement schemes that are practical using today's quantum platforms. In all these protocols, a quantum state is repeatedly prepared and measured in a randomly chosen basis; then a classical computer processes the measurement outcomes to estimate the desired property. The randomization of the measurement procedure has distinct advantages; for example, a single data set can be employed multiple times to pursue a variety of applications, and imperfections in the measurements are mapped to a simplified noise model that can more easily be mitigated. We discuss a range of use cases that have already been realized in quantum devices, including Hamiltonian simulation tasks, probes of quantum chaos, measurements of nonlocal order parameters, and comparison of quantum states produced in distantly separated laboratories. By providing a workable method for translating a complex quantum state into a succinct classical representation that preserves a rich variety of relevant physical properties, the randomized measurement toolbox strengthens our ability to grasp and control the quantum world.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random quantum circuits are approximate unitary $t$-designs in depth $O\left(nt^{5+o(1)}\right)$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16571</link>
    <author>Jonas Haferkamp</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The applications of random quantum circuits range from quantum computing and quantum many-body systems to the physics of black holes. Many of these applications are related to the generation of quantum pseudorandomness: Random quantum circuits are known to approximate unitary $t$-designs. Unitary $t$-designs are probability distributions that mimic Haar randomness up to $t$th moments. In a seminal paper, Brandão, Harrow and Horodecki prove that random quantum circuits in a brickwork architecture of depth $O(n t^{10.5})$ are approximate unitary $t$-design. In this work, we revisit this argument, which lower bounds the spectral gap of moment operators for local random quantum circuits by $\Omega(n^{-1}t^{-9.5})$. We improve this lower bound to $\Omega(n^{-1}t^{-4-o(1)})$. A direct consequence of this scaling is that random quantum circuits generate approximate unitary $t$-designs in depth $O(nt^{5+o(1)})$. Our techniques involve Gao's quantum union bound and the unreasonable effectiveness of the Clifford group. As an auxiliary result, we prove a near optimal convergence to the Haar measure for random Clifford unitaries interleaved with Haar random single qubit unitaries in Wasserstein distance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Modern applications of machine learning in quantum sciences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04198</link>
    <author>Anna Dawid, Julian Arnold, Borja Requena, Alexander Gresch, Marcin Płodzień, Kaelan Donatella, Kim Nicoli, Paolo Stornati, Rouven Koch, Miriam Büttner, Robert Okuła, Gorka Muñoz-Gil, Rodrigo A. Vargas-Hernández, Alba Cervera-Lierta, Juan Carrasquilla, Vedran Dunjko, Marylou Gabrié, Patrick Huembeli, Evert van Nieuwenburg, Filippo Vicentini, et al (9)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In these Lecture Notes, we provide a comprehensive introduction to the most recent advances in the application of machine learning methods in quantum sciences. We cover the use of deep learning and kernel methods in supervised, unsupervised, and reinforcement learning algorithms for phase classification, representation of many-body quantum states, quantum feedback control, and quantum circuits optimization. Moreover, we introduce and discuss more specialized topics such as differentiable programming, generative models, statistical approach to machine learning, and quantum machine learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Verifiable Quantum Advantage without Structure</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02063</link>
    <author>Takashi Yamakawa, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show the following hold, unconditionally unless otherwise stated, relative to a random oracle with probability 1: - There are NP search problems solvable by BQP machines but not BPP machines. - There exist functions that are one-way, and even collision resistant, against classical adversaries but are easily inverted quantumly. Similar separations hold for digital signatures and CPA-secure public key encryption (the latter requiring the assumption of a classically CPA-secure encryption scheme). Interestingly, the separation does not necessarily extend to the case of other cryptographic objects such as PRGs. - There are unconditional publicly verifiable proofs of quantumness with the minimal rounds of interaction: for uniform adversaries, the proofs are non-interactive, whereas for non-uniform adversaries the proofs are two message public coin. - Our results do not appear to contradict the Aaronson-Ambanis conjecture. Assuming this conjecture, there exist publicly verifiable certifiable randomness, again with the minimal rounds of interaction. By replacing the random oracle with a concrete cryptographic hash function such as SHA2, we obtain plausible Minicrypt instantiations of the above results. Previous analogous results all required substantial structure, either in terms of highly structured oracles and/or algebraic assumptions in Cryptomania and beyond.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hierarchies of resources for measurement-based quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.09965</link>
    <author>Markus Frembs, Sam Roberts, Earl T. Campbell, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For certain restricted computational tasks, quantum mechanics provides a provable advantage over any possible classical implementation. Several of these results have been proven using the framework of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), where non-locality and more generally contextuality have been identified as necessary resources for certain quantum computations. Here, we consider the computational power of MBQC in more detail by refining its resource requirements, both on the allowed operations and the number of accessible qubits. More precisely, we identify which Boolean functions can be computed in non-adaptive MBQC, with local operations contained within a finite level in the Clifford hierarchy. Moreover, for non-adaptive MBQC restricted to certain subtheories such as stabiliser MBQC, we compute the minimal number of qubits required to compute a given Boolean function. Our results point towards hierarchies of resources that more sharply characterise the power of MBQC beyond the binary of contextuality vs non-contextuality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of variational quantum algorithms: a quantum optimal transport approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03455</link>
    <author>Giacomo De Palma, Milad Marvian, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The impressive progress in quantum hardware of the last years has raised the interest of the quantum computing community in harvesting the computational power of such devices. However, in the absence of error correction, these devices can only reliably implement very shallow circuits or comparatively deeper circuits at the expense of a nontrivial density of errors. In this work, we obtain extremely tight limitation bounds for standard NISQ proposals in both the noisy and noiseless regimes, with or without error-mitigation tools. The bounds limit the performance of both circuit model algorithms, such as QAOA, and also continuous-time algorithms, such as quantum annealing. In the noisy regime with local depolarizing noise $p$, we prove that at depths $L=\cO(p^{-1})$ it is exponentially unlikely that the outcome of a noisy quantum circuit outperforms efficient classical algorithms for combinatorial optimization problems like Max-Cut. Although previous results already showed that classical algorithms outperform noisy quantum circuits at constant depth, these results only held for the expectation value of the output. Our results are based on newly developed quantum entropic and concentration inequalities, which constitute a homogeneous toolkit of theoretical methods from the quantum theory of optimal mass transport whose potential usefulness goes beyond the study of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved Quantum Algorithms for Fidelity Estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.15993</link>
    <author>András Gilyén, Alexander Poremba</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fidelity is a fundamental measure for the closeness of two quantum states, which is important both from a theoretical and a practical point of view. Yet, in general, it is difficult to give good estimates of fidelity, especially when one works with mixed states over Hilbert spaces of very high dimension. Although, there has been some progress on fidelity estimation, all prior work either requires a large number of identical copies of the relevant states, or relies on unproven heuristics. In this work, we improve on both of these aspects by developing new and efficient quantum algorithms for fidelity estimation with provable performance guarantees in case at least one of the states is approximately low-rank. Our algorithms use advanced quantum linear algebra techniques, such as the quantum singular value transformation, as well as density matrix exponentiation and quantum spectral sampling. As a complementary result, we prove that fidelity estimation to any non-trivial constant additive accuracy is hard in general, by giving a sample complexity lower bound that depends polynomially on the dimension. Moreover, if circuit descriptions for the relevant states are provided, we show that the task is hard for the complexity class called (honest verifier) quantum statistical zero knowledge via a reduction to a closely related result by Watrous.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Parameterized Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08002</link>
    <author>Michael J. Bremner, Zhengfeng Ji, Ryan L. Mann, Luke Mathieson, Mauro E.S. Morales, Alexis T.E. Shaw</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Parameterized complexity theory was developed in the 1990s to enrich the complexity-theoretic analysis of problems that depend on a range of parameters. In this paper we establish a quantum equivalent of classical parameterized complexity theory, motivated by the need for new tools for the classifications of the complexity of real-world problems. We introduce the quantum analogues of a range of parameterized complexity classes and examine the relationship between these classes, their classical counterparts, and well-studied problems. This framework exposes a rich classification of the complexity of parameterized versions of QMA-hard problems, demonstrating, for example, a clear separation between the Quantum Circuit Satisfiability problem and the Local Hamiltonian problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adiabatic paths of Hamiltonians, symmetries of topological order, and automorphism codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11137</link>
    <author>David Aasen, Zhenghan Wang, Matthew B. Hastings</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recent "honeycomb code" is a fault-tolerant quantum memory defined by a sequence of checks which implements a nontrivial automorphism of the toric code. We argue that a general framework to understand this code is to consider continuous adiabatic paths of gapped Hamiltonians and we give a conjectured description of the fundamental group and second and third homotopy groups of this space in two spatial dimensions. A single cycle of such a path can implement some automorphism of the topological order of that Hamiltonian. We construct such paths for arbitrary automorphisms of two-dimensional doubled topological order. Then, realizing this in the case of the toric code, we turn this path back into a sequence of checks, constructing an automorphism code closely related to the honeycomb code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-enhanced Markov chain Monte Carlo</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.12497</link>
    <author>David Layden, Guglielmo Mazzola, Ryan V. Mishmash, Mario Motta, Pawel Wocjan, Jin-Sung Kim, Sarah Sheldon</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Sampling from complicated probability distributions is a hard computational problem arising in many fields, including statistical physics, optimization, and machine learning. Quantum computers have recently been used to sample from complicated distributions that are hard to sample from classically, but which seldom arise in applications. Here we introduce a quantum algorithm to sample from distributions that pose a bottleneck in several applications, which we implement on a superconducting quantum processor. The algorithm performs Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC), a popular iterative sampling technique, to sample from the Boltzmann distribution of classical Ising models. In each step, the quantum processor explores the model in superposition to propose a random move, which is then accepted or rejected by a classical computer and returned to the quantum processor, ensuring convergence to the desired Boltzmann distribution. We find that this quantum algorithm converges in fewer iterations than common classical MCMC alternatives on relevant problem instances, both in simulations and experiments. It therefore opens a new path for quantum computers to solve useful--not merely difficult--problems in the near term.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An analytic theory for the dynamics of wide quantum neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16711</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Khadijeh Najafi, Kunal Sharma, Francesco Tacchino, Liang Jiang, Antonio Mezzacapo</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Parametrized quantum circuits can be used as quantum neural networks and have the potential to outperform their classical counterparts when trained for addressing learning problems. To date, much of the results on their performance on practical problems are heuristic in nature. In particular, the convergence rate for the training of quantum neural networks is not fully understood. Here, we analyze the dynamics of gradient descent for the training error of a class of variational quantum machine learning models. We define wide quantum neural networks as parameterized quantum circuits in the limit of a large number of qubits and variational parameters. We then find a simple analytic formula that captures the average behavior of their loss function and discuss the consequences of our findings. For example, for random quantum circuits, we predict and characterize an exponential decay of the residual training error as a function of the parameters of the system. We finally validate our analytic results with numerical experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailored XZZX codes for biased noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16486</link>
    <author>Qian Xu, Nam Mannucci, Alireza Seif, Aleksander Kubica, Steven T. Flammia, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction (QEC) for generic errors is challenging due to the demanding threshold and resource requirements. Interestingly, when physical noise is biased, we can tailor our QEC schemes to the noise to improve performance. Here we study a family of codes having XZZX-type stabilizer generators, including a set of cyclic codes generalized from the five-qubit code and a set of topological codes that we call generalized toric codes (GTCs). We show that these XZZX codes are highly qubit efficient if tailored to biased noise. To characterize the code performance, we use the notion of effective distance, which generalizes code distance to the case of biased noise and constitutes a proxy for the logical failure rate. We find that the XZZX codes can achieve a favorable resource scaling by this metric under biased noise. We also show that the XZZX codes have remarkably high thresholds that reach what is achievable by random codes, and furthermore they can be efficiently decoded using matching decoders. Finally, by adding only one flag qubit, the XZZX codes can realize fault-tolerant QEC while preserving their large effective distance. In combination, our results show that tailored XZZX codes give a resource-efficient scheme for fault-tolerant QEC against biased noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Algorithms for Testing Hamiltonian Symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.10017</link>
    <author>Margarite L. LaBorde, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Symmetries in a Hamiltonian play an important role in quantum physics because they correspond directly with conserved quantities of the related system. In this paper, we propose quantum algorithms capable of testing whether a Hamiltonian exhibits symmetry with respect to a group. We demonstrate that familiar expressions of Hamiltonian symmetry in quantum mechanics correspond directly with the acceptance probabilities of our algorithms. We execute one of our symmetry-testing algorithms on existing quantum computers for simple examples of both symmetric and asymmetric cases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Routing with Teleportation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04185</link>
    <author>Dhruv Devulapalli, Eddie Schoute, Aniruddha Bapat, Andrew M. Childs, Alexey V. Gorshkov</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of implementing arbitrary permutations of qubits under interaction constraints in quantum systems that allow for arbitrarily fast local operations and classical communication (LOCC). In particular, we show examples of speedups over swap-based and more general unitary routing methods by distributing entanglement and using LOCC to perform quantum teleportation. We further describe an example of an interaction graph for which teleportation gives a logarithmic speedup in the worst-case routing time over swap-based routing. We also study limits on the speedup afforded by quantum teleportation - showing an $O(\sqrt{N \log N})$ upper bound on the separation in routing time for any interaction graph - and give tighter bounds for some common classes of graphs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Imaging stars with quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06044</link>
    <author>Zixin Huang, Gavin K. Brennen, Yingkai Ouyang</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The development of high-resolution, large-baseline optical interferometers would revolutionize astronomical imaging. However, classical techniques are hindered by physical limitations including loss, noise, and the fact that the received light is generally quantum in nature. We show how to overcome these issues using quantum communication techniques. We present a general framework for using quantum error correction codes for protecting and imaging starlight received at distant telescope sites. In our scheme, the quantum state of light is coherently captured into a non-radiative atomic state via Stimulated Raman Adiabatic Passage, which is then imprinted into a quantum error correction code. The code protects the signal during subsequent potentially noisy operations necessary to extract the image parameters. We show that even a small quantum error correction code can offer significant protection against noise. For large codes, we find noise thresholds below which the information can be preserved. Our scheme represents an application for near-term quantum devices that can increase imaging resolution beyond what is feasible using classical techniques.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum variational learning for quantum error-correcting codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03560</link>
    <author>Chenfeng Cao, Chao Zhang, Zipeng Wu, Markus Grassl, Bei Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error-correcting codes (QECCs) are believed to be a necessity for large-scale fault-tolerant quantum computation. In the past two decades, various methods of QECC constructions have been developed, leading to many good families of codes. However, the majority of these codes are not suitable for near-term quantum devices. Here we present VarQEC, a noise-resilient variational quantum algorithm to search for quantum codes with a hardware-efficient encoding circuit. The cost functions are inspired by the most general and fundamental requirements of a QECC, the Knill-Laflamme conditions. Given the target noise channel (or the target code parameters) and the hardware connectivity graph, we optimize a shallow variational quantum circuit to prepare the basis states of an eligible code. In principle, VarQEC can find quantum codes for any error model, whether additive or non-additive, degenerate or non-degenerate, pure or impure. We have verified its effectiveness by (re)discovering some symmetric and asymmetric codes, e.g., $((n,2^{n-6},3))_2$ for $n$ from 7 to 14. We also found new $((6,2,3))_2$ and $((7,2,3))_2$ codes that are not equivalent to any stabilizer code, and extensive numerical evidence with VarQEC suggests that a $((7,3,3))_2$ code does not exist. Furthermore, we found many new channel-adaptive codes for error models involving nearest-neighbor correlated errors. Our work sheds new light on the understanding of QECC in general, which may also help to enhance near-term device performance with channel-adaptive error-correcting codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A cellular automaton decoder for a noise-bias tailored color code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16534</link>
    <author>Jonathan F. San Miguel, Dominic J. Williamson, Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Self-correcting quantum memories demonstrate robust properties that can be exploited to improve active quantum error-correction protocols. Here we propose a cellular automaton decoder for a variation of the color code where the bases of the physical qubits are locally rotated, which we call the XYZ color code. The local transformation means our decoder demonstrates key properties of a two-dimensional fractal code if the noise acting on the system is infinitely biased towards dephasing, namely, no string-like logical operators. As such, in the high-bias limit, our local decoder reproduces the behavior of a partially self-correcting memory. At low error rates, our simulations show that the memory time diverges polynomially with system size without intervention from a global decoder, up to some critical system size that grows as the error rate is lowered. Furthermore, although we find that we cannot reproduce partially self-correcting behavior at finite bias, our numerics demonstrate improved memory times at realistic noise biases. Our results therefore motivate the design of tailored cellular automaton decoders that help to reduce the bandwidth demands of global decoding for realistic noise models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ground state preparation and energy estimation on early fault-tolerant quantum computers via quantum eigenvalue transformation of unitary matrices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.05955</link>
    <author>Yulong Dong, Lin Lin, Yu Tong</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Under suitable assumptions, the algorithms in [Lin, Tong, Quantum 2020] can estimate the ground state energy and prepare the ground state of a quantum Hamiltonian with near-optimal query complexities. However, this is based on a block encoding input model of the Hamiltonian, whose implementation is known to require a large resource overhead. We develop a tool called quantum eigenvalue transformation of unitary matrices with real polynomials (QET-U), which uses a controlled Hamiltonian evolution as the input model, a single ancilla qubit and no multi-qubit control operations, and is thus suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum devices. This leads to a simple quantum algorithm that outperforms all previous algorithms with a comparable circuit structure for estimating the ground state energy. For a class of quantum spin Hamiltonians, we propose a new method that exploits certain anti-commutation relations and further removes the need of implementing the controlled Hamiltonian evolution. Coupled with Trotter based approximation of the Hamiltonian evolution, the resulting algorithm can be very suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum devices. We demonstrate the performance of the algorithm using IBM Qiskit for the transverse field Ising model. If we are further allowed to use multi-qubit Toffoli gates, we can then implement amplitude amplification and a new binary amplitude estimation algorithm, which increases the circuit depth but decreases the total query complexity. The resulting algorithm saturates the near-optimal complexity for ground state preparation and energy estimating using a constant number of ancilla qubits (no more than 3).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Looped Pipelines Enabling Effective 3D Qubit Lattices in a Strictly 2D Device</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13123</link>
    <author>Zhenyu Cai, Adam Siegel, Simon Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many quantum computing platforms are based on a fundamentally two-dimensional physical layout. However, there are advantages (for example in fault-tolerant systems) to having a 3D architecture. Here we explore a concept called looped pipelines which permits one to obtain many of the advantages of a 3D lattice while operating a strictly 2D device. The concept leverages qubit shuttling, a well-established feature in platforms like semiconductor spin qubits and trapped-ion qubits. The looped pipeline architecture has similar hardware requirements to other shuttling approaches, but can process a stack of qubit arrays instead of just one. Simple patterns of intra- and inter-loop interactions allow one to embody diverse schemes from NISQ-era error mitigation through to fault-tolerant codes. For the former, protocols involving multiple states can be implemented with a similar space-time resource as preparing one noisy copy. For the latter, one can realise a far broader variety of code structures; in particular, we consider a stack of 2D codes within which transversal CNOTs are available. We find that this can achieve a cost saving of up to a factor of $\sim 80$ in the space-time overhead for magic state distillation (and a factor of $\sim 200$ with modest additional hardware). Using numerical modelling and experimentally-motivated noise models we verify that the looped pipeline approach provides these benefits without significant reduction in the code's threshold.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Shorter quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.10064</link>
    <author>Vadym Kliuchnikov, Kristin Lauter, Romy Minko, Adam Paetznick, Christophe Petit</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a novel procedure for approximating general single-qubit unitaries from a finite universal gate set by reducing the problem to a novel magnitude approximation problem, achieving an immediate improvement in sequence length by a factor of 7/9. Extending the works arXiv:1612.01011 and arXiv:1612.02689, we show that taking probabilistic mixtures of channels to solve fallback (arXiv:1409.3552) and magnitude approximation problems saves factor of two in approximation costs. In particular, over the Clifford+$\sqrt{\mathrm{T}}$ gate set we achieve an average non-Clifford gate count of $0.23\log_2(1/\varepsilon)+2.13$ and T-count $0.56\log_2(1/\varepsilon)+5.3$ with mixed fallback approximations for diamond norm accuracy $\varepsilon$. This paper provides a holistic overview of gate approximation, in addition to these new insights. We give an end-to-end procedure for gate approximation for general gate sets related to some quaternion algebras, providing pedagogical examples using common fault-tolerant gate sets (V, Clifford+T and Clifford+$\sqrt{\mathrm{T}}$). We also provide detailed numerical results for Clifford+T and Clifford+$\sqrt{\mathrm{T}}$ gate sets. In an effort to keep the paper self-contained, we include an overview of the relevant algorithms for integer point enumeration and relative norm equation solving. We provide a number of further applications of the magnitude approximation problems, as well as improved algorithms for exact synthesis, in the Appendices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms from fluctuation theorems: Thermal-state preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08882</link>
    <author>Zoe Holmes, Gopikrishnan Muraleedharan, Rolando D. Somma, Yigit Subasi, Burak Şahinoğlu</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fluctuation theorems provide a correspondence between properties of quantum systems in thermal equilibrium and a work distribution arising in a non-equilibrium process that connects two quantum systems with Hamiltonians $H_0$ and $H_1=H_0+V$. Building upon these theorems, we present a quantum algorithm to prepare a purification of the thermal state of $H_1$ at inverse temperature $\beta \ge 0$ starting from a purification of the thermal state of $H_0$. The complexity of the quantum algorithm, given by the number of uses of certain unitaries, is $\tilde {\cal O}(e^{\beta (\Delta \! A- w_l)/2})$, where $\Delta \! A$ is the free-energy difference between $H_1$ and $H_0,$ and $w_l$ is a work cutoff that depends on the properties of the work distribution and the approximation error $\epsilon>0$. If the non-equilibrium process is trivial, this complexity is exponential in $\beta \|V\|$, where $\|V\|$ is the spectral norm of $V$. This represents a significant improvement of prior quantum algorithms that have complexity exponential in $\beta \|H_1\|$ in the regime where $\|V\|\ll \|H_1\|$. The dependence of the complexity in $\epsilon$ varies according to the structure of the quantum systems. It can be exponential in $1/\epsilon$ in general, but we show it to be sublinear in $1/\epsilon$ if $H_0$ and $H_1$ commute, or polynomial in $1/\epsilon$ if $H_0$ and $H_1$ are local spin systems. The possibility of applying a unitary that drives the system out of equilibrium allows one to increase the value of $w_l$ and improve the complexity even further. To this end, we analyze the complexity for preparing the thermal state of the transverse field Ising model using different non-equilibrium unitary processes and see significant complexity improvements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Distributed quantum error correction for chip-level catastrophic errors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16488</link>
    <author>Qian Xu, Alireza Seif, Haoxiong Yan, Nam Mannucci, Bernard Ousmane Sane, Rodney Van Meter, Andrew N. Cleland, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction holds the key to scaling up quantum computers. Cosmic ray events severely impact the operation of a quantum computer by causing chip-level catastrophic errors, essentially erasing the information encoded in a chip. Here, we present a distributed error correction scheme to combat the devastating effect of such events by introducing an additional layer of quantum erasure error correcting code across separate chips. We show that our scheme is fault tolerant against chip-level catastrophic errors and discuss its experimental implementation using superconducting qubits with microwave links. Our analysis shows that in state-of-the-art experiments, it is possible to suppress the rate of these errors from 1 per 10 seconds to less than 1 per month.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error propagation in NISQ devices for solving classical optimization problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.15632</link>
    <author>Guillermo González-García, Rahul Trivedi, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a random circuit model to analyze the impact of noise on the performance of variational quantum circuits for classical optimization problems. Our model accounts for the propagation of arbitrary single qubit errors through the circuit. We find that even with a small noise rate, the quality of the obtained classical optima is low on average and a single-qubit error rate of $1 / nD$, where $n$ is the number of qubits and $D$ is the circuit depth, is needed for the possibility of a quantum advantage. We estimate that this translates to an error rate lower than $10^{-6}$ using QAOA for classical optimization problems with 2D circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Cleaning Lemma of Quantum Coding Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04699</link>
    <author>Gleb Kalachev, Sergey Sadov</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The term "Cleaning Lemma" refers to a family of similar propositions that have been used in Quantum Coding Theory to estimate the minimum distance of a code in terms of its length and dimension. We show that the mathematical core is a simple fact of linear algebra of inner product spaces; moreover, it admits a further reduction to a combinatorial, lattice-theoretical level. Several concrete variants of the Cleaning Lemma and some additional propositions are derived as corollaries of the proposed approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bi-PPT channels are entanglement breaking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01685</link>
    <author>Alexander Müller-Hermes, Satvik Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a recent paper, Hirche and Leditzky introduced the notion of bi-PPT channels which are quantum channels that stay completely positive under composition with a transposition and such that the same property holds for one of their complementary channels. They asked whether there are examples of such channels that are not antidegradable. We show that this is not the case, since bi-PPT channels are always entanglement breaking. We also show that degradable quantum channels staying completely positive under composition with a transposition are entanglement breaking.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring magic on a quantum processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.00015</link>
    <author>Salvatore F.E. Oliviero, Lorenzo Leone, Alioscia Hamma, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic states are the resource that allows quantum computers to attain an advantage over classical computers. This resource consists in the deviation from a property called stabilizerness which in turn implies that stabilizer circuits can be efficiently simulated on a classical computer. Without magic, no quantum computer can do anything that a classical computer cannot do. Given the importance of magic for quantum computation, it would be useful to have a method for measuring the amount of magic in a quantum state. In this work, we propose and experimentally demonstrate a protocol for measuring magic based on randomized measurements. Our experiments are carried out on two IBM Quantum Falcon processors. This protocol can provide a characterization of the effectiveness of a quantum hardware in producing states that cannot be effectively simulated on a classical computer. We show how from these measurements one can construct realistic noise models affecting the hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Clifford Circuits can be Properly PAC Learned if and only if $\textsf{RP}=\textsf{NP}$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06638</link>
    <author>Daniel Liang</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a dataset of input states, measurements, and probabilities, is it possible to efficiently predict the measurement probabilities associated with a quantum circuit? Recent work of Caro and Datta (2020) studied the problem of PAC learning quantum circuits in an information theoretic sense, leaving open questions of computational efficiency. In particular, one candidate class of circuits for which an efficient learner might have been possible was that of Clifford circuits, since the corresponding set of states generated by such circuits, called stabilizer states, are known to be efficiently PAC learnable (Rocchetto 2018). Here we provide a negative result, showing that proper learning of CNOT circuits is hard for classical learners unless $\textsf{RP} = \textsf{NP}$. As the classical analogue and subset of Clifford circuits, this naturally leads to a hardness result for Clifford circuits as well. Additionally, we show that if $\textsf{RP} = \textsf{NP}$ then there would exist efficient proper learning algorithms for CNOT and Clifford circuits. By similar arguments, we also find that an efficient proper quantum learner for such circuits exists if and only if $\textsf{NP} \subseteq \textsf{RQP}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Detecting entanglement in quantum many-body systems via permutation moments</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.08391</link>
    <author>Zhenhuan Liu, Yifan Tang, Hao Dai, Pengyu Liu, Shu Chen, Xiongfeng Ma</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Multipartite entanglement plays an essential role in both quantum information science and many-body physics. Due to the exponentially large dimension and complex geometric structure of the state space, the detection of entanglement in many-body systems is extremely challenging in reality. Conventional means, like entanglement witness and entropy criterion, either highly depend on the prior knowledge of the studied systems or the detection capability is relatively weak. In this work, we propose a framework for designing multipartite entanglement criteria based on permutation moments, which have an effective implementation with either the generalized control-SWAP quantum circuits or the random unitary techniques. These criteria show strong detection capability in the multi-qubit Ising model with a long-range $XY$ Hamiltonian. The quantities associated with these criteria have clear physical meaning and can be used as entanglement quantifiers, with which we show the entanglement scaling transition in a quantum dynamical phase transition. Furthermore, our framework can also be generalized to detect the much more complicated entanglement structure in quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Variational Ansatz for the Ground State of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02923</link>
    <author>Paul M. Schindler, Tommaso Guaita, Tao Shi, Eugene Demler, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an ansatz for the ground states of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model, a paradigmatic model for quantum spin glasses. Our ansatz, based on the concept of generalized coherent states, very well captures the fundamental aspects of the model, including the ground state energy and the position of the spin glass phase transition. It further enables us to study some previously unexplored features, such as the non-vanishing longitudinal field regime and the entanglement structure of the ground states. We find that the ground state entanglement can be captured by a simple ensemble of weighted graph states with normally distributed phase gates, leading to a volume law entanglement, contrasting with predictions based on entanglement monogamy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement area law for 1D gauge theories and bosonic systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16012</link>
    <author>Nilin Abrahamsen, Yuan Su, Yu Tong, Nathan Wiebe</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove an entanglement area law for a class of 1D quantum systems involving infinite-dimensional local Hilbert spaces. This class of quantum systems include bosonic models such as the Hubbard-Holstein model, and both U(1) and SU(2) lattice gauge theories in one spatial dimension. Our proof relies on new results concerning the robustness of the ground state and spectral gap to the truncation of Hilbert space, applied within the approximate ground state projector (AGSP) framework from previous work. In establishing this area law, we develop a system-size independent bound on the expectation value of local observables for Hamiltonians without translation symmetry, which may be of separate interest. Our result provides theoretical justification for using tensor network methods to study the ground state properties of quantum systems with infinite local degrees of freedom.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>