
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A smallest computable entanglement monotone</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00835</link>
    <author>J. Eisert, M. M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Rains relative entropy of a bipartite quantum state is the tightest known upper bound on its distillable entanglement - which has a crisp physical interpretation of entanglement as a resource - and it is efficiently computable by convex programming. It has not been known to be a selective entanglement monotone in its own right. In this work, we strengthen the interpretation of the Rains relative entropy by showing that it is monotone under the action of selective operations that completely preserve the positivity of the partial transpose, reasonably quantifying entanglement. That is, we prove that Rains relative entropy of an ensemble generated by such an operation does not exceed the Rains relative entropy of the initial state in expectation, giving rise to the smallest, most conservative known computable selective entanglement monotone. Additionally, we show that this is true not only for the original Rains relative entropy, but also for Rains relative entropies derived from various Renyi relative entropies. As an application of these findings, we prove, in both the non-asymptotic and asymptotic settings, that the probabilistic approximate distillable entanglement of a state is bounded from above by various Rains relative entropies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Algorithms for Gibbs state preparation on noiseless and noisy random quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14688</link>
    <author>Oles Shtanko, Ramis Movassagh</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 30 2021</pubDate>
    <description>The most promising and practical candidate to demonstrate a drastic advantage of quantum computers over classical ones is the simulation of quantum matter. Despite the advances in simulation of the time evolution, preparing thermal states of quantum many-body systems remains notoriously a difficult yet important task. The existing algorithms either require quantum phase estimation rendering them impractical for current noisy hardware, or are variational which face obstacles such as initialization, barren plateaus, and a general lack of provable convergence. We propose two quantum algorithms with provable guarantees to prepare thermal states on current noisy quantum hardware. The first algorithm requires postselection on intermediate measurements and runs on a quantum circuit with $poly(n)$ depth, where $n$ is the number of qubits. This algorithm requires a significantly smaller number of gates than previous such algorithms. The second algorithm is tailored to ergodic interacting systems which are a vast subset of physical Hamiltonians. This algorithm can potentially sample thermal distributions in polynomial time. In addition, both of our algorithms have free parameters that can be optimized or trained to mitigate noise and computational errors. We illustrate our algorithms by running them on the latest IBM quantum hardware and in particular simulate them for the Fermi-Hubbard model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Realizing an Error-Correcting Surface Code with Superconducting Qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.13505</link>
    <author>Youwei Zhao, Yangsen Ye, He-Liang Huang, Yiming Zhang, Dachao Wu, Huijie Guan, Qingling Zhu, Zuolin Wei, Tan He, Sirui Cao, Fusheng Chen, Tung-Hsun Chung, Hui Deng, Daojin Fan, Ming Gong, Cheng Guo, Shaojun Guo, Lianchen Han, Na Li, Shaowei Li, et al (19)</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 28 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction is a critical technique for transitioning from noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices to fully fledged quantum computers. The surface code, which has a high threshold error rate, is the leading quantum error correction code for two-dimensional grid architecture. So far, the repeated error correction capability of the surface code has not been realized experimentally. Here, we experimentally implement an error-correcting surface code, the distance-3 surface code which consists of 17 qubits, on the \textitZuchongzhi 2.1 superconducting quantum processor. By executing several consecutive error correction cycles, the logical error can be significantly reduced after applying corrections, achieving the repeated error correction of surface code for the first time. This experiment represents a fully functional instance of an error-correcting surface code, providing a key step on the path towards scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing matrix product states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01824</link>
    <author>Mehdi Soleimanifar, John Wright</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Devising schemes for testing the amount of entanglement in quantum systems has played a crucial role in quantum computing and information theory. Here, we study the problem of testing whether an unknown state $|\psi\rangle$ is a matrix product state (MPS) in the property testing model. MPS are a class of physically-relevant quantum states which arise in the study of quantum many-body systems. A quantum state $|\psi_{1,...,n}\rangle$ comprised of $n$ qudits is said to be an MPS of bond dimension $r$ if the reduced density matrix $\psi_{1,...,k}$ has rank $r$ for each $k \in \{1,...,n\}$. When $r=1$, this corresponds to the set of product states. For larger values of $r$, this yields a more expressive class of quantum states, which are allowed to possess limited amounts of entanglement. In the property testing model, one is given $m$ identical copies of $|\psi\rangle$, and the goal is to determine whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ or whether $|\psi\rangle$ is far from all such states. For the case of product states, we study the product test, a simple two-copy test previously analyzed by Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010), and a key ingredient in their proof that $\mathsf{QMA(2)}=\mathsf{QMA}(k)$ for $k \geq 2$. We give a new and simpler analysis of the product test which achieves an optimal bound for a wide range of parameters, answering open problems of Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010) and Montanaro and de Wolf (2016). For the case of $r\geq 2$, we give an efficient algorithm for testing whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ using $m = O(n r^2)$ copies, independent of the dimensions of the qudits, and we show that $\Omega(n^{1/2})$ copies are necessary for this task. This lower bound shows that a dependence on the number of qudits $n$ is necessary, in sharp contrast to the case of product states where a constant number of copies suffices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Merkle Trees</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14317</link>
    <author>Lijie Chen, Ramis Movassagh</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 30 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Commitment scheme is a central task in cryptography, where a party (typically called a prover) stores a piece of information (e.g., a bit string) with the promise of not changing it. This information can be accessed by another party (typically called the verifier), who can later learn the information and verify that it was not meddled with. Merkle tree is a well-known construction for doing so in a succinct manner, in which the verfier can learn any part of the information by receiving a short proof from the honest prover. Despite its significance in classical cryptography, there was no quantum analog of the Merkle tree. A direct generalization using the Quantum Random Oracle Model (QROM) does not seem to be secure. In this work, we propose the quantum Merkle tree. It is based on what we call the Quantum Haar Random Oracle Model (QHROM). In QHROM, both the prover and the verifier have access to a Haar random quantum oracle G and its inverse. Using the quantum Merkle tree, we propose a succinct quantum argument for the Gap-k-Local-Hamiltonian problem. We prove it is secure against semi-honest provers in QHROM and conjecture its general security. Assuming the Quantum PCP conjecture is true, this succinct argument extends to all of QMA. This work raises a number of interesting open research problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Practical and Efficient Hamiltonian Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00190</link>
    <author>Wenjun Yu, Jinzhao Sun, Zeyao Han, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>With the fast development of quantum technology, the size of quantum systems we can digitally manipulate and analogly probe increase drastically. In order to have a better control and understanding of the quantum hardware, an important task is to characterize the interaction, i.e., to learn the Hamiltonian, which determines both static or dynamic properties of the system. Conventional Hamiltonian learning methods either require costly process tomography or adopt impractical assumptions, such as prior information of the Hamiltonian structure and the ground or thermal states of the system. In this work, we present a practical and efficient Hamiltonian learning method that circumvents these limitations. The proposed method can efficiently learn any Hamiltonian that is sparse on the Pauli basis using only short time dynamics and local operations without any information of the Hamiltonian or preparing any eigenstates or thermal states. The method has scalable complexity and vanishing failure probability regarding the qubit number. Meanwhile, it is free from state preparation and measurement error and robust against a certain amount of circuit and shot noise. We numerically test the scaling and the estimation accuracy of the method for transverse field Ising Hamiltonian with random interaction strengths and molecular Hamiltonians, both with varying sizes. All these results verify the practicality and efficacy of the method, paving the way for a systematic understanding of large quantum systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence of contextuality and Wigner function negativity in continuous-variable quantum optics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14788</link>
    <author>Jonas Haferkamp, Juani Bermejo-Vega</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One of the central foundational questions of physics is to identify what makes a system quantum as opposed to classical. One seminal notion of classicality of a quantum system is the existence of a non-contextual hidden variable model as introduced in the early work by Bell, Kochen and Specker. In quantum optics, the non-negativity of the Wigner function is a ubiquitous notion of classicality. In this work we establish an equivalence between these two concepts. In particular, we show that any non-contextual hidden variable model for Gaussian quantum optics has an alternative non-negative Wigner function description. Conversely, it was known that the Wigner representation provides a non-negative non-contextual description of Gaussian quantum optics. It follows that contextuality and Wigner negativity are equivalent notions of non-classicality and equivalent resources for this quantum subtheory. In particular, both contextuality and Wigner negativity are necessary for a computational speed-up of quantum Gaussian optics. At the technical level, our result holds true for any subfamily of Gaussian measurements that include homodyne measurements, i.e., measurements of standard quadrature observables.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Yet Another Proof of the Joint Convexity of Relative Entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.13763</link>
    <author>Mary Beth Ruskai</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 28 2021</pubDate>
    <description>The joint convexity of the map $(X,A) \mapsto X^* A^{-1} X$, an integral representation of convex operator functions, and an observation of Ando are used to obtain a simple proof of both the joint convexity of relative entropy and a trace convexity result of Lieb. The latter was the key ingredient in the original proof of the strong subadditivity of quantum entropy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limits on Parameter Estimation of Quantum Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01738</link>
    <author>Vishal Katariya</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The aim of this thesis is to develop a theoretical framework to study parameter estimation of quantum channels. We study the task of estimating unknown parameters encoded in a channel in the sequential setting. A sequential strategy is the most general way to use a channel multiple times. Our goal is to establish lower bounds (called Cramer-Rao bounds) on the estimation error. The bounds we develop are universally applicable; i.e., they apply to all permissible quantum dynamics. We consider the use of catalysts to enhance the power of a channel estimation strategy. This is termed amortization. The power of a channel for a parameter estimation is determined by its Fisher information. Thus, we study how much a catalyst quantum state can enhance the Fisher information of a channel by defining the amortized Fisher information. We establish our bounds by proving that for certain Fisher information quantities, catalyst states do not improve the performance of a sequential estimation protocol compared to a parallel one. The technical term for this is an amortization collapse. We use this to establish bounds when estimating one parameter, or multiple parameters simultaneously. Our bounds apply universally and we also cast them as optimization problems. For the single parameter case, we establish bounds for general quantum channels using both the symmetric logarithmic derivative (SLD) Fisher information and the right logarithmic derivative (RLD) Fisher information. The task of estimating multiple parameters simultaneously is more involved than the single parameter case, because the Cramer-Rao bounds take the form of matrix inequalities. We establish a scalar Cramer-Rao bound for multiparameter channel estimation using the RLD Fisher information. For both single and multiparameter estimation, we provide a no-go condition for the so-called Heisenberg scaling using our RLD-based bound.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact quantum query complexity of computing Hamming weight modulo powers of two and three</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14682</link>
    <author>Arjan Cornelissen, Nikhil S. Mande, Maris Ozols, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 30 2021</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of computing the Hamming weight of an $n$-bit string modulo $m$, for any positive integer $m \leq n$ whose only prime factors are 2 and 3. We show that the exact quantum query complexity of this problem is $\left\lceil n(1 - 1/m) \right\rceil$. The upper bound is via an iterative query algorithm whose core components are the well-known 1-query quantum algorithm (essentially due to Deutsch) to compute the Hamming weight a 2-bit string mod 2 (i.e., the parity of the input bits), and a new 2-query quantum algorithm to compute the Hamming weight of a 3-bit string mod 3. We show a matching lower bound (in fact for arbitrary moduli $m$) via a variant of the polynomial method [de Wolf, SIAM J. Comput., 32(3), 2003]. This bound is for the weaker task of deciding whether or not a given $n$-bit input has Hamming weight 0 modulo $m$, and it holds even in the stronger non-deterministic quantum query model where an algorithm must have positive acceptance probability iff its input evaluates to 1. For $m>2$ our lower bound exceeds $n/2$, beating the best lower bound provable using the general polynomial method [Theorem 4.3, Beals et al., J. ACM 48(4), 2001].</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>
