<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Logical blocks for fault-tolerant topological quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.12160</link>
    <author>Hector Bombin, Chris Dawson, Ryan V. Mishmash, Naomi Nickerson, Fernando Pastawski, Sam Roberts</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 24 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Logical gates are the building blocks of fault-tolerant quantum computation. While quantum error-corrected memories have been extensively studied in the literature, detailed analyses of thresholds and resource overheads of universal logical gate sets have so far been limited. In this paper, we present a comprehensive framework for universal fault-tolerant logic motivated by the combined need for (i) platform-independent logical gate definitions, (ii) flexible and scalable tools for numerical analysis, and (iii) exploration of novel schemes for universal logic that improve resource overheads. We first introduce the theory of fault-tolerant channels for describing logical gates holistically in space-time. Focusing on channels based on surface codes, we introduce explicit, platform-independent representations of topological logic gates -- called logical blocks -- and generate new, overhead-efficient methods for universal quantum computation. As a specific example, we propose fault-tolerant schemes based on surface codes concatenated with more general low-density parity check (LDPC) codes. The logical blocks framework enables a convenient mapping from an abstract description of the logical gate to a precise set of physical instructions for both circuit-based and fusion-based quantum computation (FBQC). Using this, we numerically simulate a surface-code-based universal gate set implemented with FBQC, and verify that the threshold for fault-tolerant gates is consistent with the bulk memory threshold. We find that boundaries, defects, and twists, can significantly impact the logical error rate scaling, with periodic boundary conditions potentially halving the memory resource requirements. Motivated by the favorable logical error rate suppression for boundaryless computation, we introduce a novel computational scheme based on the teleportation of twists that may offer further resource reductions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing matrix product states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01824</link>
    <author>Mehdi Soleimanifar, John Wright</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Devising schemes for testing the amount of entanglement in quantum systems has played a crucial role in quantum computing and information theory. Here, we study the problem of testing whether an unknown state $|\psi\rangle$ is a matrix product state (MPS) in the property testing model. MPS are a class of physically-relevant quantum states which arise in the study of quantum many-body systems. A quantum state $|\psi_{1,...,n}\rangle$ comprised of $n$ qudits is said to be an MPS of bond dimension $r$ if the reduced density matrix $\psi_{1,...,k}$ has rank $r$ for each $k \in \{1,...,n\}$. When $r=1$, this corresponds to the set of product states. For larger values of $r$, this yields a more expressive class of quantum states, which are allowed to possess limited amounts of entanglement. In the property testing model, one is given $m$ identical copies of $|\psi\rangle$, and the goal is to determine whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ or whether $|\psi\rangle$ is far from all such states. For the case of product states, we study the product test, a simple two-copy test previously analyzed by Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010), and a key ingredient in their proof that $\mathsf{QMA(2)}=\mathsf{QMA}(k)$ for $k \geq 2$. We give a new and simpler analysis of the product test which achieves an optimal bound for a wide range of parameters, answering open problems of Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010) and Montanaro and de Wolf (2016). For the case of $r\geq 2$, we give an efficient algorithm for testing whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ using $m = O(n r^2)$ copies, independent of the dimensions of the qudits, and we show that $\Omega(n^{1/2})$ copies are necessary for this task. This lower bound shows that a dependence on the number of qudits $n$ is necessary, in sharp contrast to the case of product states where a constant number of copies suffices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction with fractal topological codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03568</link>
    <author>Arpit Dua, Tomas Jochym-O'Connor, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, a class of fractal surface codes (FSCs), has been constructed on fractal lattices with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$, which admits a fault-tolerant non-Clifford CCZ gate. We investigate the performance of such FSCs as fault-tolerant quantum memories. We prove that there exist decoding strategies with non-zero thresholds for bit-flip and phase-flip errors in the FSCs with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$. For the bit-flip errors, we adapt the sweep decoder, developed for string-like syndromes in the regular 3D surface code, to the FSCs by designing suitable modifications on the boundaries of the holes in the fractal lattice. Moreover, our adaptation of the sweep decoder for the FSCs maintains its self-correcting and single-shot nature. For the phase-flip errors, we employ the minimum-weight-perfect-matching (MWPM) decoder for the point-like syndromes. We report a sustainable fault-tolerant threshold ($\sim 1.7\%$) under phenomenological noise for the sweep decoder and the code capacity threshold (lower bounded by $2.95\%$) for the MWPM decoder for a particular FSC with Hausdorff dimension $D_H\approx2.966$. The latter can be mapped to the critical point of a zero-temperature confinement-Higgs transition on the fractal lattice, which is tunable via the Hausdorff dimension.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A smallest computable entanglement monotone</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00835</link>
    <author>J. Eisert, M. M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Rains relative entropy of a bipartite quantum state is the tightest known upper bound on its distillable entanglement - which has a crisp physical interpretation of entanglement as a resource - and it is efficiently computable by convex programming. It has not been known to be a selective entanglement monotone in its own right. In this work, we strengthen the interpretation of the Rains relative entropy by showing that it is monotone under the action of selective operations that completely preserve the positivity of the partial transpose, reasonably quantifying entanglement. That is, we prove that Rains relative entropy of an ensemble generated by such an operation does not exceed the Rains relative entropy of the initial state in expectation, giving rise to the smallest, most conservative known computable selective entanglement monotone. Additionally, we show that this is true not only for the original Rains relative entropy, but also for Rains relative entropies derived from various Renyi relative entropies. As an application of these findings, we prove, in both the non-asymptotic and asymptotic settings, that the probabilistic approximate distillable entanglement of a state is bounded from above by various Rains relative entropies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Realizing an Error-Correcting Surface Code with Superconducting Qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.13505</link>
    <author>Youwei Zhao, Yangsen Ye, He-Liang Huang, Yiming Zhang, Dachao Wu, Huijie Guan, Qingling Zhu, Zuolin Wei, Tan He, Sirui Cao, Fusheng Chen, Tung-Hsun Chung, Hui Deng, Daojin Fan, Ming Gong, Cheng Guo, Shaojun Guo, Lianchen Han, Na Li, Shaowei Li, et al (19)</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 28 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction is a critical technique for transitioning from noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices to fully fledged quantum computers. The surface code, which has a high threshold error rate, is the leading quantum error correction code for two-dimensional grid architecture. So far, the repeated error correction capability of the surface code has not been realized experimentally. Here, we experimentally implement an error-correcting surface code, the distance-3 surface code which consists of 17 qubits, on the \textitZuchongzhi 2.1 superconducting quantum processor. By executing several consecutive error correction cycles, the logical error can be significantly reduced after applying corrections, achieving the repeated error correction of surface code for the first time. This experiment represents a fully functional instance of an error-correcting surface code, providing a key step on the path towards scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Free-Fermion Subsystem Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07254</link>
    <author>Adrian Chapman, Steven T. Flammia, Alicia J. Kollár</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider quantum error-correcting subsystem codes whose gauge generators realize a translation-invariant, free-fermion-solvable spin model. In this setting, errors are suppressed by a Hamiltonian whose terms are the gauge generators of the code and whose exact spectrum and eigenstates can be found via a generalized Jordan-Wigner transformation. Such solutions are characterized by the frustration graph of the Hamiltonian: the graph whose vertices are Hamiltonian terms, which are neighboring if the terms anticommute. We provide methods for embedding a given frustration graph in the anticommutation relations of a spin model and present the first known example of an exactly solvable spin model with a two-dimensional free-fermion description and exact topological qubits. This model can be viewed as a free-fermionized version of the two-dimensional Bacon-Shor code. Using graph-theoretic tools to study the unit cell, we give an efficient algorithm for deciding if a given translation-invariant spin model is solvable, and explicitly construct the solution. Further, we examine the energetics of these exactly solvable models from the graph-theoretic perspective and show that the relevant gaps of the spin model correspond to known graph-theoretic quantities: the skew energy and the median eigenvalue of an oriented graph. Finally, we numerically search for models which have large spectral gaps above the ground state spin configuration and thus exhibit particularly robust thermal suppression of errors. These results suggest that optimal models will have low dimensionality and odd coordination numbers, and that the primary limit to energetic error suppression is the skew energy difference between different symmetry sectors rather than single-particle excitations of the free fermions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Algorithms for Gibbs state preparation on noiseless and noisy random quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14688</link>
    <author>Oles Shtanko, Ramis Movassagh</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 30 2021</pubDate>
    <description>The most promising and practical candidate to demonstrate a drastic advantage of quantum computers over classical ones is the simulation of quantum matter. Despite the advances in simulation of the time evolution, preparing thermal states of quantum many-body systems remains notoriously a difficult yet important task. The existing algorithms either require quantum phase estimation rendering them impractical for current noisy hardware, or are variational which face obstacles such as initialization, barren plateaus, and a general lack of provable convergence. We propose two quantum algorithms with provable guarantees to prepare thermal states on current noisy quantum hardware. The first algorithm requires postselection on intermediate measurements and runs on a quantum circuit with $poly(n)$ depth, where $n$ is the number of qubits. This algorithm requires a significantly smaller number of gates than previous such algorithms. The second algorithm is tailored to ergodic interacting systems which are a vast subset of physical Hamiltonians. This algorithm can potentially sample thermal distributions in polynomial time. In addition, both of our algorithms have free parameters that can be optimized or trained to mitigate noise and computational errors. We illustrate our algorithms by running them on the latest IBM quantum hardware and in particular simulate them for the Fermi-Hubbard model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence between fermion-to-qubit mappings in two spatial dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05153</link>
    <author>Yu-An Chen, Yijia Xu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We argue that all locality-preserving mappings between fermionic observables and Pauli matrices on a two-dimensional lattice can be generated from the exact bosonization in Ref. [1], whose gauge constraints project onto the subspace of the toric code with emergent fermions. Starting from the exact bosonization and applying Clifford finite-depth generalized local unitary (gLU) transformation, we can achieve all possible fermion-to-qubit mappings (up to the re-pairing of Majorana fermions). In particular, we discover a new super-compact encoding using 1.25 qubits per fermion on the square lattice, which is lower than any method in the literature. We prove the existence of fermion-to-qubit mappings with qubit-fermion ratios $r=1+ \frac{1}{2k}$ for positive integers $k$, where the proof utilizes the trivialness of quantum cellular automata (QCA) in two spatial dimensions. When the ratio approaches 1, the fermion-to-qubit mapping reduces to the 1d Jordan-Wigner transformation along a certain path in the two-dimensional lattice. Finally, we explicitly demonstrate that the Bravyi-Kitaev superfast simulation, the Verstraete-Cirac auxiliary method, Kitaev's exactly solved model, the Majorana loop stabilizer codes, and the compact fermion-to-qubit mapping can all be obtained from the exact bosonization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A circuit-level protocol and analysis for twist-based lattice surgery</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05678</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Lattice surgery is a measurement-based technique for performing fault-tolerant quantum computation in two dimensions. When using the surface code, the most general lattice surgery operations require lattice irregularities called twist defects. However, implementing twist-based lattice surgery may require additional resources, such as extra device connectivity, and could lower the threshold and overall performance for the surface code. Here we provide an explicit twist-based lattice surgery protocol and its requisite connectivity layout. We also provide new stabilizer measurement circuits for measuring twist defects which are compatible with our chosen gate scheduling. We undertake the first circuit-level error correction simulations during twist-based lattice surgery using a biased depolarizing noise model. Our results indicate a slight decrease in the threshold for timelike logical failures compared to lattice surgery protocols with no twist defects in the bulk. However, comfortably below threshold (i.e. with CNOT infidelities below $5 \times 10^{-3}$), the performance degradation is mild and in fact preferable over proposed alternative twist-free schemes. Lastly, we provide an efficient scheme for measuring $Y$ operators along boundaries of surface codes which bypasses certain steps that were required in previous schemes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Practical and Efficient Hamiltonian Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00190</link>
    <author>Wenjun Yu, Jinzhao Sun, Zeyao Han, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>With the fast development of quantum technology, the size of quantum systems we can digitally manipulate and analogly probe increase drastically. In order to have a better control and understanding of the quantum hardware, an important task is to characterize the interaction, i.e., to learn the Hamiltonian, which determines both static or dynamic properties of the system. Conventional Hamiltonian learning methods either require costly process tomography or adopt impractical assumptions, such as prior information of the Hamiltonian structure and the ground or thermal states of the system. In this work, we present a practical and efficient Hamiltonian learning method that circumvents these limitations. The proposed method can efficiently learn any Hamiltonian that is sparse on the Pauli basis using only short time dynamics and local operations without any information of the Hamiltonian or preparing any eigenstates or thermal states. The method has scalable complexity and vanishing failure probability regarding the qubit number. Meanwhile, it is free from state preparation and measurement error and robust against a certain amount of circuit and shot noise. We numerically test the scaling and the estimation accuracy of the method for transverse field Ising Hamiltonian with random interaction strengths and molecular Hamiltonians, both with varying sizes. All these results verify the practicality and efficacy of the method, paving the way for a systematic understanding of large quantum systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Merkle Trees</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14317</link>
    <author>Lijie Chen, Ramis Movassagh</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 30 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Commitment scheme is a central task in cryptography, where a party (typically called a prover) stores a piece of information (e.g., a bit string) with the promise of not changing it. This information can be accessed by another party (typically called the verifier), who can later learn the information and verify that it was not meddled with. Merkle tree is a well-known construction for doing so in a succinct manner, in which the verfier can learn any part of the information by receiving a short proof from the honest prover. Despite its significance in classical cryptography, there was no quantum analog of the Merkle tree. A direct generalization using the Quantum Random Oracle Model (QROM) does not seem to be secure. In this work, we propose the quantum Merkle tree. It is based on what we call the Quantum Haar Random Oracle Model (QHROM). In QHROM, both the prover and the verifier have access to a Haar random quantum oracle G and its inverse. Using the quantum Merkle tree, we propose a succinct quantum argument for the Gap-k-Local-Hamiltonian problem. We prove it is secure against semi-honest provers in QHROM and conjecture its general security. Assuming the Quantum PCP conjecture is true, this succinct argument extends to all of QMA. This work raises a number of interesting open research problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence of contextuality and Wigner function negativity in continuous-variable quantum optics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14788</link>
    <author>Jonas Haferkamp, Juani Bermejo-Vega</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One of the central foundational questions of physics is to identify what makes a system quantum as opposed to classical. One seminal notion of classicality of a quantum system is the existence of a non-contextual hidden variable model as introduced in the early work by Bell, Kochen and Specker. In quantum optics, the non-negativity of the Wigner function is a ubiquitous notion of classicality. In this work we establish an equivalence between these two concepts. In particular, we show that any non-contextual hidden variable model for Gaussian quantum optics has an alternative non-negative Wigner function description. Conversely, it was known that the Wigner representation provides a non-negative non-contextual description of Gaussian quantum optics. It follows that contextuality and Wigner negativity are equivalent notions of non-classicality and equivalent resources for this quantum subtheory. In particular, both contextuality and Wigner negativity are necessary for a computational speed-up of quantum Gaussian optics. At the technical level, our result holds true for any subfamily of Gaussian measurements that include homodyne measurements, i.e., measurements of standard quadrature observables.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Oracle separations of hybrid quantum-classical circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01904</link>
    <author>Atul Singh Arora, Alexandru Gheorghiu, Uttam Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An important theoretical problem in the study of quantum computation, that is also practically relevant in the context of near-term quantum devices, is to understand the computational power of hybrid models, that combine poly-time classical computation with short-depth quantum computation. Here, we consider two such models: CQ_d which captures the scenario of a polynomial-time classical algorithm that queries a d-depth quantum computer many times; and QC_d which is more analogous to measurement-based quantum computation and captures the scenario of a d-depth quantum computer with the ability to change the sequence of gates being applied depending on measurement outcomes processed by a classical computation. Chia, Chung & Lai (STOC 2020) and Coudron & Menda (STOC 2020) showed that these models (with d=log^O(1) (n)) are strictly weaker than BQP (the class of problems solvable by poly-time quantum computation), relative to an oracle, disproving a conjecture of Jozsa in the relativised world. We show that, despite the similarities between CQ_d and QC_d, the two models are incomparable, i.e. CQ_d $\nsubseteq$ QC_d and QC_d $\nsubseteq$ CQ_d relative to an oracle. In other words, there exist problems that one model can solve but not the other and vice versa. We do this by considering new oracle problems that capture the distinctions between the two models and by introducing the notion of an intrinsically stochastic oracle, an oracle whose responses are inherently randomised, which is used for our second result. While we leave showing the second separation relative to a standard oracle as an open problem, we believe the notion of stochastic oracles could be of independent interest for studying complexity classes which have resisted separation in the standard oracle model. Our constructions also yield simpler oracle separations between the hybrid models and BQP, compared to earlier works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking Characterization Methods for Noisy Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02243</link>
    <author>Megan L. Dahlhauser, Travis S. Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Effective methods for characterizing the noise in quantum computing devices are essential for programming and debugging circuit performance. Existing approaches vary in the information obtained as well as the amount of quantum and classical resources required, with more information generally requiring more resources. Here we benchmark the characterization methods of gate set tomography, Pauli channel noise reconstruction, and empirical direct characterization for developing models that describe noisy quantum circuit performance on a 27-qubit superconducting transmon device. We evaluate these models by comparing the accuracy of noisy circuit simulations with the corresponding experimental observations. We find that the agreement of noise model to experiment does not correlate with the information gained by characterization and that the underlying circuit strongly influences the best choice of characterization approach. Empirical direct characterization scales best of the methods we tested and produced the most accurate characterizations across our benchmarks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limits on Parameter Estimation of Quantum Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01738</link>
    <author>Vishal Katariya</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The aim of this thesis is to develop a theoretical framework to study parameter estimation of quantum channels. We study the task of estimating unknown parameters encoded in a channel in the sequential setting. A sequential strategy is the most general way to use a channel multiple times. Our goal is to establish lower bounds (called Cramer-Rao bounds) on the estimation error. The bounds we develop are universally applicable; i.e., they apply to all permissible quantum dynamics. We consider the use of catalysts to enhance the power of a channel estimation strategy. This is termed amortization. The power of a channel for a parameter estimation is determined by its Fisher information. Thus, we study how much a catalyst quantum state can enhance the Fisher information of a channel by defining the amortized Fisher information. We establish our bounds by proving that for certain Fisher information quantities, catalyst states do not improve the performance of a sequential estimation protocol compared to a parallel one. The technical term for this is an amortization collapse. We use this to establish bounds when estimating one parameter, or multiple parameters simultaneously. Our bounds apply universally and we also cast them as optimization problems. For the single parameter case, we establish bounds for general quantum channels using both the symmetric logarithmic derivative (SLD) Fisher information and the right logarithmic derivative (RLD) Fisher information. The task of estimating multiple parameters simultaneously is more involved than the single parameter case, because the Cramer-Rao bounds take the form of matrix inequalities. We establish a scalar Cramer-Rao bound for multiparameter channel estimation using the RLD Fisher information. For both single and multiparameter estimation, we provide a no-go condition for the so-called Heisenberg scaling using our RLD-based bound.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Pauli stabilizer models of twisted quantum doubles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.11394</link>
    <author>Tyler D. Ellison, Yu-An Chen, Arpit Dua, Wilbur Shirley, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Dominic J. Williamson</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 22 2021</pubDate>
    <description>We construct a Pauli stabilizer model for every two-dimensional Abelian topological order that admits a gapped boundary. Our primary example is a Pauli stabilizer model on four-dimensional qudits that belongs to the double semion (DS) phase of matter. The DS stabilizer Hamiltonian is constructed by condensing an emergent boson in a $\mathbb{Z}_4$ toric code, where the condensation is implemented by making certain two-body measurements. We rigorously verify the topological order of the DS stabilizer model by identifying an explicit finite-depth quantum circuit (with ancillary qubits) that maps its ground state subspace to that of a DS string-net model. We show that the construction of the DS stabilizer Hamiltonian generalizes to all twisted quantum doubles (TQDs) with Abelian anyons. This yields a Pauli stabilizer code on composite-dimensional qudits for each such TQD, implying that the classification of topological Pauli stabilizer codes extends well beyond stacks of toric codes - in fact, exhausting all Abelian anyon theories that admit a gapped boundary. We also demonstrate that symmetry-protected topological phases of matter characterized by type I and type II cocycles can be modeled by Pauli stabilizer Hamiltonians by gauging certain 1-form symmetries of the TQD stabilizer models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure conversion for fault-tolerant quantum computing in alkaline earth Rydberg atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03540</link>
    <author>Yue Wu, Shimon Kolkowitz, Shruti Puri, Jeff D Thompson</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Executing quantum algorithms on error-corrected logical qubits is a critical step for scalable quantum computing, but the requisite numbers of qubits and physical error rates are demanding for current experimental hardware. Recently, the development of error correcting codes tailored to particular physical noise models has helped relax these requirements. In this work, we propose a qubit encoding and gate protocol for ${}^{171}$Yb neutral atom qubits that converts the dominant physical errors into erasures, that is, errors in known locations. The key idea is to encode qubits in a metastable electronic level, such that gate errors predominantly result in transitions to disjoint subspaces whose populations can be continuously monitored via fluorescence. We estimate that 98% of errors can be converted into erasures. We quantify the benefit of this approach via circuit-level simulations of the surface code, finding a threshold increase from 0.937% to 4.15%. We also observe a larger code distance near the threshold, leading to a faster decrease in the logical error rate for the same number of physical qubits, which is important for near-term implementations. Erasure conversion should benefit any error correcting code, and may also be applied to design new gates and encodings in other qubit platforms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Algorithms for Approximating Quantum Partition Functions at Low Temperature</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06533</link>
    <author>Tyler Helmuth, Ryan L. Mann</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish an efficient approximation algorithm for the partition functions of a class of quantum spin systems at low temperature, which can be viewed as stable quantum perturbations of classical spin systems. Our algorithm is based on combining the contour representation of quantum spin systems of this type due to Borgs, Kotecký, and Ueltschi with the algorithmic framework developed by Helmuth, Perkins, and Regts, and Borgs et al.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Analytical calculation formulas for capacities of classical and classical-quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02450</link>
    <author>Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive an analytical calculation formula for the channel capacity of a classical channel without any iteration while its existing algorithms require iterations and the number of iteration depends on the required precision level. Hence, our formula is its first analytical formula without any iteration. We apply the obtained formula to examples and see how the obtained formula works in these examples. Then, we extend it to the channel capacity of a classical-quantum (cq-) channel. Many existing studies proposed algorithms for a cq-channel and all of them require iterations. Our extended analytical algorithm have also no iteration and output the exactly optimum values.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Yet Another Proof of the Joint Convexity of Relative Entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.13763</link>
    <author>Mary Beth Ruskai</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 28 2021</pubDate>
    <description>The joint convexity of the map $(X,A) \mapsto X^* A^{-1} X$, an integral representation of convex operator functions, and an observation of Ando are used to obtain a simple proof of both the joint convexity of relative entropy and a trace convexity result of Lieb. The latter was the key ingredient in the original proof of the strong subadditivity of quantum entropy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Depth optimization of CZ, CNOT, and Clifford circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05215</link>
    <author>Dmitri Maslov, Ben Zindorf</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We seek to develop better upper bound guarantees on the depth of quantum CZ gate, CNOT gate, and Clifford circuits than those reported previously. We focus on the number of qubits $n\,{\leq}\,$1,345,000 [1], which represents the most practical use case. Our upper bound on the depth of CZ circuits is $\lfloor n/2 + 0.4993{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.0191{\cdot}\log(n) - 10.9139\rfloor$, improving best known depth by a factor of roughly 2. We extend the constructions used to prove this upper bound to obtain depth upper bound of $\lfloor n + 1.9496{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.5075{\cdot}\log(n) - 23.4269 \rfloor$ for CNOT gate circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $4/3$ over state of the art, and depth upper bound of $\lfloor 2n + 2.9487{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 8.4909{\cdot}\log(n) - 44.4798\rfloor$ for Clifford circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $5/3$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact quantum query complexity of computing Hamming weight modulo powers of two and three</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14682</link>
    <author>Arjan Cornelissen, Nikhil S. Mande, Maris Ozols, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 30 2021</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of computing the Hamming weight of an $n$-bit string modulo $m$, for any positive integer $m \leq n$ whose only prime factors are 2 and 3. We show that the exact quantum query complexity of this problem is $\left\lceil n(1 - 1/m) \right\rceil$. The upper bound is via an iterative query algorithm whose core components are the well-known 1-query quantum algorithm (essentially due to Deutsch) to compute the Hamming weight a 2-bit string mod 2 (i.e., the parity of the input bits), and a new 2-query quantum algorithm to compute the Hamming weight of a 3-bit string mod 3. We show a matching lower bound (in fact for arbitrary moduli $m$) via a variant of the polynomial method [de Wolf, SIAM J. Comput., 32(3), 2003]. This bound is for the weaker task of deciding whether or not a given $n$-bit input has Hamming weight 0 modulo $m$, and it holds even in the stronger non-deterministic quantum query model where an algorithm must have positive acceptance probability iff its input evaluates to 1. For $m>2$ our lower bound exceeds $n/2$, beating the best lower bound provable using the general polynomial method [Theorem 4.3, Beals et al., J. ACM 48(4), 2001].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Diagonal unitary and orthogonal symmetries in quantum theory II: Evolution operators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.11123</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 22 2021</pubDate>
    <description>We study bipartite unitary operators which stay invariant under the local actions of diagonal unitary and orthogonal groups. We investigate structural properties of these operators, arguing that the diagonal symmetry makes them suitable for analytical study. As a first application, we construct large new families of dual unitary gates in arbitrary finite dimensions, which are important toy models for entanglement spreading in quantum circuits. We then analyze the non-local nature of these invariant operators, both in discrete (operator Schmidt rank) and continuous (entangling power) settings. Our scrutiny reveals that these operators can be used to simulate any bipartite unitary gate via stochastic local operations and classical communication. Furthermore, we establish a one-to-one connection between the set of local diagonal unitary invariant dual unitary operators with maximum entangling power and the set of complex Hadamard matrices. Finally, we discuss distinguishability of unitary operators in the setting of the stated diagonal symmetry.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum networks self-test all entangled states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05032</link>
    <author>Ivan Šupić, Joseph Bowles, Marc-Olivier Renou, Antonio Acín, Matty J. Hoban</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Certifying quantum properties with minimal assumptions is a fundamental problem in quantum information science. Self-testing is a method to infer the underlying physics of a quantum experiment only from the measured statistics. While all bipartite pure entangled states can be self-tested, little is known about how to self-test quantum states of an arbitrary number of systems. Here, we introduce a framework for network-assisted self-testing and use it to self-test any pure entangled quantum state of an arbitrary number of systems. The scheme requires the preparation of a number of singlets that scales linearly with the number of systems, and the implementation of standard projective and Bell measurements, all feasible with current technology. When all the network constraints are exploited, the obtained self-testing certification is stronger than what is achievable in any Bell-type scenario. Our work does not only solve an open question in the field, but also shows how properly designed networks offer new opportunities for the certification of quantum phenomena.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Distributed Algorithms for Detection of Cliques</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03000</link>
    <author>Keren Censor-Hillel, Orr Fischer, François Le Gall, Dean Leitersdorf, Rotem Oshman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The possibilities offered by quantum computing have drawn attention in the distributed computing community recently, with several breakthrough results showing quantum distributed algorithms that run faster than the fastest known classical counterparts, and even separations between the two models. A prime example is the result by Izumi, Le Gall, and Magniez [STACS 2020], who showed that triangle detection by quantum distributed algorithms is easier than triangle listing, while an analogous result is not known in the classical case. In this paper we present a framework for fast quantum distributed clique detection. This improves upon the state-of-the-art for the triangle case, and is also more general, applying to larger clique sizes. Our main technical contribution is a new approach for detecting cliques by encapsulating this as a search task for nodes that can be added to smaller cliques. To extract the best complexities out of our approach, we develop a framework for nested distributed quantum searches, which employ checking procedures that are quantum themselves. Moreover, we show a circuit-complexity barrier on proving a lower bound of the form $\Omega(n^{3/5+\epsilon})$ for $K_p$-detection for any $p \geq 4$, even in the classical (non-quantum) distributed CONGEST setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Toward Trainability of Deep Quantum Neural Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.15002</link>
    <author>Kaining Zhang, Min-Hsiu Hsieh, Liu Liu, Dacheng Tao</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Neural Networks (QNNs) with random structures have poor trainability due to the exponentially vanishing gradient as the circuit depth and the qubit number increase. This result leads to a general belief that a deep QNN will not be feasible. In this work, we provide the first viable solution to the vanishing gradient problem for deep QNNs with theoretical guarantees. Specifically, we prove that for circuits with controlled-layer architectures, the expectation of the gradient norm can be lower bounded by a value that is independent of the qubit number and the circuit depth. Our results follow from a careful analysis of the gradient behaviour on parameter space consisting of rotation angles, as employed in almost any QNNs, instead of relying on impractical 2-design assumptions. We explicitly construct examples where only our QNNs are trainable and converge, while others in comparison cannot.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Deniable Encryption in a Quantum World</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.14988</link>
    <author>Andrea Coladangelo, Shafi Goldwasser, Umesh Vazirani</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>(Sender-)Deniable encryption provides a very strong privacy guarantee: a sender who is coerced by an attacker into "opening" their ciphertext after-the-fact is able to generate "fake" local random choices that are consistent with any plaintext of their choice. The only known fully-efficient constructions of public-key deniable encryption rely on indistinguishability obfuscation (iO) (which currently can only be based on sub-exponential hardness assumptions). In this work, we study (sender-)deniable encryption in a setting where the encryption procedure is a quantum algorithm, but the ciphertext is classical. We propose two notions of deniable encryption in this setting. The first notion, called quantum deniability, parallels the classical one. We give a fully efficient construction satisfying this definition, assuming the quantum hardness of the Learning with Errors (LWE) problem. The second notion, unexplainability, starts from a new perspective on deniability, and leads to a natural common view of deniability in the classical and quantum settings. We give a construction which is secure in the random oracle model, assuming the quantum hardness of LWE. Notably, our construction satisfies a strong form of unexplainability which is impossible to achieve classically, thus highlighting a new quantum phenomenon that may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quadratic speedup for spatial search by continuous-time quantum walk</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.12746</link>
    <author>Simon Apers, Shantanav Chakraborty, Leonardo Novo, Jérémie Roland</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 24 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Continuous-time quantum walks provide a natural framework to tackle the fundamental problem of finding a node among a set of marked nodes in a graph, known as spatial search. Whether spatial search by continuous-time quantum walk provides a quadratic advantage over classical random walks has been an outstanding problem. Thus far, this advantage is obtained only for specific graphs or when a single node of the underlying graph is marked. In this article, we provide a new continuous-time quantum walk search algorithm that completely resolves this: our algorithm can find a marked node in any graph with any number of marked nodes, in a time that is quadratically faster than classical random walks. The overall algorithm is quite simple, requiring time evolution of the quantum walk Hamiltonian followed by a projective measurement. A key component of our algorithm is a purely analog procedure to perform operations on a state of the form $e^{-tH^2}|\psi\rangle$, for a given Hamiltonian $H$: it only requires evolving $H$ for time scaling as $\sqrt{t}$. This allows us to quadratically fast-forward the dynamics of a continuous-time classical random walk. The applications of our work thus go beyond the realm of quantum walks and can lead to new analog quantum algorithms for preparing ground states of Hamiltonians or solving optimization problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On nonlinear transformations in quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.12307</link>
    <author>Zoë Holmes, Nolan Coble, Andrew T. Sornborger, Yiğit Subaşı</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 24 2021</pubDate>
    <description>While quantum computers are naturally well-suited to implementing linear operations, it is less clear how to implement nonlinear operations on quantum computers. However, nonlinear subroutines may prove key to a range of applications of quantum computing from solving nonlinear equations to data processing and quantum machine learning. Here we develop algorithms for implementing nonlinear transformations of input quantum states. Our algorithms are framed around the concept of a weighted state, a mathematical entity describing the output of an operational procedure involving both quantum circuits and classical post-processing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cut query algorithms with star contraction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05674</link>
    <author>Simon Apers, Yuval Efron, Paweł Gawrychowski, Troy Lee, Sagnik Mukhopadhyay, Danupon Nanongkai</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the complexity of determining the edge connectivity of a simple graph with cut queries. We show that (i) there is a bounded-error randomized algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $O(n)$ cut queries, and (ii) there is a bounded-error quantum algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $\~O(\sqrt{n})$ cut queries. We prove these results using a new technique called "star contraction" to randomly contract edges of a graph while preserving non-trivial minimum cuts. In star contraction vertices randomly contract an edge incident on a small set of randomly chosen vertices. In contrast to the related 2-out contraction technique of Ghaffari, Nowicki, and Thorup [SODA'20], star contraction only contracts vertex-disjoint star subgraphs, which allows it to be efficiently implemented via cut queries. The $O(n)$ bound from item (i) was not known even for the simpler problem of connectivity, and improves the $O(n\log^3 n)$ bound by Rubinstein, Schramm, and Weinberg [ITCS'18]. The bound is tight under the reasonable conjecture that the randomized communication complexity of connectivity is $\Omega(n\log n)$, an open question since the seminal work of Babai, Frankl, and Simon [FOCS'86]. The bound also excludes using edge connectivity on simple graphs to prove a superlinear randomized query lower bound for minimizing a symmetric submodular function. Item (ii) gives a nearly-quadratic separation with the randomized complexity and addresses an open question of Lee, Santha, and Zhang [SODA'21]. The algorithm can also be viewed as making $\~O(\sqrt{n})$ matrix-vector multiplication queries to the adjacency matrix. Finally, we demonstrate the use of star contraction outside of the cut query setting by designing a one-pass semi-streaming algorithm for computing edge connectivity in the vertex arrival setting. This contrasts with the edge arrival setting where two passes are required.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>