<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Learning to predict arbitrary quantum processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14894</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Sitan Chen, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an efficient machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting any unknown quantum process $\mathcal{E}$ over $n$ qubits. For a wide range of distributions $\mathcal{D}$ on arbitrary $n$-qubit states, we show that this ML algorithm can learn to predict any local property of the output from the unknown process $\mathcal{E}$, with a small average error over input states drawn from $\mathcal{D}$. The ML algorithm is computationally efficient even when the unknown process is a quantum circuit with exponentially many gates. Our algorithm combines efficient procedures for learning properties of an unknown state and for learning a low-degree approximation to an unknown observable. The analysis hinges on proving new norm inequalities, including a quantum analogue of the classical Bohnenblust-Hille inequality, which we derive by giving an improved algorithm for optimizing local Hamiltonians. Overall, our results highlight the potential for ML models to predict the output of complex quantum dynamics much faster than the time needed to run the process itself.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Challenges in Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15844</link>
    <author>Daniel Gottesman</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I will give an overview of what I see as some of the most important future directions in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation. In particular, I will give a brief summary of the major problems that need to be solved in fault tolerance based on low-density parity check codes and in hardware-specific fault tolerance. I will then conclude with a discussion of a possible new paradigm for designing fault-tolerant protocols based on a space-time picture of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A classical oracle separation between QMA and QCMA</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15380</link>
    <author>Anand Natarajan, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It is a long-standing open question in quantum complexity theory whether the definition of $\textit{non-deterministic}$ quantum computation requires quantum witnesses $(\textsf{QMA})$ or if classical witnesses suffice $(\textsf{QCMA})$. We make progress on this question by constructing a randomized classical oracle separating the respective computational complexity classes. Previous separations [Aaronson-Kuperberg (CCC'07), Fefferman-Kimmel (MFCS'18)] required a quantum unitary oracle. The separating problem is deciding whether a distribution supported on regular un-directed graphs either consists of multiple connected components (yes instances) or consists of one expanding connected component (no instances) where the graph is given in an adjacency-list format by the oracle. Therefore, the oracle is a distribution over $n$-bit boolean functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum state preparation without coherent arithmetic</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14892</link>
    <author>Sam McArdle, András Gilyén, Mario Berta</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a versatile method for preparing a quantum state whose amplitudes are given by some known function. Unlike existing approaches, our method does not require handcrafted reversible arithmetic circuits, or quantum memory loads, to encode the function values. Instead, we use a template quantum eigenvalue transformation circuit to convert a low cost block encoding of the sine function into the desired function. Our method uses only 4 ancilla qubits (3 if the approximating polynomial has definite parity), providing order-of-magnitude qubit count reductions compared to state-of-the-art approaches, while using a similar number of Toffoli gates if the function can be well represented by a polynomial or Fourier approximation. Like black-box methods, the complexity of our approach depends on the 'L2-norm filling-fraction' of the function. We demonstrate the efficiency of our method for preparing states commonly used in quantum algorithms, such as Gaussian and Kaiser window states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Greatly improved higher-order product formulae for quantum simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15817</link>
    <author>Mauro E.S. Morales, Pedro C.S. Costa, Daniel K. Burgarth, Yuval R. Sanders, Dominic W. Berry</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for simulation of Hamiltonian evolution are often based on product formulae like Trotter. The fractal method of Suzuki gives a systematic way to find arbitrarily high-order product formulae, but results in a large number of exponentials. On the other hand, an alternative way, with a minimum number of exponentials, for 6th and 8th order product formulae is given by Yoshida. In this work, we not only extended Yoshida's method to 10th order, but we also found hundreds of new 8th order product formulae. Moreover, we found an 8th order product formula that is over $1000$ times more accurate than the best product formula of Yoshida.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A super-polynomial quantum-classical separation for density modelling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14936</link>
    <author>Niklas Pirnay, Ryan Sweke, Jens Eisert, Jean-Pierre Seifert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Density modelling is the task of learning an unknown probability density function from samples, and is one of the central problems of unsupervised machine learning. In this work, we show that there exists a density modelling problem for which fault-tolerant quantum computers can offer a super-polynomial advantage over classical learning algorithms, given standard cryptographic assumptions. Along the way, we provide a variety of additional results and insights, of potential interest for proving future distribution learning separations between quantum and classical learning algorithms. Specifically, we (a) provide an overview of the relationships between hardness results in supervised learning and distribution learning, and (b) show that any weak pseudo-random function can be used to construct a classically hard density modelling problem. The latter result opens up the possibility of proving quantum-classical separations for density modelling based on weaker assumptions than those necessary for pseudo-random functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hunting for quantum-classical crossover in condensed matter problems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14109</link>
    <author>Nobuyuki Yoshioka, Tsuyoshi Okubo, Yasunari Suzuki, Yuki Koizumi, Wataru Mizukami</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The intensive pursuit for quantum algorithms with speedup in terms of computational complexity has further led to this modernized crucial question: \it When and how will quantum computers outperform classical computers?. The next milestone in the context of this quantum transcendence is undoubtedly the realization of quantum acceleration in practical problems. Here we provide a clear evidence and arguments that the primary target is likely to be condensed matter physics. Our primary contributions are summarized as follows: 1) Proposal of systematic error/runtime analysis on state-of-the-art classical algorithm based on tensor networks; 2) Dedicated and high-resolution analysis on quantum resource performed at the level of executable logical instructions; 3) Clarification of quantum-classical crosspoint for ground-state simulation to be within runtime of hours using only a few hundreds of thousand physical qubits for 2d Heisenberg and 2d Fermi-Hubbard models. To our knowledge, we argue that condensed matter problems offer the earliest platform for demonstration of practical quantum advantage that is order-of-magnitude more feasible than ever known candidates, in terms of both qubit counts and total runtime.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The $2T$-qutrit, a two-mode bosonic qutrit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16188</link>
    <author>Aurélie Denys, Anthony Leverrier</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Building on the observation that bosonic cat codes live in the span of coherent states indexed by a finite subgroup of the complex numbers, we consider a two-mode bosonic code where the coherent states now form a finite subgroup of the quaternions. We focus on the binary tetrahedral group, denoted $2T$, which admits 24 elements forming the vertices of the 24-cell, a regular four-dimensional polytope, and define a bosonic qutrit that appears to be quite robust in the regime of low loss. We initiate a study of the properties of this qutrit and identify stabilisers as well as logical operators for this bosonic code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Discrete Bulk Reconstruction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15601</link>
    <author>Scott Aaronson, Jason Pollack</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>According to the AdS/CFT correspondence, the geometries of certain spacetimes are fully determined by quantum states that live on their boundaries -- indeed, by the von Neumann entropies of portions of those boundary states. This work investigates to what extent the geometries can be reconstructed from the entropies in polynomial time. Bouland, Fefferman, and Vazirani (2019) argued that the AdS/CFT map can be exponentially complex if one wants to reconstruct regions such as the interiors of black holes. Our main result provides a sort of converse: we show that, in the special case of a single 1D boundary, if the input data consists of a list of entropies of contiguous boundary regions, and if the entropies satisfy a single inequality called Strong Subadditivity, then we can construct a graph model for the bulk in linear time. Moreover, the bulk graph is planar, it has $O(N^2)$ vertices (the information-theoretic minimum), and it's ``universal,'' with only the edge weights depending on the specific entropies in question. From a combinatorial perspective, our problem boils down to an ``inverse'' of the famous min-cut problem: rather than being given a graph and asked to find a min-cut, here we're given the values of min-cuts separating various sets of vertices, and need to find a weighted undirected graph consistent with those values. Our solution to this problem relies on the notion of a ``bulkless'' graph, which might be of independent interest for AdS/CFT. We also make initial progress on the case of multiple 1D boundaries -- where the boundaries could be connected via wormholes -- including an upper bound of $O(N^4)$ vertices whenever a planar bulk graph exists (thus putting the problem into the complexity class $\mathsf{NP}$).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction with metastable states of trapped ions using erasure conversion</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15024</link>
    <author>Mingyu Kang, Wesley C. Campbell, Kenneth R. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Erasures, or errors with known locations, are a more favorable type of error for quantum error-correcting codes than Pauli errors. Converting physical noise into erasures can significantly improve the performance of quantum error correction. Here we apply the idea of performing erasure conversion by encoding qubits into metastable atomic states, proposed by Wu, Kolkowitz, Puri, and Thompson [Nat. Comm. 13, 4657 (2022)], to trapped ions. We suggest an erasure-conversion scheme for metastable trapped-ion qubits and develop a detailed model of various types of errors. We then compare the logical performance of ground and metastable qubits on the surface code under various physical constraints and discuss the trade offs.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>