<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Uncertainty relations from graph theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02197</link>
    <author>Carlos de Gois, Kiara Hansenne, Otfried Gühne</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum measurements are inherently probabilistic. Further defying our classical intuition, quantum theory often forbids us to precisely determine the outcomes of simultaneous measurements. This phenomenon is captured and quantified through uncertainty relations. Although studied since the inception of quantum theory, this problem of determining the possible expectation values of a collection of quantum measurements remains, in general, unsolved. By constructing a close connection between observables and graph theory, we derive uncertainty relations valid for any set of dichotomic observables. These relations are, in many cases, tight, and related to the size of the maximum clique of the associated graph. As applications, they can be straightforwardly used to build entropic uncertainty relations, separability criteria and entanglement witnesses.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Syndrome-Derived Error Rates as a Benchmark of Quantum Hardware</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00553</link>
    <author>James R. Wootton</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correcting codes are designed to pinpoint exactly when and where errors occur in quantum circuits. This feature is the foundation of their primary task: to support fault-tolerant quantum computation. However, this feature could used as the basis of benchmarking: By analyzing the outputs of even small-scale quantum error correction circuits, a detailed picture can be constructed of error processes across a quantum device. Here we perform an example of such an analysis, using the results of small repetition codes to determine the error rate of each qubit while idle during a syndrome measurement. This provides an idea of the errors experienced by the qubits across a device while they are part of the kind of circuit that we expect to be typical in fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The classical cost of transmitting a qubit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02244</link>
    <author>Martin J. Renner, Armin Tavakoli, Marco Túlio Quintino</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider general prepare-and-measure scenarios in which Alice can transmit qubit states to Bob, who can perform general measurements in the form of positive operator-valued measures (POVMs). We show that the statistics obtained in any such quantum protocol can be simulated by the purely classical means of shared randomness and two bits of communication. Furthermore, we prove that two bits of communication is the minimal cost of a perfect classical simulation. In addition, we apply our methods to Bell scenarios, which extends the well-known Toner and Bacon protocol. In particular, two bits of communication are enough to simulate all quantum correlations associated to arbitrary local POVMs applied to any entangled two-qubit state.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classification of measurement-based quantum wire in stabilizer PEPS</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00616</link>
    <author>Paul Herringer, Robert Raussendorf</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a class of translation-invariant 2D tensor network states with a stabilizer symmetry, which we call stabilizer PEPS. The cluster state, GHZ state, and states in the toric code belong to this class. We investigate the transmission capacity of stabilizer PEPS for measurement-based quantum wire, and arrive at a complete classification of transmission behaviors. The transmission behaviors fall into 13 classes, one of which corresponds to Clifford quantum cellular automata. In addition, we identify 12 other classes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact electronic states with shallow quantum circuits through global optimisation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00085</link>
    <author>Hugh G. A. Burton, Daniel Marti-Dafcik, David P. Tew, David J. Wales</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers promise to revolutionise electronic simulations by overcoming the exponential scaling of many-electron problems. While electronic wave functions can be represented using a product of fermionic unitary operators, shallow quantum circuits for exact states have not yet been achieved. We construct universal wave functions from gate-efficient, symmetry-preserving fermionic operators by introducing an algorithm that globally optimises the wave function in the discrete ansatz design and the continuous parameter spaces. Our approach maximises the accuracy that can be obtained with near-term quantum circuits. Highly accurate numerical simulations on strongly correlated molecules, including water and molecular nitrogen, and the condensed-matter Hubbard model, demonstrate that our algorithm reliably advances the state-of-the-art, defining a new paradigm for quantum simulations featuring strong electron correlation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cryptography with Certified Deletion</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.01754</link>
    <author>James Bartusek, Dakshita Khurana</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a new, unifying framework that yields an array of cryptographic primitives with \em certified deletion. These primitives enable a party in possession of a quantum ciphertext to generate a classical certificate that the encrypted plaintext has been information-theoretically deleted, and cannot be recovered even given unbounded computational resources. For any $X \in \{\mathsf{public}\text{-}\mathsf{key},\mathsf{attribute\text{-}based},\mathsf{fully\text{-}homomorphic},\mathsf{witness},\mathsf{timed}\text{-}\mathsf{release}\}$, our compiler yields post-quantum $X$ encryption with certified deletion, assuming post-quantum $X$ encryption. In addition, assuming the existence of statistically binding commitments, our compiler yields statistically binding commitments with certified everlasting hiding as well as statistically sound zero-knowledge proofs for QMA with certified everlasting zero-knowledge. We also introduce and construct information-theoretic secret sharing with certified deletion. While encryption with certified deletion was first introduced by [BI20] in the context of an information-theoretic one-time pad, existing proposals [Unr14,HMNY21,HMNY22,Por22] for \em public-key primitives with certified deletion (1) have complex tailored constructions and non-generic proofs, (2) are not known to satisfy everlasting security after deletion in the plain model, and in many cases (3) resort to idealized models or stronger cryptographic assumptions like obfuscation. We remedy this situation by developing a novel proof technique to argue that a bit $b$ has been \em information-theoretically deleted from an adversary's view once they produce a valid deletion certificate, despite having been previously \em information-theoretically determined by the ciphertext they held in their view. This may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Positive maps and entanglement in real Hilbert spaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02510</link>
    <author>Giulio Chiribella, Kenneth R. Davidson, Vern I. Paulsen, Mizanur Rahaman</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The theory of positive maps plays a central role in operator algebras and functional analysis, and has countless applications in quantum information science. The theory was originally developed for operators acting on complex Hilbert spaces, and little is known about its variant on real Hilbert spaces. In this article we study positive maps acting on a full matrix algebra over the reals, pointing out a number of fundamental differences with the complex case and discussing their implications in quantum information. We provide a necessary and sufficient condition for a real map to admit a positive complexification, and connect the existence of positive maps with non-positive complexification with the existence of mixed states that are entangled in real Hilbert space quantum mechanics, but separable in the complex version, providing explicit examples both for the maps and for the states. Finally, we discuss entanglement breaking and PPT maps, and we show that a straightforward real version of the PPT-squared conjecture is false even in dimension 2. Nevertheless, we show that the original PPT-squared conjecture implies a different conjecture for real maps, in which the PPT property is replaced by a stronger property of invariance under partial transposition (IPT). When the IPT property is assumed, we prove an asymptotic version of the conjecture.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Geometric structure of thermal cones</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02237</link>
    <author>A. de Oliveira Junior, Jakub Czartowski, Karol Życzkowski, Kamil Korzekwa</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The second law of thermodynamics imposes a fundamental asymmetry in the flow of events. The so-called thermodynamic arrow of time introduces an ordering that divides the system's state space into past, future and incomparable regions. In this work, we analyse the structure of the resulting thermal cones, i.e., sets of states that a given state can thermodynamically evolve to (the future thermal cone) or evolve from (the past thermal cone). Specifically, for a $d$-dimensional classical state of a system interacting with a heat bath, we find explicit construction of the past thermal cone and the incomparable region. Moreover, we provide a detailed analysis of their behaviour based on newly introduced thermodynamic monotones given by the volumes of thermal cones. Finally, we point out that our results also apply to other majorisation-based resource theories (such as that of entanglement and coherence), since the partial ordering describing allowed state transformations is then the opposite of the thermodynamic order in the infinite temperature limit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Clifford Circuit Initialisation for Variational Quantum Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.01539</link>
    <author>M. H. Cheng, K. E. Khosla, C. N. Self, M. Lin, B. X. Li, A. C. Medina, M. S. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an initialisation method for variational quantum algorithms applicable to intermediate scale quantum computers. The method uses simulated annealing of the efficiently simulable Clifford parameter points as a pre-optimisation to find a low energy initial condition. We numerically demonstrate the effectiveness of the technique, and how it depends on Hamiltonian structure, number of qubits and circuit depth. While a range of different problems are considered, we note that the method is particularly useful for quantum chemistry problems. This presented method could help achieve a quantum advantage in noisy or fault-tolerant intermediate scale devices, even though we prove in general that the method is not arbitrarily scalable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning Quantum Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.00298</link>
    <author>Valentin Gebhart, Raffaele Santagati, Antonio Andrea Gentile, Erik Gauger, David Craig, Natalia Ares, Leonardo Banchi, Florian Marquardt, Luca Pezze', Cristian Bonato</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum technologies hold the promise to revolutionise our society with ground-breaking applications in secure communication, high-performance computing and ultra-precise sensing. One of the main features in scaling up quantum technologies is that the complexity of quantum systems scales exponentially with their size. This poses severe challenges in the efficient calibration, benchmarking and validation of quantum states and their dynamical control. While the complete simulation of large-scale quantum systems may only be possible with a quantum computer, classical characterisation and optimisation methods (supported by cutting edge numerical techniques) can still play an important role. Here, we review classical approaches to learning quantum systems, their correlation properties, their dynamics and their interaction with the environment. We discuss theoretical proposals and successful implementations in different physical platforms such as spin qubits, trapped ions, photonic and atomic systems, and superconducting circuits. This review provides a brief background for key concepts recurring across many of these approaches, such as the Bayesian formalism or Neural Networks, and outlines open questions.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>