<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The randomized measurement toolbox</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11374</link>
    <author>Andreas Elben, Steven T. Flammia, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, John Preskill, Benoît Vermersch, Peter Zoller</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Increasingly sophisticated programmable quantum simulators and quantum computers are opening unprecedented opportunities for exploring and exploiting the properties of highly entangled complex quantum systems. The complexity of large quantum systems is the source of their power, but also makes them difficult to control precisely or characterize accurately using measured classical data. We review recently developed protocols for probing the properties of complex many-qubit systems using measurement schemes that are practical using today's quantum platforms. In all these protocols, a quantum state is repeatedly prepared and measured in a randomly chosen basis; then a classical computer processes the measurement outcomes to estimate the desired property. The randomization of the measurement procedure has distinct advantages; for example, a single data set can be employed multiple times to pursue a variety of applications, and imperfections in the measurements are mapped to a simplified noise model that can more easily be mitigated. We discuss a range of use cases that have already been realized in quantum devices, including Hamiltonian simulation tasks, probes of quantum chaos, measurements of nonlocal order parameters, and comparison of quantum states produced in distantly separated laboratories. By providing a workable method for translating a complex quantum state into a succinct classical representation that preserves a rich variety of relevant physical properties, the randomized measurement toolbox strengthens our ability to grasp and control the quantum world.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-enhanced Markov chain Monte Carlo</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.12497</link>
    <author>David Layden, Guglielmo Mazzola, Ryan V. Mishmash, Mario Motta, Pawel Wocjan, Jin-Sung Kim, Sarah Sheldon</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Sampling from complicated probability distributions is a hard computational problem arising in many fields, including statistical physics, optimization, and machine learning. Quantum computers have recently been used to sample from complicated distributions that are hard to sample from classically, but which seldom arise in applications. Here we introduce a quantum algorithm to sample from distributions that pose a bottleneck in several applications, which we implement on a superconducting quantum processor. The algorithm performs Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC), a popular iterative sampling technique, to sample from the Boltzmann distribution of classical Ising models. In each step, the quantum processor explores the model in superposition to propose a random move, which is then accepted or rejected by a classical computer and returned to the quantum processor, ensuring convergence to the desired Boltzmann distribution. We find that this quantum algorithm converges in fewer iterations than common classical MCMC alternatives on relevant problem instances, both in simulations and experiments. It therefore opens a new path for quantum computers to solve useful--not merely difficult--problems in the near term.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Looped Pipelines Enabling Effective 3D Qubit Lattices in a Strictly 2D Device</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13123</link>
    <author>Zhenyu Cai, Adam Siegel, Simon Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many quantum computing platforms are based on a fundamentally two-dimensional physical layout. However, there are advantages (for example in fault-tolerant systems) to having a 3D architecture. Here we explore a concept called looped pipelines which permits one to obtain many of the advantages of a 3D lattice while operating a strictly 2D device. The concept leverages qubit shuttling, a well-established feature in platforms like semiconductor spin qubits and trapped-ion qubits. The looped pipeline architecture has similar hardware requirements to other shuttling approaches, but can process a stack of qubit arrays instead of just one. Simple patterns of intra- and inter-loop interactions allow one to embody diverse schemes from NISQ-era error mitigation through to fault-tolerant codes. For the former, protocols involving multiple states can be implemented with a similar space-time resource as preparing one noisy copy. For the latter, one can realise a far broader variety of code structures; in particular, we consider a stack of 2D codes within which transversal CNOTs are available. We find that this can achieve a cost saving of up to a factor of $\sim 80$ in the space-time overhead for magic state distillation (and a factor of $\sim 200$ with modest additional hardware). Using numerical modelling and experimentally-motivated noise models we verify that the looped pipeline approach provides these benefits without significant reduction in the code's threshold.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fractionalization of subsystem symmetries in two dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13244</link>
    <author>David T. Stephen, Arpit Dua, José Garre-Rubio, Dominic J. Williamson, Michael Hermele</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The fractionalization of global symmetry charges is a striking hallmark of topological quantum order. Here, we discuss the fractionalization of subsystem symmetries in two-dimensional topological phases. In line with previous no-go arguments, we show that subsystem symmetry fractionalization is not possible in many cases due to the additional rigid geometric structure of the symmetries. However, we identify a new mechanism that allows fractionalization, involving global relations between macroscopically many symmetry generators. We find that anyons can fractionalize such relations, meaning that the total charge carried under all generators involved in the global relation is non-trivial, despite the fact that these generators multiply to the identity. We first discuss the general algebraic framework needed to characterize this new type of fractionalization, and then explore this framework using a number of exactly solvable models with $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topological order, including models having line and fractal symmetries. These models all showcase another necessary property of subsystem symmetry fractionalization: fractionalized anyons must have restricted mobility when the symmetry is enforced, such that they are confined to a single line or point in the case of line and fractal symmetries, respectively. Looking forward, we expect that our identification of the importance of global relations in fractionalization will hold significance for the classification of phases with subsystem symmetries in all dimensions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Randomized Benchmarking Beyond Groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.12703</link>
    <author>Jianxin Chen, Dawei Ding, Cupjin Huang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Randomized benchmarking (RB) is the gold standard for experimentally evaluating the quality of quantum operations. The current framework for RB is centered on groups and their representations, but this can be problematic. For example, Clifford circuits need up to $O(n^2)$ gates, and thus Clifford RB cannot scale to larger devices. Attempts to remedy this include new schemes such as linear cross-entropy benchmarking (XEB), cycle benchmarking, and non-uniform RB, but they do not fall within the group-based RB framework. In this work, we formulate the universal randomized benchmarking (URB) framework which does away with the group structure and also replaces the recovery gate plus measurement component with a general "post-processing" POVM. Not only does this framework cover most of the existing benchmarking schemes, but it also gives the language for and helps inspire the formulation of new schemes. We specifically consider a class of URB schemes called twirling schemes. For twirling schemes, the post-processing POVM approximately factorizes into an intermediate channel, inverting maps, and a final measurement. This leads us to study the twirling map corresponding to the gate ensemble specified by the scheme. We prove that if this twirling map is strictly within unit distance of the Haar twirling map in induced diamond norm, the probability of measurement as a function of gate length is a single exponential decay up to small error terms. The core technical tool we use is the matrix perturbation theory of linear operators on quantum channels.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>High Dimensional Quantum Learning With Small Quantum Computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13739</link>
    <author>Simon C. Marshall, Casper Gyurik, Vedran Dunjko</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers hold great promise to enhance machine learning, but their current qubit counts restrict the realisation of this promise. In an attempt to placate this limitation techniques can be applied for evaluating a quantum circuit using a machine with fewer qubits than the circuit naively requires. These techniques work by evaluating many smaller circuits on the smaller machine, that are then combined in a polynomial to replicate the output of the larger machine. This scheme requires more circuit evaluations than are practical for general circuits. However, we investigate the possibility that for certain applications many of these subcircuits are superfluous, and that a much smaller sum is sufficient to estimate the full circuit. We construct a machine learning model that may be capable of approximating the outputs of the larger circuit with much fewer circuit evaluations. We successfully apply our model to the task of digit recognition, using simulated quantum computers much smaller than the data dimension. The model is also applied to the task of approximating a random 10 qubit PQC with simulated access to a 5 qubit computer, even with only relatively modest number of circuits our model provides an accurate approximation of the 10 qubit PQCs output, superior to a neural network attempt. The developed method might be useful for implementing quantum models on larger data throughout the NISQ era.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The power of qutrits for non-adaptive measurement-based quantum computing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.12411</link>
    <author>Jelena Mackeprang, Daniel Bhatti, Matty J. Hoban, Stefanie Barz</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Non-locality is not only one of the most prominent quantum features but can also serve as a resource for various information-theoretical tasks. Analysing it from an information-theoretical perspective has linked it to applications such as non-adaptive measurement-based quantum computing (NMQC). In this type of quantum computing the goal is to output a multivariate function. The success of such a computation can be related to the violation of a generalised Bell inequality. So far, the investigation of binary NMQC with qubits has shown that quantum correlations can compute all Boolean functions using at most $2^n-1$ qubits, whereas local hidden variables (LHVs) are restricted to linear functions. Here, we extend these results to NMQC with qutrits and prove that quantum correlations enable the computation of all ternary functions using the generalised qutrit Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) state as a resource and at most $3^n-1$ qutrits. This yields a corresponding generalised GHZ type paradox for any ternary function that LHVs cannot compute. We give an example for an $n$-variate function that can be computed with only $n+1$ qutrits, which leads to convenient generalised qutrit Bell inequalities whose quantum bound is maximal. Finally, we prove that not all functions can be computed efficiently with qutrit NMQC by presenting a counterexample.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New Quantum Algorithms for Computing Quantum Entropies and Distances</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13522</link>
    <author>Qisheng Wang, Ji Guan, Junyi Liu, Zhicheng Zhang, Mingsheng Ying</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a series of quantum algorithms for computing a wide range of quantum entropies and distances, including the von Neumann entropy, quantum Rényi entropy, trace distance, and fidelity. The proposed algorithms significantly outperform the best known (and even quantum) ones in the low-rank case, some of which achieve exponential speedups. In particular, for $N$-dimensional quantum states of rank $r$, our proposed quantum algorithms for computing the von Neumann entropy, trace distance and fidelity within additive error $\varepsilon$ have time complexity of $\tilde O(r^2/\varepsilon^2)$, $\tilde O(r^5/\varepsilon^6)$ and $\tilde O(r^{6.5}/\varepsilon^{7.5})$, respectively. In contrast, the known algorithms for the von Neumann entropy and trace distance require quantum time complexity of $\Omega(N)$ [AISW19,GL20,GHS21], and the best known one for fidelity requires $\tilde O(r^{21.5}/\varepsilon^{23.5})$ [WZC+21]. The key idea of our quantum algorithms is to extend block-encoding from unitary operators in previous work to quantum states (i.e., density operators). It is realized by developing several convenient techniques to manipulate quantum states and extract information from them. In particular, we introduce a novel technique for eigenvalue transformation of density operators and their (non-integer) positive powers, based on the powerful quantum singular value transformation (QSVT) [GSLW19]. The advantage of our techniques over the existing methods is that no restrictions on density operators are required; in sharp contrast, the previous methods usually require a lower bound of the minimal non-zero eigenvalue of density operators. In addition, we provide some techniques of independent interest for trace estimation, linear combinations, and eigenvalue threshold projectors of (subnormalized) density operators, which will be, we believe, useful in other quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive variational algorithms for quantum Gibbs state preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.12757</link>
    <author>Ada Warren, Linghua Zhu, Nicholas J. Mayhall, Edwin Barnes, Sophia E. Economou</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The preparation of Gibbs thermal states is an important task in quantum computation with applications in quantum simulation, quantum optimization, and quantum machine learning. However, many algorithms for preparing Gibbs states rely on quantum subroutines which are difficult to implement on near-term hardware. Here, we address this by (i) introducing an objective function that, unlike the free energy, is easily measured, and (ii) using dynamically generated, problem-tailored ansätze. This allows for arbitrarily accurate Gibbs state preparation using low-depth circuits. To verify the effectiveness of our approach, we numerically demonstrate that our algorithm can prepare high-fidelity Gibbs states across a broad range of temperatures and for a variety of Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum dynamics is not strictly bidivisible</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.13451</link>
    <author>David Davalos, Mario Ziman</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We address the question of the existence of quantum channels that are divisible in two quantum channels but not in three, or more generally channels divisible in $n$ but not in $n+1$ parts. We show that for the qubit, those channels \textitdo not exist, whereas for general finite-dimensional quantum channels the same holds at least for full Kraus rank channels. To prove these results we introduce a novel decomposition of quantum channels which separates them in a boundary and Markovian part, and it holds for any finite dimension. Additionally, the introduced decomposition amounts to the well known connection between divisibility classes and implementation types of quantum dynamical maps.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>