<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Non-Pauli Errors in the Three-Dimensional Surface Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05746</link>
    <author>Thomas R. Scruby, Michael Vasmer, Dan E. Browne</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A powerful feature of stabiliser error correcting codes is the fact that stabiliser measurement projects arbitrary errors to Pauli errors, greatly simplifying the physical error correction process as well as classical simulations of code performance. However, logical non-Clifford operations can map Pauli errors to non-Pauli (Clifford) errors, and while subsequent stabiliser measurements will project the Clifford errors back to Pauli errors the resulting distributions will possess additional correlations that depend on both the nature of the logical operation and the structure of the code. Previous work has studied these effects when applying a transversal $T$ gate to the three-dimensional colour code and shown the existence of a non-local "linking charge" phenomenon between membranes of intersecting errors. In this work we generalise these results to the case of a $CCZ$ gate in the three-dimensional surface code and find that many aspects of the problem are much more easily understood in this setting. In particular, the emergence of linking charge is a local effect rather than a non-local one. We use the relative simplicity of Clifford errors in this setting to simulate their effect on the performance of a single-shot magic state preparation process (the first such simulation to account for the full effect of these errors) and find that while they lead to an increase in the logical error rate their effect on the threshold is minimal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An exact quantum hidden subgroup algorithm and applications to solvable groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04047</link>
    <author>Muhammad Imran, Gabor Ivanyos</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a polynomial time exact quantum algorithm for the hidden subgroup problem in $Z_{m^k}^n$. The algorithm uses the quantum Fourier transform modulo m and does not require factorization of m. For smooth m, i.e., when the prime factors of m are of size poly(log m), the quantum Fourier transform can be exactly computed using the method discovered independently by Cleve and Coppersmith, while for general m, the algorithm of Mosca and Zalka is available. Even for m=3 and k=1 our result appears to be new. We also present applications to compute the structure of abelian and solvable groups whose order has the same (but possibly unknown) prime factors as m. The applications for solvable groups also rely on an exact version of a technique proposed by Watrous for computing the uniform superposition of elements of subgroups.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Counting unitaries of T-depth one</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04163</link>
    <author>Vadym Kliuchnikov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits is $ \sum_{m=1}^{n}\tfrac{1}{m!}\prod_{k=0}^{m-1}(4^n/2^k - 2^k) \times \# \mathcal{C}_n, $ where $\#\mathcal{C}_n$ is the size of the $n$-qubit Clifford group, that is the number of unitaries of T-depth zero. The number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits grows as $2^{\Omega(n^2)} \cdot \# \mathcal{C}_n$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement estimation in tensor network states via sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04089</link>
    <author>Noa Feldman, Augustine Kshetrimayum, Jens Eisert, Moshe Goldstein</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a method for extracting meaningful entanglement measures of tensor network states in general dimensions. Current methods require the explicit reconstruction of the density matrix, which is highly demanding, or the contraction of replicas, which requires an effort exponential in the number of replicas and which is costly in terms of memory. In contrast, our method requires the stochastic sampling of matrix elements of the classically represented reduced states with respect to random states drawn from simple product probability measures constituting frames. Even though not corresponding to physical operations, such matrix elements are straightforward to calculate for tensor network states, and their moments provide the Rényi entropies and negativities as well as their symmetry-resolved components. We test our method on the one-dimensional critical XX chain and the two-dimensional toric code. Although the cost is exponential in the subsystem size, it is sufficiently moderate so that - in contrast with other approaches - accurate results can be obtained on a personal computer for relatively large subsystem sizes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Three-dimensional quantum cellular automata from chiral semion surface topological order and beyond</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05442</link>
    <author>Wilbur Shirley, Yu-An Chen, Arpit Dua, Tyler D. Ellison, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Dominic J. Williamson</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We construct a novel three-dimensional quantum cellular automaton (QCA) based on a system with short-range entangled bulk and chiral semion boundary topological order. We argue that either the QCA is nontrivial, i.e. not a finite-depth circuit of local quantum gates, or there exists a two-dimensional commuting projector Hamiltonian realizing the chiral semion topological order (characterized by $U(1)_2$ Chern-Simons theory). Our QCA is obtained by first constructing the Walker-Wang Hamiltonian of a certain premodular tensor category of order four, then condensing the deconfined bulk boson at the level of lattice operators. We show that the resulting Hamiltonian hosts chiral semion surface topological order in the presence of a boundary and can be realized as a non-Pauli stabilizer code on qubits, from which the QCA is defined. The construction is then generalized to a class of QCAs defined by non-Pauli stabilizer codes on ${2^n}$-dimensional qudits that feature surface anyons described by $U(1)_{2^n}$ Chern-Simons theory. Our results support the conjecture that the group of nontrivial three-dimensional QCAs is isomorphic to the Witt group of non-degenerate braided fusion categories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matrix concentration inequalities and efficiency of random universal sets of quantum gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05371</link>
    <author>Piotr Dulian, Adam Sawicki</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For a random set $\mathcal{S}$ of quantum gates we provide bounds on the probability that $\mathcal{S}$ forms a $\delta$-approximate $t$-design. In particular we show how many random gates are needed to have a $\delta$-approximate $t$-design with high probability. We also analyze how $\delta$ concentrates around its expected value $\mathbb{E}\delta$ for random $\mathcal{S}$. Our results are valid for both symmetric and non-symmetric sets of gates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Neural-Network Decoders for Quantum Error Correction using Surface Codes:A Space Exploration of the Hardware Cost-Performance Trade-Offs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05741</link>
    <author>Ramon Overwater, Masoud Babaie, Fabio Sebastiano</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Error Correction (QEC) is required in quantum computers to mitigate the effect of errors on physical qubits. When adopting a QEC scheme based on surface codes, error decoding is the most computationally expensive task in the classical electronic back-end. Decoders employing neural networks (NN) are well-suited for this task but their hardware implementation has not been presented yet. This work presents a space exploration of fully-connected feed-forward NN decoders for small distance surface codes. The goal is to optimize the neural network for high decoding performance, while keeping a minimalistic hardware implementation. This is needed to meet the tight delay constraints of real-time surface code decoding. We demonstrate that hardware based NN-decoders can achieve high decoding performance comparable to other state-of-the-art decoding algorithms whilst being well below the tight delay requirements $(\approx 440\ \mathrm{ns})$ of current solid-state qubit technologies for both ASIC designs $(<30\ \mathrm{ns})$ and FPGA implementations $(<90\ \mathrm{ns})$. These results designates NN-decoders as fitting candidates for an integrated hardware implementation in future large-scale quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement catalysis for quantum states and noisy channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05228</link>
    <author>Chandan Datta, Tulja Varun Kondra, Marek Miller, Alexander Streltsov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many applications of the emerging quantum technologies, such as quantum teleportation and quantum key distribution, require singlets, maximally entangled states of two quantum bits. It is thus of utmost importance to develop optimal procedures for establishing singlets between remote parties. As has been shown very recently, singlets can be obtained from other quantum states by using a quantum catalyst, an entangled quantum system which is not changed in the procedure. In this work we put this idea further, investigating properties of entanglement catalysis and its role for quantum communication. For transformations between bipartite pure states we prove the existence of a universal catalyst, which can enable all possible transformations in this setup. We demonstrate the advantage of catalysis in asymptotic settings, going beyond the typical assumption of independent and identically distributed systems. We further develop methods to estimate the number of singlets which can be established via a noisy quantum channel when assisted by entangled catalysts. For various types of quantum channels our results lead to optimal protocols, allowing to establish the maximal number of singlets with a single use of the channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal logic with encoded spin qubits in silicon</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03605</link>
    <author>Aaron J. Weinstein, Matthew D. Reed, Aaron M. Jones, Reed W. Andrews, David Barnes, Jacob Z. Blumoff, Larken E. Euliss, Kevin Eng, Bryan Fong, Sieu D. Ha, Daniel R. Hulbert, Clayton Jackson, Michael Jura, Tyler E. Keating, Joseph Kerckhoff, Andrey A. Kiselev, Justine Matten, Golam Sabbir, Aaron Smith, Jeffrey Wright, et al (3)</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Qubits encoded in a decoherence-free subsystem and realized in exchange-coupled silicon quantum dots are promising candidates for fault-tolerant quantum computing. Benefits of this approach include excellent coherence, low control crosstalk, and configurable insensitivity to certain error sources. Key difficulties are that encoded entangling gates require a large number of control pulses and high-yielding quantum dot arrays. Here we show a device made using the single-layer etch-defined gate electrode architecture that achieves both the required functional yield needed for full control and the coherence necessary for thousands of calibrated exchange pulses to be applied. We measure an average two-qubit Clifford fidelity of $97.1 \pm 0.2\%$ with randomized benchmarking. We also use interleaved randomized benchmarking to demonstrate the controlled-NOT gate with $96.3 \pm 0.7\%$ fidelity, SWAP with $99.3 \pm 0.5\%$ fidelity, and a specialized entangling gate that limits spreading of leakage with $93.8 \pm 0.7\%$ fidelity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying information scrambling via Classical Shadow Tomography on Programmable Quantum Simulators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05132</link>
    <author>Max McGinley, Sebastian Leontica, Samuel J. Garratt, Jovan Jovanovic, Steven H. Simon</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop techniques to probe the dynamics of quantum information, and implement them experimentally on an IBM superconducting quantum processor. Our protocols adapt shadow tomography for the study of time evolution channels rather than of quantum states, and rely only on single-qubit operations and measurements. We identify two unambiguous signatures of quantum information scrambling, neither of which can be mimicked by dissipative processes, and relate these to many-body teleportation. By realizing quantum chaotic dynamics in experiment, we measure both signatures, and support our results with numerical simulations of the quantum system. We additionally investigate operator growth under this dynamics, and observe behaviour characteristic of quantum chaos. As our methods require only a single quantum state at a time, they can be readily applied on a wide variety of quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>