<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Learning many-body Hamiltonians with Heisenberg-limited scaling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03030</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Yu Tong, Di Fang, Yuan Su</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Learning a many-body Hamiltonian from its dynamics is a fundamental problem in physics. In this work, we propose the first algorithm to achieve the Heisenberg limit for learning an interacting $N$-qubit local Hamiltonian. After a total evolution time of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-1})$, the proposed algorithm can efficiently estimate any parameter in the $N$-qubit Hamiltonian to $\epsilon$-error with high probability. The proposed algorithm is robust against state preparation and measurement error, does not require eigenstates or thermal states, and only uses $\mathrm{polylog}(\epsilon^{-1})$ experiments. In contrast, the best previous algorithms, such as recent works using gradient-based optimization or polynomial interpolation, require a total evolution time of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ and $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ experiments. Our algorithm uses ideas from quantum simulation to decouple the unknown $N$-qubit Hamiltonian $H$ into noninteracting patches, and learns $H$ using a quantum-enhanced divide-and-conquer approach. We prove a matching lower bound to establish the asymptotic optimality of our algorithm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from classical LTCs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02999</link>
    <author>Zhiyang He, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide a completely self-contained construction of a family of NLTS Hamiltonians [Freedman and Hastings, 2014] based on ideas from [Anshu, Breuckmann, and Nirkhe, 2022], [Cross, He, Natarajan, Szegedy, and Zhu, 2022] and [Eldar and Harrow, 2017]. Crucially, it does not require optimal-parameter quantum LDPC codes and can be built from simple classical LTCs such as the repetition code on an expander graph. Furthermore, it removes the constant-rate requirement from the construction of Anshu, Breuckmann, and Nirkhe.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Floquet codes without parent subsystem codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02468</link>
    <author>Margarita Davydova, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Shankar Balasubramanian</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a new class of error-correcting dynamic codes in two and three dimensions that has no explicit connection to any parent subsystem code. The two-dimensional code, which we call the CSS Floquet code, is geometrically similar to that of the honeycomb code by Hastings and Haah, and also dynamically embeds an instantaneous toric code. However, unlike the honeycomb code it possesses an explicit CSS structure and its gauge checks do not form a subsystem code. Nevertheless, we show that our dynamic protocol conserves logical information and possesses a threshold for error correction. We generalize this construction to three dimensions and obtain a code that fault-tolerantly alternates between realizing two type-I fracton models, the checkerboard and the X-cube model. Finally, we show the compatibility of our CSS Floquet code protocol and the honeycomb code by showing the possibility of randomly switching between the two protocols without information loss while still measuring error syndromes. We call this more general aperiodic structure `dynamic tree codes', which we also generalize to three dimensions. Under a certain correlated randomness constraint, this code is error correcting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A perturbative gadget for delaying the onset of barren plateaus in variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03099</link>
    <author>Simon Cichy, Paul K. Faehrmann, Sumeet Khatri, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms are being explored as a promising approach to finding useful applications for noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers. However, cost functions corresponding to many problems of interest are inherently global, defined by Hamiltonians with many-body interactions. Consequently, the optimization landscape can exhibit exponentially vanishing gradients, so-called barren plateaus, rendering optimal solutions difficult to find. Strategies for mitigating barren plateaus are therefore needed to make variational quantum algorithms trainable and capable of running on larger-scale quantum devices. In this work, we contribute the toolbox of perturbative gadgets to the portfolio of methods being explored in the quest for making noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices useful. Specifically, we introduce a novel perturbative gadget, tailored to variational quantum algorithms, that can be used to avoid barren plateaus. Our perturbative gadget encodes an arbitrary many-body Hamiltonian corresponding to a global cost function into the low-energy subspace of a three-body Hamiltonian. Our construction requires $rk$ additional qubits for a $k$-body Hamiltonian comprising $r$ terms. We provide rigorous guarantees on the optimization of the local cost function defined by our three-body gadget Hamiltonian with respect to the original cost function, and we prove that this local cost function exhibits non-vanishing gradients, thus delaying the onset of barren plateaus. We then provide numerical demonstrations to show the functioning of our approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum state tomography via non-convex Riemannian gradient descent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.04717</link>
    <author>Ming-Chien Hsu, En-Jui Kuo, Wei-Hsuan Yu, Jian-Feng Cai, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recovery of an unknown density matrix of large size requires huge computational resources. The recent Factored Gradient Descent (FGD) algorithm and its variants achieved state-of-the-art performance since they could mitigate the dimensionality barrier by utilizing some of the underlying structures of the density matrix. Despite their theoretical guarantee of a linear convergence rate, the convergence in practical scenarios is still slow because the contracting factor of the FGD algorithms depends on the condition number $\kappa$ of the ground truth state. Consequently, the total number of iterations can be as large as $O(\sqrt{\kappa}\ln(\frac{1}{\varepsilon}))$ to achieve the estimation error $\varepsilon$. In this work, we derive a quantum state tomography scheme that improves the dependence on $\kappa$ to the logarithmic scale; namely, our algorithm could achieve the approximation error $\varepsilon$ in $O(\ln(\frac{1}{\kappa\varepsilon}))$ steps. The improvement comes from the application of the non-convex Riemannian gradient descent (RGD). The contracting factor in our approach is thus a universal constant that is independent of the given state. Our theoretical results of extremely fast convergence and nearly optimal error bounds are corroborated by numerical results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>One-Wayness in Quantum Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03394</link>
    <author>Tomoyuki Morimae, Takashi Yamakawa</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The existence of one-way functions is one of the most fundamental assumptions in classical cryptography. In the quantum world, on the other hand, there are evidences that some cryptographic primitives can exist even if one-way functions do not exist. We therefore have the following important open problem in quantum cryptography: What is the most fundamental element in quantum cryptography? In this direction, Brakerski, Canetti, and Qian recently defined a notion called EFI pairs, which are pairs of efficiently generatable states that are statistically distinguishable but computationally indistinguishable, and showed its equivalence with some cryptographic primitives including commitments, oblivious transfer, and general multi-party computations. However, their work focuses on decision-type primitives and does not cover search-type primitives like quantum money and digital signatures. In this paper, we study properties of one-way state generators (OWSGs), which are a quantum analogue of one-way functions. We first revisit the definition of OWSGs and generalize it by allowing mixed output states. Then we show the following results. (1) We define a weaker version of OWSGs, weak OWSGs, and show that they are equivalent to OWSGs. (2) Quantum digital signatures are equivalent to OWSGs. (3) Private-key quantum money schemes (with pure money states) imply OWSGs. (4) Quantum pseudo one-time pad schemes imply both OWSGs and EFI pairs. (5) We introduce an incomparable variant of OWSGs, which we call secretly-verifiable and statistically-invertible OWSGs, and show that they are equivalent to EFI pairs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hello Quantum World! A rigorous but accessible first-year university course in quantum information science</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02868</link>
    <author>Sophia E. Economou, Edwin Barnes</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Addressing workforce shortages within the Quantum Information Science and Engineering (QISE) community requires attracting and retaining students from diverse backgrounds early on in their undergraduate education. Here, we describe a course we developed called Hello Quantum World! that introduces a broad range of fundamental quantum information and computation concepts in a rigorous way but without requiring any knowledge of mathematics beyond high-school algebra nor any prior knowledge of quantum mechanics. Some of the topics covered include superposition, entanglement, quantum gates, teleportation, quantum algorithms, and quantum error correction. The course is designed for first-year undergraduate students, both those pursuing a degree in QISE and those who are seeking to be `quantum-aware'.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-tolerant Coding for Entanglement-Assisted Communication</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02939</link>
    <author>Paula Belzig, Matthias Christandl, Alexander Müller-Hermes</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Channel capacities quantify the optimal rates of sending information reliably over noisy channels. Usually, the study of capacities assumes that the circuits which sender and receiver use for encoding and decoding consist of perfectly noiseless gates. In the case of communication over quantum channels, however, this assumption is widely believed to be unrealistic, even in the long-term, due to the fragility of quantum information, which is affected by the process of decoherence. Christandl and Müller-Hermes have therefore initiated the study of fault-tolerant channel coding for quantum channels, i.e. coding schemes where encoder and decoder circuits are affected by noise, and have used techniques from fault-tolerant quantum computing to establish coding theorems for sending classical and quantum information in this scenario. Here, we extend these methods to the case of entanglement-assisted communication, in particular proving that the fault-tolerant capacity approaches the usual capacity when the gate error approaches zero. A main tool, which might be of independent interest, is the introduction of fault-tolerant entanglement distillation. We furthermore focus on the modularity of the techniques used, so that they can be easily adopted in other fault-tolerant communication scenarios.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Computation for Periodic Solids in Second Quantization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02403</link>
    <author>Aleksei V. Ivanov, Christoph Sünderhauf, Nicole Holzmann, Tom Ellaby, Rachel N. Kerber, Glenn Jones, Joan Camps</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work, we present a quantum algorithm for ground-state energy calculations of periodic solids on error-corrected quantum computers. The algorithm is based on the sparse qubitization approach in second quantization and developed for Bloch and Wannier basis sets. We show that Wannier functions require less computational resources with respect to Bloch functions because: (i) the L$_1$ norm of the Hamiltonian is considerably lower and (ii) the translational symmetry of Wannier functions can be exploited in order to reduce the amount of classical data that must be loaded into the quantum computer. The resource requirements of the quantum algorithm are estimated for periodic solids such as NiO and PdO. These transition metal oxides are industrially relevant for their catalytic properties. We find that ground-state energy estimation of Hamiltonians approximated using 200--900 spin orbitals requires \it ca.~$10{}^{10}$--$10^{12}$ T gates and up to $3\cdot10^8$ physical qubits for a physical error rate of $0.1\%$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal Quantum Speedup for Branch-and-Bound, Branch-and-Cut, and Tree-Search Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03210</link>
    <author>Shouvanik Chakrabarti, Pierre Minssen, Romina Yalovetzky, Marco Pistoia</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Mixed Integer Programs (MIPs) model many optimization problems of interest in Computer Science, Operations Research, and Financial Engineering. Solving MIPs is NP-Hard in general, but several solvers have found success in obtaining near-optimal solutions for problems of intermediate size. Branch-and-Cut algorithms, which combine Branch-and-Bound logic with cutting-plane routines, are at the core of modern MIP solvers. Montanaro proposed a quantum algorithm with a near-quadratic speedup compared to classical Branch-and-Bound algorithms in the worst case, when every optimal solution is desired. In practice, however, a near-optimal solution is satisfactory, and by leveraging tree-search heuristics to search only a portion of the solution tree, classical algorithms can perform much better than the worst-case guarantee. In this paper, we propose a quantum algorithm, Incremental-Quantum-Branch-and-Bound, with universal near-quadratic speedup over classical Branch-and-Bound algorithms for every input, i.e., if classical Branch-and-Bound has complexity $Q$ on an instance that leads to solution depth $d$, Incremental-Quantum-Branch-and-Bound offers the same guarantees with a complexity of $\tilde{O}(\sqrt{Q}d)$. Our results are valid for a wide variety of search heuristics, including depth-based, cost-based, and $A^{\ast}$ heuristics. Universal speedups are also obtained for Branch-and-Cut as well as heuristic tree search. Our algorithms are directly comparable to commercial MIP solvers, and guarantee near quadratic speedup whenever $Q \gg d$. We use numerical simulation to verify that $Q \gg d$ for typical instances of the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model, Maximum Independent Set, and Portfolio Optimization; as well as to extrapolate the dependence of $Q$ on input size parameters. This allows us to project the typical performance of our quantum algorithms for these important problems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>