<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure qubits: Overcoming the $T_1$ limit in superconducting circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05461</link>
    <author>Aleksander Kubica, Arbel Haim, Yotam Vaknin, Fernando Brandão, Alex Retzker</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The amplitude damping time, $T_1$, has long stood as the major factor limiting quantum fidelity in superconducting circuits, prompting concerted efforts in the material science and design of qubits aimed at increasing $T_1$. In contrast, the dephasing time, $T_{\phi}$, can usually be extended above $T_1$ (via, e.g., dynamical decoupling), to the point where it does not limit fidelity. In this article we propose a scheme for overcoming the conventional $T_1$ limit on fidelity by designing qubits in a way that amplitude damping errors can be detected and converted into erasure errors. Compared to standard qubit implementations our scheme improves the performance of fault-tolerant protocols, as numerically demonstrated by the circuit-noise simulations of the surface code. We describe two simple qubit implementations with superconducting circuits and discuss procedures for detecting amplitude damping errors, performing entangling gates, and extending $T_\phi$. Our results suggest that engineering efforts should focus on improving $T_\phi$ and the quality of quantum coherent control, as they effectively become the limiting factor on the performance of fault-tolerant protocols.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A local pre-decoder to reduce the bandwidth and latency of quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04660</link>
    <author>Samuel C. Smith, Benjamin J. Brown, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A fault-tolerant quantum computer will be supported by a classical decoding system interfacing with quantum hardware to perform quantum error correction. It is important that the decoder can keep pace with the quantum clock speed, within the limitations on communication that are imposed by the physical architecture. To this end we propose a local `pre-decoder', which makes greedy corrections to reduce the amount of syndrome data sent to a standard matching decoder. We study these classical overheads for the surface code under a phenomenological phase-flip noise model with imperfect measurements. We find substantial improvements in the runtime of the global decoder and the communication bandwidth by using the pre-decoder. For instance, to achieve a logical failure probability of $f = 10^{-15}$ using qubits with physical error rate $p = 10^{-3}$ and a distance $d=22$ code, we find that the bandwidth cost is reduced by a factor of $1000$, and the time taken by a matching decoder is sped up by a factor of $200$. To achieve this target failure probability, the pre-decoding approach requires a $50\%$ increase in the qubit count compared with the optimal decoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise-resilient phase estimation with randomized compiling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04100</link>
    <author>Yanwu Gu, Yunheng Ma, Nicolo Forcellini, Dong E. Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop an error mitigation method for the control-free phase estimation. We prove a theorem that under the first-order correction, the noise channels with only Hermitian Kraus operators do not change the phases of a unitary operator, and therefore, the benign types of noise for phase estimation are identified. By using the randomized compiling protocol, we can convert the generic noise in the phase estimation circuits into stochastic Pauli noise, which satisfies the condition of our theorem. Thus we achieve a noise-resilient phase estimation without any quantum resource overhead. The simulated experiments show that our method can significantly reduce the estimation error of the phases by up to two orders of magnitude. Our method paves the way for the utilization of quantum phase estimation before the advent of fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New Quantum Codes from CSS Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05353</link>
    <author>Markus Grassl</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a new propagation rule for CSS codes. Starting with a CSS code $[\![n,k,d]\!]_q$, we construct a CSS code with parameters $[\![n-2,k,d-1]\!]_q$. In general, one would only obtain a code with parameters $[\![n-2,k,d-2]\!]_q$. The construction applies to asymmetric quantum codes from the CSS construction as well.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Glasses -- a review</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05417</link>
    <author>L. F. Cugliandolo, M. Mueller</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We review the research on quantum glasses, with a focus on their equilibrium dynamics and the interplay between glassiness and localization phenomena. Interesting relations with the SYK model are discussed.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning for Quantum Technologies</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.03836</link>
    <author>Mario Krenn, Jonas Landgraf, Thomas Foesel, Florian Marquardt</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In recent years, the dramatic progress in machine learning has begun to impact many areas of science and technology significantly. In the present perspective article, we explore how quantum technologies are benefiting from this revolution. We showcase in illustrative examples how scientists in the past few years have started to use machine learning and more broadly methods of artificial intelligence to analyze quantum measurements, estimate the parameters of quantum devices, discover new quantum experimental setups, protocols, and feedback strategies, and generally improve aspects of quantum computing, quantum communication, and quantum simulation. We highlight open challenges and future possibilities and conclude with some speculative visions for the next decade.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Role of Quantum Communication and Loss in Attacks on Quantum Position Verification</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04341</link>
    <author>Rene Allerstorfer, Harry Buhrman, Florian Speelman, Philip Verduyn Lunel</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the role of quantum communication in attacks on quantum position verification. In this work, we construct the first known example of a QPV protocol that is provably secure against unentangled attackers restricted to classical communication, but can be perfectly attacked by local operations and a single round of simultaneous quantum communication indicating that allowing for quantum communication may break security. We also show that any protocol secure against classical communication can be transformed into a protocol secure against quantum communication. We further show, using arguments based on the monogamy of entanglement, that the task of Bell state discrimination cannot be done locally with a single round of quantum communication, not even probabilistically (when we allow attackers to say loss sometimes), making this the first fully loss-tolerant QPV task secure against quantum communication attacks. Finally, we observe that any multi-round QPV protocol can be attacked with a linear amount of entanglement if the loss is high enough.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reconstructing complex states of a 20-qubit quantum simulator</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04862</link>
    <author>Murali K. Kurmapu, V.V. Tiunova, E.S. Tiunov, Martin Ringbauer, Christine Maier, Rainer Blatt, Thomas Monz, Aleksey K. Fedorov, A.I. Lvovsky</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A prerequisite to the successful development of quantum computers and simulators is precise understanding of physical processes occurring therein, which can be achieved by measuring the quantum states they produce. However, the resources required for traditional quantum-state estimation scale exponentially with the system size, highlighting the need for alternative approaches. Here we demonstrate an efficient method for complete characterization of complex multi-qubit quantum states. Using a variational version of the matrix product state ansatz, we perform the full tomography of quantum states produced in a 20-qubit trapped-ion Ising-type quantum simulator, using the data acquired in only 27 bases with 1000 measurements in each basis. We observe superior state reconstruction quality and faster convergence compared to the methods based on neural network quantum state representations: restricted Boltzmann machines and feedforward neural networks with autoregressive architecture. Our results pave the way towards efficient experimental characterization of complex states produced by the dynamics of many-body quantum systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-Classical Hybrid Systems and their Quasifree Transformations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05020</link>
    <author>Lars Dammeier, Reinhard F. Werner</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study continuous variable systems, in which quantum and classical degrees of freedom are combined and treated on the same footing. Thus all systems, including the inputs or outputs to a channel, may be quantum-classical hybrids. This allows a unified treatment of a large variety of quantum operations involving measurements or dependence on classical parameters. The basic variables are given by canonical operators with scalar commutators. Some variables may commute with all others and hence generate a classical subsystem. We systematically study the class of "quasifree" operations, which are characterized equivalently either by an intertwining condition for phase-space translations or by the requirement that, in the Heisenberg picture, Weyl operators are mapped to multiples of Weyl operators. This includes the well-known Gaussian operations, evolutions with quadratic Hamiltonians, and "linear Bosonic channels", but allows for much more general kinds of noise. For example, all states are quasifree. We sketch the analysis of quasifree preparation, measurement, repeated observation, cloning, teleportation, dense coding, the setup for the classical limit, and some aspects of irreversible dynamics, together with the precise salient tradeoffs of uncertainty, error, and disturbance. Although the spaces of observables and states are infinite dimensional for every non-trivial system that we consider, we treat the technicalities related to this in a uniform and conclusive way, providing a calculus that is both easy to use and fully rigorous.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Computing theta function</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05405</link>
    <author>Alexander Barvinok</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Let $f: {\Bbb R}^n \longrightarrow {\Bbb R}$ be a positive definite quadratic form and let $y \in {\Bbb R}^n$ be a point. We present a fully polynomial randomized approximation scheme (FPRAS) for computing $\sum_{x \in {\Bbb Z}^n} e^{-f(x)}$, provided the eigenvalues of $f$ lie in the interval roughly between $s$ and $e^{s}$ and for computing $\sum_{x \in {\Bbb Z}^n} e^{-f(x-y)}$, provided the eigenvalues of $f$ lie in the interval roughly between $e^{-s}$ and $s^{-1}$ for some $s \geq 3$. To compute the first sum, we represent it as the integral of an explicit log-concave function on ${\Bbb R}^n$, and to compute the second sum, we use the reciprocity relation for theta functions. Choosing $s \sim \log n$, we apply the results to test the existence of sufficiently many short integer vectors in a given subspace $L \subset {\Bbb R}^n$ or in the vicinity of $L$.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>