<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13228</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas Breuckmann, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of non-trivial complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). We prove this conjecture by showing that the recently discovered families of constant-rate and linear-distance QLDPC codes correspond to NLTS local Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical surrogates for quantum learning models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11740</link>
    <author>Franz J. Schreiber, Jens Eisert, Johannes Jakob Meyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The advent of noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers has put the search for possible applications to the forefront of quantum information science. One area where hopes for an advantage through near-term quantum computers are high is quantum machine learning, where variational quantum learning models based on parametrized quantum circuits are discussed. In this work, we introduce the concept of a classical surrogate, a classical model which can be efficiently obtained from a trained quantum learning model and reproduces its input-output relations. As inference can be performed classically, the existence of a classical surrogate greatly enhances the applicability of a quantum learning strategy. However, the classical surrogate also challenges possible advantages of quantum schemes. As it is possible to directly optimize the ansatz of the classical surrogate, they create a natural benchmark the quantum model has to outperform. We show that large classes of well-analyzed re-uploading models have a classical surrogate. We conducted numerical experiments and found that these quantum models show no advantage in performance or trainability in the problems we analyze. This leaves only generalization capability as possible point of quantum advantage and emphasizes the dire need for a better understanding of inductive biases of quantum learning models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Pair Measurement Surface Code on Pentagons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12780</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, I present a way to compile the surface code into two-body parity measurements ("pair measurements"), where the pair measurements run along the edges of a Cairo pentagonal tiling. The resulting circuit improves on prior work by Chao et al. by using fewer pair measurements per four-body stabilizer measurement (5 instead of 6) and fewer time steps per round of stabilizer measurement (6 instead of 10). Using Monte Carlo sampling, I show that these improvements increase the threshold of the surface code when compiling into pair measurements from $\approx 0.2\%$ to $\approx 0.4\%$, and also that they improve the teraquop footprint at a $0.1\%$ physical gate error rate from $\approx6000$ qubits to $\approx3000$ qubits. However, I also show that Chao et al's construction will have a smaller teraquop footprint for physical gate error rates below $\approx 0.03\%$ (due to bidirectional hook errors in my construction). I also compare to the planar honeycomb code, showing that although this work does noticeably reduce the gap between the surface code and the honeycomb code (when compiling into pair measurements), the honeycomb code is still more efficient (threshold $\approx 0.8\%$, teraquop footprint at $0.1\%$ of $\approx 1000$).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement as a shortcut to long-range entangled quantum matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13527</link>
    <author>Tsung-Cheng Lu, Leonardo A. Lessa, Isaac H. Kim, Timothy H. Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The preparation of long-range entangled states using unitary circuits is limited by Lieb-Robinson bounds, but circuits with projective measurements and feedback (``adaptive circuits'') can evade such restrictions. We introduce four classes of local adaptive circuits that enable low-depth preparation of long-range entangled quantum matter characterized by gapped topological orders and conformal field theories (CFTs). The four classes are inspired by distinct physical insights, including tensor-network constructions, short-range entangled states with non-trivial braiding structures, multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (MERA), and parton constructions. A large class of topological orders, including chiral and symmetry-enriched topological orders, can be prepared in constant depth or time, and one-dimensional CFT states and non-abelian topological orders with both solvable and non-solvable groups can be prepared in depth scaling logarithmically with system size. Our work illustrates the practical and conceptual versatility of measurement for state preparation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Monogamy of entanglement between cones</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11805</link>
    <author>Guillaume Aubrun, Alexander Müller-Hermes, Martin Plávala</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A separable quantum state shared between parties $A$ and $B$ can be symmetrically extended to a quantum state shared between party $A$ and parties $B_1,\ldots ,B_k$ for every $k\in\mathbf{N}$. Quantum states that are not separable, i.e., entangled, do not have this property. This phenomenon is known as "monogamy of entanglement". We show that monogamy is not only a feature of quantum theory, but that it characterizes the minimal tensor product of general pairs of convex cones $\mathsf{C}_A$ and $\mathsf{C}_B$: The elements of the minimal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\min} \mathsf{C}_B$ are precisely the tensors that can be symmetrically extended to elements in the maximal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\max} \mathsf{C}^{\otimes_{\max} k}_B$ for every $k\in\mathbf{N}$. Equivalently, the minimal tensor product of two cones is the intersection of the nested sets of $k$-extendible tensors. It is a natural question when the minimal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\min} \mathsf{C}_B$ coincides with the set of $k$-extendible tensors for some finite $k$. We show that this is universally the case for every cone $\mathsf{C}_A$ if and only if $\mathsf{C}_B$ is a polyhedral cone with a base given by a product of simplices. Our proof makes use of a new characterization of products of simplices up to affine equivalence that we believe is of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Detecting and Eliminating Quantum Noise of Quantum Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13743</link>
    <author>Shuanghong Tang, Congcong Zheng, Kun Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work, we propose a two-stage procedure to systematically address quantum noise inherent in quantum measurements. The idea behind it is intuitive: we first detect and then eliminate quantum noise so that the classical noise assumption is satisfied and measurement error mitigation works. In the first stage, inspired by coherence witness in the resource theory of quantum coherence, we design an efficient method to detect quantum noise. It works by fitting the difference between two measurement statistics to the Fourier series, where the statistics are obtained using maximally coherent states with relative phase and maximally mixed states as inputs. The fitting coefficients quantitatively benchmark quantum noise. In the second stage, we design various methods to eliminate quantum noise, inspired by the Pauli twirling technique. They work by executing randomly sampled Pauli gates before the measurement device and conditionally flipping the measurement outcomes in such a way that the effective measurement device contains only classical noise. We demonstrate the feasibility of the two-stage procedure numerically on Baidu Quantum Platform. Remarkably, the results show that quantum noise in measurement devices is significantly suppressed, and the quantum computation accuracy is substantially improved. We highlight that the two-stage procedure complements existing measurement error mitigation techniques, and they together form a standard toolbox for manipulating measurement errors in near-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From Tensor Network Quantum States to Tensorial Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12363</link>
    <author>Dian Wu, Riccardo Rossi, Filippo Vicentini, Giuseppe Carleo</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that any matrix product state (MPS) can be exactly represented by a recurrent neural network (RNN) with a linear memory update. We generalize this RNN architecture to 2D lattices using a multilinear memory update. It supports perfect sampling and wave function evaluation in polynomial time, and can represent an area law of entanglement entropy. Numerical evidence shows that it can encode the wave function using a bond dimension lower by orders of magnitude when compared to MPS, with an accuracy that can be systematically improved by increasing the bond dimension.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast Classical Simulation of Hamiltonian Dynamics by Simultaneous Diagonalization Using Clifford Transformation with Parallel Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11664</link>
    <author>Yoshiaki Kawase, Keisuke Fujii</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulating quantum many-body dynamics is important both for fundamental understanding of physics and practical applications for quantum information processing. Therefore, classical simulation methods have been developed so far. Specifically, the Trotter-Suzuki decomposition can analyze a highly complex quantum dynamics, if the number of qubits is sufficiently small so that main memory can store the state vector. However, simulation of quantum dynamics via Trotter-Suzuki decomposition requires huge number of steps, each of which accesses the state vector, and hence the simulation time becomes impractically long. To settle this issue, we propose a technique to accelerate simulation of quantum dynamics via simultaneous diagonalization of mutually commuting Pauli groups, which is also attracting a lot of attention to reduce the measurement overheads in quantum algorithms. We group the Hamiltonian into mutually commputing Pauli strings, and each of them are diagonalized in the computational basis via a Clifford transformation. Since diagonal operators are applied on the state vector simultaneously with minimum memory access, this method successfully use performance of highly parallel processors such as Graphics Processing Units (GPU). Compared to an implementation using one of the fastest simulators of quantum computers, the numerical experiments have shown that our method provides a few tens of times acceleration.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Many-Body Scars: A Quasiparticle Perspective</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11528</link>
    <author>Anushya Chandran, Thomas Iadecola, Vedika Khemani, Roderich Moessner</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Weakly interacting quasiparticles play a central role in the low-energy description of many phases of quantum matter. At higher energies, however, quasiparticles cease to be well-defined in generic many-body systems due to a proliferation of decay channels. In this review, we discuss the phenomenon of quantum many-body scars, which can give rise to certain species of stable quasiparticles throughout the energy spectrum. This goes along with a set of unusual non-equilibrium phenomena including many-body revivals and non-thermal stationary states. We provide a pedagogical exposition of this physics via a simple yet comprehensive example, that of a spin-1 XY model. We place our discussion in the broader context of symmetry-based constructions of many-body scar states, projector embeddings, and Hilbert space fragmentation. We conclude with a summary of experimental progress and theoretical puzzles.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-Convex Optimization by Hamiltonian Alternation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14072</link>
    <author>Anuj Apte, Kunal Marwaha, Arvind Murugan</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A major obstacle to non-convex optimization is the problem of getting stuck in local minima. We introduce a novel metaheuristic to handle this issue, creating an alternate Hamiltonian that shares minima with the original Hamiltonian only within a chosen energy range. We find that repeatedly minimizing each Hamiltonian in sequence allows an algorithm to escape local minima. This technique is particularly straightforward when the ground state energy is known, and one obtains an improvement even without this knowledge. We demonstrate this technique by using it to find the ground state for instances of a Sherrington-Kirkpatrick spin glass.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>