<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Short Proofs of Linear Growth of Quantum Circuit Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05668</link>
    <author>Zhi Li</author>
    <pubDate>May 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The complexity of a quantum gate, defined as the minimal number of elementary gates to build it, is an important concept in quantum information and computation. It is shown recently that the complexity of quantum gates built from random quantum circuits almost surely grows linearly with the number of building blocks. In this article, we provide two short proofs of this fact. We also discuss a discrete version of quantum circuit complexity growth.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploiting symmetry in variational quantum machine learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06217</link>
    <author>Johannes Jakob Meyer, Marian Mularski, Elies Gil-Fuster, Antonio Anna Mele, Francesco Arzani, Alissa Wilms, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>May 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum machine learning is an extensively studied application of near-term quantum computers. The success of variational quantum learning models crucially depends on finding a suitable parametrization of the model that encodes an inductive bias relevant to the learning task. However, precious little is known about guiding principles for the construction of suitable parametrizations. In this work, we holistically explore when and how symmetries of the learning problem can be exploited to construct quantum learning models with outcomes invariant under the symmetry of the learning task. Building on tools from representation theory, we show how a standard gateset can be transformed into an equivariant gateset that respects the symmetries of the problem at hand through a process of gate symmetrization. We benchmark the proposed methods on two toy problems that feature a non-trivial symmetry and observe a substantial increase in generalization performance. As our tools can also be applied in a straightforward way to other variational problems with symmetric structure, we show how equivariant gatesets can be used in variational quantum eigensolvers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Beyond Barren Plateaus: Quantum Variational Algorithms Are Swamped With Traps</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05786</link>
    <author>Eric R. Anschuetz, Bobak T. Kiani</author>
    <pubDate>May 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One of the most important properties of classical neural networks is how surprisingly trainable they are, though their training algorithms typically rely on optimizing complicated, nonconvex loss functions. Previous results have shown that unlike the case in classical neural networks, variational quantum models are often not trainable. The most studied phenomenon is the onset of barren plateaus in the training landscape of these quantum models, typically when the models are very deep. This focus on barren plateaus has made the phenomenon almost synonymous with the trainability of quantum models. Here, we show that barren plateaus are only a part of the story. We prove that a wide class of variational quantum models -- which are shallow, and exhibit no barren plateus -- have only a superpolynomially small fraction of local minima within any constant energy from the global minimum, rendering these models untrainable if no good initial guess of the optimal parameters is known. We also study the trainability of variational quantum algorithms from a statistical query framework, and show that noisy optimization of a wide variety of quantum models is impossible with a sub-exponential number of queries. Finally, we numerically confirm our results on a variety of problem instances. Though we exclude a wide variety of quantum algorithms here, we give reason for optimism for certain classes of variational algorithms and discuss potential ways forward in showing the practical utility of such algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An optimal oracle separation of classical and quantum hybrid schemes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.04633</link>
    <author>Atsuya Hasegawa, François Le Gall</author>
    <pubDate>May 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, Chia, Chung and Lai (STOC 2020) and Coudron and Menda (STOC 2020) have shown that there exists an oracle $\mathcal{O}$ such that $\mathsf{BQP}^\mathcal{O} \neq (\mathsf{BPP^{BQNC}})^\mathcal{O} \cup (\mathsf{BQNC^{BPP}})^\mathcal{O}$. In fact, Chia et al. proved a stronger statement: for any depth parameter $d$, there exists an oracle that separates quantum depth $d$ and $2d+1$, when polynomial-time classical computation is allowed. This implies that relative to an oracle, doubling quantum depth gives classical and quantum hybrid schemes more computational power. In this paper, we show that for any depth parameter $d$, there exists an oracle that separates quantum depth $d$ and $d+1$, when polynomial-time classical computation is allowed. This gives an optimal oracle separation of classical and quantum hybrid schemes. To prove our result, we consider $d$-Bijective Shuffling Simon's Problem (which is a variant of $d$-Shuffling Simon's Problem considered by Chia et al.) and an oracle inspired by an "in-place" permutation oracle.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fundamental limitations on optimization in variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05056</link>
    <author>Hao-Kai Zhang, Chengkai Zhu, Geng Liu, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Exploring quantum applications of near-term quantum devices is a rapidly growing field of quantum information science with both theoretical and practical interests. A leading paradigm to establish such near-term quantum applications is variational quantum algorithms (VQAs). These algorithms use a classical optimizer to train a parameterized quantum circuit to accomplish certain tasks, where the circuits are usually randomly initialized. In this work, we prove that for a broad class of such random circuits, the variation range of the cost function via adjusting any local quantum gate within the circuit vanishes exponentially in the number of qubits with a high probability. This result can unify the restrictions on gradient-based and gradient-free optimizations in a natural manner and reveal extra harsh constraints on the training landscapes of VQAs. Hence a fundamental limitation on the trainability of VQAs is unraveled, indicating the essence of the optimization hardness in the Hilbert space with exponential dimension. We further showcase the validity of our results with numerical simulations of representative VQAs. We believe that these results would deepen our understanding of the scalability of VQAs and shed light on the search for near-term quantum applications with advantages.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multivariable quantum signal processing (M-QSP): prophecies of the two-headed oracle</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06261</link>
    <author>Zane M. Rossi, Isaac L. Chuang</author>
    <pubDate>May 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent work shows that quantum signal processing (QSP) and its multi-qubit lifted version, quantum singular value transformation (QSVT), unify and improve the presentation of most quantum algorithms. QSP/QSVT characterize the ability, by alternating ansätze, to obliviously transform the singular values of subsystems of unitary matrices by polynomial functions; these algorithms are numerically stable and analytically well-understood. That said, QSP/QSVT require consistent access to a single oracle, and say nothing about computing joint properties of two or more oracles; these can be far cheaper to compute given the ability to pit oracles against one another coherently. This work introduces a corresponding theory of QSP over multiple variables: M-QSP. Surprisingly, despite the non-existence of the fundamental theorem of algebra for multivariable polynomials, there exist necessary and sufficient conditions under which a desired stable multivariable polynomial transformation is possible. Moreover, the classical subroutines used by QSP protocols survive in the multivariable setting for non-obvious reasons. Up to a well-defined conjecture, we give proof that the family of achievable multivariable transforms is as loosely constrained as could be expected. M-QSP is numerically stable and inherits the approximative efficiency of its single-variable analogue; however, its underlying theory is substantively more complex. M-QSP provides one bridge from quantum algorithms to a rich theory of algebraic geometry over multiple variables. The unique ability of M-QSP to obliviously approximate joint functions of multiple variables coherently leads to novel speedups incommensurate with those of other quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical verification of quantum depth</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.04656</link>
    <author>Nai-Hui Chia, Shih-Han Hung</author>
    <pubDate>May 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present two protocols for classical verification of quantum depth. Our protocols allow a purely classical verifier to distinguish devices with different quantum circuit depths even in the presence of classical computation. We show that a device with quantum circuit depth at most d will be rejected by the verifier even if the prover applies additional polynomial-time classical computation to cheat. On the other hand, the verifier accepts a device which has quantum circuit depth d' for some d'>d. In our first protocol, we introduce an additional untrusted quantum machine which shares entanglements with the target machine. Applying a robust self-test, our first protocol certifies the depth of the target machine with information theoretic security and nearly optimal separation. The protocol relies on the oracle separation problem for quantum depth by Chia, Chung and Lai [STOC 2020] and a transformation from an oracle separation problem to a two-player non-local game. Our second protocol certifies the quantum depth of a single device based on quantum hardness of learning with errors. The protocol relies on the noisy trapdoor claw-free function family and the idea of pointer chasing to force the prover to keep quantum coherence until all preceding message exchanges are completed. To our knowledge, we give the first constructions for distinguishing hybrid quantum-classical computers with different circuit depths in unrelativized models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Equivariant quantum circuits for learning on weighted graphs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06109</link>
    <author>Andrea Skolik, Michele Cattelan, Sheir Yarkoni, Thomas Bäck, Vedran Dunjko</author>
    <pubDate>May 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms are the leading candidate for near-term advantage on noisy quantum hardware. When training a parametrized quantum circuit to solve a specific task, the choice of ansatz is one of the most important factors that determines the trainability and performance of the algorithm. Problem-tailored ansatzes have become the standard for tasks in optimization or quantum chemistry, and yield more efficient algorithms with better performance than unstructured approaches. In quantum machine learning (QML), however, the literature on ansatzes that are motivated by the training data structure is scarce. Considering that it is widely known that unstructured ansatzes can become untrainable with increasing system size and circuit depth, it is of key importance to also study problem-tailored circuit architectures in a QML context. In this work, we introduce an ansatz for learning tasks on weighted graphs that respects an important graph symmetry, namely equivariance under node permutations. We evaluate the performance of this ansatz on a complex learning task on weighted graphs, where a ML model is used to implement a heuristic for a combinatorial optimization problem. We analytically study the expressivity of our ansatz at depth one, and numerically compare the performance of our model on instances with up to 20 qubits to ansatzes where the equivariance property is gradually broken. We show that our ansatz outperforms all others even in the small-instance regime. Our results strengthen the notion that symmetry-preserving ansatzes are a key to success in QML and should be an active area of research in order to enable near-term advantages in this field.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Stabilizer Inactivation for Message-Passing Decoding of Quantum LDPC Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06125</link>
    <author>Julien du Crest, Mehdi Mhalla, Valentin Savin</author>
    <pubDate>May 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a post-processing method for message-passing (MP) decoding of CSS quantum LDPC codes, called stabilizer-inactivation (SI). It relies on inactivating a set of qubits, supporting a check in the dual code, and then running the MP decoding again. This allows MP decoding to converge outside the inactivated set of qubits, while the error on these is determined by solving a small, constant size, linear system. Compared to the state of the art post-processing method based on ordered statistics decoding (OSD), we show through numerical simulations that MP-SI outperforms MP-OSD for different quantum LDPC code constructions, different MP decoding algorithms, and different MP scheduling strategies, while having a significantly reduced complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact solution for the quantum and private capacities of bosonic dephasing channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05736</link>
    <author>Ludovico Lami, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>May 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The capacities of noisy quantum channels capture the ultimate rates of information transmission across quantum communication lines, and the quantum capacity plays a key role in determining the overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation platforms. In the case of bosonic systems, central to many applications, no closed formulas for these capacities were known for bosonic dephasing channels, a key class of non-Gaussian channels modelling, e.g., noise affecting superconducting circuits or fiber-optic communication channels. Here we provide the first exact calculation of the quantum, private, two-way assisted quantum, and secret-key agreement capacities of all bosonic dephasing channels. We prove that that they are equal to the relative entropy of the distribution underlying the channel to the uniform distribution. Our result solves a problem that has been open for over a decade, having been posed originally by [Jiang & Chen, Quantum and Nonlinear Optics 244, 2010].</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>