<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Unitary property testing lower bounds by polynomials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05885</link>
    <author>Adrian She, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study unitary property testing, where a quantum algorithm is given query access to a black-box unitary and has to decide whether it satisfies some property. In addition to containing the standard quantum query complexity model (where the unitary encodes a binary string) as a special case, this model contains "inherently quantum" problems that have no classical analogue. Characterizing the query complexity of these problems requires new algorithmic techniques and lower bound methods. Our main contribution is a generalized polynomial method for unitary property testing problems. By leveraging connections with invariant theory, we apply this method to obtain lower bounds on problems such as determining recurrence times of unitaries, approximating the dimension of a marked subspace, and approximating the entanglement entropy of a marked state. We also present a unitary property testing-based approach towards an oracle separation between $\mathsf{QMA}$ and $\mathsf{QMA(2)}$, a long standing question in quantum complexity theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Depth in the Random Oracle Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06454</link>
    <author>Atul Singh Arora, Andrea Coladangelo, Matthew Coudron, Alexandru Gheorghiu, Uttam Singh, Hendrik Waldner</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a comprehensive characterization of the computational power of shallow quantum circuits combined with classical computation. Specifically, for classes of search problems, we show that the following statements hold, relative to a random oracle: (a) $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}}} \neq \mathsf{BQP}$. This refutes Jozsa's conjecture [QIP 05] in the random oracle model. As a result, this gives the first instantiatable separation between the classes by replacing the oracle with a cryptographic hash function, yielding a resolution to one of Aaronson's ten semi-grand challenges in quantum computing. (b) $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}} \nsubseteq \mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}}$ and $\mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}} \nsubseteq \mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}}$. This shows that there is a subtle interplay between classical computation and shallow quantum computation. In fact, for the second separation, we establish that, for some problems, the ability to perform adaptive measurements in a single shallow quantum circuit, is more useful than the ability to perform polynomially many shallow quantum circuits without adaptive measurements. (c) There exists a 2-message proof of quantum depth protocol. Such a protocol allows a classical verifier to efficiently certify that a prover must be performing a computation of some minimum quantum depth. Our proof of quantum depth can be instantiated using the recent proof of quantumness construction by Yamakawa and Zhandry [STOC 22].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum divide and conquer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06419</link>
    <author>Andrew M. Childs, Robin Kothari, Matt Kovacs-Deak, Aarthi Sundaram, Daochen Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The divide-and-conquer framework, used extensively in classical algorithm design, recursively breaks a problem of size $n$ into smaller subproblems (say, $a$ copies of size $n/b$ each), along with some auxiliary work of cost $C^{\textrm{aux}}(n)$, to give a recurrence relation $$C(n) ≤a \,C(n/b) + C^\textrmaux(n)$$ for the classical complexity $C(n)$. We describe a quantum divide-and-conquer framework that, in certain cases, yields an analogous recurrence relation $$C_Q(n) ≤\sqrta \u2009C_Q(n/b) + O(C^\textrmaux_Q(n))$$ that characterizes the quantum query complexity. We apply this framework to obtain near-optimal quantum query complexities for various string problems, such as (i) recognizing regular languages; (ii) decision versions of String Rotation and String Suffix; and natural parameterized versions of (iii) Longest Increasing Subsequence and (iv) Longest Common Subsequence.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement-based quantum computation in finite one-dimensional systems: string order implies computational power</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05089</link>
    <author>Robert Raussendorf, Wang Yang, Arnab Adhikary</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a new framework for assessing the power of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) on short-range entangled symmetric resource states, in spatial dimension one. It requires fewer assumptions than previously known. The formalism can handle finitely extended systems (as opposed to the thermodynamic limit), and does not require translation-invariance. Further, we strengthen the connection between MBQC computational power and string order. Namely, we establish that whenever a suitable set of string order parameters is non-zero, a corresponding set of unitary gates can be realized with fidelity arbitrarily close to unity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum state tomography via non-convex Riemannian gradient descent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.04717</link>
    <author>Ming-Chien Hsu, En-Jui Kuo, Wei-Hsuan Yu, Jian-Feng Cai, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recovery of an unknown density matrix of large size requires huge computational resources. The recent Factored Gradient Descent (FGD) algorithm and its variants achieved state-of-the-art performance since they could mitigate the dimensionality barrier by utilizing some of the underlying structures of the density matrix. Despite their theoretical guarantee of a linear convergence rate, the convergence in practical scenarios is still slow because the contracting factor of the FGD algorithms depends on the condition number $\kappa$ of the ground truth state. Consequently, the total number of iterations can be as large as $O(\sqrt{\kappa}\ln(\frac{1}{\varepsilon}))$ to achieve the estimation error $\varepsilon$. In this work, we derive a quantum state tomography scheme that improves the dependence on $\kappa$ to the logarithmic scale; namely, our algorithm could achieve the approximation error $\varepsilon$ in $O(\ln(\frac{1}{\kappa\varepsilon}))$ steps. The improvement comes from the application of the non-convex Riemannian gradient descent (RGD). The contracting factor in our approach is thus a universal constant that is independent of the given state. Our theoretical results of extremely fast convergence and nearly optimal error bounds are corroborated by numerical results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>One-Wayness in Quantum Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03394</link>
    <author>Tomoyuki Morimae, Takashi Yamakawa</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The existence of one-way functions is one of the most fundamental assumptions in classical cryptography. In the quantum world, on the other hand, there are evidences that some cryptographic primitives can exist even if one-way functions do not exist. We therefore have the following important open problem in quantum cryptography: What is the most fundamental element in quantum cryptography? In this direction, Brakerski, Canetti, and Qian recently defined a notion called EFI pairs, which are pairs of efficiently generatable states that are statistically distinguishable but computationally indistinguishable, and showed its equivalence with some cryptographic primitives including commitments, oblivious transfer, and general multi-party computations. However, their work focuses on decision-type primitives and does not cover search-type primitives like quantum money and digital signatures. In this paper, we study properties of one-way state generators (OWSGs), which are a quantum analogue of one-way functions. We first revisit the definition of OWSGs and generalize it by allowing mixed output states. Then we show the following results. (1) We define a weaker version of OWSGs, weak OWSGs, and show that they are equivalent to OWSGs. (2) Quantum digital signatures are equivalent to OWSGs. (3) Private-key quantum money schemes (with pure money states) imply OWSGs. (4) Quantum pseudo one-time pad schemes imply both OWSGs and EFI pairs. (5) We introduce an incomparable variant of OWSGs, which we call secretly-verifiable and statistically-invertible OWSGs, and show that they are equivalent to EFI pairs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Post-Quantum Zero-Knowledge with Space-Bounded Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06093</link>
    <author>Prabhanjan Ananth, Alex B. Grilo</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The traditional definition of quantum zero-knowledge stipulates that the knowledge gained by any quantum polynomial-time verifier in an interactive protocol can be simulated by a quantum polynomial-time algorithm. One drawback of this definition is that it allows the simulator to consume significantly more computational resources than the verifier. We argue that this drawback renders the existing notion of quantum zero-knowledge not viable for certain settings, especially when dealing with near-term quantum devices. In this work, we initiate a fine-grained notion of post-quantum zero-knowledge that is more compatible with near-term quantum devices. We introduce the notion of $(s,f)$ space-bounded quantum zero-knowledge. In this new notion, we require that an $s$-qubit malicious verifier can be simulated by a quantum polynomial-time algorithm that uses at most $f(s)$-qubits, for some function $f(\cdot)$, and no restriction on the amount of the classical memory consumed by either the verifier or the simulator. We explore this notion and establish both positive and negative results: - For verifiers with logarithmic quantum space $s$ and (arbitrary) polynomial classical space, we show that $(s,f)$-space-bounded QZK, for $f(s)=2s$, can be achieved based on the existence of post-quantum one-way functions. Moreover, our protocol runs in constant rounds. - For verifiers with super-logarithmic quantum space $s$, assuming the existence of post-quantum secure one-way functions, we show that $(s,f)$-space-bounded QZK protocols, with fully black-box simulation (classical analogue of black-box simulation) can only be achieved for languages in BQP.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Commitments to Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05138</link>
    <author>Sam Gunn, Nathan Ju, Fermi Ma, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>What does it mean to commit to a quantum state? In this work, we propose a simple answer: a commitment to quantum messages is binding if, after the commit phase, the committed state is hidden from the sender's view. We accompany this new definition with several instantiations. We build the first non-interactive succinct quantum state commitments, which can be seen as an analogue of collision-resistant hashing for quantum messages. We also show that hiding quantum state commitments (QSCs) are implied by any commitment scheme for classical messages. All of our constructions can be based on quantum-cryptographic assumptions that are implied by but are potentially weaker than one-way functions. Commitments to quantum states open the door to many new cryptographic possibilities. Our flagship application of a succinct QSC is a quantum-communication version of Kilian's succinct arguments for any language that has quantum PCPs with constant error and polylogarithmic locality. Plugging in the PCP theorem, this yields succinct arguments for NP under significantly weaker assumptions than required classically; moreover, if the quantum PCP conjecture holds, this extends to QMA. At the heart of our security proof is a new rewinding technique for extracting quantum information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing fermionic encodings for both Hamiltonian and hardware</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05652</link>
    <author>Riley W. Chien, Joel Klassen</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work we present a method for generating a fermionic encoding tailored to a set of target fermionic operators and to a target hardware connectivity. Our method uses brute force search, over the space of all encodings which map from Majorana monomials to Pauli operators, to find an encoding which optimizes a target cost function. In contrast to earlier works in this direction, our method searches over an extremely broad class of encodings which subsumes all known second quantized encodings that constitute algebra homomorphisms. In order to search over this class, we give a clear mathematical explanation of how precisely it is characterized, and how to translate this characterization into constructive search criteria. A benefit of searching over this class is that our method is able to supply fairly general optimality guarantees on solutions. A second benefit is that our method is, in principal, capable of finding more efficient representations of fermionic systems when the set of fermionic operators under consideration are faithfully represented by a smaller quotient algebra. Given the high algorithmic cost of performing the search, we adapt our method to handle translationally invariant systems that can be described by a small unit cell that is less costly. We demonstrate our method on various pairings of target fermionic operators and hardware connectivities. We additionally show how our method can be extended to find error detecting fermionic encodings in this class.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Complexity of NISQ</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07234</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Jordan Cotler, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Jerry Li</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recent proliferation of NISQ devices has made it imperative to understand their computational power. In this work, we define and study the complexity class $\textsf{NISQ} $, which is intended to encapsulate problems that can be efficiently solved by a classical computer with access to a NISQ device. To model existing devices, we assume the device can (1) noisily initialize all qubits, (2) apply many noisy quantum gates, and (3) perform a noisy measurement on all qubits. We first give evidence that $\textsf{BPP}\subsetneq \textsf{NISQ}\subsetneq \textsf{BQP}$, by demonstrating super-polynomial oracle separations among the three classes, based on modifications of Simon's problem. We then consider the power of $\textsf{NISQ}$ for three well-studied problems. For unstructured search, we prove that $\textsf{NISQ}$ cannot achieve a Grover-like quadratic speedup over $\textsf{BPP}$. For the Bernstein-Vazirani problem, we show that $\textsf{NISQ}$ only needs a number of queries logarithmic in what is required for $\textsf{BPP}$. Finally, for a quantum state learning problem, we prove that $\textsf{NISQ}$ is exponentially weaker than classical computation with access to noiseless constant-depth quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>