<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction with fractal topological codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03568</link>
    <author>Arpit Dua, Tomas Jochym-O'Connor, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, a class of fractal surface codes (FSCs), has been constructed on fractal lattices with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$, which admits a fault-tolerant non-Clifford CCZ gate. We investigate the performance of such FSCs as fault-tolerant quantum memories. We prove that there exist decoding strategies with non-zero thresholds for bit-flip and phase-flip errors in the FSCs with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$. For the bit-flip errors, we adapt the sweep decoder, developed for string-like syndromes in the regular 3D surface code, to the FSCs by designing suitable modifications on the boundaries of the holes in the fractal lattice. Moreover, our adaptation of the sweep decoder for the FSCs maintains its self-correcting and single-shot nature. For the phase-flip errors, we employ the minimum-weight-perfect-matching (MWPM) decoder for the point-like syndromes. We report a sustainable fault-tolerant threshold ($\sim 1.7\%$) under phenomenological noise for the sweep decoder and the code capacity threshold (lower bounded by $2.95\%$) for the MWPM decoder for a particular FSC with Hausdorff dimension $D_H\approx2.966$. The latter can be mapped to the critical point of a zero-temperature confinement-Higgs transition on the fractal lattice, which is tunable via the Hausdorff dimension.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence between fermion-to-qubit mappings in two spatial dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05153</link>
    <author>Yu-An Chen, Yijia Xu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We argue that all locality-preserving mappings between fermionic observables and Pauli matrices on a two-dimensional lattice can be generated from the exact bosonization in Ref. [1], whose gauge constraints project onto the subspace of the toric code with emergent fermions. Starting from the exact bosonization and applying Clifford finite-depth generalized local unitary (gLU) transformation, we can achieve all possible fermion-to-qubit mappings (up to the re-pairing of Majorana fermions). In particular, we discover a new super-compact encoding using 1.25 qubits per fermion on the square lattice, which is lower than any method in the literature. We prove the existence of fermion-to-qubit mappings with qubit-fermion ratios $r=1+ \frac{1}{2k}$ for positive integers $k$, where the proof utilizes the trivialness of quantum cellular automata (QCA) in two spatial dimensions. When the ratio approaches 1, the fermion-to-qubit mapping reduces to the 1d Jordan-Wigner transformation along a certain path in the two-dimensional lattice. Finally, we explicitly demonstrate that the Bravyi-Kitaev superfast simulation, the Verstraete-Cirac auxiliary method, Kitaev's exactly solved model, the Majorana loop stabilizer codes, and the compact fermion-to-qubit mapping can all be obtained from the exact bosonization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure conversion for fault-tolerant quantum computing in alkaline earth Rydberg atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03540</link>
    <author>Yue Wu, Shimon Kolkowitz, Shruti Puri, Jeff D Thompson</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Executing quantum algorithms on error-corrected logical qubits is a critical step for scalable quantum computing, but the requisite numbers of qubits and physical error rates are demanding for current experimental hardware. Recently, the development of error correcting codes tailored to particular physical noise models has helped relax these requirements. In this work, we propose a qubit encoding and gate protocol for ${}^{171}$Yb neutral atom qubits that converts the dominant physical errors into erasures, that is, errors in known locations. The key idea is to encode qubits in a metastable electronic level, such that gate errors predominantly result in transitions to disjoint subspaces whose populations can be continuously monitored via fluorescence. We estimate that 98% of errors can be converted into erasures. We quantify the benefit of this approach via circuit-level simulations of the surface code, finding a threshold increase from 0.937% to 4.15%. We also observe a larger code distance near the threshold, leading to a faster decrease in the logical error rate for the same number of physical qubits, which is important for near-term implementations. Erasure conversion should benefit any error correcting code, and may also be applied to design new gates and encodings in other qubit platforms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Distributed Algorithms for Detection of Cliques</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03000</link>
    <author>Keren Censor-Hillel, Orr Fischer, François Le Gall, Dean Leitersdorf, Rotem Oshman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The possibilities offered by quantum computing have drawn attention in the distributed computing community recently, with several breakthrough results showing quantum distributed algorithms that run faster than the fastest known classical counterparts, and even separations between the two models. A prime example is the result by Izumi, Le Gall, and Magniez [STACS 2020], who showed that triangle detection by quantum distributed algorithms is easier than triangle listing, while an analogous result is not known in the classical case. In this paper we present a framework for fast quantum distributed clique detection. This improves upon the state-of-the-art for the triangle case, and is also more general, applying to larger clique sizes. Our main technical contribution is a new approach for detecting cliques by encapsulating this as a search task for nodes that can be added to smaller cliques. To extract the best complexities out of our approach, we develop a framework for nested distributed quantum searches, which employ checking procedures that are quantum themselves. Moreover, we show a circuit-complexity barrier on proving a lower bound of the form $\Omega(n^{3/5+\epsilon})$ for $K_p$-detection for any $p \geq 4$, even in the classical (non-quantum) distributed CONGEST setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Systematic Literature Review: Quantum Machine Learning and its applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04093</link>
    <author>David Peral García, Juan Cruz-Benito, Francisco José García-Peñalvo</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing is the process of performing calculations using quantum mechanics. This field studies the quantum behavior of certain subatomic particles for subsequent use in performing calculations, as well as for large-scale information processing. These capabilities can give quantum computers an advantage in terms of computational time and cost over classical computers. Nowadays, there are scientific challenges that are impossible to perform by classical computation due to computational complexity or the time the calculation would take, and quantum computation is one of the possible answers. However, current quantum devices have not yet the necessary qubits and are not fault-tolerant enough to achieve these goals. Nonetheless, there are other fields like machine learning or chemistry where quantum computation could be useful with current quantum devices. This manuscript aims to present a Systematic Literature Review of the papers published between 2017 and 2021 to identify, analyze and classify the different algorithms used in quantum machine learning and their applications. Consequently, this study identified 52 articles that used quantum machine learning techniques and algorithms. The main types of found algorithms are quantum implementations of classical machine learning algorithms, such as support vector machines or the k-nearest neighbor model, and classical deep learning algorithms, like quantum neural networks. Many articles try to solve problems currently answered by classical machine learning but using quantum devices and algorithms. Even though results are promising, quantum machine learning is far from achieving its full potential. An improvement in the quantum hardware is required since the existing quantum computers lack enough quality, speed, and scale to allow quantum computing to achieve its full potential.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Consilience between QBism and Phenomenology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04734</link>
    <author>Hans Christian von Baeyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two decades after its creation, the interpretation of quantum mechanics called QBism is entering a new phase. Since it shares a personalist, subjective world-view with phenomenology, the philosophical study of human experience, there is a growing interest in the relationship between the two subjects. I call attention to the little-known philosopher Samuel Todes, whose phenomenology focused on the essential role of the human body in our understanding of the world. After reviewing this radical proposal, and illustrating it with some examples, I recommend it as an interesting mediator between the communities of physicists and phenomenologists. In addition, I argue that it may prove useful for promoting the public understanding of QBism.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum networks self-test all entangled states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05032</link>
    <author>Ivan Šupić, Joseph Bowles, Marc-Olivier Renou, Antonio Acín, Matty J. Hoban</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Certifying quantum properties with minimal assumptions is a fundamental problem in quantum information science. Self-testing is a method to infer the underlying physics of a quantum experiment only from the measured statistics. While all bipartite pure entangled states can be self-tested, little is known about how to self-test quantum states of an arbitrary number of systems. Here, we introduce a framework for network-assisted self-testing and use it to self-test any pure entangled quantum state of an arbitrary number of systems. The scheme requires the preparation of a number of singlets that scales linearly with the number of systems, and the implementation of standard projective and Bell measurements, all feasible with current technology. When all the network constraints are exploited, the obtained self-testing certification is stronger than what is achievable in any Bell-type scenario. Our work does not only solve an open question in the field, but also shows how properly designed networks offer new opportunities for the certification of quantum phenomena.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dynamical preparation of quantum spin liquids in Rydberg atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04034</link>
    <author>Giuliano Giudici, Mikhail D. Lukin, Hannes Pichler</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We theoretically analyze recent experiments [G. Semeghini et al., Science 374, 1242 (2021)] demonstrating the onset of a topological spin liquid using a programmable quantum simulator based on Rydberg atom arrays. In the experiment, robust signatures of topological order emerge in out-of-equilibrium states that are prepared using a quasi-adiabatic state preparation protocol. We show theoretically that the state preparation protocol can be optimized to target the fixed point of the topological phase -- the resonating valence bond (RVB) state of hard dimers -- in a time that scales linearly with the number of atoms. Moreover, we provide a two-parameter variational manifold of tensor network (TN) states that accurately describe the many-body dynamics of the preparation process. Using this approach we analyze the nature of the non-equilibrium state, establishing the emergence of topological order.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Snowmass White Paper: Quantum Aspects of Black Holes and the Emergence of Spacetime</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03096</link>
    <author>Raphael Bousso, Xi Dong, Netta Engelhardt, Thomas Faulkner, Thomas Hartman, Stephen H. Shenker, Douglas Stanford</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Black holes provide a window into the microscopic structure of spacetime in quantum gravity. Recently the quantum information contained in Hawking radiation has been calculated, verifying a key aspect of the consistency of black hole evaporation with quantum mechanical unitarity. This calculation relied crucially on recent progress in understanding the emergence of bulk spacetime from a boundary holographic description. Spacetime wormholes have played an important role in understanding the underpinnings of this result, and the precision study of such wormholes, in this and other contexts, has been enabled by the development of low-dimensional models of holography. In this white paper we review these developments and describe some of the deep open questions in this subject. These include the nature of the black hole interior, potential applications to quantum cosmology, the gravitational explanation of the fine structure of black holes, and the development of further connections to quantum information and laboratory quantum simulation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>QAOA pseudo-Boltzmann states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03358</link>
    <author>Pablo Díez-Valle, Diego Porras, Juan José García-Ripoll</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this letter, we provide analytical and numerical evidence that the single-layer Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) on universal Ising spin models produces thermal states with Gaussian perturbations. We find that these pseudo-Boltzman states can not be efficiently simulated on classical computers according to state-of-art techniques, and we relate this distribution to the optimization potential of QAOA. Moreover, we observe that the temperature depends on a hidden universal correlation between the energy of a state and the covariance of other energy levels and the Hamming distances of the state to those energies.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>