<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Random quantum circuits are approximate unitary $t$-designs in depth $O\left(nt^{5+o(1)}\right)$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16571</link>
    <author>Jonas Haferkamp</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The applications of random quantum circuits range from quantum computing and quantum many-body systems to the physics of black holes. Many of these applications are related to the generation of quantum pseudorandomness: Random quantum circuits are known to approximate unitary $t$-designs. Unitary $t$-designs are probability distributions that mimic Haar randomness up to $t$th moments. In a seminal paper, Brandão, Harrow and Horodecki prove that random quantum circuits in a brickwork architecture of depth $O(n t^{10.5})$ are approximate unitary $t$-design. In this work, we revisit this argument, which lower bounds the spectral gap of moment operators for local random quantum circuits by $\Omega(n^{-1}t^{-9.5})$. We improve this lower bound to $\Omega(n^{-1}t^{-4-o(1)})$. A direct consequence of this scaling is that random quantum circuits generate approximate unitary $t$-designs in depth $O(nt^{5+o(1)})$. Our techniques involve Gao's quantum union bound and the unreasonable effectiveness of the Clifford group. As an auxiliary result, we prove a near optimal convergence to the Haar measure for random Clifford unitaries interleaved with Haar random single qubit unitaries in Wasserstein distance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved Quantum Algorithms for Fidelity Estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.15993</link>
    <author>András Gilyén, Alexander Poremba</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fidelity is a fundamental measure for the closeness of two quantum states, which is important both from a theoretical and a practical point of view. Yet, in general, it is difficult to give good estimates of fidelity, especially when one works with mixed states over Hilbert spaces of very high dimension. Although, there has been some progress on fidelity estimation, all prior work either requires a large number of identical copies of the relevant states, or relies on unproven heuristics. In this work, we improve on both of these aspects by developing new and efficient quantum algorithms for fidelity estimation with provable performance guarantees in case at least one of the states is approximately low-rank. Our algorithms use advanced quantum linear algebra techniques, such as the quantum singular value transformation, as well as density matrix exponentiation and quantum spectral sampling. As a complementary result, we prove that fidelity estimation to any non-trivial constant additive accuracy is hard in general, by giving a sample complexity lower bound that depends polynomially on the dimension. Moreover, if circuit descriptions for the relevant states are provided, we show that the task is hard for the complexity class called (honest verifier) quantum statistical zero knowledge via a reduction to a closely related result by Watrous.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailored XZZX codes for biased noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16486</link>
    <author>Qian Xu, Nam Mannucci, Alireza Seif, Aleksander Kubica, Steven T. Flammia, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction (QEC) for generic errors is challenging due to the demanding threshold and resource requirements. Interestingly, when physical noise is biased, we can tailor our QEC schemes to the noise to improve performance. Here we study a family of codes having XZZX-type stabilizer generators, including a set of cyclic codes generalized from the five-qubit code and a set of topological codes that we call generalized toric codes (GTCs). We show that these XZZX codes are highly qubit efficient if tailored to biased noise. To characterize the code performance, we use the notion of effective distance, which generalizes code distance to the case of biased noise and constitutes a proxy for the logical failure rate. We find that the XZZX codes can achieve a favorable resource scaling by this metric under biased noise. We also show that the XZZX codes have remarkably high thresholds that reach what is achievable by random codes, and furthermore they can be efficiently decoded using matching decoders. Finally, by adding only one flag qubit, the XZZX codes can realize fault-tolerant QEC while preserving their large effective distance. In combination, our results show that tailored XZZX codes give a resource-efficient scheme for fault-tolerant QEC against biased noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An analytic theory for the dynamics of wide quantum neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16711</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Khadijeh Najafi, Kunal Sharma, Francesco Tacchino, Liang Jiang, Antonio Mezzacapo</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Parametrized quantum circuits can be used as quantum neural networks and have the potential to outperform their classical counterparts when trained for addressing learning problems. To date, much of the results on their performance on practical problems are heuristic in nature. In particular, the convergence rate for the training of quantum neural networks is not fully understood. Here, we analyze the dynamics of gradient descent for the training error of a class of variational quantum machine learning models. We define wide quantum neural networks as parameterized quantum circuits in the limit of a large number of qubits and variational parameters. We then find a simple analytic formula that captures the average behavior of their loss function and discuss the consequences of our findings. For example, for random quantum circuits, we predict and characterize an exponential decay of the residual training error as a function of the parameters of the system. We finally validate our analytic results with numerical experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A cellular automaton decoder for a noise-bias tailored color code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16534</link>
    <author>Jonathan F. San Miguel, Dominic J. Williamson, Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Self-correcting quantum memories demonstrate robust properties that can be exploited to improve active quantum error-correction protocols. Here we propose a cellular automaton decoder for a variation of the color code where the bases of the physical qubits are locally rotated, which we call the XYZ color code. The local transformation means our decoder demonstrates key properties of a two-dimensional fractal code if the noise acting on the system is infinitely biased towards dephasing, namely, no string-like logical operators. As such, in the high-bias limit, our local decoder reproduces the behavior of a partially self-correcting memory. At low error rates, our simulations show that the memory time diverges polynomially with system size without intervention from a global decoder, up to some critical system size that grows as the error rate is lowered. Furthermore, although we find that we cannot reproduce partially self-correcting behavior at finite bias, our numerics demonstrate improved memory times at realistic noise biases. Our results therefore motivate the design of tailored cellular automaton decoders that help to reduce the bandwidth demands of global decoding for realistic noise models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Distributed quantum error correction for chip-level catastrophic errors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16488</link>
    <author>Qian Xu, Alireza Seif, Haoxiong Yan, Nam Mannucci, Bernard Ousmane Sane, Rodney Van Meter, Andrew N. Cleland, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction holds the key to scaling up quantum computers. Cosmic ray events severely impact the operation of a quantum computer by causing chip-level catastrophic errors, essentially erasing the information encoded in a chip. Here, we present a distributed error correction scheme to combat the devastating effect of such events by introducing an additional layer of quantum erasure error correcting code across separate chips. We show that our scheme is fault tolerant against chip-level catastrophic errors and discuss its experimental implementation using superconducting qubits with microwave links. Our analysis shows that in state-of-the-art experiments, it is possible to suppress the rate of these errors from 1 per 10 seconds to less than 1 per month.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bi-PPT channels are entanglement breaking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01685</link>
    <author>Alexander Müller-Hermes, Satvik Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a recent paper, Hirche and Leditzky introduced the notion of bi-PPT channels which are quantum channels that stay completely positive under composition with a transposition and such that the same property holds for one of their complementary channels. They asked whether there are examples of such channels that are not antidegradable. We show that this is not the case, since bi-PPT channels are always entanglement breaking. We also show that degradable quantum channels staying completely positive under composition with a transposition are entanglement breaking.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement area law for 1D gauge theories and bosonic systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16012</link>
    <author>Nilin Abrahamsen, Yuan Su, Yu Tong, Nathan Wiebe</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove an entanglement area law for a class of 1D quantum systems involving infinite-dimensional local Hilbert spaces. This class of quantum systems include bosonic models such as the Hubbard-Holstein model, and both U(1) and SU(2) lattice gauge theories in one spatial dimension. Our proof relies on new results concerning the robustness of the ground state and spectral gap to the truncation of Hilbert space, applied within the approximate ground state projector (AGSP) framework from previous work. In establishing this area law, we develop a system-size independent bound on the expectation value of local observables for Hamiltonians without translation symmetry, which may be of separate interest. Our result provides theoretical justification for using tensor network methods to study the ground state properties of quantum systems with infinite local degrees of freedom.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring magic on a quantum processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.00015</link>
    <author>Salvatore F.E. Oliviero, Lorenzo Leone, Alioscia Hamma, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic states are the resource that allows quantum computers to attain an advantage over classical computers. This resource consists in the deviation from a property called stabilizerness which in turn implies that stabilizer circuits can be efficiently simulated on a classical computer. Without magic, no quantum computer can do anything that a classical computer cannot do. Given the importance of magic for quantum computation, it would be useful to have a method for measuring the amount of magic in a quantum state. In this work, we propose and experimentally demonstrate a protocol for measuring magic based on randomized measurements. Our experiments are carried out on two IBM Quantum Falcon processors. This protocol can provide a characterization of the effectiveness of a quantum hardware in producing states that cannot be effectively simulated on a classical computer. We show how from these measurements one can construct realistic noise models affecting the hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Characterization and Verification of Trotterized Digital Quantum Simulation via Hamiltonian and Liouvillian Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.15846</link>
    <author>Lorenzo Pastori, Tobias Olsacher, Christian Kokail, Peter Zoller</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The goal of digital quantum simulation is to approximate the dynamics of a given target Hamiltonian via a sequence of quantum gates, a procedure known as Trotterization. The quality of this approximation can be controlled by the so called Trotter step, that governs the number of required quantum gates per unit simulation time, and is intimately related to the existence of a time-independent, quasilocal Hamiltonian that governs the stroboscopic dynamics, refered to as the Floquet Hamiltonian of the Trotterization. In this work, we propose a Hamiltonian learning scheme to reconstruct the implemented Floquet Hamiltonian order-by-order in the Trotter step: this procedure is efficient, i.e., it requires a number of measurements that scales polynomially in the system size, and can be readily implemented in state-of-the-art experiments. With numerical examples, we propose several applications of our method in the context of verification of quantum devices, from the characterization of the distinct sources of errors in digital quantum simulators to the design of new types of quantum gates. Furthermore, we show how our approach can be extended to the case of non-unitary dynamics and used to learn Floquet Liouvillians, thereby offering a way of characterizing the dissipative processes present in NISQ quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>