<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Complexity of NISQ</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07234</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Jordan Cotler, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Jerry Li</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recent proliferation of NISQ devices has made it imperative to understand their computational power. In this work, we define and study the complexity class $\textsf{NISQ} $, which is intended to encapsulate problems that can be efficiently solved by a classical computer with access to a NISQ device. To model existing devices, we assume the device can (1) noisily initialize all qubits, (2) apply many noisy quantum gates, and (3) perform a noisy measurement on all qubits. We first give evidence that $\textsf{BPP}\subsetneq \textsf{NISQ}\subsetneq \textsf{BQP}$, by demonstrating super-polynomial oracle separations among the three classes, based on modifications of Simon's problem. We then consider the power of $\textsf{NISQ}$ for three well-studied problems. For unstructured search, we prove that $\textsf{NISQ}$ cannot achieve a Grover-like quadratic speedup over $\textsf{BPP}$. For the Bernstein-Vazirani problem, we show that $\textsf{NISQ}$ only needs a number of queries logarithmic in what is required for $\textsf{BPP}$. Finally, for a quantum state learning problem, we prove that $\textsf{NISQ}$ is exponentially weaker than classical computation with access to noiseless constant-depth quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise can be helpful for variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06723</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Frederik Wilde, Antonio Anna Mele, Liang Jiang, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Saddle points constitute a crucial challenge for first-order gradient descent algorithms. In notions of classical machine learning, they are avoided for example by means of stochastic gradient descent methods. In this work, we provide evidence that the saddle points problem can be naturally avoided in variational quantum algorithms by exploiting the presence of stochasticity. We prove convergence guarantees of the approach and its practical functioning at hand of examples. We argue that the natural stochasticity of variational algorithms can be beneficial for avoiding strict saddle points, i.e., those saddle points with at least one negative Hessian eigenvalue. This insight that some noise levels could help in this perspective is expected to add a new perspective to notions of near-term variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Unitary property testing lower bounds by polynomials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05885</link>
    <author>Adrian She, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study unitary property testing, where a quantum algorithm is given query access to a black-box unitary and has to decide whether it satisfies some property. In addition to containing the standard quantum query complexity model (where the unitary encodes a binary string) as a special case, this model contains "inherently quantum" problems that have no classical analogue. Characterizing the query complexity of these problems requires new algorithmic techniques and lower bound methods. Our main contribution is a generalized polynomial method for unitary property testing problems. By leveraging connections with invariant theory, we apply this method to obtain lower bounds on problems such as determining recurrence times of unitaries, approximating the dimension of a marked subspace, and approximating the entanglement entropy of a marked state. We also present a unitary property testing-based approach towards an oracle separation between $\mathsf{QMA}$ and $\mathsf{QMA(2)}$, a long standing question in quantum complexity theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum divide and conquer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06419</link>
    <author>Andrew M. Childs, Robin Kothari, Matt Kovacs-Deak, Aarthi Sundaram, Daochen Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The divide-and-conquer framework, used extensively in classical algorithm design, recursively breaks a problem of size $n$ into smaller subproblems (say, $a$ copies of size $n/b$ each), along with some auxiliary work of cost $C^{\textrm{aux}}(n)$, to give a recurrence relation $$C(n) ≤a \,C(n/b) + C^\textrmaux(n)$$ for the classical complexity $C(n)$. We describe a quantum divide-and-conquer framework that, in certain cases, yields an analogous recurrence relation $$C_Q(n) ≤\sqrta \u2009C_Q(n/b) + O(C^\textrmaux_Q(n))$$ that characterizes the quantum query complexity. We apply this framework to obtain near-optimal quantum query complexities for various string problems, such as (i) recognizing regular languages; (ii) decision versions of String Rotation and String Suffix; and natural parameterized versions of (iii) Longest Increasing Subsequence and (iv) Longest Common Subsequence.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Circuit depth versus energy in topologically ordered systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06796</link>
    <author>Arkin Tikku, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove a nontrivial circuit-depth lower bound for preparing a low-energy state of a locally interacting quantum many-body system in two dimensions, assuming the circuit is geometrically local. For preparing any state which has an energy density of at most $\epsilon$ with respect to Kitaev's toric code Hamiltonian on a two dimensional lattice $\Lambda$, we prove a lower bound of $\Omega\left(\min\left(1/\epsilon^{\frac{1-\alpha}{2}}, \sqrt{|\Lambda|}\right)\right)$ for any $\alpha >0$. We discuss two implications. First, our bound implies that the lowest energy density obtainable from a large class of existing variational circuits (e.g., Hamiltonian variational ansatz) cannot, in general, decay exponentially with the circuit depth. Second, if long-range entanglement is present in the ground state, this can lead to a nontrivial circuit-depth lower bound even at nonzero energy density. Unlike previous approaches to prove circuit-depth lower bounds for preparing low energy states, our proof technique does not rely on the ground state to be degenerate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Depth in the Random Oracle Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06454</link>
    <author>Atul Singh Arora, Andrea Coladangelo, Matthew Coudron, Alexandru Gheorghiu, Uttam Singh, Hendrik Waldner</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a comprehensive characterization of the computational power of shallow quantum circuits combined with classical computation. Specifically, for classes of search problems, we show that the following statements hold, relative to a random oracle: (a) $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}}} \neq \mathsf{BQP}$. This refutes Jozsa's conjecture [QIP 05] in the random oracle model. As a result, this gives the first instantiatable separation between the classes by replacing the oracle with a cryptographic hash function, yielding a resolution to one of Aaronson's ten semi-grand challenges in quantum computing. (b) $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}} \nsubseteq \mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}}$ and $\mathsf{QNC}^{\mathsf{BPP}} \nsubseteq \mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{QNC}}$. This shows that there is a subtle interplay between classical computation and shallow quantum computation. In fact, for the second separation, we establish that, for some problems, the ability to perform adaptive measurements in a single shallow quantum circuit, is more useful than the ability to perform polynomially many shallow quantum circuits without adaptive measurements. (c) There exists a 2-message proof of quantum depth protocol. Such a protocol allows a classical verifier to efficiently certify that a prover must be performing a computation of some minimum quantum depth. Our proof of quantum depth can be instantiated using the recent proof of quantumness construction by Yamakawa and Zhandry [STOC 22].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement-based quantum computation in finite one-dimensional systems: string order implies computational power</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.05089</link>
    <author>Robert Raussendorf, Wang Yang, Arnab Adhikary</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a new framework for assessing the power of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) on short-range entangled symmetric resource states, in spatial dimension one. It requires fewer assumptions than previously known. The formalism can handle finitely extended systems (as opposed to the thermodynamic limit), and does not require translation-invariance. Further, we strengthen the connection between MBQC computational power and string order. Namely, we establish that whenever a suitable set of string order parameters is non-zero, a corresponding set of unitary gates can be realized with fidelity arbitrarily close to unity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Random-Bond Ising Model and its dual in Hyperbolic Spaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07227</link>
    <author>Benedikt Placke, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the thermodynamic properties of the random-bond Ising model (RBIM) on closed hyperbolic surfaces using Monte Carlo and high-temperature series expansion techniques. We also analyze the dual-RBIM, that is the model that in the absence of disorder is related to the RBIM via the Kramers-Wannier duality. Even on self-dual lattices this model is different from the RBIM, unlike in the euclidean case. We explain this anomaly by a careful re-derivation of the Kramers--Wannier duality. For the (dual-)RBIM, we compute the paramagnet-to-ferromagnet phase transition as a function of both temperature $T$ and the fraction of antiferromagnetic bonds $p$. We find that as temperature is decreased in the RBIM, the paramagnet gives way to either a ferromagnet or a spin-glass phase via a second-order transition compatible with mean-field behavior. In contrast, the dual-RBIM undergoes a strongly first order transition from the paramagnet to the ferromagnet both in the absence of disorder and along the Nishimori line. We study both transitions for a variety of hyperbolic tessellations and comment on the role of coordination number and curvature. The extent of the ferromagnetic phase in the dual-RBIM corresponds to the correctable phase of hyperbolic surface codes under independent bit- and phase-flip noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Representation Theory for Geometric Quantum Machine Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07980</link>
    <author>Michael Ragone, Paolo Braccia, Quynh T. Nguyen, Louis Schatzki, Patrick J. Coles, Frederic Sauvage, Martin Larocca, M. Cerezo</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent advances in classical machine learning have shown that creating models with inductive biases encoding the symmetries of a problem can greatly improve performance. Importation of these ideas, combined with an existing rich body of work at the nexus of quantum theory and symmetry, has given rise to the field of Geometric Quantum Machine Learning (GQML). Following the success of its classical counterpart, it is reasonable to expect that GQML will play a crucial role in developing problem-specific and quantum-aware models capable of achieving a computational advantage. Despite the simplicity of the main idea of GQML -- create architectures respecting the symmetries of the data -- its practical implementation requires a significant amount of knowledge of group representation theory. We present an introduction to representation theory tools from the optics of quantum learning, driven by key examples involving discrete and continuous groups. These examples are sewn together by an exposition outlining the formal capture of GQML symmetries via "label invariance under the action of a group representation", a brief (but rigorous) tour through finite and compact Lie group representation theory, a reexamination of ubiquitous tools like Haar integration and twirling, and an overview of some successful strategies for detecting symmetries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Post-Quantum Zero-Knowledge with Space-Bounded Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06093</link>
    <author>Prabhanjan Ananth, Alex B. Grilo</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The traditional definition of quantum zero-knowledge stipulates that the knowledge gained by any quantum polynomial-time verifier in an interactive protocol can be simulated by a quantum polynomial-time algorithm. One drawback of this definition is that it allows the simulator to consume significantly more computational resources than the verifier. We argue that this drawback renders the existing notion of quantum zero-knowledge not viable for certain settings, especially when dealing with near-term quantum devices. In this work, we initiate a fine-grained notion of post-quantum zero-knowledge that is more compatible with near-term quantum devices. We introduce the notion of $(s,f)$ space-bounded quantum zero-knowledge. In this new notion, we require that an $s$-qubit malicious verifier can be simulated by a quantum polynomial-time algorithm that uses at most $f(s)$-qubits, for some function $f(\cdot)$, and no restriction on the amount of the classical memory consumed by either the verifier or the simulator. We explore this notion and establish both positive and negative results: - For verifiers with logarithmic quantum space $s$ and (arbitrary) polynomial classical space, we show that $(s,f)$-space-bounded QZK, for $f(s)=2s$, can be achieved based on the existence of post-quantum one-way functions. Moreover, our protocol runs in constant rounds. - For verifiers with super-logarithmic quantum space $s$, assuming the existence of post-quantum secure one-way functions, we show that $(s,f)$-space-bounded QZK protocols, with fully black-box simulation (classical analogue of black-box simulation) can only be achieved for languages in BQP.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>