<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Saturation and recurrence of quantum complexity in random quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09734</link>
    <author>Michał Oszmaniec, Michał Horodecki, Nicholas Hunter-Jones</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum complexity is a measure of the minimal number of elementary operations required to approximately prepare a given state or unitary channel. Recently, this concept has found applications beyond quantum computing -- in studying the dynamics of quantum many-body systems and the long-time properties of AdS black holes. In this context Brown and Susskind conjectured that the complexity of a chaotic quantum system grows linearly in time up to times exponential in the system size, saturating at a maximal value, and remaining maximally complex until undergoing recurrences at doubly-exponential times. In this work we prove the saturation and recurrence of the complexity of quantum states and unitaries in a model of chaotic time-evolution based on random quantum circuits, in which a local random unitary transformation is applied to the system at every time step. Importantly, our findings hold for quite general random circuit models, irrespective of the gate set and geometry of qubit interactions. Our results advance an understanding of the long-time behaviour of chaotic quantum systems and could shed light on the physics of black hole interiors. From a technical perspective our results are based on establishing new quantitative connections between the Haar measure and high-degree approximate designs, as well as the fact that random quantum circuits of sufficiently high depth converge to approximate designs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient and robust estimation of many-qubit Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09567</link>
    <author>Daniel Stilck França, Liubov A. Markovich, V. V. Dobrovitski, Albert H. Werner, Johannes Borregaard</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Characterizing the interactions and dynamics of quantum mechanical systems is an essential task in the development of quantum technologies. We propose a novel protocol for estimating the underlying Hamiltonian dynamics and Markovian noise of a multi-qubit device. It is based on the efficient estimation of the time-derivatives of few qubit observables using polynomial interpolation. For finite range dynamics, our protocol exponentially improves the necessary time-resolution of the measurements and quadratically reduces the overall sample complexity compared to previous approaches. Furthermore, we show that our protocol can characterize the dynamics of systems with algebraically decaying interactions. The implementation of the protocol requires only the preparation of product states and single-qubit measurements, rendering it applicable for the characterization of both current and future quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Topological phases of unitary dynamics: Classification in Clifford category</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09141</link>
    <author>Jeongwan Haah</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A quantum cellular automaton (QCA) or a causal unitary is by definition an automorphism of local operator algebra, by which local operators are mapped to local operators. Quantum circuits of small depth, local Hamiltonian evolutions for short time, and translations (shifts) are examples. A Clifford QCA is one that maps any Pauli operator to a finite tensor product of Pauli operators. Here, we obtain a complete table of groups $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p)$ of translation invariant Clifford QCA in any spatial dimension $\mathsf d \ge 0$ modulo Clifford quantum circuits and shifts over prime $p$-dimensional qudits, where the circuits and shifts are allowed to obey only coarser translation invariance. The group $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p)$ is nonzero only for $\mathsf d = 2k+3$ if $p=2$ and $\mathsf d = 4k+3$ if $p$ is odd where~$k \ge 0$ is any integer, in which case $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p) \cong \widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p)$, the classical Witt group of nonsingular quadratic forms over the finite field $\mathbb F_p$. It is well known that $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_2) \cong \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z$, $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p) \cong \mathbb Z/4\mathbb Z$ if $p = 3 \bmod 4$, and $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p)\cong \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z \oplus \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z$ if $p = 1 \bmod 4$. The classification is achieved by a dimensional descent, which is a reduction of Laurent extension theorems for algebraic $L$-groups of surgery theory in topology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Candidate for a self-correcting quantum memory in two dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09767</link>
    <author>Simon Lieu, Yu-Jie Liu, Alexey V. Gorshkov</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An interesting problem in the field of quantum error correction involves finding a physical system that hosts a "self-correcting quantum memory," defined as an encoded qubit coupled to an environment that naturally wants to correct errors. To date, a quantum memory stable against finite-temperature effects is only known in four spatial dimensions or higher. Here, we take a different approach to realize a stable quantum memory by relying on a driven-dissipative environment. We propose a new model which appears to self correct against both bit-flip and phase-flip errors in two dimensions: A square lattice composed of photonic "cat qubits" coupled via dissipative terms which tend to fix errors locally. Inspired by the presence of two distinct $\mathbb{Z}_2$-symmetry-broken phases, our scheme relies on Ising-like dissipators to protect against bit flips and on a driven-dissipative photonic environment to protect against phase flips.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Correlations in typicality and an affirmative solution to the exact catalytic entropy conjecture</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08915</link>
    <author>Henrik Wilming</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I show that if a finite-dimensional density matrix has strictly smaller von Neumann entropy than a second one of the same dimension (and the rank is not bigger), then sufficiently (but finitely) many tensor-copies of the first density matrix majorize a density matrix whose single-body marginals are all exactly equal to the second density matrix. This implies an affirmative solution of the exact catalytic entropy conjecture (CEC) introduced by Boes et al. [PRL 122, 210402 (2019)]. Both the Lemma and the solution to the CEC transfer to the classical setting of finite-dimensional probability vectors (with permutations of entries instead of unitary transformations for the CEC).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tensor Network Algorithms: a Route Map</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.10345</link>
    <author>Mari Carmen Bañuls</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tensor networks provide extremely powerful tools for the study of complex classical and quantum many-body problems. Over the last two decades, the increment in the number of techniques and applications has been relentless, and especially the last ten years have seen an explosion of new ideas and results that may be overwhelming for the newcomer. This short review introduces the basic ideas, the best established methods and some of the most significant algorithmic developments that are expanding the boundaries of the tensor network potential. The goal is to help the reader not only appreciate the many possibilities offered by tensor networks, but also find their way through state-of-the-art codes, their applicability and some avenues of ongoing progress.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimising shadow tomography with generalised measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08990</link>
    <author>H. Chau Nguyen, Jan Lennart Bönsel, Jonathan Steinberg, Otfried Gühne</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Advances in quantum technology require scalable techniques to efficiently extract information from a quantum system, such as expectation values of observables or its entropy. Traditional tomography is limited to a handful of qubits and shadow tomography has been suggested as a scalable replacement for larger systems. Shadow tomography is conventionally analysed based on outcomes of ideal projective measurements on the system upon application of randomised unitaries. Here, we suggest that shadow tomography can be much more straightforwardly formulated for generalised measurements, or positive operator valued measures. Based on the idea of the least-square estimator, shadow tomography with generalised measurements is both more general and simpler than the traditional formulation with randomisation of unitaries. In particular, this formulation allows us to analyse theoretical aspects of shadow tomography in detail. For example, we provide a detailed study of the implication of symmetries in shadow tomography. Shadow tomography with generalised measurements is also indispensable in realistic implementation of quantum mechanical measurements, when noise is unavoidable. Moreover, we also demonstrate how the optimisation of measurements for shadow tomography tailored toward a particular set of observables can be carried out.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Estimating the frame potential of large-scale quantum circuit sampling using tensor networks up to 50 qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09900</link>
    <author>Minzhao Liu, Junyu Liu, Yuri Alexeev, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop numerical protocols for estimating the frame potential, the 2-norm distance between a given ensemble and the exact Haar randomness, using the \textttQTensor platform. Our tensor-network-based algorithm has polynomial complexity for shallow circuits and is high performing using CPU and GPU parallelism. We apply the above methods to two problems: the Brown-Susskind conjecture, with local and parallel random circuits in terms of the Haar distance and the approximate $k$-design properties of the hardware efficient ansätze in quantum machine learning, which induce the barren plateau problem. We estimate frame potentials with these ensembles up to 50 qubits and $k=5$, examine the Haar distance of the hardware-efficient ansätze, and verify the Brown-Susskind conjecture numerically. Our work shows that large-scale tensor network simulations could provide important hints toward open problems in quantum information science.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Machine learning applications for noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09414</link>
    <author>Brian Coyle</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum machine learning has proven to be a fruitful area in which to search for potential applications of quantum computers. This is particularly true for those available in the near term, so called noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. In this Thesis, we develop and study three quantum machine learning applications suitable for NISQ computers, ordered in terms of increasing complexity of data presented to them. These algorithms are variational in nature and use parameterised quantum circuits (PQCs) as the underlying quantum machine learning model. The first application area is quantum classification using PQCs, where the data is classical feature vectors and their corresponding labels. Here, we study the robustness of certain data encoding strategies in such models against noise present in a quantum computer. The second area is generative modelling using quantum computers, where we use quantum circuit Born machines to learn and sample from complex probability distributions. We discuss and present a framework for quantum advantage for such models, propose gradient-based training methods and demonstrate these both numerically and on the Rigetti quantum computer up to 28 qubits. For our final application, we propose a variational algorithm in the area of approximate quantum cloning, where the data becomes quantum in nature. For the algorithm, we derive differentiable cost functions, prove theoretical guarantees such as faithfulness, and incorporate state of the art methods such as quantum architecture search. Furthermore, we demonstrate how this algorithm is useful in discovering novel implementable attacks on quantum cryptographic protocols, focusing on quantum coin flipping and key distribution as examples.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Say NO to Optimization: A Non-Orthogonal Quantum Eigensolver</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09039</link>
    <author>Unpil Baek, Diptarka Hait, James Shee, Oskar Leimkuhler, William J. Huggins, Torin F. Stetina, Martin Head-Gordon, K. Birgitta Whaley</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A balanced description of both static and dynamic correlations in electronic systems with nearly degenerate low-lying states presents a challenge for multi-configurational methods on classical computers. We present here a quantum algorithm utilizing the action of correlating cluster operators to provide high-quality wavefunction ansätze employing a non-orthogonal multireference basis that captures a significant portion of the exact wavefunction in a highly compact manner, and that allows computation of the resulting energies and wavefunctions at polynomial cost with a quantum computer. This enables a significant improvement over the corresponding classical non-orthogonal solver, which incurs an exponential cost when evaluating off-diagonal matrix elements between the ansatz states, and is therefore intractable. We implement the non-orthogonal quantum eigensolver (NOQE) here with an efficient ansatz parameterization inspired by classical quantum chemistry methods that succeed in capturing significant amounts of electronic correlation accurately. By taking advantage of classical methods for chemistry, NOQE provides a flexible, compact, and rigorous description of both static and dynamic electronic correlation, making it an attractive method for the calculation of electronic states of a wide range of molecular systems.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>