<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A polynomial-time classical algorithm for noisy random circuit sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03999</link>
    <author>Dorit Aharonov, Xun Gao, Zeph Landau, Yunchao Liu, Umesh Vazirani</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a polynomial time classical algorithm for sampling from the output distribution of a noisy random quantum circuit in the regime of anti-concentration to within inverse polynomial total variation distance. This gives strong evidence that, in the presence of a constant rate of noise per gate, random circuit sampling (RCS) cannot be the basis of a scalable experimental violation of the extended Church-Turing thesis. Our algorithm is not practical in its current form, and does not address finite-size RCS based quantum supremacy experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailoring three-dimensional topological codes for biased noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02116</link>
    <author>Eric Huang, Arthur Pesah, Christopher T. Chubb, Michael Vasmer, Arpit Dua</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tailored topological stabilizer codes in two dimensions have been shown to exhibit high storage threshold error rates and improved subthreshold performance under biased Pauli noise. Three-dimensional (3D) topological codes can allow for several advantages including a transversal implementation of non-Clifford logical gates, single-shot decoding strategies, parallelized decoding in the case of fracton codes as well as construction of fractal lattice codes. Motivated by this, we tailor 3D topological codes for enhanced storage performance under biased Pauli noise. We present Clifford deformations of various 3D topological codes, such that they exhibit a threshold error rate of $50\%$ under infinitely biased Pauli noise. Our examples include the 3D surface code on the cubic lattice, the 3D surface code on a checkerboard lattice that lends itself to a subsystem code with a single-shot decoder, the 3D color code, as well as fracton models such as the X-cube model, the Sierpinski model and the Haah code. We use the belief propagation with ordered statistics decoder (BP-OSD) to study threshold error rates at finite bias. We also present a rotated layout for the 3D surface code, which uses roughly half the number of physical qubits for the same code distance under appropriate boundary conditions. Imposing coprime periodic dimensions on this rotated layout leads to logical operators of weight $O(n)$ at infinite bias and a corresponding $\exp[-O(n)]$ subthreshold scaling of the logical failure rate, where $n$ is the number of physical qubits in the code. Even though this scaling is unstable due to the existence of logical representations with $O(1)$ low-rate Pauli errors, the number of such representations scales only polynomially for the Clifford-deformed code, leading to an enhanced effective distance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Homomorphic Logical Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03625</link>
    <author>Shilin Huang, Tomas Jochym-O'Connor, Theodore J. Yoder</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shor and Steane ancilla are two well-known methods for fault-tolerant logical measurements, which are successful on small codes and their concatenations. On large quantum low-density-parity-check (LDPC) codes, however, Shor and Steane measurements have impractical time and space overhead respectively. In this work, we widen the choice of ancilla codes by unifying Shor and Steane measurements into a single framework, called homomorphic measurements. For any Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) code with the appropriate ancilla code, one can avoid repetitive measurements or complicated ancilla state preparation procedures such as distillation, which overcomes the difficulties of both Shor and Steane methods. As an example, we utilize the theory of covering spaces to construct homomorphic measurement protocols for arbitrary $X$- or $Z$-type logical Pauli operators on surface codes in general, including the toric code and hyperbolic surface codes. Conventional surface code decoders, such as minimum-weight perfect matching, can be directly applied to our constructions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Invertible subalgebras</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02086</link>
    <author>Jeongwan Haah</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce invertible subalgebras of local operator algebras on lattices. An invertible subalgebra is defined to be one such that every local operator can be locally expressed by elements of the inveritible subalgebra and those of the commutant. On a two-dimensional lattice, an invertible subalgebra hosts a chiral anyon theory by a commuting Hamiltonian, which is believed not to be possible on a full local operator algebra. We prove that the stable equivalence classes of $D$-dimensional invertible subalgebras form an abelian group under tensor product, isomorphic to the group of all $D+1$ dimensional QCA modulo blending equivalence and shifts. In an appendix, we consider a metric on the group of all QCA on infinite lattices and prove that the metric completion contains the time evolution by local Hamiltonians, which is only approximately locality-preserving. Our metric topology is strictly finer than the strong topology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Pseudorandom (Function-Like) Quantum State Generators: New Definitions and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01444</link>
    <author>Prabhanjan Ananth, Aditya Gulati, Luowen Qian, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Pseudorandom quantum states (PRS) are efficiently constructible states that are computationally indistinguishable from being Haar-random, and have recently found cryptographic applications. We explore new definitions, new properties and applications of pseudorandom states, and present the following contributions: 1. New Definitions: We study variants of pseudorandom function-like state (PRFS) generators, introduced by Ananth, Qian, and Yuen (CRYPTO'22), where the pseudorandomness property holds even when the generator can be queried adaptively or in superposition. We show feasibility of these variants assuming the existence of post-quantum one-way functions. 2. Classical Communication: We show that PRS generators with logarithmic output length imply commitment and encryption schemes with classical communication. Previous constructions of such schemes from PRS generators required quantum communication. 3. Simplified Proof: We give a simpler proof of the Brakerski--Shmueli (TCC'19) result that polynomially-many copies of uniform superposition states with random binary phases are indistinguishable from Haar-random states. 4. Necessity of Computational Assumptions: We also show that a secure PRS with output length logarithmic, or larger, in the key length necessarily requires computational assumptions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Invertible bimodule categories and generalized Schur orthogonality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01947</link>
    <author>Jacob C. Bridgeman, Laurens Lootens, Frank Verstraete</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Schur orthogonality relations are a cornerstone in the representation theory of groups. We utilize a generalization to weak Hopf algebras to provide a new, readily verifiable condition on the skeletal data for deciding whether a given bimodule category is invertible and therefore defines a Morita equivalence. As a first application, we provide an algorithm for the construction of the full skeletal data of the invertible bimodule category associated to a given module category, which is obtained in a unitary gauge when the underlying categories are unitary. As a second application, we show that our condition for invertibility is equivalent to the notion of MPO-injectivity, thereby closing an open question concerning tensor network representations of string-net models exhibiting topological order. We discuss applications to generalized symmetries, including a generalized Wigner-Eckart theorem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Pauli topological subsystem codes from Abelian anyon theories</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03798</link>
    <author>Tyler D. Ellison, Yu-An Chen, Arpit Dua, Wilbur Shirley, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Dominic J. Williamson</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We construct Pauli topological subsystem codes characterized by arbitrary two-dimensional Abelian anyon theories--this includes anyon theories with degenerate braiding relations and those without a gapped boundary to the vacuum. Our work both extends the classification of two-dimensional Pauli topological subsystem codes to systems of composite-dimensional qudits and establishes that the classification is at least as rich as that of Abelian anyon theories. We exemplify the construction with topological subsystem codes defined on four-dimensional qudits based on the $\mathbb{Z}_4^{(1)}$ anyon theory with degenerate braiding relations and the chiral semion theory--both of which cannot be captured by topological stabilizer codes. The construction proceeds by "gauging out" certain anyon types of a topological stabilizer code. This amounts to defining a gauge group generated by the stabilizer group of the topological stabilizer code and a set of anyonic string operators for the anyon types that are gauged out. The resulting topological subsystem code is characterized by an anyon theory containing a proper subset of the anyons of the topological stabilizer code. We thereby show that every Abelian anyon theory is a subtheory of a stack of toric codes and a certain family of twisted quantum doubles that generalize the double semion anyon theory. We further prove a number of general statements about the logical operators of translation invariant topological subsystem codes and define their associated anyon theories in terms of higher-form symmetries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Certificate games</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03396</link>
    <author>Sourav Chakraborty, Anna Gál, Sophie Laplante, Rajat Mittal, Anupa Sunny</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce and study Certificate Game complexity, a measure of complexity based on the probability of winning a game where two players are given inputs with different function values and are asked to output $i$ such that $x_i\neq y_i$ (zero-communication setting). We give upper and lower bounds for private coin, public coin, shared entanglement and non-signaling strategies, and give some separations. We show that complexity in the public coin model is upper bounded by Randomized query and Certificate complexity. On the other hand, it is lower bounded by fractional and randomized certificate complexity, making it a good candidate to prove strong lower bounds on randomized query complexity. Complexity in the private coin model is bounded from below by zero-error randomized query complexity. The quantum measure highlights an interesting and surprising difference between classical and quantum query models. Whereas the public coin certificate game complexity is bounded from above by randomized query complexity, the quantum certificate game complexity can be quadratically larger than quantum query complexity. We use non-signaling, a notion from quantum information, to give a lower bound of $n$ on the quantum certificate game complexity of the $OR$ function, whose quantum query complexity is $\Theta(\sqrt{n})$, then go on to show that this ``non-signaling bottleneck'' applies to all functions with high sensitivity, block sensitivity or fractional block sensitivity. We consider the single-bit version of certificate games (inputs of the two players have Hamming distance $1$). We prove that the single-bit version of certificate game complexity with shared randomness is equal to sensitivity up to constant factors, giving a new characterization of sensitivity. The single-bit version with private randomness is equal to $\lambda^2$, where $\lambda$ is the spectral sensitivity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An interpretation of Union-Find Decoder on Weighted Graphs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03288</link>
    <author>Yue Wu, Namitha Liyanage, Lin Zhong</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Union-Find (UF) and Minimum-Weight Perfect Matching (MWPM) are popular decoder designs for surface codes. The former has significantly lower time complexity than the latter but is considered somewhat inferior, in terms of decoding accuracy. In this work we present an interpretation of UF decoders that explains why UF and MWPM decoders perform closely in some cases: the UF decoder is an approximate implementation of the blossom algorithm used for MWPM. This interpretation allows a generalization of UF decoders for weighted decoding graphs and explains why UF decoders achieve high accuracy for certain surface codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Conventions for Quantum Pseudocode</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02559</link>
    <author>E. Knill</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A few conventions for thinking about and writing quantum pseudocode are proposed. The conventions can be used for presenting any quantum algorithm down to the lowest level and are consistent with a quantum random access machine (QRAM) model for quantum computing. In principle a formal version of quantum pseudocode could be used in a future extension of a conventional language.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>