<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Clifford Circuits can be Properly PAC Learned if and only if $\textsf{RP}=\textsf{NP}$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06638</link>
    <author>Daniel Liang</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a dataset of input states, measurements, and probabilities, is it possible to efficiently predict the measurement probabilities associated with a quantum circuit? Recent work of Caro and Datta (2020) studied the problem of PAC learning quantum circuits in an information theoretic sense, leaving open questions of computational efficiency. In particular, one candidate class of circuits for which an efficient learner might have been possible was that of Clifford circuits, since the corresponding set of states generated by such circuits, called stabilizer states, are known to be efficiently PAC learnable (Rocchetto 2018). Here we provide a negative result, showing that proper learning of CNOT circuits is hard for classical learners unless $\textsf{RP} = \textsf{NP}$. As the classical analogue and subset of Clifford circuits, this naturally leads to a hardness result for Clifford circuits as well. Additionally, we show that if $\textsf{RP} = \textsf{NP}$ then there would exist efficient proper learning algorithms for CNOT and Clifford circuits. By similar arguments, we also find that an efficient proper quantum learner for such circuits exists if and only if $\textsf{NP} \subseteq \textsf{RQP}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Imaging stars with quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06044</link>
    <author>Zixin Huang, Gavin K. Brennen, Yingkai Ouyang</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The development of high-resolution, large-baseline optical interferometers would revolutionize astronomical imaging. However, classical techniques are hindered by physical limitations including loss, noise, and the fact that the received light is generally quantum in nature. We show how to overcome these issues using quantum communication techniques. We present a general framework for using quantum error correction codes for protecting and imaging starlight received at distant telescope sites. In our scheme, the quantum state of light is coherently captured into a non-radiative atomic state via Stimulated Raman Adiabatic Passage, which is then imprinted into a quantum error correction code. The code protects the signal during subsequent potentially noisy operations necessary to extract the image parameters. We show that even a small quantum error correction code can offer significant protection against noise. For large codes, we find noise thresholds below which the information can be preserved. Our scheme represents an application for near-term quantum devices that can increase imaging resolution beyond what is feasible using classical techniques.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ground state preparation and energy estimation on early fault-tolerant quantum computers via quantum eigenvalue transformation of unitary matrices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.05955</link>
    <author>Yulong Dong, Lin Lin, Yu Tong</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Under suitable assumptions, the algorithms in [Lin, Tong, Quantum 2020] can estimate the ground state energy and prepare the ground state of a quantum Hamiltonian with near-optimal query complexities. However, this is based on a block encoding input model of the Hamiltonian, whose implementation is known to require a large resource overhead. We develop a tool called quantum eigenvalue transformation of unitary matrices with real polynomials (QET-U), which uses a controlled Hamiltonian evolution as the input model, a single ancilla qubit and no multi-qubit control operations, and is thus suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum devices. This leads to a simple quantum algorithm that outperforms all previous algorithms with a comparable circuit structure for estimating the ground state energy. For a class of quantum spin Hamiltonians, we propose a new method that exploits certain anti-commutation relations and further removes the need of implementing the controlled Hamiltonian evolution. Coupled with Trotter based approximation of the Hamiltonian evolution, the resulting algorithm can be very suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum devices. We demonstrate the performance of the algorithm using IBM Qiskit for the transverse field Ising model. If we are further allowed to use multi-qubit Toffoli gates, we can then implement amplitude amplification and a new binary amplitude estimation algorithm, which increases the circuit depth but decreases the total query complexity. The resulting algorithm saturates the near-optimal complexity for ground state preparation and energy estimating using a constant number of ancilla qubits (no more than 3).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Establishing trust in quantum computations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07568</link>
    <author>Timothy Proctor, Stefan Seritan, Erik Nielsen, Kenneth Rudinger, Kevin Young, Robin Blume-Kohout, Mohan Sarovar</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Real-world quantum computers have grown sufficiently complex that they can no longer be simulated by classical supercomputers, but their computational power remains limited by errors. These errors corrupt the results of quantum algorithms, and it is no longer always feasible to use classical simulations to directly check the correctness of quantum computations. Without practical methods for quantifying the accuracy with which a quantum algorithm has been executed, it is difficult to establish trust in the results of a quantum computation. Here we solve this problem, by introducing a simple and efficient technique for measuring the fidelity with which an as-built quantum computer can execute an algorithm. Our technique converts the algorithm's quantum circuits into a set of closely related circuits whose success rates can be efficiently measured. It enables measuring the fidelity of quantum algorithm executions both in the near-term, with algorithms run on hundreds or thousands of physical qubits, and into the future, with algorithms run on logical qubits protected by quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tight Bounds for Quantum State Certification with Incoherent Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07155</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Brice Huang, Jerry Li, Allen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of quantum state certification, where we are given the description of a mixed state $\sigma \in \mathbb{C}^{d \times d}$, $n$ copies of a mixed state $\rho \in \mathbb{C}^{d \times d}$, and $\varepsilon > 0$, and we are asked to determine whether $\rho = \sigma$ or whether $\| \rho - \sigma \|_1 > \varepsilon$. When $\sigma$ is the maximally mixed state $\frac{1}{d} I_d$, this is known as mixedness testing. We focus on algorithms which use incoherent measurements, i.e. which only measure one copy of $\rho$ at a time. Unlike those that use entangled, multi-copy measurements, these can be implemented without persistent quantum memory and thus represent a large class of protocols that can be run on current or near-term devices. For mixedness testing, there is a folklore algorithm which uses incoherent measurements and only needs $O(d^{3/2} / \varepsilon^2)$ copies. The algorithm is non-adaptive, that is, its measurements are fixed ahead of time, and is known to be optimal for non-adaptive algorithms. However, when the algorithm can make arbitrary incoherent measurements, the best known lower bound is only $\Omega (d^{4/3} / \varepsilon^2)$ [Bubeck-Chen-Li '20], and it has been an outstanding open problem to close this polynomial gap. In this work, 1) we settle the copy complexity of mixedness testing with incoherent measurements and show that $\Omega (d^{3/2} / \varepsilon^2)$ copies are necessary, and 2) we show the instance-optimal bounds for state certification to general $\sigma$ first derived by [Chen-Li-O'Donnell '21] for non-adaptive measurements also hold for arbitrary incoherent measurements. Qualitatively, our results say that adaptivity does not help at all for these problems. Our results are based on new techniques that allow us to reduce the problem to understanding certain matrix martingales, which we believe may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matrix product operator algebras I: representations of weak Hopf algebras and projected entangled pair states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.05940</link>
    <author>Andras Molnar, Alberto Ruiz de Alarcón, José Garre-Rubio, Norbert Schuch, J. Ignacio Cirac, David Pérez-García</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Matrix Product Operators (MPOs) are tensor networks representing operators acting on 1D systems. They model a wide variety of situations, including communication channels with memory effects, quantum cellular automata, mixed states in 1D quantum systems, or holographic boundary models associated to 2D quantum systems. A scenario where MPOs have proven particularly useful is to represent algebras of non-trivial symmetries. Concretely, the boundary of both symmetry protected and topologically ordered phases in 2D quantum systems exhibit symmetries in the form of MPOs. In this paper, we develop a theory of MPOs as representations of algebraic structures. We establish a dictionary between algebra and MPO properties which allows to transfer results between both setups, covering the cases of pre-bialgebras, weak bialgebras, and weak Hopf algebras. We define the notion of pulling-through algebras, which abstracts the minimal requirements needed to define topologically ordered 2D tensor networks from MPO algebras. We show, as one of our main results, that any semisimple pivotal weak Hopf algebra is a pulling-trough algebra. We demonstrate the power of this framework by showing that they can be used to construct Kitaev's quantum double models for Hopf algebras solely from an MPO representation of the Hopf algebra, in the exact same way as MPO symmetries obtained from fusion categories can be used to construct Levin-Wen string-net models, and to explain all their topological features; it thus allows to describe both Kitaev and string-net models on the same formal footing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matrix Product Operator Algebras II: Phases of Matter for 1D Mixed States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06295</link>
    <author>Alberto Ruiz de Alarcón, José Garre-Rubio, András Molnár, David Pérez-García</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The classification of topological phases of matter is fundamental to understand and characterize the properties of quantum materials. In this paper we study phases of matter in one-dimensional open quantum systems. We define two mixed states to be in the same phase if both states can be transformed into the other by a shallow circuit of local quantum channels. We aim to understand the phase diagram of matrix product density operators that are renormalization fixed points. These states arise, for example, as boundaries of two-dimensional topologically ordered states. We first construct families of such states based on C*-weak Hopf algebras, the algebras whose representations form a fusion category. More concretely, we provide explicit local fine-graining and local coarse-graining quantum channels for the renormalization procedure of these states. Finally, we prove that those arising from C*-Hopf algebras are in the trivial phase.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>ADAPT-VQE is insensitive to rough parameter landscapes and barren plateaus</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07179</link>
    <author>Harper R. Grimsley, George S. Barron, Edwin Barnes, Sophia E. Economou, Nicholas J. Mayhall</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum eigensolvers (VQEs) represent a powerful class of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms for computing molecular energies. Various numerical issues exist for these methods, however, including barren plateaus and large numbers of local minima. In this work, we consider Adaptive, Problem-Tailored (ADAPT)-VQE ansätze, and examine how they are impacted by these local minima. We find that while ADAPT-VQE does not remove local minima, the gradient-informed, one-operator-at-a-time circuit construction seems to accomplish two things: First, it provides an initialization strategy that is dramatically better than random initialization, and which is applicable in situations where chemical intuition cannot help with initialization, i.e., when Hartree-Fock is a poor approximation to the ground state. Second, even if an ADAPT-VQE iteration converges to a local trap at one step, it can still "burrow" toward the exact solution by adding more operators, which preferentially deepens the occupied trap. This same mechanism helps highlight a surprising feature of ADAPT-VQE: It should not suffer optimization problems due to "barren plateaus". Even if barren plateaus appear in the parameter landscape, our analysis and simulations reveal that ADAPT-VQE avoids such regions by design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum many-body systems in thermal equilibrium</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08349</link>
    <author>Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The thermal or equilibrium ensemble is one of the most ubiquitous states of matter. For models comprised of many locally interacting quantum particles, it describes a wide range of physical situations, relevant to condensed matter physics, high energy physics, quantum chemistry and quantum computing, among others. We give a pedagogical overview of some of the most important universal features about the physics and complexity of these states, which have the locality of the Hamiltonian at its core. We focus on mathematically rigorous statements, many of them inspired by ideas and tools from quantum information theory. These include bounds on their correlations, the form of the subsystems, various statistical properties, and the performance of classical and quantum algorithms. We also include a summary of a few of the most important technical tools, as well as some self-contained proofs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Density Matrix Renormalization Group with Tensor Processing Units</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.05693</link>
    <author>Martin Ganahl, Jackson Beall, Markus Hauru, Adam G. M. Lewis, Jae Hyeon Yoo, Yijian Zou, Guifre Vidal</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Google's Tensor Processing Units (TPUs) are integrated circuits specifically built to accelerate and scale up machine learning workloads. They can perform fast distributed matrix multiplications and therefore be repurposed for other computationally intensive tasks. In this work we demonstrate the use of TPUs for accelerating and scaling up the density matrix renormalization group (DMRG), a powerful numerical approach to compute the ground state of a local quantum many-body Hamiltonian. The cost of DMRG scales with system size $N$ as $O(ND^3)$, where the so-called bond dimension $D$ regulates how expressive the underlying matrix product state (MPS) variational ansatz is. We consider lattice models in two spatial dimensions, with square lattices of size $10\times 10$ (free fermions) and $20\times 20$ (transverse field Ising model), for which the required MPS bond dimension is known to scale at least as $\exp(\sqrt{N})$. Using half of a TPU v3 pod (namely $1,\!024$ TPU v3 cores) we reached an unprecedentedly large bond dimension $D = 2^{16} = 65,\!536$, for which optimizing a single MPS tensor took about 2 minutes.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>