<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Physics of Quantum Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08064</link>
    <author>John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Rapid ongoing progress in quantum information science makes this an apt time for a Solvay Conference focused on The Physics of Quantum Information. Here I review four intertwined themes encompassed by this topic: Quantum computer science, quantum hardware, quantum matter, and quantum gravity. Though the time scale for broad practical impact of quantum computation is still uncertain, in the near future we can expect noteworthy progress toward scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing, and discoveries enabled by programmable quantum simulators. In the longer term, controlling highly complex quantum matter will open the door to profound scientific advances and powerful new technologies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal algorithms for learning quantum phase states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07851</link>
    <author>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Sergey Bravyi, Arkopal Dutt, Theodore J. Yoder</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the complexity of learning $n$-qubit quantum phase states. A degree-$d$ phase state is defined as a superposition of all $2^n$ basis vectors $x$ with amplitudes proportional to $(-1)^{f(x)}$, where $f$ is a degree-$d$ Boolean polynomial over $n$ variables. We show that the sample complexity of learning an unknown degree-$d$ phase state is $\Theta(n^d)$ if we allow separable measurements and $\Theta(n^{d-1})$ if we allow entangled measurements. Our learning algorithm based on separable measurements has runtime $\textsf{poly}(n)$ (for constant $d$) and is well-suited for near-term demonstrations as it requires only single-qubit measurements in the Pauli $X$ and $Z$ bases. We show similar bounds on the sample complexity for learning generalized phase states with complex-valued amplitudes. We further consider learning phase states when $f$ has sparsity-$s$, degree-$d$ in its $\mathbb{F}_2$ representation (with sample complexity $O(2^d sn)$), $f$ has Fourier-degree-$t$ (with sample complexity $O(2^{2t})$), and learning quadratic phase states with $\varepsilon$-global depolarizing noise (with sample complexity $O(n^{1+\varepsilon})$). These learning algorithms give us a procedure to learn the diagonal unitaries of the Clifford hierarchy and IQP circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mean estimation when you have the source code; or, quantum Monte Carlo methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07544</link>
    <author>Robin Kothari, Ryan O'Donnell</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Suppose $\boldsymbol{y}$ is a real random variable, and one is given access to ``the code'' that generates it (for example, a randomized or quantum circuit whose output is $\boldsymbol{y}$). We give a quantum procedure that runs the code $O(n)$ times and returns an estimate $\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}}$ for $\mu = \mathrm{E}[\boldsymbol{y}]$ that with high probability satisfies $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/n$, where $\sigma = \mathrm{stddev}[\boldsymbol{y}]$. This dependence on $n$ is optimal for quantum algorithms. One may compare with classical algorithms, which can only achieve the quadratically worse $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/\sqrt{n}$. Our method improves upon previous works, which either made additional assumptions about $\boldsymbol{y}$, and/or assumed the algorithm knew an a priori bound on $\sigma$, and/or used additional logarithmic factors beyond $O(n)$. The central subroutine for our result is essentially Grover's algorithm but with complex phases.ally Grover's algorithm but with complex phases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadows of fermions with particle number symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08964</link>
    <author>Guang Hao Low</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider classical shadows of fermion wavefunctions with $\eta$ particles occupying $n$ modes. We prove that of all $k$-reduced density matrices may be simultaneously estimated to an average variance of $\epsilon^{2}$ using at most $\binom{\eta}{k}\big(1-\frac{\eta-k}{n}\big)^{k}\frac{1+n}{1+n-k}/\epsilon^{2}$ measurements in random single-particle bases that conserve particle number, and provide an estimator that is computationally efficient. This is a super-exponential improvement over the $\binom{n}{k}\sqrt{\pi k}/\epsilon^{2}$ scaling of prior approaches as $n$ can be arbitrarily larger than $\eta$ in natural problems. Our method, in the worst-case of half-filling, still provides a factor of $4^{k}$ advantage in sample complexity, and also estimates all $\eta$-reduced density matrices, applicable to estimating overlaps with all single Slater determinants, with at most $\frac{4}{3}/\epsilon^{2}$ samples, which is additionally independent of $\eta$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Solving boolean satisfiability problems with the quantum approximate optimization algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06909</link>
    <author>Sami Boulebnane, Ashley Montanaro</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) is one of the most prominent proposed applications for near-term quantum computing. Here we study the ability of QAOA to solve hard constraint satisfaction problems, as opposed to optimization problems. We focus on the fundamental boolean satisfiability problem, in the form of random $k$-SAT. We develop analytic bounds on the average success probability of QAOA over random boolean formulae at the satisfiability threshold, as the number of variables $n$ goes to infinity. The bounds hold for fixed parameters and when $k$ is a power of 2. We complement these theoretical results with numerical results on the performance of QAOA for small $n$, showing that these match the limiting theoretical bounds closely. We then use these results to compare QAOA with leading classical solvers. In the case of random 8-SAT, we find that for around 14 ansatz layers, QAOA matches the scaling performance of the highest-performance classical solver we tested, WalkSATlm. For larger numbers of layers, QAOA outperforms WalkSATlm, with an ultimate level of advantage that is still to be determined. Our methods provide a framework for analysing the performance of QAOA for hard constraint satisfaction problems and finding further speedups over classical algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Putting paradoxes to work: contextuality in measurement-based quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06624</link>
    <author>Robert Raussendorf</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a joint cohomological framework for measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC) and the corresponding contextuality proofs. The central object in this framework is an element in the second cohomology group of the chain complex describing a given MBQC. It contains the function computed, up to gauge equivalence, and at the same time is a contextuality witness. The present cohomological description only applies to temporally flat MBQCs, and we outline an approach for extending it to the temporally ordered case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A hybrid framework for estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08416</link>
    <author>You Zhou, Zhenhuan Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states, such as the moment $\tr(\rho^m)$, is of fundamental and practical interest in quantum science and technology. Here we show a quantum-classical hybrid framework to measure them, where the quantum part is constituted by the generalized swap test, and the classical part is realized by postprocessing the result from randomized measurements. This hybrid framework utilizes the partial coherent power of the intermediate-scale quantum processor and, at the same time, dramatically reduces the number of quantum measurements and the cost of classical postprocessing. We demonstrate the advantage of our framework in the tasks of state-moment estimation and quantum error mitigation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum circuits for solving local fermion-to-qubit mappings</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07192</link>
    <author>Jannes Nys, Giuseppe Carleo</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Local Hamiltonians of fermionic systems on a lattice can be mapped onto local qubit Hamiltonians. Maintaining the locality of the operators comes at the expense of increasing the Hilbert space with auxiliary degrees of freedom. In order to retrieve the lower-dimensional physical Hilbert space that represents fermionic degrees of freedom, one must satisfy a set of constraints. In this work, we introduce quantum circuits that exactly satisfy these stringent constraints. We demonstrate how maintaining locality allows one to carry out a Trotterized time-evolution with constant circuit depth per time step. Our construction is particularly advantageous to simulate the time evolution operator of fermionic systems in d>1 dimensions. We also discuss how these families of circuits can be used as variational quantum states, focusing on two approaches: a first one based on general constant-fermion-number gates, and a second one based on the Hamiltonian variational ansatz where the eigenstates are represented by parametrized time-evolution operators. We apply our methods to the problem of finding the ground state and time-evolved states of the spinless 2D Fermi-Hubbard model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Codimension-2 defects and higher symmetries in (3+1)D topological phases</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07367</link>
    <author>Maissam Barkeshli, Yu-An Chen, Sheng-Jie Huang, Ryohei Kobayashi, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>(3+1)D topological phases of matter can host a broad class of non-trivial topological defects of codimension-1, 2, and 3, of which the well-known point charges and flux loops are special cases. The complete algebraic structure of these defects defines a higher category, and can be viewed as an emergent higher symmetry. This plays a crucial role both in the classification of phases of matter and the possible fault-tolerant logical operations in topological quantum error correcting codes. In this paper, we study several examples of such higher codimension defects from distinct perspectives. We mainly study a class of invertible codimension-2 topological defects, which we refer to as twist strings. We provide a number of general constructions for twist strings, in terms of gauging lower dimensional invertible phases, layer constructions, and condensation defects. We study some special examples in the context of $\mathbb{Z}_2$ gauge theory with fermionic charges, in $\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2$ gauge theory with bosonic charges, and also in non-Abelian discrete gauge theories based on dihedral ($D_n$) and alternating ($A_6$) groups. The intersection between twist strings and Abelian flux loops sources Abelian point charges, which defines an $H^4$ cohomology class that characterizes part of an underlying 3-group symmetry of the topological order. The equations involving background gauge fields for the 3-group symmetry have been explicitly written down for various cases. We also study examples of twist strings interacting with non-Abelian flux loops (defining part of a non-invertible higher symmetry), examples of non-invertible codimension-2 defects, and examples of interplay of codimension-2 defects with codimension-1 defects. We also find an example of geometric, not fully topological, twist strings in (3+1)D $A_6$ gauge theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The grammar of the Ising model: A new complexity hierarchy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08301</link>
    <author>Tobias Reinhart, Gemma De las Cuevas</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>How complex is an Ising model? Usually, this is measured by the computational complexity of its ground state energy problem. Yet, this complexity measure only distinguishes between planar and non-planar interaction graphs, and thus fails to capture properties such as the average node degree, the number of long range interactions, or the dimensionality of the lattice. Herein, we introduce a new complexity measure for Ising models and thoroughly classify Ising models with respect to it. Specifically, given an Ising model we consider the decision problem corresponding to the function graph of its Hamiltonian, and classify this problem in the Chomsky hierarchy. We prove that the language of this decision problem is (i) regular if and only if the Ising model is finite, (ii) constructive context free if and only if the Ising model is linear and its edge language is regular, (iii) constructive context sensitive if and only if the edge language of the Ising model is context sensitive, and (iv) decidable if and only if the edge language of the Ising model is decidable. We apply this theorem to show that the 1d Ising model and the Ising model on layerwise complete graphs are constructive context free, and the 2d Ising model, the all-to-all Ising model, and the Ising model on perfect binary trees are constructive context sensitive. We also provide a grammar for the 1d and 2d Ising model. This work is a first step in the characterisation of physical interactions in terms of grammars.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>