<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Time-energy uncertainty relation for noisy quantum metrology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13707</link>
    <author>Philippe Faist, Mischa P. Woods, Victor V. Albert, Joseph M. Renes, Jens Eisert, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Detection of weak forces and precise measurement of time are two of the many applications of quantum metrology to science and technology. We consider a quantum system initialized in a pure state and whose evolution is goverened by a Hamiltonian $H$; a measurement can later estimate the time $t$ for which the system has evolved. In this work, we introduce and study a fundamental trade-off which relates the amount by which noise reduces the accuracy of a quantum clock to the amount of information about the energy of the clock that leaks to the environment. Specifically, we consider an idealized scenario in which Alice prepares an initial pure state of the clock, allows the clock to evolve for a time $t$ that is not precisely known, and then transmits the clock through a noisy channel to Bob. The environment (Eve) receives any information that is lost. We prove that Bob's loss of quantum Fisher information (QFI) about $t$ is equal to Eve's gain of QFI about a complementary energy parameter. We also prove a more general trade-off that applies when Bob and Eve wish to estimate the values of parameters associated with two non-commuting observables. We derive the necessary and sufficient conditions for the accuracy of the clock to be unaffected by the noise. These are a subset of the Knill-Laflamme error-correction conditions; states satisfying these conditions are said to form a metrological code. We provide a scheme to construct metrological codes in the stabilizer formalism. We show that there are metrological codes that cannot be written as a quantum error-correcting code with similar distance in which the Hamiltonian acts as a logical operator, potentially offering new schemes for constructing states that do not lose any sensitivity upon application of a noisy channel. We discuss applications of our results to sensing using a many-body state subject to erasure or amplitude-damping noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matchgate Shadows for Fermionic Quantum Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13723</link>
    <author>Kianna Wan, William J. Huggins, Joonho Lee, Ryan Babbush</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>"Classical shadows" are estimators of an unknown quantum state, constructed from suitably distributed random measurements on copies of that state [Nature Physics 16, 1050-1057]. Here, we analyze classical shadows obtained using random matchgate circuits, which correspond to fermionic Gaussian unitaries. We prove that the first three moments of the Haar distribution over the continuous group of matchgate circuits are equal to those of the discrete uniform distribution over only the matchgate circuits that are also Clifford unitaries; thus, the latter forms a "matchgate 3-design." This implies that the classical shadows resulting from the two ensembles are functionally equivalent. We show how one can use these matchgate shadows to efficiently estimate inner products between an arbitrary quantum state and fermionic Gaussian states, as well as the expectation values of local fermionic operators and various other quantities, thus surpassing the capabilities of prior work. As a concrete application, this enables us to apply wavefunction constraints that control the fermion sign problem in the quantum-classical auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm (QC-AFQMC) [Nature 603, 416-420], without the exponential post-processing cost incurred by the original approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>What is nonclassical about uncertainty relations?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11779</link>
    <author>Lorenzo Catani, Matthew Leifer, Giovanni Scala, David Schmid, Robert W. Spekkens</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Uncertainty relations express limits on the extent to which the outcomes of distinct measurements on a single state can be made jointly predictable. The existence of nontrivial uncertainty relations in quantum theory is generally considered to be a way in which it entails a departure from the classical worldview. However, this view is undermined by the fact that there exist operational theories which exhibit nontrivial uncertainty relations but which are consistent with the classical worldview insofar as they admit of a generalized-noncontextual ontological model. This prompts the question of what aspects of uncertainty relations, if any, cannot be realized in this way and so constitute evidence of genuine nonclassicality. We here consider uncertainty relations describing the tradeoff between the predictability of a pair of binary-outcome measurements (e.g., measurements of Pauli X and Pauli Z observables in quantum theory). We show that, for a class of theories satisfying a particular symmetry property, the functional form of this predictability tradeoff is constrained by noncontextuality to be below a linear curve. Because qubit quantum theory has the relevant symmetry property, the fact that it has a quadratic tradeoff between these predictabilities is a violation of this noncontextual bound, and therefore constitutes an example of how the functional form of an uncertainty relation can witness contextuality. We also deduce the implications for a selected group of operational foils to quantum theory and consider the generalization to three measurements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying Nonstabilizerness of Matrix Product States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13076</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, Lorenzo Piroli</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Nonstabilizerness, also known as magic, quantifies the number of non-Clifford operations needed in order to prepare a quantum state. As typical measures either involve minimization procedures or a computational cost exponential in the number of qubits $N$, it is notoriously hard to characterize for many-body states. In this work, we show that nonstabilizerness, as quantified by the recently introduced Stabilizer Rényi Entropies (SREs), can be computed efficiently for matrix product states (MPSs). Specifically, given an MPS of bond-dimension $\chi$ and integer Rényi index $n>1$, we show that the SRE can be expressed in terms of the norm of an MPS with bond-dimension $\chi^{2n}$. For translation-invariant states, this allows us to extract magic from a single tensor, the transfer matrix, while for generic MPSs this construction yields a computational cost linear in $N$ and polynomial in $\chi$. We exploit this observation to revisit the study of ground-state magic in the quantum Ising chain, providing accurate numerical results up to large system sizes. We analyze the SRE near criticality and investigate its dependence on the local computational basis. We show that it is in general not maximal at the critical point, and interpret our findings in terms of ``long-range magic''.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Publicly verifiable quantum money from random lattices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13135</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu, Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Publicly verifiable quantum money is a protocol for the preparation of quantum states that can be efficiently verified by any party for authenticity but is computationally infeasible to counterfeit. We develop a cryptographic scheme for publicly verifiable quantum money based on Gaussian superpositions over random lattices. We introduce a verification-of-authenticity procedure based on the lattice discrete Fourier transform, and subsequently prove the unforgeability of our quantum money under the hardness of the short vector problem from lattice-based cryptography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14280</link>
    <author>Matthew P. A. Fisher, Vedika Khemani, Adam Nahum, Sagar Vijay</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum circuits -- built from local unitary gates and local measurements -- are a new playground for quantum many-body physics and a tractable setting to explore universal collective phenomena far-from-equilibrium. These models have shed light on longstanding questions about thermalization and chaos, and on the underlying universal dynamics of quantum information and entanglement. In addition, such models generate new sets of questions and give rise to phenomena with no traditional analog, such as new dynamical phases in quantum systems that are monitored by an external observer. Quantum circuit dynamics is also topical in view of experimental progress in building digital quantum simulators that allow control of precisely these ingredients. Randomness in the circuit elements allows a high level of theoretical control, with a key theme being mappings between real-time quantum dynamics and effective classical lattice models or dynamical processes. Many of the universal phenomena that can be identified in this tractable setting apply to much wider classes of more structured many-body dynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Resources for bosonic quantum computational advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11781</link>
    <author>Ulysse Chabaud, Mattia Walschaers</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers promise to dramatically outperform their classical counterparts. However, the non-classical resources enabling such computational advantages are challenging to pinpoint, as it is not a single resource but the subtle interplay of many that can be held responsible for these potential advantages. In this work, we show that every bosonic quantum computation can be recast into a continuous-variable sampling computation where all computational resources are contained in the input state. Using this reduction, we derive a general classical algorithm for the strong simulation of bosonic computations, whose complexity scales with the non-Gaussian stellar rank of both the input state and the measurement setup. We further study the conditions for an efficient classical simulation of the associated continuous-variable sampling computations and identify an operational notion of non-Gaussian entanglement based on the lack of passive separability, thus clarifying the interplay of bosonic quantum computational resources such as squeezing, non-Gaussianity and entanglement.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Do Quantum Circuit Born Machines Generalize?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13645</link>
    <author>Kaitlin Gili, Mohamed Hibat-Allah, Marta Mauri, Chris Ballance, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In recent proposals of quantum circuit models for generative tasks, the discussion about their performance has been limited to their ability to reproduce a known target distribution. For example, expressive model families such as Quantum Circuit Born Machines (QCBMs) have been almost entirely evaluated on their capability to learn a given target distribution with high accuracy. While this aspect may be ideal for some tasks, it limits the scope of a generative model's assessment to its ability to memorize data rather than generalize. As a result, there has been little understanding of a model's generalization performance and the relation between such capability and the resource requirements, e.g., the circuit depth and the amount of training data. In this work, we leverage upon a recently proposed generalization evaluation framework to begin addressing this knowledge gap. We first investigate the QCBM's learning process of a cardinality-constrained distribution and see an increase in generalization performance while increasing the circuit depth. In the 12-qubit example presented here, we observe that with as few as 30% of the valid patterns as the training set, the QCBM exhibits the best generalization performance toward generating unseen and valid patterns. Lastly, we assess the QCBM's ability to generalize not only to valid features, but to high-quality bitstrings distributed according to an adequately biased distribution. We see that the QCBM is able to effectively learn the bias and generate unseen samples with higher quality than those in the training set. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work in the literature that presents the QCBM's generalization performance as an integral evaluation metric for quantum generative models, and demonstrates the QCBM's ability to generalize to high-quality, desired novel samples.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The minimal communication cost for simulating entangled qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.12457</link>
    <author>Martin J. Renner, Marco Túlio Quintino</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyse the amount of classical communication required to reproduce the statistics of local projective measurements on a general pair of entangled qubits, $|\Psi_{AB}>=\sqrt{p}\ |00>+\sqrt{1-p}\ |11>$ ($1/2\leq p \leq 1$). We construct a classical protocol that perfectly simulates local projective measurements on all entangled qubit pairs by communicating one classical trit. Additionally, when $\frac{2p(1-p)}{2p-1} \log{\left(\frac{p}{1-p}\right)}+2(1-p)\leq1$, approximately $0.835 \leq p \leq 1$, we present a classical protocol that requires only a single bit of communication. The latter model even allows a perfect classical simulation with an average communication cost that approaches zero in the limit where the degree of entanglement approaches zero ($p \to 1$). This proves that the communication cost for simulating weakly entangled qubit pairs is strictly smaller than for the maximally entangled one.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Many-body quantum chaos and emergence of Ginibre ensemble</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.12390</link>
    <author>Saumya Shivam, Andrea De Luca, David A. Huse, Amos Chan</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish a connection between many-body quantum chaotic (MBQC) systems and the Ginibre random matrix ensemble (GinUE) - namely that non-Hermitian GinUE behaviors emerge in spatially-extended MBQC systems in the space direction, just as Hermitian random matrix behaviours emerge in MBQC systems in the time direction. We demonstrate the emergence of GinUE firstly in translational invariant (TI) MBQC systems, which can be associated with dual transfer matrices with complex-valued spectra, before generalizing to spatially-random systems. We argue and demonstrate that the dual spectra of TI MBQC systems necessarily have non-trivial and universal correlations due to the existence of a linear ramp in the spectral form factor (SFF). We show that, firstly, the spectral statistics of the dual spectra, probed by the dissipative spectral form factor and spacing distribution, falls under the universality class of the GinUE, and in particular displays level repulsion in the complex plane. Secondly, we obtain an exact analytical expression of SFF for the GinUE, and show that it universally describes the SFF of TI MBQC systems in the scaling limit where $t$ and $L$ are large, while the ratio between $L$ and $L_{\mathrm{Th}}$, the many body Thouless length is fixed. Thirdly, we propose variations of Ginibre models accounting for time periodicity, such that the SFF of Floquet MBQC (with or without TI) can be analytically described, thereby removing the necessity of TI for the emergence of GinUE. Lastly, we remark that locality and the many-body nature of MBQC systems are required for the emergence of the GinUE in large system sizes.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>