<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Learning Distributions over Quantum Measurement Outcomes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03007</link>
    <author>Weiyuan Gong, Scott Aaronson</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shadow tomography for quantum states provides a sample efficient approach for predicting the properties of quantum systems when the properties are restricted to expectation values of $2$-outcome POVMs. However, these shadow tomography procedures yield poor bounds if there are more than 2 outcomes per measurement. In this paper, we consider a general problem of learning properties from unknown quantum states: given an unknown $d$-dimensional quantum state $\rho$ and $M$ unknown quantum measurements $\mathcal{M}_1,...,\mathcal{M}_M$ with $K\geq 2$ outcomes, estimating the probability distribution for applying $\mathcal{M}_i$ on $\rho$ to within total variation distance $\epsilon$. Compared to the special case when $K=2$, we need to learn unknown distributions instead of values. We develop an online shadow tomography procedure that solves this problem with high success probability requiring $\tilde{O}(K\log^2M\log d/\epsilon^4)$ copies of $\rho$. We further prove an information-theoretic lower bound that at least $\Omega(\min\{d^2,K+\log M\}/\epsilon^2)$ copies of $\rho$ are required to solve this problem with high success probability. Our shadow tomography procedure requires sample complexity with only logarithmic dependence on $M$ and $d$ and is sample-optimal for the dependence on $K$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Concentration bounds for quantum states and limitations on the QAOA from polynomial approximations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02715</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Tony Metger</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove concentration bounds for the following classes of quantum states: (i) output states of shallow quantum circuits, answering an open question from [DPMRF22]; (ii) injective matrix product states; (iii) output states of dense Hamiltonian evolution, i.e. states of the form $e^{\iota H^{(p)}} \cdots e^{\iota H^{(1)}} |\psi_0\rangle$ for any $n$-qubit product state $|\psi_0\rangle$, where each $H^{(i)}$ can be any local commuting Hamiltonian satisfying a norm constraint, including dense Hamiltonians with interactions between any qubits. Our proofs use polynomial approximations to show that these states are close to local operators. This implies that the distribution of the Hamming weight of a computational basis measurement (and of other related observables) concentrates. An example of (iii) are the states produced by the quantum approximate optimisation algorithm (QAOA). Using our concentration results for these states, we show that for a random spin model, the QAOA can only succeed with negligible probability even at super-constant level $p = o(\log \log n)$. This gives the first limitations on the QAOA on dense instances at super-constant level, improving upon the recent result [BGMZ22].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Overcoming entropic limitations on asymptotic state transformations through probabilistic protocols</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03362</link>
    <author>Bartosz Regula, Ludovico Lami, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum relative entropy is known to play a key role in determining the asymptotic convertibility of quantum states in general resource-theoretic settings, often constituting the unique monotone that is relevant in the asymptotic regime. We show that this is no longer the case when one allows stochastic protocols that may only succeed with some probability, in which case the quantum relative entropy is insufficient to characterize the rates of asymptotic state transformations, and a new entropic quantity based on a regularization of Hilbert's projective metric comes into play. Such a scenario is motivated by a setting where the cost associated with transformations of quantum states, typically taken to be the number of copies of a given state, is instead identified with the size of the quantum memory needed to realize the protocol. Our approach allows for constructing transformation protocols that achieve strictly higher rates than those imposed by the relative entropy. Focusing on the task of resource distillation, we give broadly applicable strong converse bounds on the asymptotic rates of probabilistic distillation protocols, and show them to be tight in relevant settings such as entanglement distillation with non-entangling operations. This generalizes and extends previously known limitations that only apply to deterministic protocols. Our methods are based on recent results for probabilistic one-shot transformations as well as a new asymptotic equipartition property for the projective relative entropy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sample optimal tomography of quantum Markov chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02240</link>
    <author>Li Gao, Nengkun Yu</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A state on a tripartite quantum system $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C} $ forms a Markov chain, i.e., quantum conditional independence, if it can be reconstructed from its marginal on $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}$ by a quantum operation from $\mathcal{H}_{B}$ to $\mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C}$ via the famous Petz map: a quantum Markov chain $\rho_{ABC}$ satisfies $\rho_{ABC}=\rho_{BC}^{1/2}(\rho_B^{-1/2}\rho_{AB}\rho_B^{-1/2}\otimes id_C)\rho_{BC}^{1/2}$. In this paper, we study the robustness of the Petz map for different metrics, i.e., the closeness of marginals implies the closeness of the Petz map outcomes. The robustness results are dimension-independent for infidelity $\delta$ and trace distance $\epsilon$. The applications of robustness results are The sample complexity of quantum Markov chain tomography, i.e., how many copies of an unknown quantum Markov chain are necessary and sufficient to determine the state, is $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\delta})$, and $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\epsilon^2}) $. The sample complexity of quantum Markov Chain certification, i.e., to certify whether a tripartite state equals a fixed given quantum Markov Chain $\sigma_{ABC}$ or at least $\delta$-far from $\sigma_{ABC}$, is ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\delta})$, and ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\epsilon^2})$. $\tilde{O}(\frac{\min\{d_Ad_B^3d_C^3,d_A^3d_B^3d_C\}}{\epsilon^2})$ copies to test whether $\rho_{ABC}$ is a quantum Markov Chain or $\epsilon$-far from its Petz recovery state. We generalized the tomography results into multipartite quantum system by showing $\tilde{O}(\frac{n^2\max_{i} \{d_i^2d_{i+1}^2\}}{\delta})$ copies for infidelity $\delta$ are enough for $n$-partite quantum Markov chain tomography with $d_i$ being the dimension of the $i$-th subsystem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Approximation Algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02589</link>
    <author>Robbie King</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give an approximation algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut which works by rounding an SDP relaxation to an entangled quantum state. The SDP is used to choose the parameters of a variational quantum circuit. The entangled state is then represented as the quantum circuit applied to a product state. It achieves an approximation ratio of 0.582, significantly improving on the algorithms of Anshu, Gosset, Morenz, 0.531, and Parekh, Thompson, 0.533. In addition, we also study the EPR Hamiltonian, which we argue is a natural intermediate problem which isolates some key quantum features of local Hamiltonian problems. For the EPR Hamiltonian, we give an approximation algorithm with approximation ratio $\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Accelerating the variational quantum eigensolver using parallelism</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03796</link>
    <author>Lana Mineh, Ashley Montanaro</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers are getting larger and larger, but device fidelities may not be able to keep up with the increase in qubit numbers. One way to make use of a large device that has a limited gate depth is to run many small circuits simultaneously. In this paper we detail our investigations into running circuits in parallel on the Rigetti Aspen-M-1 device. We run two-qubit circuits in parallel to solve a simple instance of the Hubbard model using the variational quantum eigensolver. We present results for running up to 33 circuits in parallel (66 qubits), showing that with the use of error mitigation techniques it is possible to make use of, and gain a real-time speedup from, parallelisation on current quantum hardware. We obtain a speedup by $18\times$ for exploring the VQE energy landscape, and by more than $8\times$ for running VQE optimisation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the computational hardness needed for quantum cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.04101</link>
    <author>Zvika Brakerski, Ran Canetti, Luowen Qian</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the classical model of computation, it is well established that one-way functions (OWF) are essential for almost every computational cryptographic application. In the quantum setting, however, OWFs appear not to be essential (Kretschmer 2021; Ananth et al., Morimae and Yamakawa 2022), and the question of whether a minimal primitive exists remains open. We consider EFI pairs -- efficiently samplable, statistically far but computationally indistinguishable pairs of distributions. Building on the work of Yan (2022) which shows equivalence between EFI pairs and statistical commitment schemes, we show that EFI pairs are necessary and sufficient for a large class of quantum-cryptographic applications. Specifically, while it was known how to construct commitments schemes, oblivious transfer, and general secure multiparty computation from any EFI, we show how to construct EFI pairs from minimalistic versions of each one of these primitives. We also construct from EFI quantum computational zero knowledge ($\mathsf{QCZK}$) proofs for all of $\mathsf{QIP}$, and construct EFI pairs from essentially any non-trivial $\mathsf{QCZK}$. This suggests that, for much of quantum cryptography, EFI pairs play a similar role to that played by OWFs in the classical setting: they are simple to describe, essential, and also serve as a linchpin for demonstrating equivalence between primitives.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable and Flexible Classical Shadow Tomography with Tensor Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02093</link>
    <author>Ahmed A. Akhtar, Hong-Ye Hu, Yi-Zhuang You</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classical shadow tomography is a powerful randomized measurement protocol for predicting many properties of a quantum state with few measurements. Two classical shadow protocols have been extensively studied in the literature: the single-qubit (local) Pauli measurement, which is well suited for predicting local operators but inefficient for large operators; and the global Clifford measurement, which is efficient for low-rank operators but infeasible on near-term quantum devices due to the extensive gate overhead. In this work, we demonstrate a scalable classical shadow tomography approach for generic randomized measurements implemented with finite-depth local Clifford random unitary circuits, which interpolates between the limits of Pauli and Clifford measurements. The method combines the recently proposed locally-scrambled classical shadow tomography framework with tensor network techniques to achieve scalability for computing the classical shadow reconstruction map and evaluating various physical properties. The method enables classical shadow tomography to be performed on shallow quantum circuits with superior sample efficiency and minimal gate overhead and is friendly to noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. We show that the shallow-circuit measurement protocol provides immediate, exponential advantages over the Pauli measurement protocol for predicting quasi-local operators. It also enables a more efficient fidelity estimation compared to the Pauli measurement.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Approximate Degree of DNF and CNF Formulas</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01584</link>
    <author>Alexander A. Sherstov</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The approximate degree of a Boolean function $f\colon\{0,1\}^n\to\{0,1\}$ is the minimum degree of a real polynomial $p$ that approximates $f$ pointwise: $|f(x)-p(x)|\leq1/3$ for all $x\in\{0,1\}^n.$ For every $\delta>0,$ we construct CNF and DNF formulas of polynomial size with approximate degree $\Omega(n^{1-\delta}),$ essentially matching the trivial upper bound of $n.$ This improves polynomially on previous lower bounds and fully resolves the approximate degree of constant-depth circuits ($\text{AC}^0$), a question that has seen extensive research over the past 10 years. Previously, an $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$ lower bound was known only for $\text{AC}^0$ circuits of depth that grows with $1/\delta$ (Bun and Thaler, FOCS 2017). Moreover, our CNF and DNF formulas are the simplest possible in that they have constant width. Our result holds even for one-sided approximation, and has the following further consequences. (i) We essentially settle the communication complexity of $\text{AC}^0$ circuits in the bounded-error quantum model, $k$-party number-on-the-forehead randomized model, and $k$-party number-on-the-forehead nondeterministic model: we prove that for every $\delta>0$, these models require $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$, $\Omega(n/4^kk^2)^{1-\delta}$, and $\Omega(n/4^kk^2)^{1-\delta}$, respectively, bits of communication even for polynomial-size constant-width CNF formulas. (ii) In particular, we show that the multiparty communication class $\text{coNP}_k$ can be separated essentially optimally from $\text{NP}_k$ and $\text{BPP}_k$ by a particularly simple function, a polynomial-size constant-width CNF. (iii) We give an essentially tight separation, of $O(1)$ versus $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$, for the one-sided versus two-sided approximate degree of a function; and $O(1)$ versus $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$ for the one-sided approximate degree of a function $f$ versus its negation $\neg f$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Observational entropy, coarse quantum states, and Petz recovery: information-theoretic properties and bounds</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03803</link>
    <author>Francesco Buscemi, Joseph Schindler, Dominik Šafránek</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Observational entropy provides a general notion of quantum coarse-grained entropy that appropriately interpolates between Boltzmann's and Gibbs' entropies, and has recently been argued to provide a useful measure of out-of-equilibrium thermodynamic entropy. Here we study the mathematical properties of observational entropy from an information-theoretic viewpoint, especially making use of recently strengthened forms of relative entropy monotonicity, approximate recovery, and Petz's transpose map. We present new bounds on observational entropy applying in general, as well as bounds related to sequential and finer/coarser measurements. The general bounds are related to a recovered ``coarse'' state $\rho_{\mathrm{rec}}$, which we show arises both from approximate recovery and from Bayesian state retrodiction given only coarse-grained knowledge. We then discuss an implementable upper bound on distance between this $\rho_{\mathrm{rec}}$ and the true $\rho$, with applications to state identification. As a by-product of the analysis we also rederive from an information-theoretic perspective some main results of observational entropy theory.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>