<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Saturation and recurrence of quantum complexity in random quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09734</link>
    <author>Michał Oszmaniec, Michał Horodecki, Nicholas Hunter-Jones</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum complexity is a measure of the minimal number of elementary operations required to approximately prepare a given state or unitary channel. Recently, this concept has found applications beyond quantum computing -- in studying the dynamics of quantum many-body systems and the long-time properties of AdS black holes. In this context Brown and Susskind conjectured that the complexity of a chaotic quantum system grows linearly in time up to times exponential in the system size, saturating at a maximal value, and remaining maximally complex until undergoing recurrences at doubly-exponential times. In this work we prove the saturation and recurrence of the complexity of quantum states and unitaries in a model of chaotic time-evolution based on random quantum circuits, in which a local random unitary transformation is applied to the system at every time step. Importantly, our findings hold for quite general random circuit models, irrespective of the gate set and geometry of qubit interactions. Our results advance an understanding of the long-time behaviour of chaotic quantum systems and could shed light on the physics of black hole interiors. From a technical perspective our results are based on establishing new quantitative connections between the Haar measure and high-degree approximate designs, as well as the fact that random quantum circuits of sufficiently high depth converge to approximate designs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient and robust estimation of many-qubit Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09567</link>
    <author>Daniel Stilck França, Liubov A. Markovich, V. V. Dobrovitski, Albert H. Werner, Johannes Borregaard</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Characterizing the interactions and dynamics of quantum mechanical systems is an essential task in the development of quantum technologies. We propose a novel protocol for estimating the underlying Hamiltonian dynamics and Markovian noise of a multi-qubit device. It is based on the efficient estimation of the time-derivatives of few qubit observables using polynomial interpolation. For finite range dynamics, our protocol exponentially improves the necessary time-resolution of the measurements and quadratically reduces the overall sample complexity compared to previous approaches. Furthermore, we show that our protocol can characterize the dynamics of systems with algebraically decaying interactions. The implementation of the protocol requires only the preparation of product states and single-qubit measurements, rendering it applicable for the characterization of both current and future quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Topological phases of unitary dynamics: Classification in Clifford category</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09141</link>
    <author>Jeongwan Haah</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A quantum cellular automaton (QCA) or a causal unitary is by definition an automorphism of local operator algebra, by which local operators are mapped to local operators. Quantum circuits of small depth, local Hamiltonian evolutions for short time, and translations (shifts) are examples. A Clifford QCA is one that maps any Pauli operator to a finite tensor product of Pauli operators. Here, we obtain a complete table of groups $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p)$ of translation invariant Clifford QCA in any spatial dimension $\mathsf d \ge 0$ modulo Clifford quantum circuits and shifts over prime $p$-dimensional qudits, where the circuits and shifts are allowed to obey only coarser translation invariance. The group $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p)$ is nonzero only for $\mathsf d = 2k+3$ if $p=2$ and $\mathsf d = 4k+3$ if $p$ is odd where~$k \ge 0$ is any integer, in which case $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p) \cong \widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p)$, the classical Witt group of nonsingular quadratic forms over the finite field $\mathbb F_p$. It is well known that $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_2) \cong \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z$, $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p) \cong \mathbb Z/4\mathbb Z$ if $p = 3 \bmod 4$, and $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p)\cong \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z \oplus \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z$ if $p = 1 \bmod 4$. The classification is achieved by a dimensional descent, which is a reduction of Laurent extension theorems for algebraic $L$-groups of surgery theory in topology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Candidate for a self-correcting quantum memory in two dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09767</link>
    <author>Simon Lieu, Yu-Jie Liu, Alexey V. Gorshkov</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An interesting problem in the field of quantum error correction involves finding a physical system that hosts a "self-correcting quantum memory," defined as an encoded qubit coupled to an environment that naturally wants to correct errors. To date, a quantum memory stable against finite-temperature effects is only known in four spatial dimensions or higher. Here, we take a different approach to realize a stable quantum memory by relying on a driven-dissipative environment. We propose a new model which appears to self correct against both bit-flip and phase-flip errors in two dimensions: A square lattice composed of photonic "cat qubits" coupled via dissipative terms which tend to fix errors locally. Inspired by the presence of two distinct $\mathbb{Z}_2$-symmetry-broken phases, our scheme relies on Ising-like dissipators to protect against bit flips and on a driven-dissipative photonic environment to protect against phase flips.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tensor Network Algorithms: a Route Map</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.10345</link>
    <author>Mari Carmen Bañuls</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tensor networks provide extremely powerful tools for the study of complex classical and quantum many-body problems. Over the last two decades, the increment in the number of techniques and applications has been relentless, and especially the last ten years have seen an explosion of new ideas and results that may be overwhelming for the newcomer. This short review introduces the basic ideas, the best established methods and some of the most significant algorithmic developments that are expanding the boundaries of the tensor network potential. The goal is to help the reader not only appreciate the many possibilities offered by tensor networks, but also find their way through state-of-the-art codes, their applicability and some avenues of ongoing progress.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Estimating the frame potential of large-scale quantum circuit sampling using tensor networks up to 50 qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09900</link>
    <author>Minzhao Liu, Junyu Liu, Yuri Alexeev, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop numerical protocols for estimating the frame potential, the 2-norm distance between a given ensemble and the exact Haar randomness, using the \textttQTensor platform. Our tensor-network-based algorithm has polynomial complexity for shallow circuits and is high performing using CPU and GPU parallelism. We apply the above methods to two problems: the Brown-Susskind conjecture, with local and parallel random circuits in terms of the Haar distance and the approximate $k$-design properties of the hardware efficient ansätze in quantum machine learning, which induce the barren plateau problem. We estimate frame potentials with these ensembles up to 50 qubits and $k=5$, examine the Haar distance of the hardware-efficient ansätze, and verify the Brown-Susskind conjecture numerically. Our work shows that large-scale tensor network simulations could provide important hints toward open problems in quantum information science.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking Quantum Simulators using Quantum Chaos</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12211</link>
    <author>Daniel K. Mark, Joonhee Choi, Adam L. Shaw, Manuel Endres, Soonwon Choi</author>
    <pubDate>May 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose and analyze a sample-efficient protocol to estimate the fidelity between an experimentally prepared state and an ideal target state, applicable to a wide class of analog quantum simulators without advanced sophisticated spatiotemporal control. Our approach utilizes newly discovered universal fluctuations emerging from generic Hamiltonian dynamics, and it does not require any fine-tuned control over state preparation, quantum evolution, or readout capability. It only needs a small number of experimental measurements, achieving near optimal sample complexity: in ideal cases, a percent-level precision is obtained with $\sim 10^3$ measurements independent of system size. Furthermore, the accuracy of our fidelity estimation improves with increasing system size. We numerically demonstrate our protocol for a variety of quantum simulator platforms such as itinerant particles on optical lattices, trapped ions, and Rydberg atoms. We discuss further applications of our method for advanced tasks such as multi-parameter estimation of quantum states and processes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Privacy and correctness trade-offs for information-theoretically secure quantum homomorphic encryption</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12127</link>
    <author>Yanglin Hu, Yingkai Ouyang, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>May 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum homomorphic encryption, which allows computation by a server directly on encrypted data, is a fundamental primitive out of which more complex quantum cryptography protocols can be built. For such constructions to be possible, quantum homomorphic encryption must satisfy two privacy properties: data privacy which ensures that the input data is private from the server, and circuit privacy which ensures that the ciphertext after the computation does not reveal any additional information about the circuit used to perform it, beyond the output of the computation itself. While circuit privacy is well-studied in classical cryptography and many homomorphic encryption schemes can be equipped with it, its quantum analogue has received little attention. Here we establish a definition of circuit privacy for quantum homomorphic encryption with information-theoretic security. Furthermore, we reduce quantum oblivious transfer to quantum homomorphic encryption. Using this reduction, our work unravels fundamental trade-offs between circuit privacy, data privacy and correctness for a broad family of quantum homomorphic encryption protocols, including schemes that allow only computation of Clifford circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classically optimized Hamiltonian simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.11427</link>
    <author>Conor Mc Keever, Michael Lubasch</author>
    <pubDate>May 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Hamiltonian simulation is a promising application for quantum computers to achieve a quantum advantage. We present classical algorithms based on tensor network methods to optimize quantum circuits for this task. We show that the classically optimized circuits can be orders of magnitude more accurate than Trotter product formulas.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The rank of contextuality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.10307</link>
    <author>Karol Horodecki, Jingfang Zhou, Maciej Stankiewicz, Roberto Salazar, Paweł Horodecki, Robert Raussendorf, Ryszard Horodecki, Ravishankar Ramanathan, Emily Tyhurst</author>
    <pubDate>May 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum contextuality is one of the most recognized resources in quantum communication and computing scenarios. We provide a new quantifier of this resource, the rank of contextuality (RC). We define RC as the minimum number of non-contextual behaviors that are needed to simulate a contextual behavior. We show that the logarithm of RC is a natural contextuality measure satisfying several properties considered in the spirit of the resource-theoretic approach. The properties include faithfulness, monotonicity, and additivity under tensor product. We also give examples of how to construct contextual behaviors with an arbitrary value of RC exhibiting a natural connection between this quantifier and the arboricity of an underlying hypergraph. We also discuss exemplary areas of research in which the new measure appears as a natural quantifier.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>