<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The learnability of Pauli noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06362</link>
    <author>Senrui Chen, Yunchao Liu, Matthew Otten, Alireza Seif, Bill Fefferman, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, several noise benchmarking algorithms have been developed to characterize noisy quantum gates on today's quantum devices. A well-known issue in benchmarking is that not everything about quantum noise is learnable due to the existence of gauge freedom, leaving open the question of what information about noise is learnable and what is not, which has been unclear even for a single CNOT gate. Here we give a precise characterization of the learnability of Pauli noise channels attached to Clifford gates, showing that learnable information corresponds to the cycle space of the pattern transfer graph of the gate set, while unlearnable information corresponds to the cut space. This implies the optimality of cycle benchmarking, in the sense that it can learn all learnable information about Pauli noise. We experimentally demonstrate noise characterization of IBM's CNOT gate up to 2 unlearnable degrees of freedom, for which we obtain bounds using physical constraints. In addition, we give an attempt to characterize the unlearnable information by assuming perfect initial state preparation. However, based on the experimental data, we conclude that this assumption is inaccurate as it yields unphysical estimates, and we obtain a lower bound on state preparation noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An efficient decoder for a linear distance quantum LDPC code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06557</link>
    <author>Shouzhen Gu, Christopher A. Pattison, Eugene Tang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recent developments have shown the existence of quantum low-density parity check (qLDPC) codes with constant rate and linear distance. A natural question concerns the efficient decodability of these codes. In this paper, we present a linear time decoder for the recent quantum Tanner codes construction of asymptotically good qLDPC codes, which can correct all errors of weight up to a constant fraction of the blocklength. Our decoder is an iterative algorithm which searches for corrections within constant-sized regions. At each step, the corrections are found by reducing a locally defined and efficiently computable cost function which serves as a proxy for the weight of the remaining error.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tight Bounds for State Tomography with Incoherent Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05265</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Brice Huang, Jerry Li, Allen Liu, Mark Sellke</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the classic question of state tomography: given copies of an unknown quantum state $\rho\in\mathbb{C}^{d\times d}$, output $\widehat{\rho}$ for which $\|\rho - \widehat{\rho}\|_{\mathsf{tr}} \le \varepsilon$. When one is allowed to make coherent measurements entangled across all copies, $\Theta(d^2/\varepsilon^2)$ copies are necessary and sufficient [Haah et al. '17, O'Donnell-Wright '16]. Unfortunately, the protocols achieving this rate incur large quantum memory overheads that preclude implementation on current or near-term devices. On the other hand, the best known protocol using incoherent (single-copy) measurements uses $O(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17], and multiple papers have posed it as an open question to understand whether or not this rate is tight. In this work, we fully resolve this question, by showing that any protocol using incoherent measurements, even if they are chosen adaptively, requires $\Omega(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies, matching the upper bound of [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17]. We do so by a new proof technique which directly bounds the "tilt" of the posterior distribution after measurements, which yields a surprisingly short proof of our lower bound, and which we believe may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient decoding up to a constant fraction of the code length for asymptotically good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07571</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce and analyse an efficient decoder for the quantum Tanner codes of that can correct adversarial errors of linear weight. Previous decoders for quantum low-density parity-check codes could only handle adversarial errors of weight $O(\sqrt{n \log n})$. We also work on the link between quantum Tanner codes and the Lifted Product codes of Panteleev and Kalachev, and show that our decoder can be adapted to the latter. The decoding algorithm alternates between sequential and parallel procedures and converges in linear time.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Composite Quantum Simulations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06409</link>
    <author>Matthew Hagan, Nathan Wiebe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper we provide a framework for combining multiple quantum simulation methods, such as Trotter-Suzuki formulas and QDrift into a single composite channel that builds upon older coalescing ideas for reducing gate counts. The central idea behind our approach is to use a partitioning scheme that allocates a Hamiltonian term to the Trotter or QDrift part of a channel within the simulation. This allows us to simulate small but numerous terms using QDrift while simulating the larger terms using a high-order Trotter-Suzuki formula. We prove rigorous bounds on the diamond distance between the composite channel and the ideal simulation channel and show under what conditions the cost of implementing the composite channel is asymptotically upper bounded by the methods that comprise it for both probabilistic partitioning of terms and deterministic partitioning. Finally, we discuss strategies for determining partitioning schemes as well as methods for incorporating different simulation methods within the same framework.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Average-case hardness of estimating probabilities of random quantum circuits with a linear scaling in the error exponent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05642</link>
    <author>Hari Krovi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the hardness of computing additive approximations to output probabilities of random quantum circuits. We consider three random circuit families, namely, Haar random, $p=1$ QAOA, and random IQP circuits. Our results are as follows. For Haar random circuits with $m$ gates, we improve on prior results by showing $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hardness of average-case additive approximations to an imprecision of $2^{-O(m)}$. Efficient classical simulation of such problems would imply the collapse of the polynomial hierarchy. For constant depth circuits i.e., when $m=O(n)$, this linear scaling in the exponent is within a constant of the scaling required to show hardness of sampling. Prior to our work, such a result was shown only for Boson Sampling in Bouland et al (2021). We also use recent results in polynomial interpolation to show $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hardness under $\mathsf{BPP}$ reductions rather than $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{NP}}$ reductions. This improves the results of prior work for Haar random circuits both in terms of the error scaling and the power of reductions. Next, we consider random $p=1$ QAOA and IQP circuits and show that in the average-case, it is $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hard to approximate the output probability to within an additive error of $2^{-O(n)}$. For $p=1$ QAOA circuits, this work constitutes the first average-case hardness result for the problem of approximating output probabilities for random QAOA circuits, which include Sherrington-Kirkpatrick and Erdös-Renyi graphs. For IQP circuits, a consequence of our results is that approximating the Ising partition function with imaginary couplings to an additive error of $2^{-O(n)}$ is hard even in the average-case, which extends prior work on worst-case hardness of multiplicative approximation to Ising partition functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On Classical and Hybrid Shadows of Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06616</link>
    <author>Saumya Shivam, C. W. von Keyserlingk, S. L. Sondhi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classical shadows are a computationally efficient approach to storing quantum states on a classical computer for the purposes of estimating expectation values of local observables, obtained by performing repeated random measurements. In this note we offer some comments on this approach. We note that the resources needed to form classical shadows with bounded relative error depend strongly on the target state. We then comment on the advantages and limitations of using classical shadows to simulate many-body dynamics. In addition, we introduce the notion of a hybrid shadow, constructed from measurements on a part of the system instead of the entirety, which provides a framework to gain more insight into the nature of shadow states as one reduces the size of the subsystem measured, and a potential alternative to compressing quantum states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Connections between graphs and matrix spaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04815</link>
    <author>Yinan Li, Youming Qiao, Avi Wigderson, Yuval Wigderson, Chuanqi Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a bipartite graph $G$, the graphical matrix space $\mathcal{S}_G$ consists of matrices whose non-zero entries can only be at those positions corresponding to edges in $G$. Tutte (J. London Math. Soc., 1947), Edmonds (J. Res. Nat. Bur. Standards Sect. B, 1967) and Lovász (FCT, 1979) observed connections between perfect matchings in $G$ and full-rank matrices in $\mathcal{S}_G$. Dieudonné (Arch. Math., 1948) proved a tight upper bound on the dimensions of those matrix spaces containing only singular matrices. The starting point of this paper is a simultaneous generalization of these two classical results: we show that the largest dimension over subspaces of $\mathcal{S}_G$ containing only singular matrices is equal to the maximum size over subgraphs of $G$ without perfect matchings, based on Meshulam's proof of Dieudonné's result (Quart. J. Math., 1985). Starting from this result, we go on to establish more connections between properties of graphs and matrix spaces. For example, we establish connections between acyclicity and nilpotency, between strong connectivity and irreducibility, and between isomorphism and conjugacy/congruence. For each connection, we study three types of correspondences, namely the basic correspondence, the inherited correspondence (for subgraphs and subspaces), and the induced correspondence (for induced subgraphs and restrictions). Some correspondences lead to intriguing generalizations of classical results, such as for Dieudonné's result mentioned above, and for a celebrated theorem of Gerstenhaber regarding the largest dimension of nil matrix spaces (Amer. J. Math., 1958). Finally, we show some implications of our results to quantum information and present open problems in computational complexity motivated by these results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Concentration of quantum equilibration and an estimate of the recurrence time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.07541</link>
    <author>Jonathon Riddell, Nathan Pagliaroli, Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the dynamics of generic quantum systems concentrate around their equilibrium value when measuring at arbitrary times. This means that the probability of finding them away from equilibrium is exponentially suppressed, with a decay rate given by the effective dimension. Our result allows us to place a lower bound on the recurrence time of quantum systems, since recurrences corresponds to the rare events of finding a state away from equilibrium. In many-body systems, this bound is doubly exponential in system size. We also show corresponding results for free fermions, which display a weaker concentration and earlier recurrences.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum space, ground space traversal, and how to embed multi-prover interactive proofs into unentanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05243</link>
    <author>Sevag Gharibian, Dorian Rudolph</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Savitch's theorem states that NPSPACE computations can be simulated in PSPACE. We initiate the study of a quantum analogue of NPSPACE, denoted Streaming-QCMASPACE (SQCMASPACE), where an exponentially long classical proof is streamed to a poly-space quantum verifier. Besides two main results, we also show that a quantum analogue of Savitch's theorem is unlikely to hold, as SQCMASPACE=NEXP. For completeness, we introduce Streaming-QMASPACE (SQMASPACE) with an exponentially long streamed quantum proof, and show SQMASPACE=QMA_EXP (quantum analogue of NEXP). Our first main result shows, in contrast to the classical setting, the solution space of a quantum constraint satisfaction problem (i.e. a local Hamiltonian) is always connected when exponentially long proofs are permitted. For this, we show how to simulate any Lipschitz continuous path on the unit hypersphere via a sequence of local unitary gates, at the expense of blowing up the circuit size. This shows quantum error-correcting codes can be unable to detect one codeword erroneously evolving to another if the evolution happens sufficiently slowly, and answers an open question of [Gharibian, Sikora, ICALP 2015] regarding the Ground State Connectivity problem. Our second main result is that any SQCMASPACE computation can be embedded into "unentanglement", i.e. into a quantum constraint satisfaction problem with unentangled provers. Formally, we show how to embed SQCMASPACE into the Sparse Separable Hamiltonian problem of [Chailloux, Sattath, CCC 2012] (QMA(2)-complete for 1/poly promise gap), at the expense of scaling the promise gap with the streamed proof size. As a corollary, we obtain the first systematic construction for obtaining QMA(2)-type upper bounds on arbitrary multi-prover interactive proof systems, where the QMA(2) promise gap scales exponentially with the number of bits of communication in the interactive proof.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>