<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A single $T$-gate makes distribution learning hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03140</link>
    <author>Marcel Hinsche, Marios Ioannou, Alexander Nietner, Jonas Haferkamp, Yihui Quek, Dominik Hangleiter, Jean-Pierre Seifert, Jens Eisert, Ryan Sweke</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The task of learning a probability distribution from samples is ubiquitous across the natural sciences. The output distributions of local quantum circuits form a particularly interesting class of distributions, of key importance both to quantum advantage proposals and a variety of quantum machine learning algorithms. In this work, we provide an extensive characterization of the learnability of the output distributions of local quantum circuits. Our first result yields insight into the relationship between the efficient learnability and the efficient simulatability of these distributions. Specifically, we prove that the density modelling problem associated with Clifford circuits can be efficiently solved, while for depth $d=n^{\Omega(1)}$ circuits the injection of a single $T$-gate into the circuit renders this problem hard. This result shows that efficient simulatability does not imply efficient learnability. Our second set of results provides insight into the potential and limitations of quantum generative modelling algorithms. We first show that the generative modelling problem associated with depth $d=n^{\Omega(1)}$ local quantum circuits is hard for any learning algorithm, classical or quantum. As a consequence, one cannot use a quantum algorithm to gain a practical advantage for this task. We then show that, for a wide variety of the most practically relevant learning algorithms -- including hybrid-quantum classical algorithms -- even the generative modelling problem associated with depth $d=\omega(\log(n))$ Clifford circuits is hard. This result places limitations on the applicability of near-term hybrid quantum-classical generative modelling algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fully undistillable quantum states are separable</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05193</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Nilanjana Datta</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Assume that Alice, Bob, and Eve share a tripartite pure state $|\psi_{ABE}\rangle$. We prove that if Alice cannot distill entanglement with either Bob or Eve using $|\psi_{ABE}\rangle$ and local operations with any one of the following configurations for classical communication: $(A\to B, A\leftrightarrow E), (A\leftrightarrow B, A\to E),$ and $(A\leftrightarrow B, A\leftrightarrow E)$, then the same is also true for the other two configurations. Moreover, this happens precisely when the state is such that both its reductions $\rho_{AB}$ and $\rho_{AE}$ are separable, which is further equivalent to the reductions being PPT. This, in particular, implies that any NPT bipartite state is such that either the state itself or its complement is 2-way distillable. In proving these results, we first obtain an explicit lower bound on the 2-way distillable entanglement of low rank bipartite states. Furthermore, we show that even though not all low rank states are 1-way distillable, a randomly sampled low rank state will almost surely be 1-way distillable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The QAOA gets stuck starting from a good classical string</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05089</link>
    <author>Madelyn Cain, Edward Farhi, Sam Gutmann, Daniel Ranard, Eugene Tang</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) is designed to maximize a cost function over bit strings. While the initial state is traditionally a superposition over all strings, it is natural to try expediting the QAOA: first use a classical algorithm to produce some good string, and then run the ordinary QAOA starting in the computational basis state associated with that string. Here we report numerical experiments that this method of initializing the QAOA fails dramatically, exhibiting little to no improvement of the cost function. We investigate criteria for the rare instances in which there is any improvement at all, and we provide a statistical argument for the more typical case of no improvement. The statistical argument holds for any string that locally mimics the thermal ensemble at the appropriate temperature. Our numerical experiments indicate this property holds for typical good strings. We emphasize that our negative results only apply to our simple incarnation of the warm-start QAOA and may not apply to other approaches in the literature. We hope that our theoretical analysis will inform future algorithm design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Linear programming with unitary-equivariant constraints</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05713</link>
    <author>Dmitry Grinko, Maris Ozols</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Unitary equivariance is a natural symmetry that occurs in many contexts in physics and mathematics. Optimization problems with such symmetry can often be formulated as semidefinite programs for a $d^{p+q}$-dimensional matrix variable that commutes with $U^{\otimes p} \otimes \bar{U}^{\otimes q}$, for all $U \in \mathrm{U}(d)$. Solving such problems naively can be prohibitively expensive even if $p+q$ is small but the local dimension $d$ is large. We show that, under additional symmetry assumptions, this problem reduces to a linear program that can be solved in time that does not scale in $d$, and we provide a general framework to execute this reduction under different types of symmetries. The key ingredient of our method is a compact parametrization of the solution space by linear combinations of walled Brauer algebra diagrams. This parametrization requires the idempotents of a Gelfand--Tsetlin basis, which we obtain by adapting a general method arXiv:1606.08900 inspired by the Okounkov--Vershik approach. To illustrate potential applications, we use several toy examples from quantum information: deciding the principal eigenvalue of a quantum state, quantum majority vote, and asymmetric cloning. We also outline a possible route for extending our method to general unitary-equivariant semidefinite programs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Finite-rate sparse quantum codes aplenty</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03562</link>
    <author>Maxime Tremblay, Guillaume Duclos-Cianci, Stefanos Kourtis</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a methodology for generating random multi-qubit stabilizer codes based on solving a constraint satisfaction problem (CSP) on random bipartite graphs. This framework allows us to enforce stabilizer commutation, X/Z balancing, finite rate, sparsity, and maximum-degree constraints simultaneously in a CSP that we can then solve numerically. Using a state-of-the-art CSP solver, we obtain convincing evidence for the existence of a satisfiability threshold. Furthermore, the extent of the satisfiable phase increases with the number of qubits. In that phase, finding sparse codes becomes an easy problem. Moreover, we observe that the sparse codes found in the satisfiable phase practically achieve the channel capacity for erasure noise. Our results show that intermediate-size finite-rate sparse quantum codes are easy to find, while also demonstrating a flexible methodology for generating good codes with custom properties. We therefore establish a complete and customizable pipeline for random quantum code discovery that can be geared towards near to mid-term quantum processor layouts.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the design and analysis of near-term quantum network protocols using Markov decision processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03403</link>
    <author>Sumeet Khatri</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The quantum internet is one of the frontiers of quantum information science research. It will revolutionize the way we communicate and do other tasks, and it will allow for tasks that are not possible using the current, classical internet. The backbone of a quantum internet is entanglement distributed globally in order to allow for such novel applications to be performed over long distances. Experimental progress is currently being made to realize quantum networks on a small scale, but much theoretical work is still needed in order to understand how best to distribute entanglement, especially with the limitations of near-term quantum technologies taken into account. This work provides an initial step towards this goal. In this work, we lay out a theory of near-term quantum networks based on Markov decision processes (MDPs), and we show that MDPs provide a precise and systematic mathematical framework to model protocols for near-term quantum networks that is agnostic to the specific implementation platform. We start by simplifying the MDP for elementary links introduced in prior work, and by providing new results on policies for elementary links in the steady-state (infinite-time) limit. In particular, we show that the well-known memory-cutoff policy is optimal in the steady-state limit. Then we show how the elementary link MDP can be used to analyze a quantum network protocol in which we wait for all elementary links to be active before creating end-to-end links. We then provide an extension of the MDP formalism to two elementary links, which is useful for analyzing more sophisticated quantum network protocols. Here, as new results, we derive linear programming relaxations that allow us to obtain optimal steady-state policies with respect to the expected fidelity and waiting time of the end-to-end link.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A density-matrix renormalisation group algorithm for simulating quantum circuits with a finite fidelity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05612</link>
    <author>Thomas Ayral, Thibaud Louvet, Yiqing Zhou, Cyprien Lambert, E. Miles Stoudenmire, Xavier Waintal</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop a density-matrix renormalization group (DMRG) algorithm for the simulation of quantum circuits. This algorithm can be seen as the extension of time-dependent DMRG from the usual situation of hermitian Hamiltonian matrices to quantum circuits defined by unitary matrices. For small circuit depths, the technique is exact and equivalent to other matrix product state (MPS) based techniques. For larger depths, it becomes approximate in exchange for an exponential speed up in computational time. Like an actual quantum computer, the quality of the DMRG results is characterized by a finite fidelity. However, unlike a quantum computer, the fidelity depends strongly on the quantum circuit considered. For the most difficult possible circuit for this technique, the so-called "quantum supremacy" benchmark of Google Inc. , we find that the DMRG algorithm can generate bit strings of the same quality as the seminal Google experiment on a single computing core. For a more structured circuit used for combinatorial optimization (Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm or QAOA), we find a drastic improvement of the DMRG results with error rates dropping by a factor of 100 compared with random quantum circuits. Our results suggest that the current bottleneck of quantum computers is their fidelities rather than the number of qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tensor networks in machine learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.02851</link>
    <author>Richik Sengupta, Soumik Adhikary, Ivan Oseledets, Jacob Biamonte</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A tensor network is a type of decomposition used to express and approximate large arrays of data. A given data-set, quantum state or higher dimensional multi-linear map is factored and approximated by a composition of smaller multi-linear maps. This is reminiscent to how a Boolean function might be decomposed into a gate array: this represents a special case of tensor decomposition, in which the tensor entries are replaced by 0, 1 and the factorisation becomes exact. The collection of associated techniques are called, tensor network methods: the subject developed independently in several distinct fields of study, which have more recently become interrelated through the language of tensor networks. The tantamount questions in the field relate to expressability of tensor networks and the reduction of computational overheads. A merger of tensor networks with machine learning is natural. On the one hand, machine learning can aid in determining a factorization of a tensor network approximating a data set. On the other hand, a given tensor network structure can be viewed as a machine learning model. Herein the tensor network parameters are adjusted to learn or classify a data-set. In this survey we recover the basics of tensor networks and explain the ongoing effort to develop the theory of tensor networks in machine learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The concatenation of the Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill code with the XZZX surface code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.04383</link>
    <author>Jiaxuan Zhang, Yu-Chun Wu, Guo-Ping Guo</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bosonic codes provide an alternative option for the quantum error correction. An important category of bosonic codes called the Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) code aroused much interest recently. Theoretically, the error correction ability of GKP code is limited since it can only correct small shift errors in position and momentum quadratures. A natural approach to promote the GKP error correction for large-scale, fault-tolerant quantum computation is concatenating encoded GKP states with a stabilizer code. The performance of the XZZX surface-GKP code, i.e., the single-mode GKP code concatenated with XZZX surface code is investigated in this paper under two different noise models. Firstly, in the code-capacity noise model, the asymmetric rectangular GKP code with parameter $\lambda$ is introduced. Using the minimum weight perfect matching (MWPM) decoder combined with the continuous-variable GKP information, the optimal threshold of the XZZX-surface GKP code reaches $\sigma\approx0.67$ when $\lambda=2.1$, compared with the threshold $\sigma\approx0.60$ of the standard surface-GKP code. Secondly, we analyze the shift errors of two-qubit gates in the actual implementation, and build the full circuit-level noise model. The maximum likelihood decoding strategy is applied to each two-qubit gate with circuit-level noise, and improves the threshold from 18.6 dB in the previous work to 16.5 dB. We also estimate the overhead of the XZZX-surface GKP code which uses about 483 GKP states with squeezing more than 18.5 dB to encode a logical qubits with error rate $7.6\times10^{-6}$, compared with the qubit-based surface code using 1681 qubits to achieve almost the same logical error rate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence between simulability of high-dimensional measurements and high-dimensional steering</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.04080</link>
    <author>Benjamin D.M. Jones, Roope Uola, Thomas Cope, Marie Ioannou, Sébastien Designolle, Pavel Sekatski, Nicolas Brunner</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The effect of quantum steering arises from the judicious combination of an entangled state with a set of incompatible measurements. Recently, it was shown that this form of quantum correlations can be quantified in terms of a dimension, leading to the notion of genuine high-dimensional steering. While this naturally connects to the dimensionality of entanglement (Schmidt number), we show that this effect also directly connects to a notion of dimension for measurement incompatibility. More generally, we present a general connection between the concepts of steering and measurement incompatibility, when quantified in terms of dimension. From this connection, we propose a novel twist on the problem of simulating quantum correlations. Specifically, we show how the correlations of certain high-dimensional entangled states can be exactly recovered using only shared randomness and lower-dimensional entanglement. Finally, we derive criteria for testing the dimension of measurement incompatibility, and discuss the extension of these ideas to quantum channels.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>