<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Towards near-term quantum simulation of materials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15256</link>
    <author>Laura Clinton, Toby Cubitt, Brian Flynn, Filippo Maria Gambetta, Joel Klassen, Ashley Montanaro, Stephen Piddock, Raul A. Santos, Evan Sheridan</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulation of materials is one of the most promising applications of quantum computers. On near-term hardware the crucial constraint on these simulations is circuit depth. Many quantum simulation algorithms rely on a layer of unitary evolutions generated by each term in a Hamiltonian. This appears in time-dynamics as a single Trotter step, and in variational quantum eigensolvers under the Hamiltonian variational ansatz as a single ansatz layer. We present a new quantum algorithm design for materials modelling where the depth of a layer is independent of the system size. This design takes advantage of the locality of materials in the Wannier basis and employs a tailored fermionic encoding that preserves locality. We analyse the circuit costs of this approach and present a compiler that transforms density functional theory data into quantum circuit instructions -- connecting the physics of the material to the simulation circuit. The compiler automatically optimises circuits at multiple levels, from the base gate level to optimisations derived from the physics of the specific target material. We present numerical results for materials spanning a wide structural and technological range. Our results demonstrate a reduction of many orders of magnitude in circuit depth over standard prior methods that do not consider the structure of the Hamiltonian. For example our results improve resource requirements for Strontium Vanadate (SrVO$_3$) from 864 to 180 qubits for a $3\times3\times3$ lattice, and the circuit depth of a single Trotter or variational layer from $7.5\times 10^8$ to depth $730$. Although this is still beyond current hardware, our results show that materials simulation may be feasible on quantum computers without necessarily requiring scalable, fault-tolerant quantum computers, provided quantum algorithm design incorporates understanding of the materials and applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive Online Learning of Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00220</link>
    <author>Xinyi Chen, Elad Hazan, Tongyang Li, Zhou Lu, Xinzhao Wang, Rui Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the fundamental problem of shadow tomography, the goal is to efficiently learn an unknown $d$-dimensional quantum state using projective measurements. However, it is rarely the case that the underlying state remains stationary: changes may occur due to measurements, environmental noise, or an underlying Hamiltonian state evolution. In this paper we adopt tools from adaptive online learning to learn a changing state, giving adaptive and dynamic regret bounds for online shadow tomography that are polynomial in the number of qubits and sublinear in the number of measurements. Our analysis utilizes tools from complex matrix analysis to cope with complex numbers, which may be of independent interest in online learning. In addition, we provide numerical experiments that corroborate our theoretical results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Modular Commutators in Conformal Field Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00027</link>
    <author>Yijian Zou, Bowen Shi, Jonathan Sorce, Ian T. Lim, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The modular commutator is a recently discovered multipartite entanglement measure that quantifies the chirality of the underlying many-body quantum state. In this Letter, we derive a universal expression for the modular commutator in conformal field theories in $1+1$ dimensions and discuss its salient features. We show that the modular commutator depends only on the chiral central charge and the conformal cross ratio. We test this formula for a gapped $2+1$-dimensional system with a chiral edge, i.e., the quantum Hall state, and observe excellent agreement with numerical simulations. Furthermore, we propose the geometric dual of the modular commutator in the AdS/CFT correspondence. We argue that the modular commutator can be obtained from a set of crossing angles between intersecting Ryu-Takayanagi surfaces.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ergodic theory of diagonal orthogonal covariant quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01145</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Nilanjana Datta, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the ergodic properties of quantum channels that are covariant with respect to diagonal orthogonal transformations. We prove that the ergodic behaviour of a channel in this class is essentially governed by a classical stochastic matrix. This allows us to exploit tools from classical ergodic theory to study quantum ergodicity of such channels. As an application of our analysis, we study dual unitary brickwork circuits which have recently been proposed as minimal models of quantum chaos in many-body systems. Upon imposing a local diagonal orthogonal invariance symmetry on these circuits, the long-term behaviour of spatio-temporal correlations between local observables in such circuits is completely determined by the ergodic properties of a channel that is covariant under diagonal orthogonal transformations. We utilize this fact to show that such symmetric dual unitary circuits exhibit a rich variety of ergodic behaviours, thus emphasizing their importance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental single-setting quantum state tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00019</link>
    <author>Roman Stricker, Michael Meth, Lukas Postler, Claire Edmunds, Chris Ferrie, Rainer Blatt, Philipp Schindler, Thomas Monz, Richard Kueng, Martin Ringbauer</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers solve ever more complex tasks using steadily growing system sizes. Characterizing these quantum systems is vital, yet becoming increasingly challenging. The gold-standard is quantum state tomography (QST), capable of fully reconstructing a quantum state without prior knowledge. Measurement and classical computing costs, however, increase exponentially in the system size - a bottleneck given the scale of existing and near-term quantum devices. Here, we demonstrate a scalable and practical QST approach that uses a single measurement setting, namely symmetric informationally complete (SIC) positive operator-valued measures (POVM). We implement these nonorthogonal measurements on an ion trap device by utilizing more energy levels in each ion - without ancilla qubits. More precisely, we locally map the SIC POVM to orthogonal states embedded in a higher-dimensional system, which we read out using repeated in-sequence detections, providing full tomographic information in every shot. Combining this SIC tomography with the recently developed randomized measurement toolbox ("classical shadows") proves to be a powerful combination. SIC tomography alleviates the need for choosing measurement settings at random ("derandomization"), while classical shadows enable the estimation of arbitrary polynomial functions of the density matrix orders of magnitudes faster than standard methods. The latter enables in-depth entanglement studies, which we experimentally showcase on a 5-qubit absolutely maximally entangled (AME) state. Moreover, the fact that the full tomography information is available in every shot enables online QST in real time. We demonstrate this on an 8-qubit entangled state, as well as for fast state identification. All in all, these features single out SIC-based classical shadow estimation as a highly scalable and convenient tool for quantum state characterization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Characterizing and mitigating coherent errors in a trapped ion quantum processor using hidden inverses</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.14225</link>
    <author>Swarnadeep Majumder, Christopher G. Yale, Titus D. Morris, Daniel S. Lobser, Ashlyn D. Burch, Matthew N. H. Chow, Melissa C. Revelle, Susan M. Clark, Raphael C. Pooser</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing testbeds exhibit high-fidelity quantum control over small collections of qubits, enabling performance of precise, repeatable operations followed by measurements. Currently, these noisy intermediate-scale devices can support a sufficient number of sequential operations prior to decoherence such that small algorithms can be performed reliably. While the results of these algorithms are imperfect, these imperfections can help bootstrap quantum computer testbed development. Demonstrations of these small algorithms over the past few years, coupled with the idea that imperfect algorithm performance can be caused by several dominant noise sources in the quantum processor, which can be measured and calibrated during algorithm execution or in post-processing, has led to the use of noise mitigation to improve typical computational results. Conversely, small benchmark algorithms coupled with noise mitigation can help diagnose the nature of the noise, whether systematic or purely random. Here, we outline the use of coherent noise mitigation techniques as a characterization tool in trapped-ion testbeds. We perform model-fitting of the noisy data to determine the noise source based on realistic physics focused noise models and demonstrate that systematic noise amplification coupled with error mitigation schemes provides useful data for noise model deduction. Further, in order to connect lower level noise model details with application specific performance of near term algorithms, we experimentally construct the loss landscape of a variational algorithm under various injected noise sources coupled with error mitigation techniques. This type of connection enables application-aware hardware codesign, in which the most important noise sources in specific applications, like quantum chemistry, become foci of improvement in subsequent hardware generations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-assisted Monte Carlo algorithms for fermions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.14903</link>
    <author>Xiaosi Xu, Ying Li</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing is a promising way to systematically solve the longstanding computational problem, the ground state of a many-body fermion system. Many efforts have been made to realise certain forms of quantum advantage in this problem, for instance, the development of variational quantum algorithms. A recent work by Huggins et al. reports a novel candidate, i.e. a quantum-classical hybrid Monte Carlo algorithm with a reduced bias in comparison to its fully-classical counterpart. In this paper, we propose a family of scalable quantum-assisted Monte Carlo algorithms where the quantum computer is used at its minimal cost and still can reduce the bias. By incorporating a Bayesian inference approach, we can achieve this quantum-facilitated bias reduction with a much smaller quantum-computing cost than taking empirical mean in amplitude estimation. Besides, we show that the hybrid Monte Carlo framework is a general way to suppress errors in the ground state obtained from classical algorithms. Our work provides a Monte Carlo toolkit for achieving quantum-enhanced calculation of fermion systems on near-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Approaching optimal entangling collective measurements on quantum computing platforms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15358</link>
    <author>Lorcan O. Conlon, Tobias Vogl, Christian D. Marciniak, Ivan Pogorelov, Simon K. Yung, Falk Eilenberger, Dominic W. Berry, Fabiana S. Santana, Rainer Blatt, Thomas Monz, Ping Koy Lam, Syed M. Assad</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement is one of the most intriguing features of quantum mechanics and holds great promise for enhancing metrology and communications. Much of the focus of quantum metrology to date has been on generating highly entangled quantum states which offer better sensitivity, per resource, than can be achieved classically [1-3]. However, to reach the ultimate limits in multi-parameter quantum metrology and quantum information processing tasks, collective measurements, which generate entanglement between multiple copies of the quantum state, are necessary [4-6]. There is presently no known method for implementing arbitrary, optimal collective measurements on more than two copies of the quantum state. Here we experimentally demonstrate theoretically optimal single-copy (separable) and two-copy (entangled) collective measurements for simultaneously estimating two non-commuting qubit rotations. This allows us to draw fundamental insights about the interpretation of the uncertainty principle. We implement our optimal measurements on superconducting, trapped-ion and photonic systems, providing an indication of how future quantum-enhanced sensing networks may look. This work offers a pathway to extracting the maximal advantage of quantum mechanics for information processing tasks [7, 8].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Correlations in Molecules: A Quantum Information Toolbox for Chemists</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15881</link>
    <author>Lexin Ding, Stefan Knecht, Zoltán Zimborás, Christian Schilling</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The second quantum revolution is all about exploiting the quantum nature of atoms and molecules to execute quantum information processing tasks. To support this growing endeavor and by anticipating the key role of quantum chemistry therein, our work establishes a toolbox for systematically exploring, quantifying and dissecting correlation effects in quantum chemical systems. By utilizing the geometric picture of quantum states we compare -- on a unified basis and in an operationally meaningful way -- total, quantum and classical correlation and entanglement in molecular ground states. To maximize the quantum informational resourcefulness of molecules an orbital optimization scheme is provided, leading to a paradigm-shifting insight: A single covalent bond equates to the entanglement $2\ln(2)$. This novel and more versatile perspective on electronic structure suggests a generalization of valence bond theory, overcoming deficiencies of modern chemical bonding theories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Quantum and Classical Streaming Complexity of Quantum and Classical Max-Cut</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00213</link>
    <author>John Kallaugher, Ojas Parekh</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the space complexity of two graph streaming problems: Max-Cut and its quantum analogue, Quantum Max-Cut. Previous work by Kapralov and Krachun [STOC `19] resolved the classical complexity of the \emphclassical problem, showing that any $(2 - \varepsilon)$-approximation requires $\Omega(n)$ space (a $2$-approximation is trivial with $\textrm{O}(\log n)$ space). We generalize both of these qualifiers, demonstrating $\Omega(n)$ space lower bounds for $(2 - \varepsilon)$-approximating Max-Cut and Quantum Max-Cut, even if the algorithm is allowed to maintain a quantum state. As the trivial approximation algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut only gives a $4$-approximation, we show tightness with an algorithm that returns a $(2 + \varepsilon)$-approximation to the Quantum Max-Cut value of a graph in $\textrm{O}(\log n)$ space. Our work resolves the quantum and classical approximability of quantum and classical Max-Cut using $\textrm{o}(n)$ space. We prove our lower bounds through the techniques of Boolean Fourier analysis. We give the first application of these methods to sequential one-way quantum communication, in which each player receives a quantum message from the previous player, and can then perform arbitrary quantum operations on it before sending it to the next. To this end, we show how Fourier-analytic techniques may be used to understand the application of a quantum channel.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>