<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum complexity of the Kronecker coefficients</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11454</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Anirban Chowdhury, David Gosset, Vojtech Havlicek, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Whether or not the Kronecker coefficients of the symmetric group count some set of combinatorial objects is a longstanding open question. In this work we show that a given Kronecker coefficient is proportional to the rank of a projector that can be measured efficiently using a quantum computer. In other words a Kronecker coefficient counts the dimension of the vector space spanned by the accepting witnesses of a QMA verifier, where QMA is the quantum analogue of NP. This implies that approximating the Kronecker coefficients to within a given relative error is not harder than a certain natural class of quantum approximate counting problems that captures the complexity of estimating thermal properties of quantum many-body systems. A second consequence is that deciding positivity of Kronecker coefficients is contained in QMA, complementing a recent NP-hardness result of Ikenmeyer, Mulmuley and Walter. We obtain similar results for the related problem of approximating row sums of the character table of the symmetric group. Finally, we discuss an efficient quantum algorithm that approximates normalized Kronecker coefficients to inverse-polynomial additive error.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Qubit, a Coin, and an Advice String Walk Into a Relational Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10332</link>
    <author>Scott Aaronson, Harry Buhrman, William Kretschmer</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Relational problems (those with many possible valid outputs) are different from decision problems, but it is easy to forget just how different. This paper initiates the study of FBQP/qpoly, the class of relational problems solvable in quantum polynomial-time with the help of polynomial-sized quantum advice, along with its analogues for deterministic and randomized computation (FP, FBPP) and advice (/poly, /rpoly). Our first result is that FBQP/qpoly != FBQP/poly, unconditionally, with no oracle -- a striking contrast with what we know about the analogous decision classes. The proof repurposes the separation between quantum and classical one-way communication complexities due to Bar-Yossef, Jayram, and Kerenidis. We discuss how this separation raises the prospect of near-term experiments to demonstrate "quantum information supremacy," a form of quantum supremacy that would not depend on unproved complexity assumptions. Our second result is that FBPP is not contained in FP/poly -- that is, Adleman's Theorem fails for relational problems -- unless PSPACE is contained in NP/poly. Our proof uses IP=PSPACE and time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity. On the other hand, we show that proving FBPP not in FP/poly will be hard, as it implies a superpolynomial circuit lower bound for PromiseBPEXP. We prove the following further results: * Unconditionally, FP != FBPP and FP/poly != FBPP/poly (even when these classes are carefully defined). * FBPP/poly = FBPP/rpoly (and likewise for FBQP). For sampling problems, by contrast, SampBPP/poly != SampBPP/rpoly (and likewise for SampBQP).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Basic quantum subroutines: finding multiple marked elements and summing numbers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10244</link>
    <author>Joran van Apeldoorn, Sander Gribling, Harold Nieuwboer</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We show how to find all $k$ marked elements in a list of size $N$ using the optimal number $O(\sqrt{N k})$ of quantum queries and only a polylogarithmic overhead in the gate complexity, in the setting where one has a small quantum memory. Previous algorithms either incurred a factor $k$ overhead in the gate complexity, or had an extra factor $\log(k)$ in the query complexity. We then consider the problem of finding a multiplicative $\delta$-approximation of $s = \sum_{i=1}^N v_i$ where $v=(v_i) \in [0,1]^N$, given quantum query access to a binary description of $v$. We give an algorithm that does so, with probability at least $1-\rho$, using $O(\sqrt{N \log(1/\rho) / \delta})$ queries (under mild assumptions on $\rho$). This quadratically improves the dependence on $1/\delta$ and $\log(1/\rho)$ compared to a straightforward application of amplitude estimation. To obtain the improved $\log(1/\rho)$ dependence we use the first result.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum entropy thermalization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10165</link>
    <author>Yichen Huang, Aram W. Harrow</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 21 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In an isolated quantum many-body system undergoing unitary evolution, the entropy of a subsystem (smaller than half the system size) thermalizes if at long times, it is to leading order equal to the thermodynamic entropy of the subsystem at the same energy. In this paper, we prove entropy thermalization for a nearly integrable Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model initialized in a pure product state. The model is obtained by adding random all-to-all $4$-body interactions as a perturbation to a random free-fermion model.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Block-encoding structured matrices for data input in quantum computing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10949</link>
    <author>Christoph Sünderhauf, Earl Campbell, Joan Camps</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The cost of data input can dominate the run-time of quantum algorithms. Here, we consider data input of arithmetically structured matrices via block encoding circuits, the input model for the quantum singular value transform and related algorithms. We demonstrate how to construct block encoding circuits based on an arithmetic description of the sparsity and pattern of repeated values of a matrix. We present schemes yielding different subnormalisations of the block encoding; a comparison shows that the best choice depends on the specific matrix. The resulting circuits reduce flag qubit number according to sparsity, and data loading cost according to repeated values, leading to an exponential improvement for certain matrices. We give examples of applying our block encoding schemes to a few families of matrices, including Toeplitz and tridiagonal matrices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum spherical codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11593</link>
    <author>Shubham P. Jain, Joseph T. Iosue, Alexander Barg, Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a framework for constructing quantum codes defined on spheres by recasting such codes as quantum analogues of the classical spherical codes. We apply this framework to bosonic coding, obtaining multimode extensions of the cat codes that can outperform previous constructions while requiring a similar type of overhead. Our polytope-based cat codes consist of sets of points with large separation that at the same time form averaging sets known as spherical designs. We also recast concatenations of qubit CSS codes with cat codes as quantum spherical codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Guidable Local Hamiltonian Problems with Implications to Heuristic Ansätze State Preparation and the Quantum PCP Conjecture</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11578</link>
    <author>Jordi Weggemans, Marten Folkertsma, Chris Cade</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce 'Merlinized' versions of the recently defined Guided Local Hamiltonian problem, which we call 'Guidable Local Hamiltonian' problems. Unlike their guided counterparts, these problems do not have a guiding state provided as a part of the input, but merely come with the promise that one exists and that it satisfies certain constraints. We consider in particular two classes of guiding states: those that can be prepared efficiently by a quantum circuit; and those belonging to a class of quantum states we call classically evaluatable, which have a short classical description from which it is possible to efficiently compute expectation values of local observables classically. We show that guidable local Hamiltonian problems for both classes of guiding states are $\mathsf{QCMA}$-complete in the inverse-polynomial precision setting, but lie within $\mathsf{NP}$ (or $\mathsf{NqP}$) in certain parameter regimes when the guiding state is classically evaluatable. We discuss the implications of these results to heuristic ansätze state preparation and the quantum PCP conjecture. Our completeness results show that, from a complexity-theoretic perspective, classical ansätze prepared by classical heuristics are just as powerful as quantum ansätze prepared by quantum heuristics, so long as one has access to quantum phase estimation. In relation to the quantum PCP conjecture, we (i) define a PCP for $\mathsf{QCMA}$ and show that it is equal to $\mathsf{NP}$ under quantum reductions; (ii) show several no-go results for the existence of quantum gap amplification procedures that preserve certain ground state properties; and (iii) propose two conjectures that can be viewed as stronger versions of the NLTS theorem. Finally, we show that many of our results can be directly modified to obtain similar results for the class $\mathsf{MA}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Provably Efficient Exploration in Quantum Reinforcement Learning with Logarithmic Worst-Case Regret</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10796</link>
    <author>Han Zhong, Jiachen Hu, Yecheng Xue, Tongyang Li, Liwei Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 22 2023</pubDate>
    <description>While quantum reinforcement learning (RL) has attracted a surge of attention recently, its theoretical understanding is limited. In particular, it remains elusive how to design provably efficient quantum RL algorithms that can address the exploration-exploitation trade-off. To this end, we propose a novel UCRL-style algorithm that takes advantage of quantum computing for tabular Markov decision processes (MDPs) with $S$ states, $A$ actions, and horizon $H$, and establish an $\mathcal{O}(\mathrm{poly}(S, A, H, \log T))$ worst-case regret for it, where $T$ is the number of episodes. Furthermore, we extend our results to quantum RL with linear function approximation, which is capable of handling problems with large state spaces. Specifically, we develop a quantum algorithm based on value target regression (VTR) for linear mixture MDPs with $d$-dimensional linear representation and prove that it enjoys $\mathcal{O}(\mathrm{poly}(d, H, \log T))$ regret. Our algorithms are variants of UCRL/UCRL-VTR algorithms in classical RL, which also leverage a novel combination of lazy updating mechanisms and quantum estimation subroutines. This is the key to breaking the $\Omega(\sqrt{T})$-regret barrier in classical RL. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work studying the online exploration in quantum RL with provable logarithmic worst-case regret.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Complexity of Learning (Pseudo)random Dynamics of Black Holes and Other Chaotic Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11013</link>
    <author>Lisa Yang, Netta Engelhardt</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>It has been recently proposed that the naive semiclassical prediction of non-unitary black hole evaporation can be understood in the fundamental description of the black hole as a consequence of ignorance of high-complexity information. Validity of this conjecture implies that any algorithm which is polynomially bounded in computational complexity cannot accurately reconstruct the black hole dynamics. In this work, we prove that such bounded quantum algorithms cannot accurately predict (pseudo)random unitary dynamics, even if they are given access to an arbitrary set of polynomially complex observables under this time evolution; this shows that "learning" a (pseudo)random unitary is computationally hard. We use the common simplification of modeling black holes and more generally chaotic systems via (pseudo)random dynamics. The quantum algorithms that we consider are completely general, and their attempted guess for the time evolution of black holes is likewise unconstrained: it need not be a linear operator, and may be as general as an arbitrary (e.g. decohering) quantum channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the power of quantum entanglement in multipartite quantum XOR games</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11800</link>
    <author>Marius Junge, Carlos Palazuelos</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper we show that, given $k\geq 3$, there exist $k$-player quantum XOR games for which the entangled bias can be arbitrarily larger than the bias of the game when the players are restricted to separable strategies. In particular, quantum entanglement can be a much more powerful resource than local operations and classical communication to play these games. This result shows a strong contrast to the bipartite case, where it was recently proved that the entangled bias is always upper bounded by a universal constant times the one-way classical communication bias.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>