<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A Practical Guide to the Numerical Implementation of Tensor Networks I: Contractions, Decompositions and Gauge Freedom</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02138</link>
    <author>Glen Evenbly</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an overview of the key ideas and skills necessary to begin implementing tensor network methods numerically, which is intended to facilitate the practical application of tensor network methods for researchers that are already versed with their theoretical foundations. These skills include an introduction to the contraction of tensor networks, to optimal tensor decompositions, and to the manipulation of gauge degrees of freedom in tensor networks. The topics presented are of key importance to many common tensor network algorithms such as DMRG, TEBD, TRG, PEPS and MERA.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mitigating the quantum hype</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01925</link>
    <author>Olivier Ezratty</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We are in the midst of quantum hype with some excessive claims of quantum computing potential, many vendors' and even some research organizations' exaggerations, and a funding frenzy for very low technology readiness level startups. Governments are contributing to this hype with their large quantum initiatives and their technology sovereignty aspirations. Technology hypes are not bad per se since they create emulation, drive innovations and also contribute to attracting new talents. It works as scientists and vendors deliver progress and innovation on a continuous basis after a so-called peak of expectations. It fails with exaggerated overpromises and underdeliveries that last too long. It could cut short research and innovation funding, creating some sort of quantum winter. After looking at the shape and form of technology and science hypes and driving some lessons from past hypes, we investigate the current quantum hype and its specifics. We find that, although there is some significant uncertainty on the potential to create real scalable quantum computers, the scientific and vendor fields are relatively sane and solid compared to other technology hypes. The vendors hype has some profound and disruptive impact on the organization of fundamental research. Also, quantum technologies comprise other fields like quantum telecommunications and quantum sensing with a higher technology readiness level, which are less prone to hype. We then make some proposals to mitigate the potential negative effects of the current quantum hype including recommendations on scientific communication to strengthen the trust in quantum science, vendor behavior improvements, benchmarking methodologies, public education and putting in place a responsible research and innovation approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An exact quantum hidden subgroup algorithm and applications to solvable groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04047</link>
    <author>Muhammad Imran, Gabor Ivanyos</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a polynomial time exact quantum algorithm for the hidden subgroup problem in $Z_{m^k}^n$. The algorithm uses the quantum Fourier transform modulo m and does not require factorization of m. For smooth m, i.e., when the prime factors of m are of size poly(log m), the quantum Fourier transform can be exactly computed using the method discovered independently by Cleve and Coppersmith, while for general m, the algorithm of Mosca and Zalka is available. Even for m=3 and k=1 our result appears to be new. We also present applications to compute the structure of abelian and solvable groups whose order has the same (but possibly unknown) prime factors as m. The applications for solvable groups also rely on an exact version of a technique proposed by Watrous for computing the uniform superposition of elements of subgroups.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-inspired classical algorithm for molecular vibronic spectra</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01861</link>
    <author>Changhun Oh, Youngrong Lim, Yat Wong, Bill Fefferman, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Molecular vibronic spectra is an essential property of molecules, which is an important tool to analyze chemical components and study molecular structures. Computing molecular vibronic spectra has been a challenging task, and its best-known classical algorithm scales combinatorially in the system size. Recently, a quantum simulator, specifically Gaussian boson sampling, has been proposed to generate the spectra efficiently. Thus, molecular vibronic spectra is a candidate of tasks for which a quantum device provides a computational advantage. In this work, we propose a quantum-inspired classical algorithm for molecular vibronic spectra. We find an exact solution of the Fourier components of molecular vibronic spectra at zero temperature using the positive $P$-representation method. Thus, we can obtain the molecular vibronic spectra exactly by the inverse Fourier transformation for the solution for a given resolution. We also show that the same method applies to a finite temperature case. Therefore, computing molecular vibronic spectra, which can be mapped to a Gaussian boson sampling, does not require a quantum device. We then generalize the method beyond the Gaussian framework and find that the Fourier components are written as a loop hafnian, the exact computation of which is known to be \#P-hard. It presents an interesting theoretical separation between non-Gaussian boson sampling and Gaussian boson sampling. Meanwhile, since running an actual boson sampling circuit would incur an $1/\text{poly}(N)$ additive error for $N$ samples, we also study the possibility of achieving the same accuracy using a classical algorithm. Interestingly, when there is no squeezing in the process, one may use Gurvits's algorithm to compute the Fourier components within an additive error. We finally provide possible approaches to approximate the Fourier components and discuss their limitations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Counting unitaries of T-depth one</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04163</link>
    <author>Vadym Kliuchnikov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits is $ \sum_{m=1}^{n}\tfrac{1}{m!}\prod_{k=0}^{m-1}(4^n/2^k - 2^k) \times \# \mathcal{C}_n, $ where $\#\mathcal{C}_n$ is the size of the $n$-qubit Clifford group, that is the number of unitaries of T-depth zero. The number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits grows as $2^{\Omega(n^2)} \cdot \# \mathcal{C}_n$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement estimation in tensor network states via sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04089</link>
    <author>Noa Feldman, Augustine Kshetrimayum, Jens Eisert, Moshe Goldstein</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a method for extracting meaningful entanglement measures of tensor network states in general dimensions. Current methods require the explicit reconstruction of the density matrix, which is highly demanding, or the contraction of replicas, which requires an effort exponential in the number of replicas and which is costly in terms of memory. In contrast, our method requires the stochastic sampling of matrix elements of the classically represented reduced states with respect to random states drawn from simple product probability measures constituting frames. Even though not corresponding to physical operations, such matrix elements are straightforward to calculate for tensor network states, and their moments provide the Rényi entropies and negativities as well as their symmetry-resolved components. We test our method on the one-dimensional critical XX chain and the two-dimensional toric code. Although the cost is exponential in the subsystem size, it is sufficiently moderate so that - in contrast with other approaches - accurate results can be obtained on a personal computer for relatively large subsystem sizes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadows with Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03272</link>
    <author>Kaifeng Bu, Dax Enshan Koh, Roy J. Garcia, Arthur Jaffe</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The classical shadow estimation protocol is a noise-resilient and sample-efficient quantum algorithm for learning the properties of quantum systems. Its performance depends on the choice of a unitary ensemble, which must be chosen by a user in advance. What is the weakest assumption that can be made on the chosen unitary ensemble that would still yield meaningful and interesting results? To address this question, we consider the class of Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles, i.e. unitary ensembles that are invariant under multiplication by a Pauli operator. This class includes many previously studied ensembles like the local and global Clifford ensembles as well as locally scrambled unitary ensembles. For this class of ensembles, we provide an explicit formula for the reconstruction map corresponding to the shadow channel and give explicit sample complexity bounds. In addition, we provide two applications of our results. Our first application is to locally scrambled unitary ensembles, where we give explicit formulas for the reconstruction map and sample complexity bounds that circumvent the need to solve an exponential-sized linear system. Our second application is to the classical shadow tomography of quantum channels with Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles. Our results pave the way for more efficient or robust protocols for predicting important properties of quantum states, such as their fidelity, entanglement entropy, and quantum Fisher information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Transitions in Entanglement Complexity in Random Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02648</link>
    <author>Sarah True, Alioscia Hamma</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement is the defining characteristic of quantum mechanics. Bipartite entanglement is characterized by the von Neumann entropy. Entanglement is not just described by a number, however; it is also characterized by its level of complexity. The complexity of entanglement is at the root of the onset of quantum chaos, universal distribution of entanglement spectrum statistics, difficulty of the disentangling algorithm, and temporal entanglement fluctuations. In this paper, we numerically show how a crossover from a simple pattern of entanglement to a universal, complex pattern can be driven by doping a random Clifford circuit with $T$ gates. This work shows that quantum complexity and complex entanglement stem from the conjunction of entanglement and non-stabilizer resources, also known as magic.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Singleton bounds for entanglement-assisted classical and quantum error correcting codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02184</link>
    <author>Manideep Mamindlapally, Andreas Winter</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that entirely information theoretic methods, based on von Neumann entropies and their properties, can be used to derive Singleton bounds on the performance of entanglement-assisted hybrid classical-quantum (EACQ) error correcting codes. Concretely we show that the triple-rate region of qubits, cbits and ebits of possible EACQ codes over arbitrary alphabet sizes is contained in the quantum Shannon theoretic rate region of an associated memoryless erasure channel, which turns out to be a polytope. We show that a large part of this region is attainable by certain EACQ codes, whenever the local alphabet size (i.e. Hilbert space dimension) is large enough, in keeping with known facts about classical and quantum minimum distance separable (MDS) codes: in particular all of its extreme points and several important extremal lines.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Identification of topological phases using classically-optimized variational quantum eigensolver</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02909</link>
    <author>Ken N. Okada, Keita Osaki, Kosuke Mitarai, Keisuke Fujii</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) is regarded as a promising candidate of hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for the near-term quantum computers. Meanwhile, VQE is confronted with a challenge that statistical error associated with the measurement as well as systematic error could significantly hamper the optimization. To circumvent this issue, we propose classically-optimized VQE (co-VQE), where the whole process of the optimization is efficiently conducted on a classical computer. The efficacy of the method is guaranteed by the observation that quantum circuits with a constant (or logarithmic) depth are classically tractable via simulations of local subsystems. In co-VQE, we only use quantum computers to measure nonlocal quantities after the parameters are optimized. As proof-of-concepts, we present numerical experiments on quantum spin models with topological phases. After the optimization, we identify the topological phases by nonlocal order parameters as well as unsupervised machine learning on inner products between quantum states. The proposed method maximizes the advantage of using quantum computers while avoiding strenuous optimization on noisy quantum devices. Furthermore, in terms of quantum machine learning, our study shows an intriguing approach that employs quantum computers to generate data of quantum systems while using classical computers for the learning process.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>