<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13228</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas Breuckmann, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of non-trivial complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). We prove this conjecture by showing that the recently discovered families of constant-rate and linear-distance QLDPC codes correspond to NLTS local Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Sample Complexity Lower Bound for Quantum State Tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11185</link>
    <author>Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that $\Omega(rd/\epsilon)$ copies of an unknown rank-$r$, dimension-$d$ quantum mixed state are necessary in order to learn a classical description with $1 - \epsilon$ fidelity. This improves upon the tomography lower bounds obtained by Haah, et al. and Wright.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical surrogates for quantum learning models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11740</link>
    <author>Franz J. Schreiber, Jens Eisert, Johannes Jakob Meyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The advent of noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers has put the search for possible applications to the forefront of quantum information science. One area where hopes for an advantage through near-term quantum computers are high is quantum machine learning, where variational quantum learning models based on parametrized quantum circuits are discussed. In this work, we introduce the concept of a classical surrogate, a classical model which can be efficiently obtained from a trained quantum learning model and reproduces its input-output relations. As inference can be performed classically, the existence of a classical surrogate greatly enhances the applicability of a quantum learning strategy. However, the classical surrogate also challenges possible advantages of quantum schemes. As it is possible to directly optimize the ansatz of the classical surrogate, they create a natural benchmark the quantum model has to outperform. We show that large classes of well-analyzed re-uploading models have a classical surrogate. We conducted numerical experiments and found that these quantum models show no advantage in performance or trainability in the problems we analyze. This leaves only generalization capability as possible point of quantum advantage and emphasizes the dire need for a better understanding of inductive biases of quantum learning models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11246</link>
    <author>Cica Gustiani, Richard Meister, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods offer a highly promising route to exploiting quantum computers for chemistry tasks. Here we employ methods described in a sister paper to the present report, entitled ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits, in order to solve problems using adaptively evolving quantum circuits. Consistent with prior authors we find that this approach can outperform human-designed circuits such as the coupled-cluster or hardware-efficient ansätze, and we make comparisons for larger instances up to 14 qubits. Moreover we introduce a novel approach to constraining the circuit evolution in the physically relevant subspace, finding that this greatly improves performance and compactness of the circuits. We consider both static and dynamics properties of molecular systems. The emulation environments used is QuESTlink; all resources are open source and linked from this paper.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Pair Measurement Surface Code on Pentagons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12780</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, I present a way to compile the surface code into two-body parity measurements ("pair measurements"), where the pair measurements run along the edges of a Cairo pentagonal tiling. The resulting circuit improves on prior work by Chao et al. by using fewer pair measurements per four-body stabilizer measurement (5 instead of 6) and fewer time steps per round of stabilizer measurement (6 instead of 10). Using Monte Carlo sampling, I show that these improvements increase the threshold of the surface code when compiling into pair measurements from $\approx 0.2\%$ to $\approx 0.4\%$, and also that they improve the teraquop footprint at a $0.1\%$ physical gate error rate from $\approx6000$ qubits to $\approx3000$ qubits. However, I also show that Chao et al's construction will have a smaller teraquop footprint for physical gate error rates below $\approx 0.03\%$ (due to bidirectional hook errors in my construction). I also compare to the planar honeycomb code, showing that although this work does noticeably reduce the gap between the surface code and the honeycomb code (when compiling into pair measurements), the honeycomb code is still more efficient (threshold $\approx 0.8\%$, teraquop footprint at $0.1\%$ of $\approx 1000$).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploring ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11245</link>
    <author>Richard Meister, Cica Gustiani, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gate-level quantum circuits are often derived manually from higher level algorithms. While this suffices for small implementations and demonstrations, ultimately automatic circuit design will be required to realise complex algorithms using hardware-specific operations and connectivity. Here we explore methods for the ab initio creation of circuits within a machine, either a classical computer or a hybrid quantum-classical device. We consider a range of techniques including: methods for introducing new gate structures, optimisation of parameterised circuits and choices of cost functions, and efficient removal of low-value gates exploiting the quantum geometric tensor and other heuristics. Using these principles we tackle the tasks of automatic encoding of unitary processes and translation (recompilation) of a circuit from one form to another. Using emulated quantum computers with various noise-free gate sets we provide simple examples involving up to 10 qubits, corresponding to 20 qubits in the augmented space we use. Further applications of specific relevance to chemistry modelling are considered in a sister paper, 'Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry'.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Monogamy of entanglement between cones</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11805</link>
    <author>Guillaume Aubrun, Alexander Müller-Hermes, Martin Plávala</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A separable quantum state shared between parties $A$ and $B$ can be symmetrically extended to a quantum state shared between party $A$ and parties $B_1,\ldots ,B_k$ for every $k\in\mathbf{N}$. Quantum states that are not separable, i.e., entangled, do not have this property. This phenomenon is known as "monogamy of entanglement". We show that monogamy is not only a feature of quantum theory, but that it characterizes the minimal tensor product of general pairs of convex cones $\mathsf{C}_A$ and $\mathsf{C}_B$: The elements of the minimal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\min} \mathsf{C}_B$ are precisely the tensors that can be symmetrically extended to elements in the maximal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\max} \mathsf{C}^{\otimes_{\max} k}_B$ for every $k\in\mathbf{N}$. Equivalently, the minimal tensor product of two cones is the intersection of the nested sets of $k$-extendible tensors. It is a natural question when the minimal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\min} \mathsf{C}_B$ coincides with the set of $k$-extendible tensors for some finite $k$. We show that this is universally the case for every cone $\mathsf{C}_A$ if and only if $\mathsf{C}_B$ is a polyhedral cone with a base given by a product of simplices. Our proof makes use of a new characterization of products of simplices up to affine equivalence that we believe is of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Playing nonlocal games with phases of quantum matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11252</link>
    <author>Vir B. Bulchandani, Fiona J. Burnell, S. L. Sondhi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The parity game is an example of a nonlocal game: by sharing a Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) state before playing this game, the players can win with a higher probability than is allowed by classical physics. The GHZ state of $N$ qubits is also the ground state of the ferromagnetic quantum Ising model on $N$ qubits in the limit of vanishingly weak quantum fluctuations. Motivated by this observation, we examine the probability that $N$ players who share the ground state of a generic quantum Ising model, which exhibits non-vanishing quantum fluctuations, still win the parity game using the protocol optimized for the GHZ state. Our main result is a modified parity game for which this protocol asymptotically exhibits quantum advantage in precisely the ferromagnetic phase of the quantum Ising model. We further prove that the ground state of the exactly soluble $d=1+1$ transverse-field Ising model can provide a quantum advantage for the parity game over an even wider region, which includes the entire ferromagnetic phase, the critical point and part of the paramagnetic phase. By contrast, we find examples of topological phases and symmetry-protected topological (SPT) phases of matter, namely the deconfined phase of the toric code Hamiltonian and the $\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2$ SPT phase in one dimension, that do not exhibit an analogous quantum advantage away from their fixed points.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A note on the quantum measurement problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.10741</link>
    <author>N. David Mermin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The idea that wave-function collapse is a physical process stems from a misunderstanding of probability and the role it plays in quantum mechanics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal trade-off structure between symmetry, irreversibility, and quantum coherence in quantum processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11086</link>
    <author>Hiroyasu Tajima, Ryuji Takagi, Yui Kuramochi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Symmetry, irreversibility, and quantum coherence are foundational concepts in physics. Here, we present a universal trade-off relation that builds a bridge between these three concepts. This trade-off particularly reveals that (1) under a global symmetry, any attempt to induce local dynamics that change the conserved quantity will cause inevitable irreversibility, and (2) such irreversibility could be mitigated by quantum coherence. Our fundamental relation also admits broad applications in physics and quantum information processing. In the context of thermodynamics, we derive a trade-off relation between entropy production and quantum coherence in arbitrary isothermal processes. We also apply our relation to black hole physics and obtain a universal lower bound on how many bits of classical information thrown into a black hole become unreadable under the Hayden-Preskill model with the energy conservation law. This particularly shows that when the black hole is large enough, under suitable encoding, at least about $m/4$ bits of the thrown $m$ bits will be irrecoverable until 99 percent of the black hole evaporates. As an application to quantum information processing, we provide a lower bound on the coherence cost to implement an arbitrary quantum channel. We employ this bound to obtain a quantitative Wigner-Araki-Yanase theorem that comes with a clear operational meaning, as well as an error-coherence trade-off for unitary gate implementation and an error lower bound for approximate error correction with covariant encoding. Our main relation is based on quantum uncertainty relation, showcasing intimate connections between fundamental physical principles and ultimate operational capability.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>