<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Testing matrix product states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01824</link>
    <author>Mehdi Soleimanifar, John Wright</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Devising schemes for testing the amount of entanglement in quantum systems has played a crucial role in quantum computing and information theory. Here, we study the problem of testing whether an unknown state $|\psi\rangle$ is a matrix product state (MPS) in the property testing model. MPS are a class of physically-relevant quantum states which arise in the study of quantum many-body systems. A quantum state $|\psi_{1,...,n}\rangle$ comprised of $n$ qudits is said to be an MPS of bond dimension $r$ if the reduced density matrix $\psi_{1,...,k}$ has rank $r$ for each $k \in \{1,...,n\}$. When $r=1$, this corresponds to the set of product states. For larger values of $r$, this yields a more expressive class of quantum states, which are allowed to possess limited amounts of entanglement. In the property testing model, one is given $m$ identical copies of $|\psi\rangle$, and the goal is to determine whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ or whether $|\psi\rangle$ is far from all such states. For the case of product states, we study the product test, a simple two-copy test previously analyzed by Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010), and a key ingredient in their proof that $\mathsf{QMA(2)}=\mathsf{QMA}(k)$ for $k \geq 2$. We give a new and simpler analysis of the product test which achieves an optimal bound for a wide range of parameters, answering open problems of Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010) and Montanaro and de Wolf (2016). For the case of $r\geq 2$, we give an efficient algorithm for testing whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ using $m = O(n r^2)$ copies, independent of the dimensions of the qudits, and we show that $\Omega(n^{1/2})$ copies are necessary for this task. This lower bound shows that a dependence on the number of qudits $n$ is necessary, in sharp contrast to the case of product states where a constant number of copies suffices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error correction with fractal topological codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03568</link>
    <author>Arpit Dua, Tomas Jochym-O'Connor, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, a class of fractal surface codes (FSCs), has been constructed on fractal lattices with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$, which admits a fault-tolerant non-Clifford CCZ gate. We investigate the performance of such FSCs as fault-tolerant quantum memories. We prove that there exist decoding strategies with non-zero thresholds for bit-flip and phase-flip errors in the FSCs with Hausdorff dimension $2+\epsilon$. For the bit-flip errors, we adapt the sweep decoder, developed for string-like syndromes in the regular 3D surface code, to the FSCs by designing suitable modifications on the boundaries of the holes in the fractal lattice. Moreover, our adaptation of the sweep decoder for the FSCs maintains its self-correcting and single-shot nature. For the phase-flip errors, we employ the minimum-weight-perfect-matching (MWPM) decoder for the point-like syndromes. We report a sustainable fault-tolerant threshold ($\sim 1.7\%$) under phenomenological noise for the sweep decoder and the code capacity threshold (lower bounded by $2.95\%$) for the MWPM decoder for a particular FSC with Hausdorff dimension $D_H\approx2.966$. The latter can be mapped to the critical point of a zero-temperature confinement-Higgs transition on the fractal lattice, which is tunable via the Hausdorff dimension.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Oracle separations of hybrid quantum-classical circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01904</link>
    <author>Atul Singh Arora, Alexandru Gheorghiu, Uttam Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An important theoretical problem in the study of quantum computation, that is also practically relevant in the context of near-term quantum devices, is to understand the computational power of hybrid models, that combine poly-time classical computation with short-depth quantum computation. Here, we consider two such models: CQ_d which captures the scenario of a polynomial-time classical algorithm that queries a d-depth quantum computer many times; and QC_d which is more analogous to measurement-based quantum computation and captures the scenario of a d-depth quantum computer with the ability to change the sequence of gates being applied depending on measurement outcomes processed by a classical computation. Chia, Chung & Lai (STOC 2020) and Coudron & Menda (STOC 2020) showed that these models (with d=log^O(1) (n)) are strictly weaker than BQP (the class of problems solvable by poly-time quantum computation), relative to an oracle, disproving a conjecture of Jozsa in the relativised world. We show that, despite the similarities between CQ_d and QC_d, the two models are incomparable, i.e. CQ_d $\nsubseteq$ QC_d and QC_d $\nsubseteq$ CQ_d relative to an oracle. In other words, there exist problems that one model can solve but not the other and vice versa. We do this by considering new oracle problems that capture the distinctions between the two models and by introducing the notion of an intrinsically stochastic oracle, an oracle whose responses are inherently randomised, which is used for our second result. While we leave showing the second separation relative to a standard oracle as an open problem, we believe the notion of stochastic oracles could be of independent interest for studying complexity classes which have resisted separation in the standard oracle model. Our constructions also yield simpler oracle separations between the hybrid models and BQP, compared to earlier works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking Characterization Methods for Noisy Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02243</link>
    <author>Megan L. Dahlhauser, Travis S. Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Effective methods for characterizing the noise in quantum computing devices are essential for programming and debugging circuit performance. Existing approaches vary in the information obtained as well as the amount of quantum and classical resources required, with more information generally requiring more resources. Here we benchmark the characterization methods of gate set tomography, Pauli channel noise reconstruction, and empirical direct characterization for developing models that describe noisy quantum circuit performance on a 27-qubit superconducting transmon device. We evaluate these models by comparing the accuracy of noisy circuit simulations with the corresponding experimental observations. We find that the agreement of noise model to experiment does not correlate with the information gained by characterization and that the underlying circuit strongly influences the best choice of characterization approach. Empirical direct characterization scales best of the methods we tested and produced the most accurate characterizations across our benchmarks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure conversion for fault-tolerant quantum computing in alkaline earth Rydberg atom arrays</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03540</link>
    <author>Yue Wu, Shimon Kolkowitz, Shruti Puri, Jeff D Thompson</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Executing quantum algorithms on error-corrected logical qubits is a critical step for scalable quantum computing, but the requisite numbers of qubits and physical error rates are demanding for current experimental hardware. Recently, the development of error correcting codes tailored to particular physical noise models has helped relax these requirements. In this work, we propose a qubit encoding and gate protocol for ${}^{171}$Yb neutral atom qubits that converts the dominant physical errors into erasures, that is, errors in known locations. The key idea is to encode qubits in a metastable electronic level, such that gate errors predominantly result in transitions to disjoint subspaces whose populations can be continuously monitored via fluorescence. We estimate that 98% of errors can be converted into erasures. We quantify the benefit of this approach via circuit-level simulations of the surface code, finding a threshold increase from 0.937% to 4.15%. We also observe a larger code distance near the threshold, leading to a faster decrease in the logical error rate for the same number of physical qubits, which is important for near-term implementations. Erasure conversion should benefit any error correcting code, and may also be applied to design new gates and encodings in other qubit platforms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Analytical calculation formulas for capacities of classical and classical-quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02450</link>
    <author>Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive an analytical calculation formula for the channel capacity of a classical channel without any iteration while its existing algorithms require iterations and the number of iteration depends on the required precision level. Hence, our formula is its first analytical formula without any iteration. We apply the obtained formula to examples and see how the obtained formula works in these examples. Then, we extend it to the channel capacity of a classical-quantum (cq-) channel. Many existing studies proposed algorithms for a cq-channel and all of them require iterations. Our extended analytical algorithm have also no iteration and output the exactly optimum values.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Information Scrambling in Quantum Many-body Scarred Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01777</link>
    <author>Dong Yuan, Shun-Yao Zhang, Yu Wang, L.-M. Duan, Dong-Ling Deng</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum many-body scarred systems host special non-thermal eigenstates which support periodic revival dynamics and weakly break the ergodicity. In this paper, we study the quantum information scrambling dynamics in quantum many-body scarred systems, with a focus on the "PXP" model. We use the out-of-time-ordered correlator (OTOC) and Holevo information as measures of the information scrambling, and apply an efficient numerical method based on matrix product operators to compute them up to 41 spins. We find that both the OTOC and Holevo information exhibit a linear light cone and periodic oscillations inside the light cone for initial states within the scarred subspace, which is in sharp contrast to thermal or many-body localized systems. To explain the formation of the linear light cone structure, we provide a perturbation-type calculation based on a phenomenological model. In addition, we demonstrate that the OTOC and Holevo information dynamics of the "PXP" model can be measured using the Rydberg-atom quantum simulators with current experimental technologies, and numerically identify the measurable signatures using experimental parameters.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Distributed Algorithms for Detection of Cliques</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.03000</link>
    <author>Keren Censor-Hillel, Orr Fischer, François Le Gall, Dean Leitersdorf, Rotem Oshman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The possibilities offered by quantum computing have drawn attention in the distributed computing community recently, with several breakthrough results showing quantum distributed algorithms that run faster than the fastest known classical counterparts, and even separations between the two models. A prime example is the result by Izumi, Le Gall, and Magniez [STACS 2020], who showed that triangle detection by quantum distributed algorithms is easier than triangle listing, while an analogous result is not known in the classical case. In this paper we present a framework for fast quantum distributed clique detection. This improves upon the state-of-the-art for the triangle case, and is also more general, applying to larger clique sizes. Our main technical contribution is a new approach for detecting cliques by encapsulating this as a search task for nodes that can be added to smaller cliques. To extract the best complexities out of our approach, we develop a framework for nested distributed quantum searches, which employ checking procedures that are quantum themselves. Moreover, we show a circuit-complexity barrier on proving a lower bound of the form $\Omega(n^{3/5+\epsilon})$ for $K_p$-detection for any $p \geq 4$, even in the classical (non-quantum) distributed CONGEST setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improving Optimal Quantum State Verification</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01782</link>
    <author>Jorge Miguel-Ramiro, Ferran Riera-Sàbat, Wolfgang Dür</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Maximally entangled states are a key resource in many quantum communication and computation tasks, and their certification is a crucial element to guarantee the desired functionality. We introduce collective strategies for the efficient, local verification of ensembles of Bell pairs that make use of an initial information and noise transfer to few copies prior to their measurement. In this way the number of entangled pairs that need to be measured and hence destroyed is significantly reduced as compared to previous, even optimal, approaches that operate on individual copies. We show that our tools can be extended to other problems and larger classes of multipartite states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Capsule Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01778</link>
    <author>Zidu Liu, Pei-Xin Shen, Weikang Li, L.-M. Duan, Dong-Ling Deng</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Capsule networks, which incorporate the paradigms of connectionism and symbolism, have brought fresh insights into artificial intelligence. The capsule, as the building block of capsule networks, is a group of neurons represented by a vector to encode different features of an entity. The information is extracted hierarchically through capsule layers via routing algorithms. Here, we introduce a quantum capsule network (dubbed QCapsNet) together with a quantum dynamic routing algorithm. Our model enjoys an exponential speedup in the dynamic routing process and exhibits an enhanced representation power. To benchmark the performance of the QCapsNet, we carry out extensive numerical simulations on the classification of handwritten digits and symmetry-protected topological phases, and show that the QCapsNet can achieve the state-of-the-art accuracy and outperforms conventional quantum classifiers evidently. We further unpack the output capsule state and find that a particular subspace may correspond to a human-understandable feature of the input data, which indicates the potential explainability of such networks. Our work reveals an intriguing prospect of quantum capsule networks in quantum machine learning, which may provide a valuable guide towards explainable quantum artificial intelligence.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>