<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Parameterized Complexity of Quantum Verification</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08119</link>
    <author>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Sergey Bravyi, Chinmay Nirkhe, Bryan O'Gorman</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We initiate the study of parameterized complexity of $\textsf{QMA}$ problems in terms of the number of non-Clifford gates in the problem description. We show that for the problem of parameterized quantum circuit satisfiability, there exists a classical algorithm solving the problem with a runtime scaling exponentially in the number of non-Clifford gates but only polynomially with the system size. This result follows from our main result, that for any Clifford + $t$ $T$-gate quantum circuit satisfiability problem, the search space of optimal witnesses can be reduced to a stabilizer subspace isomorphic to at most $t$ qubits (independent of the system size). Furthermore, we derive new lower bounds on the $T$-count of circuit satisfiability instances and the $T$-count of the $W$-state assuming the classical exponential time hypothesis ($\textsf{ETH}$). Lastly, we explore the parameterized complexity of the quantum non-identity check problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The platypus of the quantum channel zoo</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08380</link>
    <author>Felix Leditzky, Debbie Leung, Vikesh Siddhu, Graeme Smith, John A. Smolin</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding quantum channels and the strange behavior of their capacities is a key objective of quantum information theory. Here we study a remarkably simple, low-dimensional, single-parameter family of quantum channels with exotic quantum information-theoretic features. As the simplest example from this family, we focus on a qutrit-to-qutrit channel that is intuitively obtained by hybridizing together a simple degradable channel and a completely useless qubit channel. Such hybridizing makes this channel's capacities behave in a variety of interesting ways. For instance, the private and classical capacity of this channel coincide and can be explicitly calculated, even though the channel does not belong to any class for which the underlying information quantities are known to be additive. Moreover, the quantum capacity of the channel can be computed explicitly, given a clear and compelling conjecture is true. This "spin alignment conjecture", which may be of independent interest, is proved in certain special cases and additional numerical evidence for its validity is provided. Finally, we generalize the qutrit channel in two ways, and the resulting channels and their capacities display similarly rich behavior. In a companion paper, we further show that the qutrit channel demonstrates superadditivity when transmitting quantum information jointly with a variety of assisting channels, in a manner unknown before.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-Pauli Errors in the Three-Dimensional Surface Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05746</link>
    <author>Thomas R. Scruby, Michael Vasmer, Dan E. Browne</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A powerful feature of stabiliser error correcting codes is the fact that stabiliser measurement projects arbitrary errors to Pauli errors, greatly simplifying the physical error correction process as well as classical simulations of code performance. However, logical non-Clifford operations can map Pauli errors to non-Pauli (Clifford) errors, and while subsequent stabiliser measurements will project the Clifford errors back to Pauli errors the resulting distributions will possess additional correlations that depend on both the nature of the logical operation and the structure of the code. Previous work has studied these effects when applying a transversal $T$ gate to the three-dimensional colour code and shown the existence of a non-local "linking charge" phenomenon between membranes of intersecting errors. In this work we generalise these results to the case of a $CCZ$ gate in the three-dimensional surface code and find that many aspects of the problem are much more easily understood in this setting. In particular, the emergence of linking charge is a local effect rather than a non-local one. We use the relative simplicity of Clifford errors in this setting to simulate their effect on the performance of a single-shot magic state preparation process (the first such simulation to account for the full effect of these errors) and find that while they lead to an increase in the logical error rate their effect on the threshold is minimal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scrambling Dynamics and Out-of-Time Ordered Correlators in Quantum Many-Body Systems: a Tutorial</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.07060</link>
    <author>Shenglong Xu, Brian Swingle</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This tutorial article introduces the physics of quantum information scrambling in quantum many-body systems. The goals are to understand how to quantify the spreading of quantum information precisely and how causality emerges in complex quantum systems. We introduce the general framework to study the dynamics of quantum information, including detection and decoding. We show that the dynamics of quantum information is closely related to operator dynamics in the Heisenberg picture, and, in certain circumstances, can be precisely quantified by the so-called out-the-time ordered correlator (OTOC). The general behavior of OTOC is discussed based on several toy models, including the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model, random circuit models, and Brownian models, in which OTOC is analytically tractable. We introduce numerical methods, both exact diagonalization and tensor network methods, to calculate OTOC for generic quantum many-body systems. We also survey current experiment schemes to measure OTOC in various quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generic nonadditivity of quantum capacity in simple channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08377</link>
    <author>Felix Leditzky, Debbie Leung, Vikesh Siddhu, Graeme Smith, John A. Smolin</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Determining capacities of quantum channels is a fundamental question in quantum information theory. Despite having rigorous coding theorems quantifying the flow of information across quantum channels, their capacities are poorly understood due to super-additivity effects. Studying these phenomena is important for deepening our understanding of quantum information, yet simple and clean examples of super-additive channels are scarce. Here we study a simple family of qutrit channels called the platypus channel, and show that it exhibits super-additivity of coherent information when used jointly with a variety of qubit channels. A higher-dimensional variant of the platypus channel displays super-additivity of quantum capacity together with an erasure channel. Subject to the "spin-alignment conjecture" introduced in a companion paper, our results on super-additivity of quantum capacity extend to lower-dimensional channels as well as larger parameter ranges. In particular, super-additivity occurs between two weakly additive channels each with large capacity on their own, in stark contrast to previous results. Remarkably, a single, novel transmission strategy achieves super-additivity in all examples. Our results show that super-additivity is much more prevalent than previously thought. It can occur across a wide variety of channels, even when both participating channels have large quantum capacity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fold-Transversal Clifford Gates for Quantum Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06647</link>
    <author>Nikolas P. Breuckmann, Simon Burton</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We generalize the concept of folding from surface codes to CSS codes by considering certain dualities within them. In particular, this gives a general method to implement logical operations in suitable LDPC quantum codes using transversal gates and qubit permutations only. To demonstrate our approach, we specifically consider a [[30, 8, 3]] hyperbolic quantum code called Bring's code. Further, we show that by restricting the logical subspace of Bring's code to four qubits, we can obtain the full Clifford group on that subspace.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing quantum circuits with Riemannian gradient-flow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.06976</link>
    <author>Roeland Wiersema, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms are a promising class of algorithms that can be performed on currently available quantum computers. In most settings, the free parameters of a variational circuit are optimized using a classical optimizer that updates parameters in Euclidean geometry. Since quantum circuits are elements of the special unitary group, we can consider an alternative optimization perspective that depends on the structure of this group. In this work, we investigate a Riemannian optimization scheme over the special unitary group and we discuss its implementation on a quantum computer. We illustrate that the resulting Riemannian gradient-flow algorithm has favorable optimization properties for deep circuits and that an approximate version of this algorithm can be performed on near-term hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Three-dimensional quantum cellular automata from chiral semion surface topological order and beyond</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05442</link>
    <author>Wilbur Shirley, Yu-An Chen, Arpit Dua, Tyler D. Ellison, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Dominic J. Williamson</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We construct a novel three-dimensional quantum cellular automaton (QCA) based on a system with short-range entangled bulk and chiral semion boundary topological order. We argue that either the QCA is nontrivial, i.e. not a finite-depth circuit of local quantum gates, or there exists a two-dimensional commuting projector Hamiltonian realizing the chiral semion topological order (characterized by $U(1)_2$ Chern-Simons theory). Our QCA is obtained by first constructing the Walker-Wang Hamiltonian of a certain premodular tensor category of order four, then condensing the deconfined bulk boson at the level of lattice operators. We show that the resulting Hamiltonian hosts chiral semion surface topological order in the presence of a boundary and can be realized as a non-Pauli stabilizer code on qubits, from which the QCA is defined. The construction is then generalized to a class of QCAs defined by non-Pauli stabilizer codes on ${2^n}$-dimensional qudits that feature surface anyons described by $U(1)_{2^n}$ Chern-Simons theory. Our results support the conjecture that the group of nontrivial three-dimensional QCAs is isomorphic to the Witt group of non-degenerate braided fusion categories.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying dynamical magic with completely stabilizer preserving operations as free</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.07867</link>
    <author>Gaurav Saxena, Gilad Gour</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we extend the resource theory of magic to the channel case by considering completely stabilizer preserving operations (CSPOs) as free. We introduce and characterize the set of CSPO preserving and completely CSPO preserving superchannels. We quantify the magic of quantum channels by extending the generalized robustness and the min relative entropy of magic from the state to the channel domain and show that they bound the single-shot dynamical magic cost and distillation. We also provide analytical conditions for qubit interconversion under CSPOs and show that it is a linear programming feasibility problem and hence can be efficiently solved. Lastly, we give a classical simulation algorithm whose runtime is related to the generalized robustness of magic for channels. Our algorithm depends on some pre-defined precision, and if there is no bound on the desired precision then it achieves a constant runtime.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matrix concentration inequalities and efficiency of random universal sets of quantum gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05371</link>
    <author>Piotr Dulian, Adam Sawicki</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For a random set $\mathcal{S}$ of quantum gates we provide bounds on the probability that $\mathcal{S}$ forms a $\delta$-approximate $t$-design. In particular we show how many random gates are needed to have a $\delta$-approximate $t$-design with high probability. We also analyze how $\delta$ concentrates around its expected value $\mathbb{E}\delta$ for random $\mathcal{S}$. Our results are valid for both symmetric and non-symmetric sets of gates.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>