<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Improved machine learning algorithm for predicting ground state properties</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.13169</link>
    <author>Laura Lewis, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Viet T. Tran, Sebastian Lehner, Richard Kueng, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Finding the ground state of a quantum many-body system is a fundamental problem in quantum physics. In this work, we give a classical machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting ground state properties with an inductive bias encoding geometric locality. The proposed ML model can efficiently predict ground state properties of an $n$-qubit gapped local Hamiltonian after learning from only $\mathcal{O}(\log(n))$ data about other Hamiltonians in the same quantum phase of matter. This improves substantially upon previous results that require $\mathcal{O}(n^c)$ data for a large constant $c$. Furthermore, the training and prediction time of the proposed ML model scale as $\mathcal{O}(n \log n)$ in the number of qubits $n$. Numerical experiments on physical systems with up to 45 qubits confirm the favorable scaling in predicting ground state properties using a small training dataset.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient learning of ground & thermal states within phases of matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.12946</link>
    <author>Emilio Onorati, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França, James D. Watson</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We consider two related tasks: (a) estimating a parameterisation of a given Gibbs state and expectation values of Lipschitz observables on this state; and (b) learning the expectation values of local observables within a thermal or quantum phase of matter. In both cases, we wish to minimise the number of samples we use to learn these properties to a given precision. For the first task, we develop new techniques to learn parameterisations of classes of systems, including quantum Gibbs states of non-commuting Hamiltonians with exponential decay of correlations and the approximate Markov property. We show it is possible to infer the expectation values of all extensive properties of the state from a number of copies that not only scales polylogarithmically with the system size, but polynomially in the observable's locality -- an exponential improvement. This set of properties includes expected values of quasi-local observables and entropies. For the second task, we develop efficient algorithms for learning observables in a phase of matter of a quantum system. By exploiting the locality of the Hamiltonian, we show that $M$ local observables can be learned with probability $1-\delta$ to precision $\epsilon$ with using only $N=O\big(\log\big(\frac{M}{\delta}\big)e^{polylog(\epsilon^{-1})}\big)$ samples -- an exponential improvement on the precision over previous bounds. Our results apply to both families of ground states of Hamiltonians displaying local topological quantum order, and thermal phases of matter with exponential decay of correlations. In addition, our sample complexity applies to the worse case setting whereas previous results only applied on average. Furthermore, we develop tools of independent interest, such as robust shadow tomography algorithms, Gibbs approximations to ground states, and generalisations of transportation cost inequalities for Gibbs states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Direct Reduction from the Polynomial to the Adversary Method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10317</link>
    <author>Aleksandrs Belovs</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The polynomial and the adversary methods are the two main tools for proving lower bounds on query complexity of quantum algorithms. Both methods have found a large number of applications, some problems more suitable for one method, some for the other. It is known though that the adversary method, in its general negative-weighted version, is tight for bounded-error quantum algorithms, whereas the polynomial method is not. By the tightness of the former, for any polynomial lower bound, there ought to exist a corresponding adversary lower bound. However, direct reduction was not known. In this paper, we give a simple and direct reduction from the polynomial method (in the form of a dual polynomial) to the adversary method. This shows that any lower bound in the form of a dual polynomial is actually an adversary lower bound of a specific form.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On classical simulation algorithms for noisy Boson Sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11532</link>
    <author>Changhun Oh, Liang Jiang, Bill Fefferman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present a classical algorithm that approximately samples from the output distribution of certain noisy Boson Sampling experiments. This algorithm is inspired by a recent result of Aharonov, Gao, Landau, Liu and Vazirani and makes use of an observation originally due to Kalai and Kindler that the output probability of Boson Sampling experiments with a Gaussian noise model can be approximated by sparse low-degree polynomials. This observation alone does not suffice for classical sampling, because its marginal probabilities might not be approximated by sparse low-degree polynomials, and furthermore, the approximated probabilities might be negative. We solve this problem by employing the first quantization representation to give an algorithm for computing the marginal probabilities of these experiments. We prove that when the overall noise rate is constant, the algorithm runs in time quasi-polynomial in the number of input photons $N$ and accuracy. When the overall noise rate scales as $1-x_1^\gamma$ for constant $x_1$ and $\gamma=\Omega(\log N)$, the running time becomes polynomial. Furthermore, we study noisy Boson Sampling with practically relevant noise models such as partial distinguishability and photon loss. We show that the same technique does not immediately apply in these settings, leaving open the possibility of a scalable demonstration of noisy quantum advantage for these noise models in certain parameter regimes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Everything is a quantum Ising model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11917</link>
    <author>Ruben Verresen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>This work shows that any $k$-local Hamiltonian of qubits can be obtained from a 4-state 'Ising' model with $k$-local diagonal interactions and a single-site transverse field -- giving a new theoretical and experimental handle on quantum matter. In particular, the classical Ising interactions can be determined by replacing each Pauli operator with a $4 \times 4$ diagonal matrix. Subsequently tuning a large transverse field projects out two of the four states, recovering the original qubit model, with qudit generalizations. This leads to striking correspondences, such as the spin-1/2 XY and Heisenberg models arising from the large-field limit of 3-state and 4-state Potts models, respectively. Similarly, the Kitaev honeycomb model emerges from classical interactions which enforce loop states on the honeycomb lattice. These generalized Ising models also display rich physics for smaller fields, including quantum criticality and topological phases of matter. This work expands what is experimentally achievable by showing how to realize any quantum spin model using only diagonal interactions and a tuneable field -- ingredients found in, e.g., tweezer arrays of Rydberg atoms or polar molecules. More broadly, 4-state spins can also be encoded in the positions of itinerant particles, exemplified by a Bose-Hubbard model realizing the Kitaev honeycomb model -- giving an experimental path to its $\mathbb Z_2$ and non-Abelian topological quantum liquids.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing quantum satisfiability</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10699</link>
    <author>Ashley Montanaro, Changpeng Shao, Dominic Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum k-SAT (the problem of determining whether a k-local Hamiltonian is frustration-free) is known to be QMA_1-complete for k >= 3, and hence likely hard for quantum computers to solve. Building on a classical result of Alon and Shapira, we show that quantum k-SAT can be solved in randomised polynomial time given the `property testing' promise that the instance is either satisfiable (by any state) or far from satisfiable by a product state; by `far from satisfiable by a product state' we mean that \epsilon n^k constraints must be removed before a product state solution exists, for some fixed \epsilon > 0. The proof has two steps: we first show that for a satisfiable instance of quantum k-SAT, most subproblems on a constant number of qubits are satisfiable by a product state. We then show that for an instance of quantum k-SAT which is far from satisfiable by a product state, most subproblems are unsatisfiable by a product state. Given the promise, quantum k-SAT may therefore be solved by checking satisfiability by a product state on randomly chosen subsystems of constant size.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An operator-algebraic formulation of self-testing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11291</link>
    <author>Connor Paddock, William Slofstra, Yuming Zhao, Yangchen Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We give a new definition of self-testing for correlations in terms of states on $C^*$-algebras. We show that this definition is equivalent to the standard definition for any class of finite-dimensional quantum models which is closed, provided that the correlation is extremal and has a full-rank model in the class. This last condition automatically holds for the class of POVM quantum models, but does not necessarily hold for the class of projective models by a result of Kaniewski and Mančinska. For extremal binary correlations and for extremal synchronous correlations, we show that any self-test for projective models is a self-test for POVM models. The question of whether there is a self-test for projective models which is not a self-test for POVM models remains open. An advantage of our new definition is that it extends naturally to commuting operator models. We show that an extremal correlation is a self-test for finite-dimensional quantum models if and only if it is a self-test for finite-dimensional commuting operator models, and also observe that many known finite-dimensional self-tests are in fact self-tests for infinite-dimensional commuting operator models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Any consistent coupling between classical gravity and quantum matter is fundamentally irreversible</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10261</link>
    <author>Thomas D. Galley, Flaminia Giacomini, John H. Selby</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>When gravity is sourced by a quantum system, there is tension between its role as the mediator of a fundamental interaction, which is expected to acquire nonclassical features, and its role in determining the properties of spacetime, which is inherently classical. Fundamentally, this tension should result in breaking one of the fundamental principles of quantum theory or general relativity, but it is usually hard to assess which one without resorting to a specific model. Here, we answer this question in a theory-independent way using General Probabilistic Theories (GPTs). We consider the interactions of the gravitational field with a single matter system, and derive a no-go theorem showing that when gravity is classical at least one of the following assumptions needs to be violated: (i) Matter degrees of freedom are described by fully non-classical degrees of freedom; (ii) Interactions between matter degrees of freedom and the gravitational field are reversible; (iii) Matter degrees of freedom back-react on the gravitational field. We argue that this implies that theories of classical gravity and quantum matter must be fundamentally irreversible, as is the case in the recent model of Oppenheim et al. Conversely if we require that the interaction between quantum matter and the gravitational field are reversible, then the gravitational field must be non-classical.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>State polynomials: positivity, optimization and nonlinear Bell inequalities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.12513</link>
    <author>Igor Klep, Victor Magron, Jurij Volčič, Jie Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2023</pubDate>
    <description>This paper introduces state polynomials, i.e., polynomials in noncommuting variables and formal states of their products. A state analog of Artin's solution to Hilbert's 17th problem is proved showing that state polynomials, positive over all matrices and matricial states, are sums of squares with denominators. Somewhat surprisingly, it is also established that a Krivine-Stengle Positivstellensatz fails to hold in the state polynomial setting. Further, archimedean Positivstellensätze in the spirit of Putinar and Helton-McCullough are presented leading to a hierarchy of semidefinite relaxations converging monotonically to the optimum of a state polynomial subject to state constraints. This hierarchy can be seen as a state analog of the Lasserre hierarchy for optimization of polynomials, and the Navascués-Pironio-Acín scheme for optimization of noncommutative polynomials. The motivation behind this theory arises from the study of correlations in quantum networks. Determining the maximal quantum violation of a polynomial Bell inequality for an arbitrary network is reformulated as a state polynomial optimization problem. Several examples of quadratic Bell inequalities in the bipartite and the bilocal tripartite scenario are analyzed. To reduce the size of the constructed SDPs, sparsity, sign symmetry and conditional expectation of the observables' group structure are exploited. To obtain the above-mentioned results, techniques from noncommutative algebra, real algebraic geometry, operator theory, and convex optimization are employed.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Security of differential phase shift QKD from relativistic principles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.11340</link>
    <author>Martin Sandfuchs, Marcus Haberland, V. Vilasini, Ramona Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 30 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The design of quantum protocols for secure key generation poses many challenges: On the one hand, they need to be practical concerning experimental realisations. On the other hand, their theoretical description must be simple enough to allow for a security proof against all possible attacks. Often, these two requirements are in conflict with each other, and the differential phase shift (DPS) QKD protocol is an excellent example of this: It is designed to be implementable with current optical telecommunication technology, which, for this protocol, comes at the cost that many standard security proof techniques do not apply to it. In this work, we give the first full security proof of DPS QKD against general attacks, including finite-size effects. The proof combines techniques from quantum information theory, quantum optics, and relativity. We first give a security proof of a QKD protocol whose security stems from relativistic constraints. We then show that DPS QKD can be formulated as an instance of the relativistic protocol. In addition, we show that coherent attacks on the DPS protocol are, in fact, stronger than collective attacks.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>