<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Saturation and recurrence of quantum complexity in random quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09734</link>
    <author>Michał Oszmaniec, Michał Horodecki, Nicholas Hunter-Jones</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum complexity is a measure of the minimal number of elementary operations required to approximately prepare a given state or unitary channel. Recently, this concept has found applications beyond quantum computing -- in studying the dynamics of quantum many-body systems and the long-time properties of AdS black holes. In this context Brown and Susskind conjectured that the complexity of a chaotic quantum system grows linearly in time up to times exponential in the system size, saturating at a maximal value, and remaining maximally complex until undergoing recurrences at doubly-exponential times. In this work we prove the saturation and recurrence of the complexity of quantum states and unitaries in a model of chaotic time-evolution based on random quantum circuits, in which a local random unitary transformation is applied to the system at every time step. Importantly, our findings hold for quite general random circuit models, irrespective of the gate set and geometry of qubit interactions. Our results advance an understanding of the long-time behaviour of chaotic quantum systems and could shed light on the physics of black hole interiors. From a technical perspective our results are based on establishing new quantitative connections between the Haar measure and high-degree approximate designs, as well as the fact that random quantum circuits of sufficiently high depth converge to approximate designs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient and robust estimation of many-qubit Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09567</link>
    <author>Daniel Stilck França, Liubov A. Markovich, V. V. Dobrovitski, Albert H. Werner, Johannes Borregaard</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Characterizing the interactions and dynamics of quantum mechanical systems is an essential task in the development of quantum technologies. We propose a novel protocol for estimating the underlying Hamiltonian dynamics and Markovian noise of a multi-qubit device. It is based on the efficient estimation of the time-derivatives of few qubit observables using polynomial interpolation. For finite range dynamics, our protocol exponentially improves the necessary time-resolution of the measurements and quadratically reduces the overall sample complexity compared to previous approaches. Furthermore, we show that our protocol can characterize the dynamics of systems with algebraically decaying interactions. The implementation of the protocol requires only the preparation of product states and single-qubit measurements, rendering it applicable for the characterization of both current and future quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Topological phases of unitary dynamics: Classification in Clifford category</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09141</link>
    <author>Jeongwan Haah</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A quantum cellular automaton (QCA) or a causal unitary is by definition an automorphism of local operator algebra, by which local operators are mapped to local operators. Quantum circuits of small depth, local Hamiltonian evolutions for short time, and translations (shifts) are examples. A Clifford QCA is one that maps any Pauli operator to a finite tensor product of Pauli operators. Here, we obtain a complete table of groups $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p)$ of translation invariant Clifford QCA in any spatial dimension $\mathsf d \ge 0$ modulo Clifford quantum circuits and shifts over prime $p$-dimensional qudits, where the circuits and shifts are allowed to obey only coarser translation invariance. The group $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p)$ is nonzero only for $\mathsf d = 2k+3$ if $p=2$ and $\mathsf d = 4k+3$ if $p$ is odd where~$k \ge 0$ is any integer, in which case $\mathfrak C(\mathsf d,p) \cong \widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p)$, the classical Witt group of nonsingular quadratic forms over the finite field $\mathbb F_p$. It is well known that $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_2) \cong \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z$, $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p) \cong \mathbb Z/4\mathbb Z$ if $p = 3 \bmod 4$, and $\widetilde{\mathfrak W}(\mathbb F_p)\cong \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z \oplus \mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z$ if $p = 1 \bmod 4$. The classification is achieved by a dimensional descent, which is a reduction of Laurent extension theorems for algebraic $L$-groups of surgery theory in topology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Correlations in typicality and an affirmative solution to the exact catalytic entropy conjecture</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08915</link>
    <author>Henrik Wilming</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I show that if a finite-dimensional density matrix has strictly smaller von Neumann entropy than a second one of the same dimension (and the rank is not bigger), then sufficiently (but finitely) many tensor-copies of the first density matrix majorize a density matrix whose single-body marginals are all exactly equal to the second density matrix. This implies an affirmative solution of the exact catalytic entropy conjecture (CEC) introduced by Boes et al. [PRL 122, 210402 (2019)]. Both the Lemma and the solution to the CEC transfer to the classical setting of finite-dimensional probability vectors (with permutations of entries instead of unitary transformations for the CEC).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The QAOA with Slow Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06845</link>
    <author>Anthony Polloreno, Graeme Smith</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) was originally developed to solve combinatorial optimization problems, but has become a standard for assessing the performance of quantum computers. Fully descriptive benchmarking techniques are often prohibitively expensive for large numbers of qubits ($n \gtrsim 10$), so the QAOA often serves in practice as a computational benchmark. The QAOA involves a classical optimization subroutine that attempts to find optimal parameters for a quantum subroutine. Unfortunately, many optimizers used for the QAOA require many shots ($N \gtrsim 1000$) per point in parameter space to get a reliable estimate of the energy being minimized. However, some experimental quantum computing platforms such as neutral atom quantum computers have slow repetition rates, placing unique requirements on the classical optimization subroutine used in the QAOA in these systems. In this paper we investigate the performance of a gradient free classical optimizer for the QAOA - dual annealing - and demonstrate that optimization is possible even with $N=1$ and $n=16$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimising shadow tomography with generalised measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08990</link>
    <author>H. Chau Nguyen, Jan Lennart Bönsel, Jonathan Steinberg, Otfried Gühne</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Advances in quantum technology require scalable techniques to efficiently extract information from a quantum system, such as expectation values of observables or its entropy. Traditional tomography is limited to a handful of qubits and shadow tomography has been suggested as a scalable replacement for larger systems. Shadow tomography is conventionally analysed based on outcomes of ideal projective measurements on the system upon application of randomised unitaries. Here, we suggest that shadow tomography can be much more straightforwardly formulated for generalised measurements, or positive operator valued measures. Based on the idea of the least-square estimator, shadow tomography with generalised measurements is both more general and simpler than the traditional formulation with randomisation of unitaries. In particular, this formulation allows us to analyse theoretical aspects of shadow tomography in detail. For example, we provide a detailed study of the implication of symmetries in shadow tomography. Shadow tomography with generalised measurements is also indispensable in realistic implementation of quantum mechanical measurements, when noise is unavoidable. Moreover, we also demonstrate how the optimisation of measurements for shadow tomography tailored toward a particular set of observables can be carried out.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hay from the haystack: explicit examples of exponential quantum circuit complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06977</link>
    <author>Yifan Jia, Michael M. Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The vast majority of quantum states and unitaries have circuit complexity exponential in the number of qubits. In a similar vein, most of them also have exponential minimum description length, which makes it difficult to pinpoint examples of exponential complexity. In this work, we construct examples of constant description length but exponential circuit complexity. We provide infinite families such that each element requires an exponential number of two-qubit gates to be generated exactly from a product and where the same is true for the approximate generation of the vast majority of elements in the family. The results are based on sets of large transcendence degree and discussed for tensor networks, diagonal unitaries, and maximally coherent states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Machine learning applications for noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09414</link>
    <author>Brian Coyle</author>
    <pubDate>May 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum machine learning has proven to be a fruitful area in which to search for potential applications of quantum computers. This is particularly true for those available in the near term, so called noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. In this Thesis, we develop and study three quantum machine learning applications suitable for NISQ computers, ordered in terms of increasing complexity of data presented to them. These algorithms are variational in nature and use parameterised quantum circuits (PQCs) as the underlying quantum machine learning model. The first application area is quantum classification using PQCs, where the data is classical feature vectors and their corresponding labels. Here, we study the robustness of certain data encoding strategies in such models against noise present in a quantum computer. The second area is generative modelling using quantum computers, where we use quantum circuit Born machines to learn and sample from complex probability distributions. We discuss and present a framework for quantum advantage for such models, propose gradient-based training methods and demonstrate these both numerically and on the Rigetti quantum computer up to 28 qubits. For our final application, we propose a variational algorithm in the area of approximate quantum cloning, where the data becomes quantum in nature. For the algorithm, we derive differentiable cost functions, prove theoretical guarantees such as faithfulness, and incorporate state of the art methods such as quantum architecture search. Furthermore, we demonstrate how this algorithm is useful in discovering novel implementable attacks on quantum cryptographic protocols, focusing on quantum coin flipping and key distribution as examples.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Say NO to Optimization: A Non-Orthogonal Quantum Eigensolver</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09039</link>
    <author>Unpil Baek, Diptarka Hait, James Shee, Oskar Leimkuhler, William J. Huggins, Torin F. Stetina, Martin Head-Gordon, K. Birgitta Whaley</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A balanced description of both static and dynamic correlations in electronic systems with nearly degenerate low-lying states presents a challenge for multi-configurational methods on classical computers. We present here a quantum algorithm utilizing the action of correlating cluster operators to provide high-quality wavefunction ansätze employing a non-orthogonal multireference basis that captures a significant portion of the exact wavefunction in a highly compact manner, and that allows computation of the resulting energies and wavefunctions at polynomial cost with a quantum computer. This enables a significant improvement over the corresponding classical non-orthogonal solver, which incurs an exponential cost when evaluating off-diagonal matrix elements between the ansatz states, and is therefore intractable. We implement the non-orthogonal quantum eigensolver (NOQE) here with an efficient ansatz parameterization inspired by classical quantum chemistry methods that succeed in capturing significant amounts of electronic correlation accurately. By taking advantage of classical methods for chemistry, NOQE provides a flexible, compact, and rigorous description of both static and dynamic electronic correlation, making it an attractive method for the calculation of electronic states of a wide range of molecular systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08154</link>
    <author>Kerstin Beer</author>
    <pubDate>May 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This PhD thesis combines two of the most exciting research areas of the last decades: quantum computing and machine learning. We introduce dissipative quantum neural networks (DQNNs), which are designed for fully quantum learning tasks, are capable of universal quantum computation and have low memory requirements while training. These networks are optimised with training data pairs in form of input and desired output states and therefore can be used for characterising unknown or untrusted quantum devices. We not only demonstrate the generalisation behaviour of DQNNs using classical simulations, but also implement them successfully on actual quantum computers. To understand the ultimate limits for such quantum machine learning methods, we discuss the quantum no free lunch theorem, which describes a bound on the probability that a quantum device, which can be modelled as a unitary process and is optimised with quantum examples, gives an incorrect output for a random input. Moreover we expand the area of applications of DQNNs in two directions. In the first case, we include additional information beyond just the training data pairs: since quantum devices are always structured, the resulting data is always structured as well. We modify the DQNN's training algorithm such that knowledge about the graph-structure of the training data pairs is included in the training process and show that this can lead to better generalisation behaviour. Both the original DQNN and the DQNN including graph structure are trained with data pairs in order to characterise an underlying relation. However, in the second extension of the algorithm we aim to learn characteristics of a set of quantum states in order to extend it to quantum states which have similar properties. Therefore we build a generative adversarial model where two DQNNs, called the generator and discriminator, are trained in a competitive way.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>