<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Inevitability of knowing less than nothing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14424</link>
    <author>Gilad Gour, Mark M. Wilde, Sarah Brandsen, Isabelle Jianing Geng</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A colloquial interpretation of entropy is that it is the knowledge gained upon learning the outcome of a random experiment. Conditional entropy is then interpreted as the knowledge gained upon learning the outcome of one random experiment after learning the outcome of another, possibly statistically dependent, random experiment. In the classical world, entropy and conditional entropy take only non-negative values, consistent with the intuition that one has regarding the aforementioned interpretations. However, for certain entangled states, one obtains negative values when evaluating commonly accepted and information-theoretically justified formulas for the quantum conditional entropy, leading to the confounding conclusion that one can know less than nothing in the quantum world. Here, we introduce a physically motivated framework for defining quantum conditional entropy, based on two simple postulates inspired by the second law of thermodynamics (non-decrease of entropy) and extensivity of entropy, and we argue that all plausible definitions of quantum conditional entropy should respect these two postulates. We then prove that all plausible quantum conditional entropies take on negative values for certain entangled states, so that it is inevitable that one can know less than nothing in the quantum world. All of our arguments are based on constructions of physical processes that respect the first postulate, the one inspired by the second law of thermodynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Extendibility of Werner States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13743</link>
    <author>D치vid Jakab, Adri치n Solymos, Zolt치n Zimbor치s</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the two-sided symmetric extendibility problem of Werner states. The interplay of the unitary symmetry of these states and the inherent bipartite permutation symmetry of the extendibility scenario allows us to map this problem into the ground state problem of a highly symmetric spin-model Hamiltonian. We solve this ground state problem analytically by utilizing the representation theory of SU(d), in particular a result related to the dominance order of Young diagrams in Littlewood-Richarson decompositions. As a result, we obtain necessary and sufficient conditions for the extendibility of Werner states for arbitrary extension size and local dimension. Interestingly, the range of extendible states has a non-trivial trade-off between the extension sizes on the two sides. We compare our result with the two-sided extendibility problem of isotropic states, where there is no such trade-off.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Synergy Between Quantum Circuits and Tensor Networks: Short-cutting the Race to Practical Quantum Advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13673</link>
    <author>Manuel S. Rudolph, Jacob Miller, Jing Chen, Atithi Acharya, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While recent breakthroughs have proven the ability of noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices to achieve quantum advantage in classically-intractable sampling tasks, the use of these devices for solving more practically relevant computational problems remains a challenge. Proposals for attaining practical quantum advantage typically involve parametrized quantum circuits (PQCs), whose parameters can be optimized to find solutions to diverse problems throughout quantum simulation and machine learning. However, training PQCs for real-world problems remains a significant practical challenge, largely due to the phenomenon of barren plateaus in the optimization landscapes of randomly-initialized quantum circuits. In this work, we introduce a scalable procedure for harnessing classical computing resources to determine task-specific initializations of PQCs, which we show significantly improves the trainability and performance of PQCs on a variety of problems. Given a specific optimization task, this method first utilizes tensor network (TN) simulations to identify a promising quantum state, which is then converted into gate parameters of a PQC by means of a high-performance decomposition procedure. We show that this task-specific initialization avoids barren plateaus, and effectively translates increases in classical resources to enhanced performance and speed in training quantum circuits. By demonstrating a means of boosting limited quantum resources using classical computers, our approach illustrates the promise of this synergy between quantum and quantum-inspired models in quantum computing, and opens up new avenues to harness the power of modern quantum hardware for realizing practical quantum advantage.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multidimensional Quantum Walks, with Application to $k$-Distinctness</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13492</link>
    <author>Stacey Jeffery, Sebastian Zur</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While the quantum query complexity of $k$-distinctness is known to be $O\left(n^{3/4-1/4(2^k-1)}\right)$ for any constant $k \geq 4$, the best previous upper bound on the time complexity was $\widetilde{O}\left(n^{1-1/k}\right)$. We give a new upper bound of $\widetilde{O}\left(n^{3/4-1/4(2^k-1)}\right)$ on the time complexity, matching the query complexity up to polylogarithmic factors. In order to achieve this upper bound, we give a new technique for designing quantum walk search algorithms, which is an extension of the electric network framework. We also show how to solve the welded trees problem in $O(n)$ queries and $O(n^2)$ time using this new technique, showing that the new quantum walk framework can achieve exponential speedups.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Comparison of unknown unitary channels with multiple uses</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12519</link>
    <author>Yutaka Hashimoto, Akihito Soeda, Mio Murao</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Comparison of quantum objects is a task to determine whether two unknown quantum objects are the same or different. It is one of the most basic information processing tasks for learning property of quantum objects, and comparison of quantum states, quantum channels, and quantum measurements have been investigated. In general, repeated uses of quantum objects improve the success probability of comparison. The optimal strategy of pure-state comparison, the comparison of quantum states for the case of multiple copies of each unknown pure state, is known, but the optimal strategy of unitary comparison, the comparison of quantum channels for the case of multiple uses of each unknown unitary channel, was not known due to the complication of the varieties of causal order structures among the uses of each unitary channel. In this paper, we investigate unitary comparison with multiple uses of unitary channels based on the quantum tester formalism. We obtain the optimal minimum-error and the optimal unambiguous strategies of unitary comparison of two unknown $d$-dimensional unitary channels $U_1$ and $U_2$ when $U_1$ can be used $N_1$ times and $U_2$ can be used $N_2$ times for $N_2 \ge (d-1)N_1$. These optimal strategies are implemented by parallel uses of the unitary channels, even though all sequential and adaptive strategies implementable by the quantum circuit model are considered. When the number of the smaller uses of the unitary channels $N_1$ is fixed, the optimal averaged success probability cannot be improved by adding more uses of $U_2$ than $N_2 = (d-1) N_1$. This feature is in contrast to the case of pure-state comparison, where adding more copies of the unknown pure states always improves the optimal averaged success probability. It highlights the difference between corresponding tasks for states and channels, which has been previously shown for quantum discrimination tasks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Locality of gapped ground states in systems with power-law decaying interactions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13057</link>
    <author>Zhiyuan Wang, Kaden R. A. Hazzard</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It has been proved that in gapped ground states of locally-interacting quantum systems, the effect of local perturbations decays exponentially with distance. However, in systems with power-law ($1/r^\alpha$) decaying interactions, no analogous statement has been shown, and there are serious mathematical obstacles to proving it with existing methods. In this paper we prove that when $\alpha$ exceeds the spatial dimension $D$, the effect of local perturbations on local properties a distance $r$ away is upper bounded by a power law $1/r^{\alpha_1}$ in gapped ground states, provided that the perturbations do not close the spectral gap. The power-law exponent $\alpha_1$ is tight if $\alpha>2D$ and interactions are two-body, where we have $\alpha_1=\alpha$. The proof is enabled by a method that avoids the use of quasiadiabatic continuation and incorporates techniques of complex analysis. This method also improves bounds on ground state correlation decay, even in short-range interacting systems. Our work generalizes the fundamental notion that local perturbations have local effects to power-law interacting systems, with broad implications for numerical simulations and experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Proofs of Quantumness from Trapdoor Permutations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12390</link>
    <author>Tomoyuki Morimae, Takashi Yamakawa</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Assume that Alice can do only classical probabilistic polynomial-time computing while Bob can do quantum polynomial-time computing. Alice and Bob communicate over only classical channels, and finally Bob gets a state $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$ with some bit strings $x_0$ and $x_1$. Is it possible that Alice can know $\{x_0,x_1\}$ but Bob cannot? Such a task, called \it remote state preparations, is indeed possible under some complexity assumptions, and is bases of many quantum cryptographic primitives such as proofs of quantumness, (classical-client) blind quantum computing, (classical) verifications of quantum computing, and quantum money. A typical technique to realize remote state preparations is to use 2-to-1 trapdoor collision resistant hash functions: Alice sends a 2-to-1 trapdoor collision resistant hash function $f$ to Bob, and Bob evaluates it on superposition and measures the image. Bob's post-measurement state is $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$, where $f(x_0)=f(x_1)=y$. With the trapdoor, Alice can learn $\{x_0,x_1\}$, but due to the collision resistance, Bob cannot. This Alice's advantage can be leveraged to realize the quantum cryptographic primitives listed above. It seems that the collision resistance is essential here. In this paper, surprisingly, we show that the collision resistance is not necessary for a restricted case: we show that (non-verifiable) remote state preparations of $|x_0\rangle+|x_1\rangle$ secure against \it classical probabilistic polynomial-time Bob can be constructed from classically-secure (full-domain) trapdoor permutations. Trapdoor permutations are not likely to imply the collision resistance, because black-box reductions from collision-resistant hash functions to trapdoor permutations are known to be impossible. As an application of our result, we construct proofs of quantumness from classically-secure (full-domain) trapdoor permutations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cycle Index Polynomials and Generalized Quantum Separability Tests</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.14596</link>
    <author>Zachary P. Bradshaw, Margarite L. LaBorde, Mark M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We address an outstanding question on the acceptance probability for the bipartite pure-state separability algorithm proposed by [LaBorde and Wilde, arXiv:2105.12758]. We prove that the analytical form of this expression is given by the cycle index polynomial of the symmetric group $S_k$, which is itself related to the Bell polynomials. After doing so, we derive a family of quantum separability tests, each of which is generated by a finite group; for all such algorithms, we show that the acceptance probability is determined by the cycle index polynomial of the group. Finally, we produce and analyze explicit circuit constructions for these tests, showing that the tests corresponding to the symmetric and cyclic groups can be executed with $O(k^2)$ and $O(k\log(k))$ controlled-SWAP gates, respectively, where $k$ is the number of copies of the state being tested.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement optimization of variational quantum simulation by classical shadow and derandomization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.13934</link>
    <author>Kouhei Nakaji, Suguru Endo, Yuichiro Matsuzaki, Hideaki Hakoshima</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulating large quantum systems is the ultimate goal of quantum computing. Variational quantum simulation (VQS) gives us a tool to achieve the goal in near-term devices by distributing the computation load to both classical and quantum computers. However, as the size of the quantum system becomes large, the execution of VQS becomes more and more challenging. One of the most severe challenges is the drastic increase in the number of measurements; for example, the number of measurements tends to increase by the fourth power of the number of qubits in a quantum simulation with a chemical Hamiltonian. This work aims to dramatically decrease the number of measurements in VQS by recently proposed shadow-based strategies such as classical shadow and derandomization. Even though previous literature shows that shadow-based strategies successfully optimize measurements in the variational quantum optimization (VQO), how to apply them to VQS was unclear due to the gap between VQO and VQS in measuring observables. In this paper, we bridge the gap by changing the way of measuring observables in VQS and propose an algorithm to optimize measurements in VQS by shadow-based strategies. Our theoretical analysis not only reveals the advantage of using our algorithm in VQS but theoretically supports using shadow-based strategies in VQO, whose advantage has only been given numerically. Additionally, our numerical experiment shows the validity of using our algorithm with a quantum chemical system.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Solvent distribution effects on quantum chemical calculations with quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12487</link>
    <author>Yuichiro Yoshida, Wataru Mizukami, Norio Yoshida</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a combination of three-dimensional reference interaction site model self-consistent field (3D-RISM-SCF) theory and the variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) to consider the solvent distribution effects within the framework of quantum-classical hybrid computing. The present method, 3D-RISM-VQE, does not include any statistical errors from the solvent configuration sampling owing to the analytical treatment of the statistical solvent distribution. We apply 3D-RISM-VQE to compute the spatial distribution functions of solvent water around a water molecule, the potential and Helmholtz energy curves of NaCl, and to conduct Helmholtz energy component analysis of H$_2$O and NH$_4^+$. Moreover, we utilize 3D-RISM-VQE to analyze the extent to which solvent effects alter the efficiency of quantum calculations compared with calculations in the gas phase using the $L^1$-norms of molecular electronic Hamiltonians. Our results demonstrate that the efficiency of quantum chemical calculations on a quantum computer in solution is virtually the same as in the gas phase.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>