<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>On a gap in the proof of the generalised quantum Stein's lemma and its consequences for the reversibility of quantum resources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02813</link>
    <author>Mario Berta, Fernando G. S. L. Brandão, Gilad Gour, Ludovico Lami, Martin B. Plenio, Bartosz Regula, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the proof of the generalised quantum Stein's lemma [Brandão & Plenio, Commun. Math. Phys. 295, 791 (2010)] is not correct due to a gap in the argument leading to Lemma III.9. Hence, the main achievability result of Brandão & Plenio is not known to hold. This puts into question a number of established results in the literature, in particular the reversibility of quantum entanglement [Brandão & Plenio, Commun. Math. Phys. 295, 829 (2010); Nat. Phys. 4, 873 (2008)] and of general quantum resources [Brandão & Gour, Phys. Rev. Lett. 115, 070503 (2015)] under asymptotically resource non-generating operations. We discuss potential ways to recover variants of the newly unsettled results using other approaches.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive constant-depth circuits for manipulating non-abelian anyons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01933</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Isaac Kim, Alexander Kliesch, Robert Koenig</author>
    <pubDate>May 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider Kitaev's quantum double model based on a finite group $G$ and describe quantum circuits for (a) preparation of the ground state, (b) creation of anyon pairs separated by an arbitrary distance, and (c) non-destructive topological charge measurement. We show that for any solvable group $G$ all above tasks can be realized by constant-depth adaptive circuits with geometrically local unitary gates and mid-circuit measurements. Each gate may be chosen adaptively depending on previous measurement outcomes. Constant-depth circuits are well suited for implementation on a noisy hardware since it may be possible to execute the entire circuit within the qubit coherence time. Thus our results could facilitate an experimental study of exotic phases of matter with a non-abelian particle statistics. We also show that adaptiveness is essential for our circuit construction. Namely, task (b) cannot be realized by non-adaptive constant-depth local circuits for any non-abelian group $G$. This is in a sharp contrast with abelian anyons which can be created and moved over an arbitrary distance by a depth-$1$ circuit composed of generalized Pauli gates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Preparing Arbitrary Continuous Functions in Quantum Registers With Logarithmic Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00519</link>
    <author>Arthur G. Rattew, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers will be able solve important problems with significant polynomial and exponential speedups over their classical counterparts, for instance in option pricing in finance, and in real-space molecular chemistry simulations. However, key applications can only achieve their potential speedup if their inputs are prepared efficiently. We effectively solve the important problem of efficiently preparing quantum states following arbitrary continuous (as well as more general) functions with complexity logarithmic in the desired resolution, and with rigorous error bounds. This is enabled by the development of a fundamental subroutine based off of the simulation of rank-1 projectors. Combined with diverse techniques from quantum information processing, this subroutine enables us to present a broad set of tools for solving practical tasks, such as state preparation, numerical integration of Lipschitz continuous functions, and superior sampling from probability density functions. As a result, our work has significant implications in a wide range of applications, for instance in financial forecasting, and in quantum simulation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Group-Invariant Quantum Machine Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02261</link>
    <author>Martin Larocca, Frederic Sauvage, Faris M. Sbahi, Guillaume Verdon, Patrick J. Coles, M. Cerezo</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Machine Learning (QML) models are aimed at learning from data encoded in quantum states. Recently, it has been shown that models with little to no inductive biases (i.e., with no assumptions about the problem embedded in the model) are likely to have trainability and generalization issues, especially for large problem sizes. As such, it is fundamental to develop schemes that encode as much information as available about the problem at hand. In this work we present a simple, yet powerful, framework where the underlying invariances in the data are used to build QML models that, by construction, respect those symmetries. These so-called group-invariant models produce outputs that remain invariant under the action of any element of the symmetry group $\mathfrak{G}$ associated to the dataset. We present theoretical results underpinning the design of $\mathfrak{G}$-invariant models, and exemplify their application through several paradigmatic QML classification tasks including cases when $\mathfrak{G}$ is a continuous Lie group and also when it is a discrete symmetry group. Notably, our framework allows us to recover, in an elegant way, several well known algorithms for the literature, as well as to discover new ones. Taken together, we expect that our results will help pave the way towards a more geometric and group-theoretic approach to QML model design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>What is the temperature of a quantum state?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00017</link>
    <author>Patryk Lipka-Bartosik, Martí Perarnau-Llobet, Nicolas Brunner</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Temperature is usually defined for physical systems at thermal equilibrium. Nevertheless one may wonder if it would be possible to attribute a meaningful notion of temperature to an arbitrary quantum state, beyond simply the thermal (Gibbs) state. In this work, we propose such a notion of temperature considering an operational task, inspired by the Zeroth Law of thermodynamics. Specifically, we define two effective temperatures for quantifying the ability of a quantum system to cool down or heat up a thermal environment. In this way we can associate an operationally meaningful notion of temperature to any quantum density matrix. We provide general expressions for these effective temperatures, for both single- and many-copy systems, establishing connections to concepts previously discussed in the literature. Finally, we consider a more sophisticated scenario where the heat exchange between the system and the thermal environment is assisted by a quantum reference frame. This leads to an effect of "coherent quantum catalysis", where the use of a coherent catalyst allows for exploiting quantum energetic coherences in the system, now leading to much colder or hotter effective temperatures.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Soft Syndrome Decoding of Quantum LDPC Codes for Joint Correction of Data and Syndrome Errors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02341</link>
    <author>Nithin Raveendran, Narayanan Rengaswamy, Asit Kumar Pradhan, Bane Vasić</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum errors are primarily detected and corrected using the measurement of syndrome information which itself is an unreliable step in practical error correction implementations. Typically, such faulty or noisy syndrome measurements are modeled as a binary measurement outcome flipped with some probability. However, the measured syndrome is in fact a discretized value of the continuous voltage or current values obtained in the physical implementation of the syndrome extraction. In this paper, we use this "soft" or analog information without the conventional discretization step to benefit the iterative decoders for decoding quantum low-density parity-check (QLDPC) codes. Syndrome-based iterative belief propagation decoders are modified to utilize the syndrome-soft information to successfully correct both data and syndrome errors simultaneously, without repeated measurements. We demonstrate the advantages of extracting the soft information from the syndrome in our improved decoders, not only in terms of comparison of thresholds and logical error rates for quasi-cyclic lifted-product QLDPC code families, but also for faster convergence of iterative decoders. In particular, the new BP decoder with noisy syndrome performs as good as the standard BP decoder under ideal syndrome.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient quantum algorithm for nonlinear reaction-diffusion equations and energy estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01141</link>
    <author>Dong An, Di Fang, Stephen Jordan, Jin-Peng Liu, Guang Hao Low, Jiasu Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Nonlinear differential equations exhibit rich phenomena in many fields but are notoriously challenging to solve. Recently, Liu et al. [1] demonstrated the first efficient quantum algorithm for dissipative quadratic differential equations under the condition $R < 1$, where $R$ measures the ratio of nonlinearity to dissipation using the $\ell_2$ norm. Here we develop an efficient quantum algorithm based on [1] for reaction-diffusion equations, a class of nonlinear partial differential equations (PDEs). To achieve this, we improve upon the Carleman linearization approach introduced in [1] to obtain a faster convergence rate under the condition $R_D < 1$, where $R_D$ measures the ratio of nonlinearity to dissipation using the $\ell_{\infty}$ norm. Since $R_D$ is independent of the number of spatial grid points $n$ while $R$ increases with $n$, the criterion $R_D<1$ is significantly milder than $R<1$ for high-dimensional systems and can stay convergent under grid refinement for approximating PDEs. As applications of our quantum algorithm we consider the Fisher-KPP and Allen-Cahn equations, which have interpretations in classical physics. In particular, we show how to estimate the mean square kinetic energy in the solution by postprocessing the quantum state that encodes it to extract derivative information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A fast quantum algorithm for computing matrix permanent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01328</link>
    <author>Joonsuk Huh</author>
    <pubDate>May 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Computing a matrix permanent is known to be a classically intractable problem. This paper presents the first polynomial time quantum algorithm for computing permanents of arbitrary $N$-dimensional square matrices with multiplicative error and additive error protocols. We transformed the well-known classical algorithm, Ryser's formula, into sums of quantum overlap integrals to develop the quantum algorithm. This requires $\mathcal{O}(N)$ and $\mathcal{O}(N^{3})$ evaluations of the real part of the quantum overlap integrals for real and complex matrices, respectively, with polynomial depth quantum circuits of $\mathcal{O}(N)$ qubits. The existence of the polynomial time multiplicative error estimation of a matrix permanent would strongly imply that quantum computers can access the #P-hard problem. Our quantum algorithm attains the milestone of opening a new direction in quantum computing and computational complexity theory. It could resolve crucial computational complexity issues like locating the bounded error quantum polynomial time (BQP) relative to the polynomial hierarchy, which has been a big complexity question. Depending on the size of a matrix norm of interest, we can also obtain an exponentially small additive error estimation and better estimation against Gurvits' classical sampling algorithm. The additive error protocol is practically implementable in noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices. Moreover, our quantum algorithm directly shows the computational complexity connection between the matrix permanent and the real-time partition function of the quantum Ising Hamiltonian.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Magic of the ground state of the transverse field Ising model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02247</link>
    <author>Salvatore F.E. Oliviero, Lorenzo Leone, Alioscia Hamma</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Ground states of quantum many-body systems are both entangled and possess a kind of quantum complexity as their preparation requires universal resources that go beyond the Clifford group and stabilizer states. These resources - sometimes dubbed as magic - are also the crucial ingredient for quantum advantage. We study the behavior of the stabilizer Rényi entropy in the integrable transverse field Ising spin chain. We show that the locality of interactions results in a localized stabilizer Rényi entropy in the gapped phase thus making this quantity computable in terms of local quantities in the gapped phase, while measurements involving $L$ spins are necessary at the critical point to obtain an error scaling with $O(L^{-1})$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complete flow-preserving rewrite rules for MBQC patterns with Pauli measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02009</link>
    <author>Tommy McElvanney, Miriam Backens</author>
    <pubDate>May 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the one-way model of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), computation proceeds via measurements on some standard resource state. So-called flow conditions ensure that the overall computation is deterministic in a suitable sense, with Pauli flow being the most general of these. Existing work on rewriting MBQC patterns while preserving the existence of flow has focused on rewrites that reduce the number of qubits. In this work, we show that introducing new $Z$-measured qubits, connected to any subset of the existing qubits, preserves the existence of Pauli flow. Furthermore, we give a unique canonical form for stabilizer ZX-diagrams inspired by recent work of Hu & Khesin [arXiv:2109.10210]. We prove that any MBQC-like stabilizer ZX-diagram with Pauli flow can be rewritten into this canonical form using only rules which preserve the existence of Pauli flow and that each of these rules can be reversed while also preserving the existence of Pauli flow. Hence we have complete graphical rewriting for MBQC-like stabilizer ZX-diagrams with Pauli flow.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>