<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Learning Distributions over Quantum Measurement Outcomes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03007</link>
    <author>Weiyuan Gong, Scott Aaronson</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shadow tomography for quantum states provides a sample efficient approach for predicting the properties of quantum systems when the properties are restricted to expectation values of $2$-outcome POVMs. However, these shadow tomography procedures yield poor bounds if there are more than 2 outcomes per measurement. In this paper, we consider a general problem of learning properties from unknown quantum states: given an unknown $d$-dimensional quantum state $\rho$ and $M$ unknown quantum measurements $\mathcal{M}_1,...,\mathcal{M}_M$ with $K\geq 2$ outcomes, estimating the probability distribution for applying $\mathcal{M}_i$ on $\rho$ to within total variation distance $\epsilon$. Compared to the special case when $K=2$, we need to learn unknown distributions instead of values. We develop an online shadow tomography procedure that solves this problem with high success probability requiring $\tilde{O}(K\log^2M\log d/\epsilon^4)$ copies of $\rho$. We further prove an information-theoretic lower bound that at least $\Omega(\min\{d^2,K+\log M\}/\epsilon^2)$ copies of $\rho$ are required to solve this problem with high success probability. Our shadow tomography procedure requires sample complexity with only logarithmic dependence on $M$ and $d$ and is sample-optimal for the dependence on $K$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Concentration bounds for quantum states and limitations on the QAOA from polynomial approximations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02715</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Tony Metger</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove concentration bounds for the following classes of quantum states: (i) output states of shallow quantum circuits, answering an open question from [DPMRF22]; (ii) injective matrix product states; (iii) output states of dense Hamiltonian evolution, i.e. states of the form $e^{\iota H^{(p)}} \cdots e^{\iota H^{(1)}} |\psi_0\rangle$ for any $n$-qubit product state $|\psi_0\rangle$, where each $H^{(i)}$ can be any local commuting Hamiltonian satisfying a norm constraint, including dense Hamiltonians with interactions between any qubits. Our proofs use polynomial approximations to show that these states are close to local operators. This implies that the distribution of the Hamming weight of a computational basis measurement (and of other related observables) concentrates. An example of (iii) are the states produced by the quantum approximate optimisation algorithm (QAOA). Using our concentration results for these states, we show that for a random spin model, the QAOA can only succeed with negligible probability even at super-constant level $p = o(\log \log n)$. This gives the first limitations on the QAOA on dense instances at super-constant level, improving upon the recent result [BGMZ22].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum supremacy in mechanical tasks: projectiles, rockets and quantum backflow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00725</link>
    <author>David Trillo, Thinh P. Le, Miguel Navascues</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a scenario where a non-relativistic one-dimensional quantum particle is prepared in some bounded region of space and left to propagate freely. After a certain amount of time, we check if the particle has reached some distant target region. We find that there exist "ultrafast" ("ultraslow") quantum states, whose probability of arrival is greater (smaller) than that of any classical system prepared in the same region with the same momentum distribution. We prove that the maximum possible difference between quantum and optimal classical arrival probabilities for projectiles, as well as for self-propelling particles or rockets, is limited by the Bracken-Melloy constant $c_{bm}$, introduced in $1969$ to characterize the maximum expression of the phenomenon known as quantum backflow. This mathematical correspondence extends to other examples of mechanical effects with a quantum advantage, whose study we advance by deriving the first rigorous upper bound $c_{bm} \leq 0.0725$. We also prove that the hard limit given by $c_{bm}$ can be overcome in a variant of the original projectile scenario: if the classical particle is required to possess, not just the same momentum distribution as the quantum particle, but also the same position distribution, then the difference between arrival probabilities can reach $0.1228$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Software Tools for Decoding Quantum Low-Density Parity Check Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01180</link>
    <author>Lucas Berent, Lukas Burgholzer, Robert Wille</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Error Correction (QEC) is an essential field of research towards the realization of large-scale quantum computers. On the theoretical side, a lot of effort is put into designing error-correcting codes that protect quantum data from errors, which inevitably happen due to the noisy nature of quantum hardware and quantum bits (qubits). Protecting data with an error-correcting code necessitates means to recover the original data, given a potentially corrupted data set-a task referred to as decoding. It is vital that decoding algorithms can recover error-free states in an efficient manner. While theoretical properties of recent QEC methods have been extensively studied, good techniques to analyze their performance in practically more relevant settings is still a widely unexplored area. In this work, we propose a set of software tools that allows to numerically experiment with so-called Quantum Low-Density Parity Check codes (QLDPC codes)-a broad class of codes, some of which have recently been shown to be asymptotically good. Based on that, we provide an implementation of a general decoder for QLDPC codes. On top of that, we propose an efficient heuristic decoder that tackles the runtime bottlenecks of the general QLDPC decoder while still maintaining comparable decoding performance. These tools eventually allow to confirm theoretical results around QLDPC codes in a more practical setting and showcase the value of software tools (in addition to theoretical considerations) for investigating codes for practical applications. The resulting tool, which is publicly available at https://github.com/lucasberent/qecc under the MIT license, is meant to provide a playground for the search for "practically good" quantum codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sample optimal tomography of quantum Markov chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02240</link>
    <author>Li Gao, Nengkun Yu</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A state on a tripartite quantum system $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C} $ forms a Markov chain, i.e., quantum conditional independence, if it can be reconstructed from its marginal on $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}$ by a quantum operation from $\mathcal{H}_{B}$ to $\mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C}$ via the famous Petz map: a quantum Markov chain $\rho_{ABC}$ satisfies $\rho_{ABC}=\rho_{BC}^{1/2}(\rho_B^{-1/2}\rho_{AB}\rho_B^{-1/2}\otimes id_C)\rho_{BC}^{1/2}$. In this paper, we study the robustness of the Petz map for different metrics, i.e., the closeness of marginals implies the closeness of the Petz map outcomes. The robustness results are dimension-independent for infidelity $\delta$ and trace distance $\epsilon$. The applications of robustness results are The sample complexity of quantum Markov chain tomography, i.e., how many copies of an unknown quantum Markov chain are necessary and sufficient to determine the state, is $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\delta})$, and $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\epsilon^2}) $. The sample complexity of quantum Markov Chain certification, i.e., to certify whether a tripartite state equals a fixed given quantum Markov Chain $\sigma_{ABC}$ or at least $\delta$-far from $\sigma_{ABC}$, is ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\delta})$, and ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\epsilon^2})$. $\tilde{O}(\frac{\min\{d_Ad_B^3d_C^3,d_A^3d_B^3d_C\}}{\epsilon^2})$ copies to test whether $\rho_{ABC}$ is a quantum Markov Chain or $\epsilon$-far from its Petz recovery state. We generalized the tomography results into multipartite quantum system by showing $\tilde{O}(\frac{n^2\max_{i} \{d_i^2d_{i+1}^2\}}{\delta})$ copies for infidelity $\delta$ are enough for $n$-partite quantum Markov chain tomography with $d_i$ being the dimension of the $i$-th subsystem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Approximation Algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02589</link>
    <author>Robbie King</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give an approximation algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut which works by rounding an SDP relaxation to an entangled quantum state. The SDP is used to choose the parameters of a variational quantum circuit. The entangled state is then represented as the quantum circuit applied to a product state. It achieves an approximation ratio of 0.582, significantly improving on the algorithms of Anshu, Gosset, Morenz, 0.531, and Parekh, Thompson, 0.533. In addition, we also study the EPR Hamiltonian, which we argue is a natural intermediate problem which isolates some key quantum features of local Hamiltonian problems. For the EPR Hamiltonian, we give an approximation algorithm with approximation ratio $\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Transition states and greedy exploration of the QAOA optimization landscape</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01159</link>
    <author>Stefan H. Sack, Raimel A. Medina, Richard Kueng, Maksym Serbyn</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The QAOA is a variational quantum algorithm, where a quantum computer implements a variational ansatz consisting of p layers of alternating unitary operators and a classical computer is used to optimize the variational parameters. For a random initialization the optimization typically leads to local minima with poor performance, motivating the search for initialization strategies of QAOA variational parameters. Although numerous heuristic intializations were shown to have a good numerical performance, an analytical understanding remains evasive. Inspired by the study of energy landscapes, in this work we focus on so-called transition states (TS) that are saddle points with a unique negative curvature direction that connects to local minima. Starting from a local minimum of QAOA with p layers, we analytically construct 2p + 1 TS for QAOA with p + 1 layers. These TS connect to new local minima, all of which are guaranteed to lower the energy compared to the minimum found for p layers. We introduce a Greedy procedure to effectively maneuver the exponentially increasing number of TS and corresponding local minima. The performance of our procedure matches the best available initialization strategy, and in addition provides a guarantee for the minimal energy to decrease with an increasing number of layers p. Generalization of analytic TS and the Greedy approach to other ansätze may provide a universal framework for initialization of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable and Flexible Classical Shadow Tomography with Tensor Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02093</link>
    <author>Ahmed A. Akhtar, Hong-Ye Hu, Yi-Zhuang You</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classical shadow tomography is a powerful randomized measurement protocol for predicting many properties of a quantum state with few measurements. Two classical shadow protocols have been extensively studied in the literature: the single-qubit (local) Pauli measurement, which is well suited for predicting local operators but inefficient for large operators; and the global Clifford measurement, which is efficient for low-rank operators but infeasible on near-term quantum devices due to the extensive gate overhead. In this work, we demonstrate a scalable classical shadow tomography approach for generic randomized measurements implemented with finite-depth local Clifford random unitary circuits, which interpolates between the limits of Pauli and Clifford measurements. The method combines the recently proposed locally-scrambled classical shadow tomography framework with tensor network techniques to achieve scalability for computing the classical shadow reconstruction map and evaluating various physical properties. The method enables classical shadow tomography to be performed on shallow quantum circuits with superior sample efficiency and minimal gate overhead and is friendly to noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. We show that the shallow-circuit measurement protocol provides immediate, exponential advantages over the Pauli measurement protocol for predicting quasi-local operators. It also enables a more efficient fidelity estimation compared to the Pauli measurement.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Approximate Degree of DNF and CNF Formulas</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01584</link>
    <author>Alexander A. Sherstov</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The approximate degree of a Boolean function $f\colon\{0,1\}^n\to\{0,1\}$ is the minimum degree of a real polynomial $p$ that approximates $f$ pointwise: $|f(x)-p(x)|\leq1/3$ for all $x\in\{0,1\}^n.$ For every $\delta>0,$ we construct CNF and DNF formulas of polynomial size with approximate degree $\Omega(n^{1-\delta}),$ essentially matching the trivial upper bound of $n.$ This improves polynomially on previous lower bounds and fully resolves the approximate degree of constant-depth circuits ($\text{AC}^0$), a question that has seen extensive research over the past 10 years. Previously, an $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$ lower bound was known only for $\text{AC}^0$ circuits of depth that grows with $1/\delta$ (Bun and Thaler, FOCS 2017). Moreover, our CNF and DNF formulas are the simplest possible in that they have constant width. Our result holds even for one-sided approximation, and has the following further consequences. (i) We essentially settle the communication complexity of $\text{AC}^0$ circuits in the bounded-error quantum model, $k$-party number-on-the-forehead randomized model, and $k$-party number-on-the-forehead nondeterministic model: we prove that for every $\delta>0$, these models require $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$, $\Omega(n/4^kk^2)^{1-\delta}$, and $\Omega(n/4^kk^2)^{1-\delta}$, respectively, bits of communication even for polynomial-size constant-width CNF formulas. (ii) In particular, we show that the multiparty communication class $\text{coNP}_k$ can be separated essentially optimally from $\text{NP}_k$ and $\text{BPP}_k$ by a particularly simple function, a polynomial-size constant-width CNF. (iii) We give an essentially tight separation, of $O(1)$ versus $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$, for the one-sided versus two-sided approximate degree of a function; and $O(1)$ versus $\Omega(n^{1-\delta})$ for the one-sided approximate degree of a function $f$ versus its negation $\neg f$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved maximum-likelihood quantum amplitude estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03321</link>
    <author>Adam Callison, Dan Browne</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum amplitude estimation is a key subroutine in a number of powerful quantum algorithms, including quantum-enhanced Monte Carlo simulation and quantum machine learning. Maximum-likelihood quantum amplitude estimation (MLQAE) is one of a number of recent approaches that employ much simpler quantum circuits than the original algorithm based on quantum phase estimation. In this article, we deepen the analysis of MLQAE to put the algorithm in a more prescriptive form, including scenarios where quantum circuit depth is limited. In the process, we observe and explain particular ranges of `exceptional' values of the target amplitude for which the algorithm fails to achieve the desired precision. We then propose and numerically validate a heuristic modification to the algorithm to overcome this problem, bringing the algorithm even closer to being useful as a practical subroutine on near- and mid-term quantum hardware.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>