<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>stateQIP = statePSPACE</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07730</link>
    <author>Tony Metger, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Complexity theory traditionally studies the hardness of solving classical computational problems. In the quantum setting, it is also natural to consider a different notion of complexity, namely the complexity of physically preparing a certain quantum state. We study the relation between two such state complexity classes: statePSPACE, which contains states that can be generated by space-uniform polynomial-space quantum circuits, and stateQIP, which contains states that a polynomial-time quantum verifier can generate by interacting with an all-powerful untrusted quantum prover. The latter class was recently introduced by Rosenthal and Yuen (ITCS 2022), who proved that statePSPACE $\subseteq$ stateQIP. Our main result is the reverse inclusion, stateQIP $\subseteq$ statePSPACE, thereby establishing equality of the two classes and providing a natural state-complexity analogue to the celebrated QIP = PSPACE theorem of Jain, et al. (J. ACM 2011). To prove this, we develop a polynomial-space quantum algorithm for solving exponentially large "PSPACE-computable" semidefinite programs (SDPs), which also prepares an optimiser encoded in a quantum state. Our SDP solver relies on recent block-encoding techniques from quantum algorithms, demonstrating that these techniques are also useful for complexity theory. Using similar techniques, we also show that optimal prover strategies for general quantum interactive protocols can be implemented in quantum polynomial space. We prove this by studying an algorithmic version of Uhlmann's theorem and establishing an upper bound on the complexity of implementing Uhlmann transformations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A note on lower bounds to variational problems with guarantees</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06142</link>
    <author>J. Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods play an important role in the study of quantum many body problems, both in the flavour of classical variational principles based on tensor networks as well as of quantum variational principles in near-term quantum computing. This brief pedagogical note stresses that for translationally invariant lattice Hamiltonians, one can easily derive efficiently computable lower bounds to ground state energies that can and should be compared with variational principles providing upper bounds. As small technical results, it is shown that (i) the Anderson bound and a (ii) common hierarchy of semi-definite relaxations both provide approximations with performance guarantees that scale like a constant in the energy density for cubic lattices. (iii) Also, the Anderson bound is systematically improved as a hierarchy of semi-definite relaxations inspired by the marginal problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A generic quantum Wielandt's inequality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08241</link>
    <author>Yifan Jia, Angela Capel</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we provide a generic version of quantum Wielandt's inequality, which gives an optimal upper bound on the minimal length $k$ such that length-$k$ products of elements in a generating system span $M_n(\mathbb{C})$ with probability one. We show that $k$ generically is of order $\Theta(\log n)$, as opposed to the general case, in which the best bound to the date is $O(n^2 \log n)$. Our result implies a new bound on the primitivity index of a random quantum channel. Furthermore, we conclude that almost any translation-invariant (with periodic boundary conditions) matrix product state with length of order $\Omega( \log n )$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian. We observe similar characteristics for matrix Lie algebras and provide numerical results for random Lie-generating systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast Quantum Algorithms for Trace Distance Estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06783</link>
    <author>Qisheng Wang, Zhicheng Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In quantum information processing, trace distance is a basic metric of distinguishability between quantum states. However, there is no known efficient approach to estimate the value of trace distance in general. In this paper, we propose efficient quantum algorithms for estimating the trace distance within additive error $\varepsilon$ between mixed quantum states of rank $r$. Specifically, we first provide a quantum algorithm using $r \cdot \widetilde O(1/\varepsilon^2)$ queries to the quantum circuits that prepare the purifications of quantum states, which achieves a linear time dependence on the rank $r$. Then, we modify this quantum algorithm to obtain another algorithm using $\widetilde O(r^2/\varepsilon^5)$ samples of quantum states, which can be applied to quantum state certification. Both algorithms have the same quantum time complexities as their query/sample complexities up to a logarithmic factor.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Asymptotic and catalytic matrix majorization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07353</link>
    <author>Muhammad Usman Farooq, Tobias Fritz, Erkka Haapasalo, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The matrix majorization problem asks, given two tuples of probability vectors, whether there exists a single stochastic matrix transforming one tuple into the other. Solving an open problem due to Mu et al, we show that if certain monotones - namely multivariate extensions of Renyi divergences - are strictly ordered between the two tuples, then for sufficiently large $n$, there exists a stochastic matrix taking $n$ copies of each input distribution to $n$ copies of the corresponding output distribution. The same conditions, with non-strict ordering for the monotones, are also necessary for such asymptotic matrix majorization. Our result also yields a map that approximately converts a single copy of each input distribution to the corresponding output distribution with the help of a catalyst that is returned unchanged. Allowing for transformation with arbitrarily small error, we find conditions that are both necessary and sufficient for such catalytic matrix majorization. We derive our results by building on a general algebraic theory of preordered semirings recently developed by one of the authors. This also allows us to recover various existing results on asymptotic and catalytic majorization as well as relative majorization in a unified manner.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Block Belief Propagation Algorithm for 2D Tensor Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05844</link>
    <author>Chu Guo, Dario Poletti, Itai Arad</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Belief propagation is a well-studied algorithm for approximating local marginals of multivariate probability distribution over complex networks, while tensor network states are powerful tools for quantum and classical many-body problems. Building on a recent connection between the belief propagation algorithm and the problem of tensor network contraction, we propose a block belief propagation algorithm for contracting two-dimensional tensor networks and approximating the ground state of $2D$ systems. The advantages of our method are three-fold: 1) the same algorithm works for both finite and infinite systems; 2) it allows natural and efficient parallelization; 3) given its flexibility it would allow to deal with different unit cells. As applications, we use our algorithm to study the $2D$ Heisenberg and transverse Ising models, and show that the accuracy of the method is comparable to state-of-the-art results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hierarchical Clifford transformations to reduce entanglement in quantum chemistry wavefunctions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07726</link>
    <author>Ryan V. Mishmash, Tanvi P. Gujarati, Mario Motta, Huanchen Zhai, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan, Antonio Mezzacapo</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The performance of computational methods for many-body physics and chemistry is strongly dependent on the choice of basis used to cast the problem; hence, the search for better bases and similarity transformations is important for progress in the field. So far, tools from theoretical quantum information have been not thoroughly explored for this task. Here we take a step in this direction by presenting efficiently computable Clifford similarity transformations for quantum chemistry Hamiltonians, which expose bases with reduced entanglement in the corresponding molecular ground states. These transformations are constructed via block diagonalization of a hierarchy of truncated molecular Hamiltonians, preserving the full spectrum of the original problem. We show that the bases introduced here allow for more efficient classical and quantum computation of ground state properties. First, we find a systematic reduction of bipartite entanglement in molecular ground states as compared to standard problem representations. This entanglement reduction has implications in classical numerical methods such as ones based on the density matrix renormalization group. Then, we develop variational quantum algorithms that exploit the structure in the new bases, showing again improved results when the hierarchical Clifford transformations are used.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New constructive counterexamples to additivity of minimum output Rényi entropy of quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07428</link>
    <author>Krzysztof Szczygielski, Michał Studziński</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper we present new families of quantum channels for which corresponding minimum output Rényi entropy is not additive. In the first part of the manuscript, motivated by work of Grudka et. al. (J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 43, 425304 (2010)), we focus on extensions of the antisymmetric space and its subspaces. Later on we analyze a special case of completely entangled subspace proposed by Parthasarathy in Proc. Math. Sci. 114, 365-374 (2004). Our construction works for every $p>2$ and dimension high enough.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Probabilistic unitary synthesis with optimal accuracy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.06307</link>
    <author>Seiseki Akibue, Go Kato, Seiichiro Tani</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 18 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The purpose of unitary synthesis is to find a gate sequence that optimally approximates a target unitary transformation. A new synthesis approach, called probabilistic synthesis, has been introduced, and its superiority has been demonstrated over traditional deterministic approaches with respect to approximation error and gate length. However, the optimality of current probabilistic synthesis algorithms is unknown. We obtain the tight lower bound on the approximation error obtained by the optimal probabilistic synthesis, which guarantees the sub-optimality of current algorithms. We also show its tight upper bound, which improves and unifies current upper bounds depending on the class of target unitaries. These two bounds reveal the fundamental relationship of approximation error between probabilistic approximation and deterministic approximation of unitary transformations. From a computational point of view, we show that the optimal probability distribution can be computed by the semidefinite program (SDP) we construct. We also construct an efficient probabilistic synthesis algorithm for single-qubit unitaries, rigorously estimate its time complexity, and show that it reduces the approximation error quadratically compared with deterministic algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Remote detectability from entanglement bootstrap I: Kirby's torus trick</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.07119</link>
    <author>Bowen Shi, Jin-Long Huang, John McGreevy</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Remote detectability is often taken as a physical assumption in the study of topologically ordered systems, and it is a central axiom of mathematical frameworks of topological quantum field theories. We show under the entanglement bootstrap approach that remote detectability is a necessary property; that is, we derive it as a theorem. Starting from a single wave function on a topologically-trivial region satisfying the entanglement bootstrap axioms, we can construct states on closed manifolds. The crucial technique is to immerse the punctured manifold into the topologically trivial region and then heal the puncture. This is analogous to Kirby's torus trick. We then analyze a special class of such manifolds, which we call pairing manifolds. For each pairing manifold, which pairs two classes of excitations, we identify an analog of the topological S-matrix. This pairing matrix is unitary, which implies remote detectability between two classes of excitations. These matrices are in general not associated with the mapping class group of the manifold. As a by-product, we can count excitation types (e.g., graph excitations in 3+1d). The pairing phenomenon occurs in many physical contexts, including systems in different dimensions, with or without gapped boundaries. We provide a variety of examples to illustrate its scope.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>