<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Challenges in Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15844</link>
    <author>Daniel Gottesman</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I will give an overview of what I see as some of the most important future directions in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation. In particular, I will give a brief summary of the major problems that need to be solved in fault tolerance based on low-density parity check codes and in hardware-specific fault tolerance. I will then conclude with a discussion of a possible new paradigm for designing fault-tolerant protocols based on a space-time picture of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Pseudoentanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.00747</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Bill Fefferman, Soumik Ghosh, Umesh Vazirani, Zixin Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum pseudorandom states are efficiently constructable states which nevertheless masquerade as Haar-random states to poly-time observers. First defined by Ji, Liu and Song, such states have found a number of applications ranging from cryptography to the AdS/CFT correspondence. A fundamental question is exactly how much entanglement is required to create such states. Haar-random states, as well as $t$-designs for $t\geq 2$, exhibit near-maximal entanglement. Here we provide the first construction of pseudorandom states with only polylogarithmic entanglement entropy across an equipartition of the qubits, which is the minimum possible. Our construction can be based on any one-way function secure against quantum attack. We additionally show that the entanglement in our construction is fully "tunable", in the sense that one can have pseudorandom states with entanglement $\Theta(f(n))$ for any desired function $\omega(\log n) \leq f(n) \leq O(n)$. More fundamentally, our work calls into question to what extent entanglement is a "feelable" quantity of quantum systems. Inspired by recent work of Gheorghiu and Hoban, we define a new notion which we call "pseudoentanglement", which are ensembles of efficiently constructable quantum states which hide their entanglement entropy. We show such states exist in the strongest form possible while simultaneously being pseudorandom states. We also describe diverse applications of our result from entanglement distillation to property testing to quantum gravity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Greatly improved higher-order product formulae for quantum simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15817</link>
    <author>Mauro E.S. Morales, Pedro C.S. Costa, Daniel K. Burgarth, Yuval R. Sanders, Dominic W. Berry</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for simulation of Hamiltonian evolution are often based on product formulae like Trotter. The fractal method of Suzuki gives a systematic way to find arbitrarily high-order product formulae, but results in a large number of exponentials. On the other hand, an alternative way, with a minimum number of exponentials, for 6th and 8th order product formulae is given by Yoshida. In this work, we not only extended Yoshida's method to 10th order, but we also found hundreds of new 8th order product formulae. Moreover, we found an 8th order product formula that is over $1000$ times more accurate than the best product formula of Yoshida.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The $2T$-qutrit, a two-mode bosonic qutrit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16188</link>
    <author>Aurélie Denys, Anthony Leverrier</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Building on the observation that bosonic cat codes live in the span of coherent states indexed by a finite subgroup of the complex numbers, we consider a two-mode bosonic code where the coherent states now form a finite subgroup of the quaternions. We focus on the binary tetrahedral group, denoted $2T$, which admits 24 elements forming the vertices of the 24-cell, a regular four-dimensional polytope, and define a bosonic qutrit that appears to be quite robust in the regime of low loss. We initiate a study of the properties of this qutrit and identify stabilisers as well as logical operators for this bosonic code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Deterministic constant-depth preparation of the AKLT state on a quantum processor using fusion measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.17548</link>
    <author>Kevin C. Smith, Eleanor Crane, Nathan Wiebe, S. M. Girvin</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ground state of the spin-1 Affleck, Kennedy, Lieb and Tasaki (AKLT) model is a paradigmatic example of both a matrix product state and a symmetry-protected topological phase, and additionally holds promise as a resource state for measurement-based quantum computation. Having a nonzero correlation length, the AKLT state cannot be exactly prepared by a constant-depth unitary circuit composed of local gates. In this work, we demonstrate that this no-go limit can be evaded by augmenting a constant-depth circuit with fusion measurements, such that the total preparation time is independent of system size and entirely deterministic. We elucidate our preparation scheme using the language of tensor networks, and furthermore show that the $\mathbb{Z}_2\times\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry of the AKLT state directly affords this speed-up over previously known preparation methods. To demonstrate the practical advantage of measurement-assisted preparation on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices, we carry out our protocol on an IBM Quantum processor. We measure both the string order and entanglement spectrum of prepared AKLT chains and, employing these as metrics, find improved results over the known (purely unitary) sequential preparation approach. We conclude with a demonstration of quantum teleportation using the AKLT state prepared by our measurement-assisted scheme. This work thus serves to provide an efficient strategy to prepare a specific resource in the form of the AKLT state and, more broadly, experimentally demonstrates the possibility for realizable improvement in state preparation afforded by measurement-based circuit depth reduction strategies on NISQ-era devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New magic state distillation factories optimized by temporally encoded lattice surgery</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15814</link>
    <author>Prithviraj Prabhu, Christopher Chamberland</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fault-tolerant quantum computers, with error correction implemented using topological codes, will most likely require lattice surgery protocols in order to implement a universal gate set. Timelike failures during lattice surgery protocols can result in logical failures during the execution of an algorithm. In addition to the spacelike distance of the topological code used to protect the qubits from errors, there is also the timelike distance which is given by the number of syndrome measurement rounds during a lattice surgery protocol. As such, a larger timelike distance requirement will result in the slowdown of an algorithm's runtime. Temporal encoding of lattice surgery (TELS) is a technique which can be used to reduce the number of syndrome measurement rounds that are required during a lattice surgery protocol. This is done by measuring an over-complete set of mutually commuting multi-qubit Pauli operators (referred to as a parallelizable Pauli set) which form codewords of a classical error correcting code. The results of the over-complete set of Pauli measurements can then be used to detect and possibly correct timelike lattice surgery failures. In this work, we introduce an improved TELS protocol and subsequently augment it with the ability to correct low-weight classical errors, resulting in greater speedups in algorithm runtimes. We also explore large families of classical error correcting codes for a wide range of parallelizable Pauli set sizes. We also apply TELS to magic state distillation protocols in the context of biased noise, where logical qubits are encoded in asymmetric surface codes. Using optimized layouts, we show improvements in the space-time cost of our magic state factories compared to previous protocols. Such improvements are achieved using computations performed in the Clifford frame.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum algorithms for classical Boolean functions via adaptive measurements: Exponential reductions in space-time resources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.01252</link>
    <author>Austin K. Daniel, Akimasa Miyake</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The limited computational power of constant-depth quantum circuits can be boosted by adapting future gates according to the outcomes of mid-circuit measurements. We formulate computation of a variety of Boolean functions in the framework of adaptive measurement-based quantum computation using a cluster state resource and a classical side-processor that can add bits modulo 2, so-called $l2$-MBQC. Our adaptive approach overcomes a known challenge that computing these functions in the nonadaptive setting requires a resource state that is exponentially large in the size of the computational input. In particular, we construct adaptive $l2$-MBQC algorithms based on the quantum signal processing technique that compute the mod-$p$ functions with the best known scaling in the space-time resources (i.e., qubit count, quantum circuit depth, classical memory size, and number of calls to the side-processor). As the subject is diverse and has a long history, the paper includes reviews of several previously constructed algorithms and recasts them as adaptive $l2$-MBQCs using cluster state resources. Our results constitute an alternative proof of an old theorem regarding an oracular separation between the power of constant-depth quantum circuits and constant-depth classical circuits with unbounded fan-in NAND and mod-$p$ gates for any prime $p$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Complete Hierarchy of Linear Systems for Certifying Quantum Entanglement of Subspaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.16389</link>
    <author>Nathaniel Johnston, Benjamin Lovitz, Aravindan Vijayaraghavan</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a hierarchy of linear systems for showing that a given subspace of pure quantum states is entangled (i.e., contains no product states). This hierarchy outperforms known methods already at the first level, and it is complete in the sense that every entangled subspace is shown to be so at some finite level of the hierarchy. It generalizes straightforwardly to the case of higher Schmidt rank, as well as the multipartite cases of completely and genuinely entangled subspaces. These hierarchies work extremely well in practice even in very large quantum systems, as they can be implemented via elementary linear algebra techniques rather than the semidefinite programming techniques that are required by previously-known hierarchies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Finite temperature tensor network algorithm for frustrated two-dimensional quantum materials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.00121</link>
    <author>Philipp Schmoll, Christian Balz, Bella Lake, Jens Eisert, Augustine Kshetrimayum</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Aimed at a more realistic classical description of natural quantum systems, we present a two-dimensional tensor network algorithm to study finite temperature properties of frustrated model quantum systems and real quantum materials. For this purpose, we introduce the infinite projected entangled simplex operator ansatz to study thermodynamic properties. To obtain state-of-the-art benchmarking results, we explore the highly challenging spin-1/2 Heisenberg anti-ferromagnet on the Kagome lattice, a system for which we investigate the melting of the magnetization plateaus at finite magnetic field and temperature. Making close connection to actual experimental data of real quantum materials, we go on to studying the finite temperature properties of Ca$_{10}$Cr$_7$O$_{28}$. We compare the magnetization curve of this material in the presence of an external magnetic field at finite temperature with classically simulated data. As a first theoretical tool that incorporates both thermal fluctuations as well as quantum correlations in the study of this material, our work contributes to settling the existing controversy between the experimental data and previous theoretical works on the magnetization process.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-Abelian Floquet Spin Liquids in a Digital Rydberg Simulator</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.00017</link>
    <author>Marcin Kalinowski, Nishad Maskara, Mikhail D. Lukin</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding topological matter is an outstanding challenge across several disciplines of physical science. Programmable quantum simulators have emerged as a powerful approach to studying such systems. While quantum spin liquids of paradigmatic toric code type have recently been realized in the laboratory, controlled exploration of topological phases with non-abelian excitations remains an open problem. We introduce and analyze a new approach to simulating topological matter based on periodic driving. Specifically, we describe a model for a so-called Floquet spin liquid, obtained through a periodic sequence of parallel quantum gate operations that effectively simulates the Hamiltonian of the non-abelian spin liquid in Kitaev's honeycomb model. We show that this approach, including the toolbox for preparation, control, and readout of topological states, can be efficiently implemented in state-of-the-art experimental platforms. One specific implementation scheme is based on Rydberg atom arrays and utilizes recently demonstrated coherent qubit transport combined with controlled-phase gate operations. We describe methods for probing the non-abelian excitations, and the associated Majorana zero modes, and simulate possible fusion and braiding experiments. Our analysis demonstrates the potential of programmable quantum simulators for exploring topological phases of matter. Extensions including simulation of Kitaev materials and lattice gauge theories are also discussed.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>