<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Efficiently improving the performance of noisy quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10672</link>
    <author>Samuele Ferracin, Akel Hashim, Jean-Loup Ville, Ravi Naik, Arnaud Carignan-Dugas, Hammam Qassim, Alexis Morvan, David I. Santiago, Irfan Siddiqi, Joel J. Wallman</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Using near-term quantum computers to achieve a quantum advantage requires efficient strategies to improve the performance of the noisy quantum devices presently available. We develop and experimentally validate two efficient error mitigation protocols named "Noiseless Output Extrapolation" and "Pauli Error Cancellation" that can drastically enhance the performance of quantum circuits composed of noisy cycles of gates. By combining popular mitigation strategies such as probabilistic error cancellation and noise amplification with efficient noise reconstruction methods, our protocols can mitigate a wide range of noise processes that do not satisfy the assumptions underlying existing mitigation protocols, including non-local and gate-dependent processes. We test our protocols on a four-qubit superconducting processor at the Advanced Quantum Testbed. We observe significant improvements in the performance of both structured and random circuits, with up to $86\%$ improvement in variation distance over the unmitigated outputs. Our experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our protocols, as well as their practicality for current hardware platforms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum State Preparation with Optimal Circuit Depth: Implementations and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11495</link>
    <author>Xiao-Ming Zhang, Tongyang Li, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum state preparation is an important subroutine for quantum computing. We show that any $n$-qubit quantum state can be prepared with a $\Theta(n)$-depth circuit using only single- and two-qubit gates, although with a cost of an exponential amount of ancillary qubits. On the other hand, for sparse quantum states with $d\geqslant2$ non-zero entries, we can reduce the circuit depth to $\Theta(\log(nd))$ with $O(nd\log d)$ ancillary qubits. The algorithm for sparse states is exponentially faster than best-known results and the number of ancillary qubits is nearly optimal and only increases polynomially with the system size. We discuss applications of the results in different quantum computing tasks, such as Hamiltonian simulation, solving linear systems of equations, and realizing quantum random access memories, and find cases with exponential reductions of the circuit depth for all these three tasks. In particular, using our algorithm, we find a family of linear system solving problems enjoying exponential speedups, even compared to the best-known quantum and classical dequantization algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simultaneous Measurement and Entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10667</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Peter Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study scenarios which arise when two spatially-separated observers, Alice and Bob, are try to identify a quantum state sampled from several possibilities. In particular, we examine their strategies for maximizing both the probability of guessing their state correctly as well as their information gain about it. It is known that there are scenarios where allowing Alice and Bob to use LOCC offers an improvement over the case where they must make their measurements simultaneously. Similarly, Alice and Bob can sometimes improve their outcomes if they have access to a Bell pair. We show how LOCC allows Alice and Bob to distinguish between two product states optimally and find that a LOCC is almost always more helpful than a Bell pair for distinguishing product states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Finding fault-tolerant Clifford circuits using SMT solvers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12450</link>
    <author>Noah Shutty, Christopher Chamberland</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Universal fault-tolerant quantum computers will require the use of efficient protocols to implement encoded operations necessary in the execution of algorithms. In this work, we show how SMT solvers can be used to automate the construction of Clifford circuits with certain fault-tolerance properties and apply our techniques to a fault-tolerant magic state preparation protocol. Part of the protocol requires converting magic states encoded in the color code to magic states encoded in the surface code. Since the teleportation step involves decoding a color code merged with a surface code, we develop a new decoding algorithm applicable to such codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailored cluster states with high threshold under biased noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.10566</link>
    <author>Jahan Claes, J. Eli Bourassa, Shruti Puri</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fault-tolerant cluster states form the basis for scalable measurement-based quantum computation. Recently, new stabilizer codes for scalable circuit-based quantum computation have been introduced that have very high thresholds under biased noise where the qubit predominantly suffers from one type of error, e.g. dephasing. However, extending these advances in stabilizer codes to generate high-threshold cluster states for biased noise has been a challenge, as the standard method for foliating stabilizer codes to generate fault-tolerant cluster states does not preserve the noise bias. In this work, we overcome this barrier by introducing a generalization of the cluster state that allows us to foliate stabilizer codes in a bias-preserving way. As an example of our approach, we construct a foliated version of the XZZX code which we call the XZZX cluster state. We demonstrate that under a circuit-level noise model, our XZZX cluster state has a threshold more than double the usual cluster state when dephasing errors are more likely than errors which cause bit flips by a factor of $O(100)$ or more.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An efficient quantum algorithm for lattice problems achieving subexponential approximation factor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.13450</link>
    <author>Lior Eldar, Sean Hallgren</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum algorithm for solving the Bounded Distance Decoding (BDD) problem with a subexponential approximation factor on a class of integer lattices. The quantum algorithm uses a well-known but challenging-to-use quantum state on lattices as a type of approximate quantum eigenvector to randomly self-reduce the BDD instance to a random BDD instance which is solvable classically. The running time of the quantum algorithm is polynomial for one range of approximation factors and subexponential time for a second range of approximation factors. The subclass of lattices we study has a natural description in terms of the lattice's periodicity and finite abelian group rank. This view makes for a clean quantum algorithm in terms of finite abelian groups, uses very relatively little from lattice theory, and suggests exploring approximation algorithms for lattice problems in parameters other than dimension alone. A talk on this paper sparked many lively discussions and resulted in a new classical algorithm matching part of our result. We leave it as a challenge to give a classcial algorithm matching the general case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum cryptography with classical communication: parallel remote state preparation for copy-protection, verification, and more</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.13445</link>
    <author>Alexandru Gheorghiu, Tony Metger, Alexander Poremba</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum mechanical effects have enabled the construction of cryptographic primitives that are impossible classically. For example, quantum copy-protection allows for a program to be encoded in a quantum state in such a way that the program can be evaluated, but not copied. Many of these cryptographic primitives are two-party protocols, where one party, Bob, has full quantum computational capabilities, and the other party, Alice, is only required to send random BB84 states to Bob. In this work, we show how such protocols can generically be converted to ones where Alice is fully classical, assuming that Bob cannot efficiently solve the LWE problem. In particular, this means that all communication between (classical) Alice and (quantum) Bob is classical, yet they can still make use of cryptographic primitives that would be impossible if both parties were classical. We apply this conversion procedure to obtain quantum cryptographic protocols with classical communication for unclonable encryption, copy-protection, computing on encrypted data, and verifiable blind delegated computation. The key technical ingredient for our result is a protocol for classically-instructed parallel remote state preparation of BB84 states. This is a multi-round protocol between (classical) Alice and (quantum polynomial-time) Bob that allows Alice to certify that Bob must have prepared $n$ uniformly random BB84 states (up to a change of basis on his space). Furthermore, Alice knows which specific BB84 states Bob has prepared, while Bob himself does not. Hence, the situation at the end of this protocol is (almost) equivalent to one where Alice sent $n$ random BB84 states to Bob. This allows us to replace the step of preparing and sending BB84 states in existing protocols by our remote-state preparation protocol in a generic and modular way.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reducing the impact of time-correlated noise on zero-noise extrapolation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11792</link>
    <author>Kevin Schultz, Ryan LaRose, Andrea Mari, Gregory Quiroz, Nathan Shammah, B. David Clader, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Zero-noise extrapolation is a quantum error mitigation technique that has typically been studied under the ideal approximation that the noise acting on a quantum device is not time-correlated. In this work, we investigate the feasibility and performance of zero-noise extrapolation in the presence of time-correlated noise. We show that, in contrast to white noise, time-correlated noise is harder to mitigate via zero-noise extrapolation because it is difficult to scale the noise level without also modifying its spectral distribution. This limitation is particularly strong if "local" gate-level methods are applied for noise scaling. However, we find that "global" noise scaling methods, e.g., global unitary folding, can be sufficiently reliable even in the presence of time-correlated noise. We also introduce gate Trotterization as a new noise scaling technique that may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Encoding qubits in multimode grid states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12337</link>
    <author>Baptiste Royer, Shraddha Sing, Steven M. Girvin</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Encoding logical quantum information in harmonic oscillator modes is a promising and hardware- efficient approach to the realization of a quantum computer. In this work, we propose to encode logical qubits in grid states of an ensemble of harmonic oscillator modes. We first discuss general results about these multimode bosonic codes; how to design them, how to practically implement them in different experimental platforms and how lattice symmetries can be leveraged to perform logical non-Clifford operations. We then introduce in detail two two-mode grid codes based on the hypercubic and D4 lattices, respectively, showing how to perform a universal set of logical operations. We demonstrate numerically that multimode grid codes have, compared to their single- mode counterpart, increased robustness against propagation of errors from ancillas used for error correction. Finally, we highlight some interesting links between multidimensional lattices and single- mode grid codes concatenated with qubit codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Efficient Quantum Readout Error Mitigation for Sparse Measurement Outcomes of Near-term Quantum Devices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11046</link>
    <author>Bo Yang, Rudy Raymond, Shumpei Uno</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The readout error on the near-term quantum devices is one of the dominant noise factors, which can be mitigated by classical post-processing called quantum readout error mitigation (QREM). The standard QREM method applies the inverse of noise calibration matrix to the outcome probability distribution using exponential computational resources to the system size. Hence this standard approach is not applicable to the current quantum devices with tens of qubits and more. We propose two efficient QREM methods on such devices whose computational complexity is $O(ns^2)$ for probability distributions on measuring $n$ qubits with $s$ shots. The main targets of the proposed methods are the sparse probability distributions where only a few states are dominant. We compare the proposed methods with several recent QREM methods on the following three cases: expectation values of GHZ state, its fidelities, and the estimation error of maximum likelihood amplitude estimation (MLAE) algorithm with modified Grover iterator. The two cases of the GHZ state are on real IBM quantum devices, while the third is by numerical simulation. The proposed methods can be applied to mitigate GHZ states up to 65 qubits on IBM Quantum devices within a few seconds to confirm the existence of a 29-qubit GHZ state with fidelity larger than 0.5. The proposed methods also succeed in the estimation of the amplitude in MLAE with the modified Grover operator where other QREM methods fail.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>