<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>An exact quantum hidden subgroup algorithm and applications to solvable groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04047</link>
    <author>Muhammad Imran, Gabor Ivanyos</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a polynomial time exact quantum algorithm for the hidden subgroup problem in $Z_{m^k}^n$. The algorithm uses the quantum Fourier transform modulo m and does not require factorization of m. For smooth m, i.e., when the prime factors of m are of size poly(log m), the quantum Fourier transform can be exactly computed using the method discovered independently by Cleve and Coppersmith, while for general m, the algorithm of Mosca and Zalka is available. Even for m=3 and k=1 our result appears to be new. We also present applications to compute the structure of abelian and solvable groups whose order has the same (but possibly unknown) prime factors as m. The applications for solvable groups also rely on an exact version of a technique proposed by Watrous for computing the uniform superposition of elements of subgroups.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Counting unitaries of T-depth one</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04163</link>
    <author>Vadym Kliuchnikov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits is $ \sum_{m=1}^{n}\tfrac{1}{m!}\prod_{k=0}^{m-1}(4^n/2^k - 2^k) \times \# \mathcal{C}_n, $ where $\#\mathcal{C}_n$ is the size of the $n$-qubit Clifford group, that is the number of unitaries of T-depth zero. The number of T-depth one unitaries on $n$ qubits grows as $2^{\Omega(n^2)} \cdot \# \mathcal{C}_n$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement estimation in tensor network states via sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04089</link>
    <author>Noa Feldman, Augustine Kshetrimayum, Jens Eisert, Moshe Goldstein</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a method for extracting meaningful entanglement measures of tensor network states in general dimensions. Current methods require the explicit reconstruction of the density matrix, which is highly demanding, or the contraction of replicas, which requires an effort exponential in the number of replicas and which is costly in terms of memory. In contrast, our method requires the stochastic sampling of matrix elements of the classically represented reduced states with respect to random states drawn from simple product probability measures constituting frames. Even though not corresponding to physical operations, such matrix elements are straightforward to calculate for tensor network states, and their moments provide the Rényi entropies and negativities as well as their symmetry-resolved components. We test our method on the one-dimensional critical XX chain and the two-dimensional toric code. Although the cost is exponential in the subsystem size, it is sufficiently moderate so that - in contrast with other approaches - accurate results can be obtained on a personal computer for relatively large subsystem sizes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Transitions in Entanglement Complexity in Random Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02648</link>
    <author>Sarah True, Alioscia Hamma</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement is the defining characteristic of quantum mechanics. Bipartite entanglement is characterized by the von Neumann entropy. Entanglement is not just described by a number, however; it is also characterized by its level of complexity. The complexity of entanglement is at the root of the onset of quantum chaos, universal distribution of entanglement spectrum statistics, difficulty of the disentangling algorithm, and temporal entanglement fluctuations. In this paper, we numerically show how a crossover from a simple pattern of entanglement to a universal, complex pattern can be driven by doping a random Clifford circuit with $T$ gates. This work shows that quantum complexity and complex entanglement stem from the conjunction of entanglement and non-stabilizer resources, also known as magic.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadows with Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03272</link>
    <author>Kaifeng Bu, Dax Enshan Koh, Roy J. Garcia, Arthur Jaffe</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The classical shadow estimation protocol is a noise-resilient and sample-efficient quantum algorithm for learning the properties of quantum systems. Its performance depends on the choice of a unitary ensemble, which must be chosen by a user in advance. What is the weakest assumption that can be made on the chosen unitary ensemble that would still yield meaningful and interesting results? To address this question, we consider the class of Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles, i.e. unitary ensembles that are invariant under multiplication by a Pauli operator. This class includes many previously studied ensembles like the local and global Clifford ensembles as well as locally scrambled unitary ensembles. For this class of ensembles, we provide an explicit formula for the reconstruction map corresponding to the shadow channel and give explicit sample complexity bounds. In addition, we provide two applications of our results. Our first application is to locally scrambled unitary ensembles, where we give explicit formulas for the reconstruction map and sample complexity bounds that circumvent the need to solve an exponential-sized linear system. Our second application is to the classical shadow tomography of quantum channels with Pauli-invariant unitary ensembles. Our results pave the way for more efficient or robust protocols for predicting important properties of quantum states, such as their fidelity, entanglement entropy, and quantum Fisher information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Identification of topological phases using classically-optimized variational quantum eigensolver</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02909</link>
    <author>Ken N. Okada, Keita Osaki, Kosuke Mitarai, Keisuke Fujii</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) is regarded as a promising candidate of hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for the near-term quantum computers. Meanwhile, VQE is confronted with a challenge that statistical error associated with the measurement as well as systematic error could significantly hamper the optimization. To circumvent this issue, we propose classically-optimized VQE (co-VQE), where the whole process of the optimization is efficiently conducted on a classical computer. The efficacy of the method is guaranteed by the observation that quantum circuits with a constant (or logarithmic) depth are classically tractable via simulations of local subsystems. In co-VQE, we only use quantum computers to measure nonlocal quantities after the parameters are optimized. As proof-of-concepts, we present numerical experiments on quantum spin models with topological phases. After the optimization, we identify the topological phases by nonlocal order parameters as well as unsupervised machine learning on inner products between quantum states. The proposed method maximizes the advantage of using quantum computers while avoiding strenuous optimization on noisy quantum devices. Furthermore, in terms of quantum machine learning, our study shows an intriguing approach that employs quantum computers to generate data of quantum systems while using classical computers for the learning process.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement catalysis for quantum states and noisy channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05228</link>
    <author>Chandan Datta, Tulja Varun Kondra, Marek Miller, Alexander Streltsov</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many applications of the emerging quantum technologies, such as quantum teleportation and quantum key distribution, require singlets, maximally entangled states of two quantum bits. It is thus of utmost importance to develop optimal procedures for establishing singlets between remote parties. As has been shown very recently, singlets can be obtained from other quantum states by using a quantum catalyst, an entangled quantum system which is not changed in the procedure. In this work we put this idea further, investigating properties of entanglement catalysis and its role for quantum communication. For transformations between bipartite pure states we prove the existence of a universal catalyst, which can enable all possible transformations in this setup. We demonstrate the advantage of catalysis in asymptotic settings, going beyond the typical assumption of independent and identically distributed systems. We further develop methods to estimate the number of singlets which can be established via a noisy quantum channel when assisted by entangled catalysts. For various types of quantum channels our results lead to optimal protocols, allowing to establish the maximal number of singlets with a single use of the channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal logic with encoded spin qubits in silicon</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.03605</link>
    <author>Aaron J. Weinstein, Matthew D. Reed, Aaron M. Jones, Reed W. Andrews, David Barnes, Jacob Z. Blumoff, Larken E. Euliss, Kevin Eng, Bryan Fong, Sieu D. Ha, Daniel R. Hulbert, Clayton Jackson, Michael Jura, Tyler E. Keating, Joseph Kerckhoff, Andrey A. Kiselev, Justine Matten, Golam Sabbir, Aaron Smith, Jeffrey Wright, et al (3)</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Qubits encoded in a decoherence-free subsystem and realized in exchange-coupled silicon quantum dots are promising candidates for fault-tolerant quantum computing. Benefits of this approach include excellent coherence, low control crosstalk, and configurable insensitivity to certain error sources. Key difficulties are that encoded entangling gates require a large number of control pulses and high-yielding quantum dot arrays. Here we show a device made using the single-layer etch-defined gate electrode architecture that achieves both the required functional yield needed for full control and the coherence necessary for thousands of calibrated exchange pulses to be applied. We measure an average two-qubit Clifford fidelity of $97.1 \pm 0.2\%$ with randomized benchmarking. We also use interleaved randomized benchmarking to demonstrate the controlled-NOT gate with $96.3 \pm 0.7\%$ fidelity, SWAP with $99.3 \pm 0.5\%$ fidelity, and a specialized entangling gate that limits spreading of leakage with $93.8 \pm 0.7\%$ fidelity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying information scrambling via Classical Shadow Tomography on Programmable Quantum Simulators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.05132</link>
    <author>Max McGinley, Sebastian Leontica, Samuel J. Garratt, Jovan Jovanovic, Steven H. Simon</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We develop techniques to probe the dynamics of quantum information, and implement them experimentally on an IBM superconducting quantum processor. Our protocols adapt shadow tomography for the study of time evolution channels rather than of quantum states, and rely only on single-qubit operations and measurements. We identify two unambiguous signatures of quantum information scrambling, neither of which can be mimicked by dissipative processes, and relate these to many-body teleportation. By realizing quantum chaotic dynamics in experiment, we measure both signatures, and support our results with numerical simulations of the quantum system. We additionally investigate operator growth under this dynamics, and observe behaviour characteristic of quantum chaos. As our methods require only a single quantum state at a time, they can be readily applied on a wide variety of quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Deconfinement and Error Thresholds in Holography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.04710</link>
    <author>Ning Bao, Charles Cao, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the error threshold properties of holographic quantum error-correcting codes. We demonstrate that holographic CFTs admit an algebraic threshold, which is related to the confinement-deconfinement phase transition. We then apply geometric intuition from holography and the Hawking-Page phase transition to motivate the CFT result, and comment on potential extensions to other confining theories.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>