<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A construction of Combinatorial NLTS</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02741</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of high complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). Here, we prove a weaker version called the combinatorial NLTS, where a quantum circuit lower bound is shown against states that violate a (small) constant fraction of local terms. This generalizes the prior NLETS results (Eldar and Harrow [2017]; Nirkhe, Vazirani and Yuen [2018]). Our construction is obtained by combining tensor networks with expander codes (Sipser and Spielman [1996]). The Hamiltonian is the parent Hamiltonian of a perturbed tensor network, inspired by the `uncle Hamiltonian' of Fernandez-Gonzalez et. al. [2015]. Thus, we deviate from the quantum CSS code Hamiltonians considered in most prior works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive Online Learning of Quantum States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00220</link>
    <author>Xinyi Chen, Elad Hazan, Tongyang Li, Zhou Lu, Xinzhao Wang, Rui Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the fundamental problem of shadow tomography, the goal is to efficiently learn an unknown $d$-dimensional quantum state using projective measurements. However, it is rarely the case that the underlying state remains stationary: changes may occur due to measurements, environmental noise, or an underlying Hamiltonian state evolution. In this paper we adopt tools from adaptive online learning to learn a changing state, giving adaptive and dynamic regret bounds for online shadow tomography that are polynomial in the number of qubits and sublinear in the number of measurements. Our analysis utilizes tools from complex matrix analysis to cope with complex numbers, which may be of independent interest in online learning. In addition, we provide numerical experiments that corroborate our theoretical results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Modular Commutators in Conformal Field Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00027</link>
    <author>Yijian Zou, Bowen Shi, Jonathan Sorce, Ian T. Lim, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The modular commutator is a recently discovered multipartite entanglement measure that quantifies the chirality of the underlying many-body quantum state. In this Letter, we derive a universal expression for the modular commutator in conformal field theories in $1+1$ dimensions and discuss its salient features. We show that the modular commutator depends only on the chiral central charge and the conformal cross ratio. We test this formula for a gapped $2+1$-dimensional system with a chiral edge, i.e., the quantum Hall state, and observe excellent agreement with numerical simulations. Furthermore, we propose the geometric dual of the modular commutator in the AdS/CFT correspondence. We argue that the modular commutator can be obtained from a set of crossing angles between intersecting Ryu-Takayanagi surfaces.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ergodic theory of diagonal orthogonal covariant quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01145</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Nilanjana Datta, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the ergodic properties of quantum channels that are covariant with respect to diagonal orthogonal transformations. We prove that the ergodic behaviour of a channel in this class is essentially governed by a classical stochastic matrix. This allows us to exploit tools from classical ergodic theory to study quantum ergodicity of such channels. As an application of our analysis, we study dual unitary brickwork circuits which have recently been proposed as minimal models of quantum chaos in many-body systems. Upon imposing a local diagonal orthogonal invariance symmetry on these circuits, the long-term behaviour of spatio-temporal correlations between local observables in such circuits is completely determined by the ergodic properties of a channel that is covariant under diagonal orthogonal transformations. We utilize this fact to show that such symmetric dual unitary circuits exhibit a rich variety of ergodic behaviours, thus emphasizing their importance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Avoiding barren plateaus via transferability of smooth solutions in Hamiltonian Variational Ansatz</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01982</link>
    <author>Antonio Anna Mele, Glen Bigan Mbeng, Giuseppe Ernesto Santoro, Mario Collura, Pietro Torta</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A large ongoing research effort focuses on Variational Quantum Algorithms (VQAs), representing leading candidates to achieve computational speed-ups on current quantum devices. The scalability of VQAs to a large number of qubits, beyond the simulation capabilities of classical computers, is still debated. Two major hurdles are the proliferation of low-quality variational local minima, and the exponential vanishing of gradients in the cost function landscape, a phenomenon referred to as barren plateaus. Here we show that by employing iterative search schemes one can effectively prepare the ground state of paradigmatic quantum many-body models, circumventing also the barren plateau phenomenon. This is accomplished by leveraging the transferability to larger system sizes of iterative solutions, displaying an intrinsic smoothness of the variational parameters, a result that does not extend to other solutions found via random-start local optimization. Our scheme could be directly tested on near-term quantum devices, running a refinement optimization in a favorable local landscape with non-vanishing gradients.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental single-setting quantum state tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00019</link>
    <author>Roman Stricker, Michael Meth, Lukas Postler, Claire Edmunds, Chris Ferrie, Rainer Blatt, Philipp Schindler, Thomas Monz, Richard Kueng, Martin Ringbauer</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers solve ever more complex tasks using steadily growing system sizes. Characterizing these quantum systems is vital, yet becoming increasingly challenging. The gold-standard is quantum state tomography (QST), capable of fully reconstructing a quantum state without prior knowledge. Measurement and classical computing costs, however, increase exponentially in the system size - a bottleneck given the scale of existing and near-term quantum devices. Here, we demonstrate a scalable and practical QST approach that uses a single measurement setting, namely symmetric informationally complete (SIC) positive operator-valued measures (POVM). We implement these nonorthogonal measurements on an ion trap device by utilizing more energy levels in each ion - without ancilla qubits. More precisely, we locally map the SIC POVM to orthogonal states embedded in a higher-dimensional system, which we read out using repeated in-sequence detections, providing full tomographic information in every shot. Combining this SIC tomography with the recently developed randomized measurement toolbox ("classical shadows") proves to be a powerful combination. SIC tomography alleviates the need for choosing measurement settings at random ("derandomization"), while classical shadows enable the estimation of arbitrary polynomial functions of the density matrix orders of magnitudes faster than standard methods. The latter enables in-depth entanglement studies, which we experimentally showcase on a 5-qubit absolutely maximally entangled (AME) state. Moreover, the fact that the full tomography information is available in every shot enables online QST in real time. We demonstrate this on an 8-qubit entangled state, as well as for fast state identification. All in all, these features single out SIC-based classical shadow estimation as a highly scalable and convenient tool for quantum state characterization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scrambling of Algebras in Open Quantum Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02033</link>
    <author>Faidon Andreadakis, Namit Anand, Paolo Zanardi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many quantitative approaches to the dynamical scrambling of information in quantum systems involve the study of out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs). In this paper, we introduce an algebraic OTOC ($\mathcal{A}$-OTOC) that allows us to study information scrambling of generalized quantum subsystems under quantum channels. For closed quantum systems, this algebraic framework was recently employed to unify quantum information-theoretic notions of operator entanglement, coherence-generating power, and Loschmidt echo. The main focus of this work is to provide a natural generalization of these techniques to open quantum systems. We first show that, for unitary dynamics, the $\mathcal{A}$-OTOC quantifies a generalized notion of information scrambling, namely between a subalgebra of observables and its commutant. For open quantum systems, on the other hand, we find a competition between the global environmental decoherence and the local scrambling of information. We illustrate this interplay by analytically studying various illustrative examples of algebras and quantum channels. To complement our analytical results, we perform numerical simulations of two paradigmatic systems: the PXP model and the Heisenberg XXX model, under dephasing. Our numerical results reveal connections with many-body scars and the stability of decoherence-free subspaces.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Advantages and limitations of quantum routing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01766</link>
    <author>Aniruddha Bapat, Andrew M. Childs, Alexey V. Gorshkov, Eddie Schoute</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Swap gate is a ubiquitous tool for moving information on quantum hardware, yet it can be considered a classical operation because it does not entangle product states. Genuinely quantum operations could outperform Swap for the task of permuting qubits within an architecture, which we call routing. We consider quantum routing in two models: (1) allowing arbitrary two-qubit unitaries, or (2) allowing Hamiltonians with norm-bounded interactions. We lower bound the circuit depth or time of quantum routing in terms of spectral properties of graphs representing the architecture interaction constraints, and give a generalized upper bound for all simple connected $n$-vertex graphs. In particular, we give conditions for a superpolynomial classical-quantum routing separation, which exclude graphs with a small spectral gap and graphs of bounded degree. Finally, we provide examples of a quadratic separation between gate-based and Hamiltonian routing models with a constant number of local ancillas per qubit and of an $\Omega(n)$ speedup if we also allow fast local interactions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Emergence of Kac-Moody Symmetry in Critical Quantum Spin Chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01656</link>
    <author>Ruoshui Wang, Yijian Zou, Guifre Vidal</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a critical quantum spin chain with a microscopic Lie-group symmetry, corresponding e.g. to $U(1)$ or $SU(2)$ spin isotropy, we numerically investigate the emergence of Kac-Moody symmetry at low energies and long distances. In that regime, one such critical quantum spin chain is described by a conformal field theory where the usual Virasoro algebra associated to conformal invariance is augmented with a Kac-Moody algebra associated to conserved currents. Specifically, we first propose a method to construct lattice operators corresponding to the Kac-Moody generators. We then numerically show that, when projected onto low energy states of the quantum spin chain, these operators indeed approximately fulfill the Kac-Moody algebra. The lattice version of the Kac-Moody generators allow us to compute the so-called level constant and to organize the low-energy eigenstates of the lattice Hamiltonian into Kac-Moody towers. We illustrate the proposal with the XXZ model and the Heisenberg model with a next-to-nearest-neighbor coupling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Quantum and Classical Streaming Complexity of Quantum and Classical Max-Cut</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00213</link>
    <author>John Kallaugher, Ojas Parekh</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate the space complexity of two graph streaming problems: Max-Cut and its quantum analogue, Quantum Max-Cut. Previous work by Kapralov and Krachun [STOC `19] resolved the classical complexity of the \emphclassical problem, showing that any $(2 - \varepsilon)$-approximation requires $\Omega(n)$ space (a $2$-approximation is trivial with $\textrm{O}(\log n)$ space). We generalize both of these qualifiers, demonstrating $\Omega(n)$ space lower bounds for $(2 - \varepsilon)$-approximating Max-Cut and Quantum Max-Cut, even if the algorithm is allowed to maintain a quantum state. As the trivial approximation algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut only gives a $4$-approximation, we show tightness with an algorithm that returns a $(2 + \varepsilon)$-approximation to the Quantum Max-Cut value of a graph in $\textrm{O}(\log n)$ space. Our work resolves the quantum and classical approximability of quantum and classical Max-Cut using $\textrm{o}(n)$ space. We prove our lower bounds through the techniques of Boolean Fourier analysis. We give the first application of these methods to sequential one-way quantum communication, in which each player receives a quantum message from the previous player, and can then perform arbitrary quantum operations on it before sending it to the next. To this end, we show how Fourier-analytic techniques may be used to understand the application of a quantum channel.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>