<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Computational advantage of quantum random sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04079</link>
    <author>Dominik Hangleiter, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum random sampling is the leading proposal for demonstrating a computational advantage of quantum computers over classical computers. Recently, first large-scale implementations of quantum random sampling have arguably surpassed the boundary of what can be simulated on existing classical hardware. In this article, we comprehensively review the theoretical underpinning of quantum random sampling in terms of computational complexity and verifiability, as well as the practical aspects of its experimental implementation using superconducting and photonic devices and its classical simulation. We discuss in detail open questions in the field and provide perspectives for the road ahead, including potential applications of quantum random sampling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved single-shot decoding of higher dimensional hypergraph product codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.03122</link>
    <author>Oscar Higgott, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work we study the single-shot performance of higher dimensional hypergraph product codes decoded using belief-propagation and ordered-statistics decoding [Panteleev and Kalachev, 2019]. We find that decoding data qubit and syndrome measurement errors together in a single stage leads to single-shot thresholds that greatly exceed all previously observed single-shot thresholds for these codes. For the 3D toric code and a phenomenological noise model, our results are consistent with a sustainable threshold of 7.1% for $Z$ errors, compared to the threshold of 2.90% previously found using a two-stage decoder [Quintavalle et al., 2021]. For the 4D toric code, for which both $X$ and $Z$ error correction is single-shot, our results are consistent with a sustainable single-shot threshold of 4.3% which is even higher than the threshold of 2.93% for the 2D toric code for the same noise model but using $L$ rounds of stabiliser measurement. We also explore the performance of balanced product and 4D hypergraph product codes which we show lead to a reduction in qubit overhead compared the surface code for phenomenological error rates as high as 1%.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Advantage in Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04078</link>
    <author>Renato Renner, Ramona Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Ever since its inception, cryptography has been caught in a vicious circle: Cryptographers keep inventing methods to hide information, and cryptanalysts break them, prompting cryptographers to invent even more sophisticated encryption schemes, and so on. But could it be that quantum information technology breaks this circle? At first sight, it looks as if it just lifts the competition between cryptographers and cryptanalysts to the next level. Indeed, quantum computers will render most of today's public key cryptosystems insecure. Nonetheless, there are good reasons to believe that cryptographers will ultimately prevail over cryptanalysts. Quantum cryptography allows us to build communication schemes whose secrecy relies only on the laws of physics as well as some minimum assumptions about the cryptographic hardware - leaving basically no room for an attack. While we are not yet there, this article provides an overview of the principles and state of the art of quantum cryptography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Resources Required to Block-Encode a Matrix of Classical Data</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.03505</link>
    <author>B. David Clader, Alexander M. Dalzell, Nikitas Stamatopoulos, Grant Salton, Mario Berta, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide modular circuit-level implementations and resource estimates for several methods of block-encoding a dense $N\times N$ matrix of classical data to precision $\epsilon$; the minimal-depth method achieves a $T$-depth of $\mathcal{O}{(\log (N/\epsilon))},$ while the minimal-count method achieves a $T$-count of $\mathcal{O}{(N\log(1/\epsilon))}$. We examine resource tradeoffs between the different approaches, and we explore implementations of two separate models of quantum random access memory (QRAM). As part of this analysis, we provide a novel state preparation routine with $T$-depth $\mathcal{O}{(\log (N/\epsilon))}$, improving on previous constructions with scaling $\mathcal{O}{(\log^2 (N/\epsilon))}$. Our results go beyond simple query complexity and provide a clear picture into the resource costs when large amounts of classical data are assumed to be accessible to quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tight Bounds for State Tomography with Incoherent Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05265</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Brice Huang, Jerry Li, Allen Liu, Mark Sellke</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the classic question of state tomography: given copies of an unknown quantum state $\rho\in\mathbb{C}^{d\times d}$, output $\widehat{\rho}$ for which $\|\rho - \widehat{\rho}\|_{\mathsf{tr}} \le \varepsilon$. When one is allowed to make coherent measurements entangled across all copies, $\Theta(d^2/\varepsilon^2)$ copies are necessary and sufficient [Haah et al. '17, O'Donnell-Wright '16]. Unfortunately, the protocols achieving this rate incur large quantum memory overheads that preclude implementation on current or near-term devices. On the other hand, the best known protocol using incoherent (single-copy) measurements uses $O(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17], and multiple papers have posed it as an open question to understand whether or not this rate is tight. In this work, we fully resolve this question, by showing that any protocol using incoherent measurements, even if they are chosen adaptively, requires $\Omega(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies, matching the upper bound of [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17]. We do so by a new proof technique which directly bounds the "tilt" of the posterior distribution after measurements, which yields a surprisingly short proof of our lower bound, and which we believe may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Provably efficient variational generative modeling of quantum many-body systems via quantum-probabilistic information geometry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04663</link>
    <author>Faris M. Sbahi, Antonio J. Martinez, Sahil Patel, Dmitri Saberi, Jae Hyeon Yoo, Geoffrey Roeder, Guillaume Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The dual tasks of quantum Hamiltonian learning and quantum Gibbs sampling are relevant to many important problems in physics and chemistry. In the low temperature regime, algorithms for these tasks often suffer from intractabilities, for example from poor sample- or time-complexity. With the aim of addressing such intractabilities, we introduce a generalization of quantum natural gradient descent to parameterized mixed states, as well as provide a robust first-order approximating algorithm, Quantum-Probabilistic Mirror Descent. We prove data sample efficiency for the dual tasks using tools from information geometry and quantum metrology, thus generalizing the seminal result of classical Fisher efficiency to a variational quantum algorithm for the first time. Our approaches extend previously sample-efficient techniques to allow for flexibility in model choice, including to spectrally-decomposed models like Quantum Hamiltonian-Based Models, which may circumvent intractable time complexities. Our first-order algorithm is derived using a novel quantum generalization of the classical mirror descent duality. Both results require a special choice of metric, namely, the Bogoliubov-Kubo-Mori metric. To test our proposed algorithms numerically, we compare their performance to existing baselines on the task of quantum Gibbs sampling for the transverse field Ising model. Finally, we propose an initialization strategy leveraging geometric locality for the modelling of sequences of states such as those arising from quantum-stochastic processes. We demonstrate its effectiveness empirically for both real and imaginary time evolution while defining a broader class of potential applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cone-Restricted Information Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04300</link>
    <author>Ian George, Eric Chitambar</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The max-relative entropy and the conditional min-entropy it induces have become central to one-shot information theory. Both may be expressed in terms of a conic program over the positive semidefinite cone. Recently, it was shown that the same conic program altered to be over the separable cone admits an operational interpretation in terms of communicating classical information over a quantum channel. In this work, we generalize this framework of replacing the cone to determine which results in quantum information theory rely upon the positive semidefinite cone and which can be generalized. We show the fully quantum Stein's lemma and asymptotic equipartition property break down if the cone exponentially increases in resourcefulness but never approximates the positive semidefinite cone. However, we show for CQ states, the separable cone is sufficient to recover the asymptotic theory, thereby drawing a strong distinction between the fully and partial quantum settings. We present parallel results for the extended conditional min-entropy. In doing so, we extend the notion of k-superpositive channels to superchannels. We also present operational uses of this framework. We first show the cone restricted min-entropy of a Choi operator captures a measure of entanglement-assisted noiseless classical communication using restricted measurements. We show that quantum majorization results naturally generalize to other cones. As a novel example, we introduce a new min-entropy-like quantity that captures the quantum majorization of quantum channels in terms of bistochastic pre-processing. Lastly, we relate this framework to general conic norms and their non-additivity. Throughout this work we emphasize the introduced measures' relationship to general convex resource theories. In particular, we look at both resource theories that capture locality and resource theories of coherence/Abelian symmetries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Neural Network Classifiers: A Tutorial</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02806</link>
    <author>Weikang Li, Zhide Lu, Dong-Ling Deng</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Machine learning has achieved dramatic success over the past decade, with applications ranging from face recognition to natural language processing. Meanwhile, rapid progress has been made in the field of quantum computation including developing both powerful quantum algorithms and advanced quantum devices. The interplay between machine learning and quantum physics holds the intriguing potential for bringing practical applications to the modern society. Here, we focus on quantum neural networks in the form of parameterized quantum circuits. We will mainly discuss different structures and encoding strategies of quantum neural networks for supervised learning tasks, and benchmark their performance utilizing Yao.jl, a quantum simulation package written in Julia Language. The codes are efficient, aiming to provide convenience for beginners in scientific works such as developing powerful variational quantum learning models and assisting the corresponding experimental demonstrations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Connections between graphs and matrix spaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04815</link>
    <author>Yinan Li, Youming Qiao, Avi Wigderson, Yuval Wigderson, Chuanqi Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a bipartite graph $G$, the graphical matrix space $\mathcal{S}_G$ consists of matrices whose non-zero entries can only be at those positions corresponding to edges in $G$. Tutte (J. London Math. Soc., 1947), Edmonds (J. Res. Nat. Bur. Standards Sect. B, 1967) and Lovász (FCT, 1979) observed connections between perfect matchings in $G$ and full-rank matrices in $\mathcal{S}_G$. Dieudonné (Arch. Math., 1948) proved a tight upper bound on the dimensions of those matrix spaces containing only singular matrices. The starting point of this paper is a simultaneous generalization of these two classical results: we show that the largest dimension over subspaces of $\mathcal{S}_G$ containing only singular matrices is equal to the maximum size over subgraphs of $G$ without perfect matchings, based on Meshulam's proof of Dieudonné's result (Quart. J. Math., 1985). Starting from this result, we go on to establish more connections between properties of graphs and matrix spaces. For example, we establish connections between acyclicity and nilpotency, between strong connectivity and irreducibility, and between isomorphism and conjugacy/congruence. For each connection, we study three types of correspondences, namely the basic correspondence, the inherited correspondence (for subgraphs and subspaces), and the induced correspondence (for induced subgraphs and restrictions). Some correspondences lead to intriguing generalizations of classical results, such as for Dieudonné's result mentioned above, and for a celebrated theorem of Gerstenhaber regarding the largest dimension of nil matrix spaces (Amer. J. Math., 1958). Finally, we show some implications of our results to quantum information and present open problems in computational complexity motivated by these results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient tensor network simulation of quantum many-body physics on sparse graphs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04701</link>
    <author>Subhayan Sahu, Brian Swingle</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study tensor network states defined on an underlying graph which is sparsely connected. Generic sparse graphs are expander graphs with a high probability, and one can represent volume law entangled states efficiently with only polynomial resources. We find that message-passing inference algorithms such as belief propagation can lead to efficient computation of local expectation values for a class of tensor network states defined on sparse graphs. As applications, we study local properties of square root states, graph states, and also employ this method to variationally prepare ground states of gapped Hamiltonians defined on generic graphs. Using the variational method we study the phase diagram of the transverse field quantum Ising model defined on sparse expander graphs.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>