<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Suppressing quantum errors by scaling a surface code logical qubit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.06431</link>
    <author>Rajeev Acharya, Igor Aleiner, Richard Allen, Trond I. Andersen, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Joao Basso, Andreas Bengtsson, Sergio Boixo, Gina Bortoli, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, Leon Brill, Michael Broughton, et al (137)</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Practical quantum computing will require error rates that are well below what is achievable with physical qubits. Quantum error correction offers a path to algorithmically-relevant error rates by encoding logical qubits within many physical qubits, where increasing the number of physical qubits enhances protection against physical errors. However, introducing more qubits also increases the number of error sources, so the density of errors must be sufficiently low in order for logical performance to improve with increasing code size. Here, we report the measurement of logical qubit performance scaling across multiple code sizes, and demonstrate that our system of superconducting qubits has sufficient performance to overcome the additional errors from increasing qubit number. We find our distance-5 surface code logical qubit modestly outperforms an ensemble of distance-3 logical qubits on average, both in terms of logical error probability over 25 cycles and logical error per cycle ($2.914\%\pm 0.016\%$ compared to $3.028\%\pm 0.023\%$). To investigate damaging, low-probability error sources, we run a distance-25 repetition code and observe a $1.7\times10^{-6}$ logical error per round floor set by a single high-energy event ($1.6\times10^{-7}$ when excluding this event). We are able to accurately model our experiment, and from this model we can extract error budgets that highlight the biggest challenges for future systems. These results mark the first experimental demonstration where quantum error correction begins to improve performance with increasing qubit number, illuminating the path to reaching the logical error rates required for computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A rapidly mixing Markov chain from any gapped quantum many-body system</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07044</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Giuseppe Carleo, David Gosset, Yinchen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the computational task of sampling a bit string $x$ from a distribution $\pi(x)=|\langle x|\psi\rangle|^2$, where $\psi$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian $H$. Our main result describes a direct link between the inverse spectral gap of $H$ and the mixing time of an associated continuous-time Markov Chain with steady state $\pi$. The Markov Chain can be implemented efficiently whenever ratios of ground state amplitudes $\langle y|\psi\rangle/\langle x|\psi\rangle$ are efficiently computable and the starting state of the chain satisfies a mild technical condition that can be efficiently checked. This extends a previously known relationship between sign-problem free Hamiltonians and Markov chains. The tool which enables this generalization is the so-called fixed-node Hamiltonian construction, previously used in Quantum Monte Carlo simulations to address the fermionic sign problem. We implement the proposed sampling algorithm numerically and use it to sample from the ground state of Haldane-Shastry Hamiltonian with up to 56 qubits. We observe empirically that our Markov chain based on the fixed-node Hamiltonian mixes more rapidly than the standard Metropolis-Hastings Markov chain.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Conservation laws and quantum error correction: towards a generalised matching decoder</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.06428</link>
    <author>Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A decoding algorithm is essential to any fault-tolerant quantum-computing architecture. In this perspective we explore decoding algorithms for the surface code; a prototypical quantum low-density parity-check code that underlies many of the leading efforts to demonstrate scalable quantum computing. Central to our discussion is the minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder. The decoder works by exploiting underlying structure that arises due to materialised symmetries among surface-code stabilizer elements. By concentrating on these symmetries, we begin to address the question of how a minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder might be generalised for other types of code. We approach this question first by investigating examples of matching decoders for other codes. These include decoding algorithms that have been specialised to correct for noise models that demonstrate a particular structure or bias with respect to certain types of code. In addition to this, we propose a systematic way of constructing a minimum-weight perfect-matching decoder for codes with certain characteristic properties. The properties we make use of are common among topological codes. We discuss the broader applicability of the proposal, and we suggest some questions we can address that may show us how to design a generalised matching decoder for arbitrary stabilizer codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Super-exponential Quantum Speedup of Equivariant Quantum Machine Learning Algorithms with SU($d$) Symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07250</link>
    <author>Han Zheng, Zimu Li, Junyu Liu, Sergii Strelchuk, Risi Kondor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a framework of the equivariant convolutional algorithms which is tailored for a number of machine-learning tasks on physical systems with arbitrary SU($d$) symmetries. It allows us to enhance a natural model of quantum computation--permutational quantum computing (PQC) [Quantum Inf. Comput., 10, 470-497 (2010)] --and defines a more powerful model: PQC+. While PQC was shown to be effectively classically simulatable, we exhibit a problem which can be efficiently solved on PQC+ machine, whereas the best known classical algorithms runs in $O(n!n^2)$ time, thus providing strong evidence against PQC+ being classically simulatable. We further discuss practical quantum machine learning algorithms which can be carried out in the paradigm of PQC+.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Constant-cost implementations of Clifford operations and multiply controlled gates using global interactions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08691</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Dmitri Maslov, Yunseong Nam</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A frequent physical-level requirement for the ability to implement quantum operations simultaneously is their commutativity. In this work, we asked if quantum computation by commuting Ising-type entangling operations and ``free'' single-qubit gates can be advantageous compared to quantum computation by the two-qubit gates and ``free'' single-qubit gates. We focused on the elements of the Clifford group and the multiply controlled gates. It turned out that such circuits and composite gates can be implemented with very little effort -- using constantly or effectively constantly many blocks of commuting sets of gates, in all cases except some with the most severe restrictions on the number of ancillary qubits available. Specifically, we show constant-cost implementations of Clifford operations with and without ancilla, constant-cost implementation of the multiply controlled gates with linearly many ancillae, and an $O(\log^*(n))$ implementation of the $n$-controlled single-target gates using logarithmically many ancillae. This shows significant (asymptotic) improvement of circuits enabled by the global gates vs those over single- and two-qubit gates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Sublinear-Time Quantum Algorithm for Approximating Partition Functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08643</link>
    <author>Arjan Cornelissen, Yassine Hamoudi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a novel quantum algorithm for estimating Gibbs partition functions in sublinear time with respect to the logarithm of the size of the state space. This is the first speed-up of this type to be obtained over the seminal nearly-linear time algorithm of Štefankovič, Vempala and Vigoda [JACM, 2009]. Our result also preserves the quadratic speed-up in precision and spectral gap achieved in previous work by exploiting the properties of quantum Markov chains. As an application, we obtain new polynomial improvements over the best-known algorithms for computing the partition function of the Ising model, and counting the number of $k$-colorings, matchings or independent sets of a graph. Our approach relies on developing new variants of the quantum phase and amplitude estimation algorithms that return nearly unbiased estimates with low variance and without destroying their initial quantum state. We extend these subroutines into a nearly unbiased quantum mean estimator that reduces the variance quadratically faster than the classical empirical mean. No such estimator was known to exist prior to our work. These properties, which are of general interest, lead to better convergence guarantees within the paradigm of simulated annealing for computing partition functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time-Efficient Constant-Space-Overhead Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08826</link>
    <author>Hayata Yamasaki, Masato Koashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Scalable realization of quantum computation to attain substantial speedups over classical computation requires fault tolerance. Conventionally, fault-tolerant quantum computation (FTQC) demands excessive space overhead of physical qubits per logical qubit. A more recent protocol to achieve constant-space-overhead FTQC using quantum low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes thus attracts considerable attention but suffers from another drawback: it incurs polynomially long time overhead. We construct an alternative avenue of FTQC to achieve constant space overhead and only quasi-polylogarithmic time overhead simultaneously via techniques for using concatenations of different quantum Hamming codes rather than quantum LDPC codes. Our protocol achieves FTQC even if a decoder has nonzero runtime, unlike the existing constant-space-overhead protocol. These results establish a foundation for realizing FTQC within feasibly bounded space overhead yet negligibly tiny slowdown.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum tomography using state-preparation unitaries</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08800</link>
    <author>Joran van Apeldoorn, Arjan Cornelissen, András Gilyén, Giacomo Nannicini</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe algorithms to obtain an approximate classical description of a $d$-dimensional quantum state when given access to a unitary (and its inverse) that prepares it. For pure states we characterize the query complexity for $\ell_q$-norm error up to logarithmic factors. As a special case, we show that it takes $\widetilde{\Theta}(d/\varepsilon)$ applications of the unitaries to obtain an $\varepsilon$-$\ell_2$-approximation of the state. For mixed states we consider a similar model, where the unitary prepares a purification of the state. In this model we give an efficient algorithm for obtaining Schatten $q$-norm estimates of a rank-$r$ mixed state, giving query upper bounds that are close to optimal. In particular, we show that a trace-norm ($q=1$) estimate can be obtained with $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(dr/\varepsilon)$ queries. This improves (assuming our stronger input model) the $\varepsilon$-dependence over the algorithm of Haah et al.\ (2017) that uses a joint measurement on $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(dr/\varepsilon^2)$ copies of the state. To our knowledge, the most sample-efficient results for pure-state tomography come from setting the rank to $1$ in generic mixed-state tomography algorithms, which can be computationally demanding. We describe sample-optimal algorithms for pure states that are easy and fast to implement. Along the way we show that an $\ell_\infty$-norm estimate of a normalized vector induces a (slightly worse) $\ell_q$-norm estimate for that vector, without losing a dimension-dependent factor in the precision. We also develop an unbiased and symmetric version of phase estimation, where the probability distribution of the estimate is centered around the true value. Finally, we give an efficient method for estimating multiple expectation values, improving over the recent result by Huggins et al.\ (2021) when the measurement operators do not fully overlap.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Amplitude Estimation from Quantum Signal Processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.08628</link>
    <author>Patrick Rall, Bryce Fuller</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Amplitude estimation algorithms are based on Grover's algorithm: alternating reflections about the input state and the desired outcome. But what if we are given the ability to perform arbitrary rotations, instead of just reflections? In this situation, we find that quantum signal processing lets us estimate the amplitude in a more flexible way. We leverage this technique to give improved and simplified algorithms for many amplitude estimation tasks: we perform non-destructive estimation without any assumptions on the amplitude, develop an algorithm with improved performance in practice, present a new method for unbiased amplitude estimation, and finally give a simpler method for trading quantum circuit depth for more repetitions of short circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Toys can't play: physical agents in Spekkens' theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07445</link>
    <author>Ladina Hausmann, Nuriya Nurgalieva, Lídia del Rio</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Information is physical, and for a physical theory to be universal, it should model observers as physical systems, with concrete memories where they store the information acquired through experiments and reasoning. Here we address these issues in Spekkens' toy theory, a non-contextual epistemically restricted model that partially mimics the behaviour of quantum mechanics. We propose a way to model physical implementations of agents, memories, measurements, conditional actions and information processing. We find that the actions of toy agents are severely limited: although there are non-orthogonal states in the theory, there is no way for physical agents to consciously prepare them. Their memories are also constrained: agents cannot forget in which of two arbitrary states a system is. Finally, we formalize the process of making inferences about other agents' experiments and model multi-agent experiments like Wigner's friend. Unlike quantum theory or box world, in the toy theory there are no inconsistencies when physical agents reason about each other's knowledge.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>