<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Chain rules for quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11153</link>
    <author>Mario Berta, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Divergence chain rules for channels relate the divergence of a pair of channel inputs and to the divergence of the corresponding channel outputs. An important special case of such a rule is the data-processing inequality, which tells us that if the same channel is applied to both inputs then the divergence cannot increase. Based on direct matrix analysis methods, we derive several Rényi divergence chain rules for channels in the quantum setting. Our results simplify and in some cases generalise previous derivations in the literature.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Out-of-distribution generalization for learning quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10268</link>
    <author>Matthias C. Caro, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Nicholas Ezzell, Joe Gibbs, Andrew T. Sornborger, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Generalization bounds are a critical tool to assess the training data requirements of Quantum Machine Learning (QML). Recent work has established guarantees for in-distribution generalization of quantum neural networks (QNNs), where training and testing data are assumed to be drawn from the same data distribution. However, there are currently no results on out-of-distribution generalization in QML, where we require a trained model to perform well even on data drawn from a distribution different from the training distribution. In this work, we prove out-of-distribution generalization for the task of learning an unknown unitary using a QNN and for a broad class of training and testing distributions. In particular, we show that one can learn the action of a unitary on entangled states using only product state training data. We numerically illustrate this by showing that the evolution of a Heisenberg spin chain can be learned using only product training states. Since product states can be prepared using only single-qubit gates, this advances the prospects of learning quantum dynamics using near term quantum computers and quantum experiments, and further opens up new methods for both the classical and quantum compilation of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Partitioning qubits in hypergraph product codes to implement logical gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10812</link>
    <author>Armanda O. Quintavalle, Paul Webster, Michael Vasmer</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The promise of high-rate low-density parity check (LDPC) codes to substantially reduce the overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation depends on constructing efficient, fault-tolerant implementations of logical gates on such codes. Transversal gates are the simplest type of fault-tolerant gate, but the potential of transversal gates on LDPC codes has hitherto been largely neglected. We investigate the transversal gates that can be implemented in hypergraph product codes, a class of LDPC codes. Our analysis is aided by the construction of a symplectic canonical basis for the logical operators of hypergraph product codes, a result that may be of independent interest. We show that in these codes transversal gates can implement Hadamard (up to logical SWAP gates) and control-Z on all logical qubits. Moreover, we show that sequences of transversal operations, interleaved with error correction, allow implementation of entangling gates between arbitrary pairs of logical qubits in the same code block. We thereby demonstrate that transversal gates can be used as the basis for universal quantum computing on LDPC codes, when supplemented with state injection.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Maximal entanglement velocity implies dual unitarity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10341</link>
    <author>Tianci Zhou, Aram W. Harrow</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A global quantum quench can be modeled by a quantum circuit with local unitary gates. In general, entanglement grows linearly at a rate given by entanglement velocity, which is upper bounded by the growth of the light cone. We show that the unitary interactions achieving the maximal rate must remain unitary if we exchange the space and time directions -- a property known as dual unitarity. Our results are robust: approximate maximal entanglement velocity also implies approximate dual unitarity. We further show that maximal entanglement velocity is always accompanied by a specific dynamical pattern of entanglement, which yields simpler analyses of several known exactly solvable models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Certifiable Randomness from a Single Quantum Device</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11353</link>
    <author>Urmila Mahadev, Umesh Vazirani, Thomas Vidick</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Brakerski et. al [BCM+18] introduced the model of cryptographic testing of a single untrusted quantum device and gave a protocol for certifiable randomness generation. We use the leakage resilience properties of the Learning With Errors problem to address a key issue left open in previous work - the rate of generation of randomness. Our new protocol can certify $\Omega(n)$ fresh bits of randomness in constant rounds, where $n$ is a parameter of the protocol and the total communication is $O(n)$, thus achieving a nearly optimal rate. The proof that the output is statistically random is conceptually simple and technically elementary.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dynamical simulation via quantum machine learning with provable generalization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10269</link>
    <author>Joe Gibbs, Zoë Holmes, Matthias C. Caro, Nicholas Ezzell, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Lukasz Cincio, Andrew T. Sornborger, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Much attention has been paid to dynamical simulation and quantum machine learning (QML) independently as applications for quantum advantage, while the possibility of using QML to enhance dynamical simulations has not been thoroughly investigated. Here we develop a framework for using QML methods to simulate quantum dynamics on near-term quantum hardware. We use generalization bounds, which bound the error a machine learning model makes on unseen data, to rigorously analyze the training data requirements of an algorithm within this framework. This provides a guarantee that our algorithm is resource-efficient, both in terms of qubit and data requirements. Our numerics exhibit efficient scaling with problem size, and we simulate 20 times longer than Trotterization on IBMQ-Bogota.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable measures of magic for quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10061</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, M. S. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic characterizes the degree of non-stabilizerness of quantum states. It is a crucial resource for quantum computing and a necessary condition for quantum advantage. However, quantifying magic beyond a few qubits has been a major challenge. Here, we introduce Bell magic to efficiently measure magic for any number of qubits. Our method can be easily implemented in experiments together with a cost-free error mitigation scheme. We experimentally demonstrate the transition of classically simulable stabilizer states into intractable quantum states on the IonQ quantum computer. For applications, Bell magic distinguishes stabilizer and magical states with a low measurement cost. Further, variational quantum algorithms can maximize the magic of quantum states via the shift-rule. Our results pave the way to benchmark the non-classical power of quantum computers, quantum simulators and quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A general framework for the composition of quantum homomorphic encryption \& quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10471</link>
    <author>Yingkai Ouyang, Peter P. Rohde</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two essential primitives for universal, cloud-based quantum computation with security based on the laws of quantum mechanics, are quantum homomorphic encryption with information-theoretic security and quantum error correction. The former enables information-theoretic security of outsourced quantum computation, while the latter allows reliable and scalable quantum computations in the presence of errors. Previously these ingredients have been considered in isolation from one another. By establishing group-theoretic requirements that these two ingredients must satisfy, we provide a general framework for composing them. Namely, a quantum homomorphic encryption scheme enhanced with quantum error correction can directly inherit its properties from its constituent quantum homomorphic encryption and quantum error correction schemes. We apply our framework to both discrete- and continuous-variable models for quantum computation, such as Pauli-key and permutation-key encryptions in the qubit model, and displacement-key encryptions in a continuous-variable model based on Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>How to simulate key properties of lithium-ion batteries with a fault-tolerant quantum computer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11890</link>
    <author>Alain Delgado, Pablo A. M. Casares, Roberto dos Reis, Modjtaba Shokrian Zini, Roberto Campos, Norge Cruz-Hernández, Arne-Christian Voigt, Angus Lowe, Soran Jahangiri, M. A. Martin-Delgado, Jonathan E. Mueller, Juan Miguel Arrazola</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>There is a pressing need to develop new rechargeable battery technologies that can offer higher energy storage, faster charging, and lower costs. Despite the success of existing methods for the simulation of battery materials, they can sometimes fall short of delivering accurate and reliable results. Quantum computing has been discussed as an avenue to overcome these issues, but only limited work has been done to outline how they may impact battery simulations. In this work, we provide a detailed answer to the following question: how can a quantum computer be used to simulate key properties of a lithium-ion battery? Based on recently-introduced first-quantization techniques, we lay out an end-to-end quantum algorithm for calculating equilibrium cell voltages, ionic mobility, and thermal stability. These can be obtained from ground-state energies of materials, which is the core calculation executed by the quantum computer using qubitization-based quantum phase estimation. The algorithm includes explicit methods for preparing approximate ground states of periodic materials in first quantization. We bring these insights together to perform the first estimation of the resources required to implement a quantum algorithm for simulating a realistic cathode material, dilithium iron silicate.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise-resilient Majorana Edge Modes on a Chain of Superconducting Qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.11372</link>
    <author>Xiao Mi, Michael Sonner, Murphy Yuezhen Niu, Kenneth W. Lee, Brooks Foxen, Rajeev Acharya, Igor Aleiner, Trond I. Andersen, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Joao Basso, Andreas Bengtsson, Gina Bortoli, Alexandre Bourassa, Leon Brill, et al (108)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Inherent symmetry of a quantum system may protect its otherwise fragile states. Leveraging such protection requires testing its robustness against uncontrolled environmental interactions. Using 47 superconducting qubits, we implement the kicked Ising model which exhibits Majorana edge modes (MEMs) protected by $\mathbb{Z}_2$ parity symmetry. Remarkably, we find that any multi-qubit Pauli operator overlapping with the MEMs exhibits a uniform decay rate comparable to single-qubit relaxation rates, irrespective of its size or composition. This finding allows us to accurately reconstruct the exponentially localized spatial profiles of the MEMs. Spectroscopic measurements further indicate exponentially suppressed hybridization between the MEMs at larger system sizes, which manifests as a strong resilience against low-frequency noise. Our work elucidates the noise sensitivity of symmetry-protected edge modes in a solid-state environment.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>