<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Erasure qubits: Overcoming the $T_1$ limit in superconducting circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05461</link>
    <author>Aleksander Kubica, Arbel Haim, Yotam Vaknin, Fernando Brandão, Alex Retzker</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The amplitude damping time, $T_1$, has long stood as the major factor limiting quantum fidelity in superconducting circuits, prompting concerted efforts in the material science and design of qubits aimed at increasing $T_1$. In contrast, the dephasing time, $T_{\phi}$, can usually be extended above $T_1$ (via, e.g., dynamical decoupling), to the point where it does not limit fidelity. In this article we propose a scheme for overcoming the conventional $T_1$ limit on fidelity by designing qubits in a way that amplitude damping errors can be detected and converted into erasure errors. Compared to standard qubit implementations our scheme improves the performance of fault-tolerant protocols, as numerically demonstrated by the circuit-noise simulations of the surface code. We describe two simple qubit implementations with superconducting circuits and discuss procedures for detecting amplitude damping errors, performing entangling gates, and extending $T_\phi$. Our results suggest that engineering efforts should focus on improving $T_\phi$ and the quality of quantum coherent control, as they effectively become the limiting factor on the performance of fault-tolerant protocols.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Wasserstein Complexity of Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06306</link>
    <author>Lu Li, Kaifeng Bu, Dax Enshan Koh, Arthur Jaffe, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a unitary transformation, what is the size of the smallest quantum circuit that implements it? This quantity, known as the quantum circuit complexity, is a fundamental property of quantum evolutions that has widespread applications in many fields, including quantum computation, quantum field theory, and black hole physics. In this letter, we obtain a new lower bound for the quantum circuit complexity in terms of a novel complexity measure that we propose for quantum circuits, which we call the quantum Wasserstein complexity. Our proposed measure is based on the quantum Wasserstein distance of order one (also called the quantum earth mover's distance), a metric on the space of quantum states. We also prove several fundamental and important properties of our new complexity measure, which stand to be of independent interest. Finally, we show that our new measure also provides a lower bound for the experimental cost of implementing quantum circuits, which implies a quantum limit on converting quantum resources to computational resources. Our results provide novel applications of the quantum Wasserstein distance and pave the way for a deeper understanding of the resources needed to implement a quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A parallel decoder for good quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05537</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a parallel decoding algorithm for recently discovered families of asymptotically good quantum low-density parity-check codes. This algorithm provably corrects arbitrary errors of weight linear in the code length, with a logarithmic number of steps. This decoder applies directly to the family of quantum Tanner codes, and serves as a subroutine for expander lifted product codes. Along the way, we exploit recently established bounds on the robustness of random tensor codes to give a tight bound on the minimum distance of quantum Tanner codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A local pre-decoder to reduce the bandwidth and latency of quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04660</link>
    <author>Samuel C. Smith, Benjamin J. Brown, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A fault-tolerant quantum computer will be supported by a classical decoding system interfacing with quantum hardware to perform quantum error correction. It is important that the decoder can keep pace with the quantum clock speed, within the limitations on communication that are imposed by the physical architecture. To this end we propose a local `pre-decoder', which makes greedy corrections to reduce the amount of syndrome data sent to a standard matching decoder. We study these classical overheads for the surface code under a phenomenological phase-flip noise model with imperfect measurements. We find substantial improvements in the runtime of the global decoder and the communication bandwidth by using the pre-decoder. For instance, to achieve a logical failure probability of $f = 10^{-15}$ using qubits with physical error rate $p = 10^{-3}$ and a distance $d=22$ code, we find that the bandwidth cost is reduced by a factor of $1000$, and the time taken by a matching decoder is sped up by a factor of $200$. To achieve this target failure probability, the pre-decoding approach requires a $50\%$ increase in the qubit count compared with the optimal decoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On establishing learning separations between classical and quantum machine learning with classical data</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.06339</link>
    <author>Casper Gyurik, Vedran Dunjko</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Despite years of effort, the quantum machine learning community has only been able to show quantum learning advantages for certain contrived cryptography-inspired datasets in the case of classical data. In this note, we discuss the challenges of finding learning problems that quantum learning algorithms can learn much faster than any classical learning algorithm, and we study how to identify such learning problems. Specifically, we reflect on the main concepts in computational learning theory pertaining to this question, and we discuss how subtle changes in definitions can mean conceptually significantly different tasks, which can either lead to a separation or no separation at all. Moreover, we study existing learning problems with a provable quantum speedup to distill sets of more general and sufficient conditions (i.e., ``checklists'') for a learning problem to exhibit a separation between classical and quantum learners. These checklists are intended to streamline one's approach to proving quantum speedups for learning problems, or to elucidate bottlenecks. Finally, to illustrate its application, we analyze examples of potential separations (i.e., when the learning problem is build from computational separations, or when the data comes from a quantum experiment) through the lens of our approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive syndrome measurements for Shor-style error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05601</link>
    <author>Theerapat Tansuwannont, Kenneth R. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Shor fault-tolerant error correction (FTEC) scheme uses transversal gates and ancilla qubits prepared in the cat state in syndrome extraction circuits to prevent propagation of errors caused by gate faults. For a stabilizer code that can correct up to $t$ errors, the traditional Shor scheme handles ancilla preparation and measurement faults by performing syndrome measurements until the syndromes are repeated $t+1$ times in a row; in the worst-case scenario, $(t+1)^2$ rounds of measurements are required. In this work, we improve the Shor FTEC scheme using an adaptive syndrome measurement technique. In particular, our protocols determine a syndrome for error correction based on information from the differences of syndromes obtained from any two consecutive rounds. Our protocol that satisfies the strong FTEC conditions requires no more than $(t+3)^2/4-1$ rounds of measurements and is applicable to any stabilizer code. Compared to the traditional method, we estimate that our adaptive measurement method could increase the fault-tolerant threshold by a factor of 4 in the large $t$ limit. We also extend our ideas to error correction satisfying the weak FTEC conditions and flag FTEC.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient recovery of variational quantum algorithms landscapes using classical signal processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05958</link>
    <author>Enrico Fontana, Ivan Rungger, Ross Duncan, Cristina Cîrstoiu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We employ spectral analysis and compressed sensing to identify settings where a variational algorithm's cost function can be recovered purely classically or with minimal quantum computer access. We present theoretical and numerical evidence supporting the viability of sparse recovery techniques. To demonstrate this approach, we use basis pursuit denoising to efficiently recover simulated Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) instances of large system size from very few samples. Our results indicate that sparse recovery can enable a more efficient use and distribution of quantum resources in the optimisation of variational algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>New Quantum Codes from CSS Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05353</link>
    <author>Markus Grassl</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a new propagation rule for CSS codes. Starting with a CSS code $[\![n,k,d]\!]_q$, we construct a CSS code with parameters $[\![n-2,k,d-1]\!]_q$. In general, one would only obtain a code with parameters $[\![n-2,k,d-2]\!]_q$. The construction applies to asymmetric quantum codes from the CSS construction as well.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Disordered Lieb-Robinson bounds in one dimension</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05509</link>
    <author>Christopher L. Baldwin, Adam Ehrenberg, Andrew Y. Guo, Alexey V. Gorshkov</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>By tightening the conventional Lieb-Robinson bounds to better handle systems which lack translation invariance, we determine the extent to which "weak links" suppress operator growth in disordered one-dimensional spin chains. In particular, we prove that ballistic growth is impossible when the distribution of coupling strengths $\mu(J)$ has a sufficiently heavy tail at small $J$, and identify the correct dynamical exponent to use instead. Furthermore, through a detailed analysis of the special case in which the couplings are genuinely random and independent, we find that the standard formulation of Lieb-Robinson bounds is insufficient to capture the complexity of the dynamics -- we must distinguish between bounds which hold for all sites of the chain and bounds which hold for a subsequence of sites, and we show by explicit example that these two can have dramatically different behaviors. All the same, our result for the dynamical exponent is tight, in that we prove by counterexample that there cannot exist any Lieb-Robinson bound with a smaller exponent. We close by discussing the implications of our results, both major and minor, for numerous applications ranging from quench dynamics to the structure of ground states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Glasses -- a review</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.05417</link>
    <author>L. F. Cugliandolo, M. Mueller</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We review the research on quantum glasses, with a focus on their equilibrium dynamics and the interplay between glassiness and localization phenomena. Interesting relations with the SYK model are discussed.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>