<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13228</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas Breuckmann, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of non-trivial complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). We prove this conjecture by showing that the recently discovered families of constant-rate and linear-distance QLDPC codes correspond to NLTS local Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multivariate trace estimation in constant quantum depth</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.15405</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Mark M. Wilde, Eneet Kaur</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>There is a folkloric belief that a depth-$\Theta(m)$ quantum circuit is needed to estimate the trace of the product of $m$ density matrices (i.e., a multivariate trace). We prove that this belief is overly conservative by constructing a constant quantum-depth circuit for the task, inspired by the method of Shor error correction. Furthermore, our circuit demands only local gates in a two dimensional circuit -- we show how to implement it in a highly parallelized way on an architecture similar to that of Google's Sycamore processor. With these features, our algorithm brings the task of multivariate trace estimation, crucial to applications in condensed matter and estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states, closer to the capabilities of near-term quantum processors. We instantiate the latter application with a theorem on estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states with ``well-behaved" polynomial approximations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Pair Measurement Surface Code on Pentagons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12780</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, I present a way to compile the surface code into two-body parity measurements ("pair measurements"), where the pair measurements run along the edges of a Cairo pentagonal tiling. The resulting circuit improves on prior work by Chao et al. by using fewer pair measurements per four-body stabilizer measurement (5 instead of 6) and fewer time steps per round of stabilizer measurement (6 instead of 10). Using Monte Carlo sampling, I show that these improvements increase the threshold of the surface code when compiling into pair measurements from $\approx 0.2\%$ to $\approx 0.4\%$, and also that they improve the teraquop footprint at a $0.1\%$ physical gate error rate from $\approx6000$ qubits to $\approx3000$ qubits. However, I also show that Chao et al's construction will have a smaller teraquop footprint for physical gate error rates below $\approx 0.03\%$ (due to bidirectional hook errors in my construction). I also compare to the planar honeycomb code, showing that although this work does noticeably reduce the gap between the surface code and the honeycomb code (when compiling into pair measurements), the honeycomb code is still more efficient (threshold $\approx 0.8\%$, teraquop footprint at $0.1\%$ of $\approx 1000$).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement as a shortcut to long-range entangled quantum matter</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13527</link>
    <author>Tsung-Cheng Lu, Leonardo A. Lessa, Isaac H. Kim, Timothy H. Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The preparation of long-range entangled states using unitary circuits is limited by Lieb-Robinson bounds, but circuits with projective measurements and feedback (``adaptive circuits'') can evade such restrictions. We introduce four classes of local adaptive circuits that enable low-depth preparation of long-range entangled quantum matter characterized by gapped topological orders and conformal field theories (CFTs). The four classes are inspired by distinct physical insights, including tensor-network constructions, short-range entangled states with non-trivial braiding structures, multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (MERA), and parton constructions. A large class of topological orders, including chiral and symmetry-enriched topological orders, can be prepared in constant depth or time, and one-dimensional CFT states and non-abelian topological orders with both solvable and non-solvable groups can be prepared in depth scaling logarithmically with system size. Our work illustrates the practical and conceptual versatility of measurement for state preparation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Detecting and Eliminating Quantum Noise of Quantum Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13743</link>
    <author>Shuanghong Tang, Congcong Zheng, Kun Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work, we propose a two-stage procedure to systematically address quantum noise inherent in quantum measurements. The idea behind it is intuitive: we first detect and then eliminate quantum noise so that the classical noise assumption is satisfied and measurement error mitigation works. In the first stage, inspired by coherence witness in the resource theory of quantum coherence, we design an efficient method to detect quantum noise. It works by fitting the difference between two measurement statistics to the Fourier series, where the statistics are obtained using maximally coherent states with relative phase and maximally mixed states as inputs. The fitting coefficients quantitatively benchmark quantum noise. In the second stage, we design various methods to eliminate quantum noise, inspired by the Pauli twirling technique. They work by executing randomly sampled Pauli gates before the measurement device and conditionally flipping the measurement outcomes in such a way that the effective measurement device contains only classical noise. We demonstrate the feasibility of the two-stage procedure numerically on Baidu Quantum Platform. Remarkably, the results show that quantum noise in measurement devices is significantly suppressed, and the quantum computation accuracy is substantially improved. We highlight that the two-stage procedure complements existing measurement error mitigation techniques, and they together form a standard toolbox for manipulating measurement errors in near-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time and Query Complexity Tradeoff for the Dihedral Coset Problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14408</link>
    <author>Maxime Remaud, jean-Pierre Tillich</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 30 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Dihedral Coset Problem (DCP) in $Z_N$ is an important quantumly defined problem to which for instance the learning with errors problem reduces.There are several algorithms for solving it. On one hand, we have algorithms \textità la Ettinger-Høyer running in $\OO{2^{c_{\SS}\log{N}}}$ time but using $\OO{\log{N}}$ queries, for some constant $c_{\SS}$. On the other hand, algorithms \textità la Kuperberg need $\OOt{2^{\sqrt{c_{\DCP}\log{N}}}}$ time and queries, for some constant $c_{\DCP}$. Despite being the subject of a lot of studies, no algorithm using an intermediate number of queries was known up till now. It means that an attacker who has, for cost or time reasons, limited queries, will be forced to use a linear query algorithm running in exponential time. We propose an algorithm taking as a parameter the number $Q$ of queries we are allowed to do, therefore interpolating between existing algorithms. We thus explicitly show that it takes $\OOt{2^{c_{\SS}\left(\log{N}-\frac{1}{c_{\DCP}}\log^2{Q}\right)}}$ time. Our algorithm improves over algorithms \textità la Ettinger-Høyer when $Q$ is minimal and matches algorithms \textità la Kuperberg when $Q$ is maximal, while offering new possibilities in between. The key point of our algorithm is to give a degree of freedom in the way coset states are preprocessed, that we then link to the parameter $Q$ to obtain an optimal algorithm with respect to $Q$. We also introduce a new sieving procedure to assemble the constructed coset states, allowing us to retrieve the secret $s$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Verification of Ground States of Frustration-Free Hamiltonians</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.15292</link>
    <author>Huangjun Zhu, Yunting Li, Tianyi Chen</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Ground states of local Hamiltonians are of key interest in many-body physics and also in quantum information processing. Efficient verification of these states are crucial to many applications, but are very challenging. Here we propose a simple, but powerful recipe for verifying the ground states of general frustration-free Hamiltonians based on local measurements. Moreover, we derive rigorous bounds on the sampling complexity by virtue of the quantum detectability lemma (with improvement) and quantum union bound. Notably, the number of samples required does not increase with the system size when the underlying Hamiltonian is local and gapped, which is the case of most interest. As an application, we propose a general approach for verifying Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki (AKLT) states on arbitrary graphs based on spin measurements, which require only a constant number of samples for AKLT states defined on various lattices. Our work is of interest not only to many tasks in quantum information processing, but also to the study of many-body physics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum mechanics? It's all fun and games until someone loses an $i$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.15343</link>
    <author>Christopher A. Fuchs, Maxim Olchanyi, Matthew B. Weiss</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>QBism regards quantum mechanics as an addition to probability theory. The addition provides an extra normative rule for decision-making agents concerned with gambling across experimental contexts, somewhat in analogy to the double-slit experiment. This establishes the meaning of the Born Rule from a QBist perspective. Moreover it suggests that the best way to formulate the Born Rule for foundational discussions is with respect to an informationally complete reference device. Recent work [DeBrota, Fuchs, and Stacey, Phys. Rev. Res. 2, 013074 (2020)] has demonstrated that reference devices employing symmetric informationally complete POVMs (or SICs) achieve a minimal quantumness: They witness the irreducible difference between classical and quantum. In this paper, we attempt to answer the analogous question for real-vector-space quantum theory. While standard quantum mechanics seems to allow SICs to exist in all finite dimensions, in the case of quantum theory over the real numbers it is known that SICs do not exist in most dimensions. We therefore attempt to identify the optimal reference device in the first real dimension without a SIC (i.e., $d=4$) in hopes of better understanding the essential role of complex numbers in quantum mechanics. In contrast to their complex counterparts, the expressions that result in a QBist understanding of real-vector-space quantum theory are surprisingly complex.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Succinct Classical Verification of Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.14929</link>
    <author>James Bartusek, Yael Tauman Kalai, Alex Lombardi, Fermi Ma, Giulio Malavolta, Vinod Vaikuntanathan, Thomas Vidick, Lisa Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We construct a classically verifiable succinct interactive argument for quantum computation (BQP) with communication complexity and verifier runtime that are poly-logarithmic in the runtime of the BQP computation (and polynomial in the security parameter). Our protocol is secure assuming the post-quantum security of indistinguishability obfuscation (iO) and Learning with Errors (LWE). This is the first succinct argument for quantum computation in the plain model; prior work (Chia-Chung-Yamakawa, TCC '20) requires both a long common reference string and non-black-box use of a hash function modeled as a random oracle. At a technical level, we revisit the framework for constructing classically verifiable quantum computation (Mahadev, FOCS '18). We give a self-contained, modular proof of security for Mahadev's protocol, which we believe is of independent interest. Our proof readily generalizes to a setting in which the verifier's first message (which consists of many public keys) is compressed. Next, we formalize this notion of compressed public keys; we view the object as a generalization of constrained/programmable PRFs and instantiate it based on indistinguishability obfuscation. Finally, we compile the above protocol into a fully succinct argument using a (sufficiently composable) succinct argument of knowledge for NP. Using our framework, we achieve several additional results, including - Succinct arguments for QMA (given multiple copies of the witness), - Succinct non-interactive arguments for BQP (or QMA) in the quantum random oracle model, and - Succinct batch arguments for BQP (or QMA) assuming post-quantum LWE (without iO).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From Tensor Network Quantum States to Tensorial Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.12363</link>
    <author>Dian Wu, Riccardo Rossi, Filippo Vicentini, Giuseppe Carleo</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that any matrix product state (MPS) can be exactly represented by a recurrent neural network (RNN) with a linear memory update. We generalize this RNN architecture to 2D lattices using a multilinear memory update. It supports perfect sampling and wave function evaluation in polynomial time, and can represent an area law of entanglement entropy. Numerical evidence shows that it can encode the wave function using a bond dimension lower by orders of magnitude when compared to MPS, with an accuracy that can be systematically improved by increasing the bond dimension.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>