<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Graphical quantum Clifford-encoder compilers from the ZX calculus</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02356</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu, Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 09 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We present a quantum compilation algorithm that maps Clifford encoders, an equivalence class of quantum circuits that arise universally in quantum error correction, into a representation in the ZX calculus. In particular, we develop a canonical form in the ZX calculus and prove canonicity as well as efficient reducibility of any Clifford encoder into the canonical form. The diagrams produced by our compiler explicitly visualize information propagation and entanglement structure of the encoder, revealing properties that may be obscured in the circuit or stabilizer-tableau representation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Speedups for Zero-Sum Games via Improved Dynamic Gibbs Sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03763</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Yosheb Getachew, Yujia Jin, Aaron Sidford, Kevin Tian</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum algorithm for computing an $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium of a zero-sum game in a $m \times n$ payoff matrix with bounded entries. Given a standard quantum oracle for accessing the payoff matrix our algorithm runs in time $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{m + n}\cdot \epsilon^{-2.5} + \epsilon^{-3})$ and outputs a classical representation of the $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium. This improves upon the best prior quantum runtime of $\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{m + n} \cdot \epsilon^{-3})$ obtained by [vAG19] and the classic $\widetilde{O}((m + n) \cdot \epsilon^{-2})$ runtime due to [GK95] whenever $\epsilon = \Omega((m +n)^{-1})$. We obtain this result by designing new quantum data structures for efficiently sampling from a slowly-changing Gibbs distribution.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Guaranteed efficient energy estimation of quantum many-body Hamiltonians using ShadowGrouping</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03385</link>
    <author>Alexander Gresch, Martin Kliesch</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Energy estimation in quantum many-body Hamiltonians is a paradigmatic task in various research fields. In particular, efficient energy estimation may be crucial in achieving a quantum advantage for a practically relevant problem. For instance, the measurement effort poses a crucial bottleneck in variational quantum algorithms. We aim to find the optimal strategy with single-qubit measurements that yields the highest provable accuracy given a total measurement budget. As a central tool, we establish new tail bounds for empirical estimators of the energy. They are useful for identifying measurement settings that improve the energy estimate the most. This task constitutes an NP-hard problem. However, we are able to circumvent this bottleneck and use the tail bounds to develop a practical efficient estimation strategy which we call ShadowGrouping. As the name suggests, it combines shadow estimation methods with grouping strategies for Pauli strings. In numerical experiments, we demonstrate that ShadowGrouping outperforms state-of-the-art methods in estimating the electronic ground-state energies of various small molecules, both in provable and effective accuracy benchmarks. Hence, this work provides a promising way, e.g., to tackle the measurement bottleneck of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hypothesis Testing for Error Mitigation: How to Evaluate Error Mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02690</link>
    <author>Abdullah Ash Saki, Amara Katabarwa, Salonik Resch, George Umbrarescu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In the noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era, quantum error mitigation will be a necessary tool to extract useful performance out of quantum devices. However, there is a big gap between the noise models often assumed by error mitigation techniques and the actual noise on quantum devices. As a consequence, there arises a gap between the theoretical expectations of the techniques and their everyday performance. Cloud users of quantum devices in particular, who often take the devices as they are, feel this gap the most. How should they parametrize their uncertainty in the usefulness of these techniques and be able to make judgement calls between resources required to implement error mitigation and the accuracy required at the algorithmic level? To answer the first question, we introduce hypothesis testing within the framework of quantum error mitigation and for the second question, we propose an inclusive figure of merit that accounts for both resource requirement and mitigation efficiency of an error mitigation implementation. The figure of merit is useful to weigh the trade-offs between the scalability and accuracy of various error mitigation methods. Finally, using the hypothesis testing and the figure of merit, we experimentally evaluate $16$ error mitigation pipelines composed of singular methods such as zero noise extrapolation, randomized compilation, measurement error mitigation, dynamical decoupling, and mitigation with estimation circuits. In total our data involved running $275,640$ circuits on two IBM quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Randomized adaptive quantum state preparation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.04201</link>
    <author>Alicia B. Magann, Sophia E. Economou, Christian Arenz</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 12 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We develop an adaptive method for quantum state preparation that utilizes randomness as an essential component and that does not require classical optimization. Instead, a cost function is minimized to prepare a desired quantum state through an adaptively constructed quantum circuit, where each adaptive step is informed by feedback from gradient measurements in which the associated tangent space directions are randomized. We provide theoretical arguments and numerical evidence that convergence to the target state can be achieved for almost all initial states. We investigate different randomization procedures and develop lower bounds on the expected cost function change, which allows for drawing connections to barren plateaus and for assessing the applicability of the algorithm to large-scale problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simultaneous superadditivity of the direct and complementary channel capacities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05142</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Sergii Strelchuk</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum communication channels differ from their classical counterparts because their capacities can be superadditive. The principle of monogamy of entanglement suggests that superadditive improvements in the transmission capacity of a channel should reduce the amount of information loss to the environment. We challenge this intuition by demonstrating that the coherent and private information of a channel and its complement can be simultaneously superadditive for arbitrarily many channel uses. To quantify the limits of this effect, we consider the notion of max (resp. total) private information of a channel, which represents the maximum (resp. sum) of the private information of the channel itself and its complement, and study its relationship with the coherent information of the individual direct and complementary channels. For a varying number of channel uses, we show that these quantities can obey different interleaving sequences of inequalities.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Path integrals for classical-quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.04677</link>
    <author>Jonathan Oppenheim, Zachary Weller-Davies</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Consistent dynamics which couples classical and quantum degrees of freedom exists. This dynamics is linear in the hybrid state, completely positive and trace preserving. Starting from completely positive classical-quantum master equations, we derive a general path integral representation for such dynamics in terms of a classical-quantum action, which includes the necessary and sufficient conditions for complete positivity and trace preservation. The path integral we study is a generalization of the Feynman path integral for quantum systems, and the stochastic path integral used to study classical stochastic processes, allowing for interaction between the classical and quantum systems. When the classical-quantum Hamiltonian is at most quadratic in the momenta we are able to derive a configuration space path integral, providing a map between master equations and covariant classical-quantum path integrals.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Discrete holography in dual-unitary circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02825</link>
    <author>Lluis Masanes</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a family of dual-unitary circuits in 1+1 dimensions which constitute a discrete analog of conformal field theories. These circuits are quantum cellular automata which are invariant under the joint action of Lorentz and scale transformations. Dual unitaries are four-legged tensors which satisfy the unitarity condition across the time as well as the space direction, a property that makes the model mathematically tractable. Using dual unitaries too, we construct tensor-network states for our 1+1 model, which are interpreted as spatial slices of curved 2+1 discrete geometries, where the metric distance is defined by the entanglement structure of the state, following Ryu-Takayanagi's prescription. The dynamics of the circuit induces a natural dynamics on these geometries, which we study for flat and anti-de Sitter spaces, and in the presence or absence of matter. We observe that the dynamics of spaces with two or more particles differs from that of zero or one, suggesting the presence of black holes. But this contrasts with the fact that the family of models appears to be non-chaotic.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Drug design on quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.04114</link>
    <author>Raffaele Santagati, Alan Aspuru-Guzik, Ryan Babbush, Matthias Degroote, Leticia Gonzalez, Elica Kyoseva, Nikolaj Moll, Markus Oppel, Robert M. Parrish, Nicholas C. Rubin, Michael Streif, Christofer S. Tautermann, Horst Weiss, Nathan Wiebe, Clemens Utschig-Utschig</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers promise to impact industrial applications, for which quantum chemical calculations are required, by virtue of their high accuracy. This perspective explores the challenges and opportunities of applying quantum computers to drug design, discusses where they could transform industrial research and elaborates on what is needed to reach this goal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Qubit recycling and the path counting problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.03725</link>
    <author>Zijian Song, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 11 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, it was shown that the qudits used in circuits of a convolutional form (e.g., Matrix Product State sand Multi-scale Entanglement Renormalization Ansatz) can be reset unitarily \hrefhttps://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevA.103.042613[Phys. Rev. A 103, 042613 (2021)], even without measurement. We analyze the fidelity of this protocol for a family of quantum circuits that interpolates between such circuits and local quantum circuits, averaged over Haar-random gates. We establish a connection between this problem and a counting of directed paths on a graph, which is determined by the shape of the quantum circuit. This connection leads to an exact expression for the fidelity of the protocol for the entire family that interpolates between convolutional circuit and random quantum circuit. For convolutional circuits of constant window size, the rate of convergence to unit fidelity is shown to be $\frac{q^2}{q^2+1}$, independent of the window size, where $q$ is the local qudit dimension. Since most applications of convolutional circuits use constant-sized windows, our result suggests that the unitary reset protocol will likely work well in such a regime. We also derive two extra results in the convolutional limit, which may be of an independent interest. First, we derive exact expressions for the correlations between reset qudits and show that it decays exponentially in the distance. Second, we derive an expression for the the fidelity in the presence of noise, expressed in terms of the quantities that define the property of the channel, such as the entanglement fidelity.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>