<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A construction of Combinatorial NLTS</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02741</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of high complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). Here, we prove a weaker version called the combinatorial NLTS, where a quantum circuit lower bound is shown against states that violate a (small) constant fraction of local terms. This generalizes the prior NLETS results (Eldar and Harrow [2017]; Nirkhe, Vazirani and Yuen [2018]). Our construction is obtained by combining tensor networks with expander codes (Sipser and Spielman [1996]). The Hamiltonian is the parent Hamiltonian of a perturbed tensor network, inspired by the `uncle Hamiltonian' of Fernandez-Gonzalez et. al. [2015]. Thus, we deviate from the quantum CSS code Hamiltonians considered in most prior works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved single-shot decoding of higher dimensional hypergraph product codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.03122</link>
    <author>Oscar Higgott, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this work we study the single-shot performance of higher dimensional hypergraph product codes decoded using belief-propagation and ordered-statistics decoding [Panteleev and Kalachev, 2019]. We find that decoding data qubit and syndrome measurement errors together in a single stage leads to single-shot thresholds that greatly exceed all previously observed single-shot thresholds for these codes. For the 3D toric code and a phenomenological noise model, our results are consistent with a sustainable threshold of 7.1% for $Z$ errors, compared to the threshold of 2.90% previously found using a two-stage decoder [Quintavalle et al., 2021]. For the 4D toric code, for which both $X$ and $Z$ error correction is single-shot, our results are consistent with a sustainable single-shot threshold of 4.3% which is even higher than the threshold of 2.93% for the 2D toric code for the same noise model but using $L$ rounds of stabiliser measurement. We also explore the performance of balanced product and 4D hypergraph product codes which we show lead to a reduction in qubit overhead compared the surface code for phenomenological error rates as high as 1%.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Avoiding barren plateaus via transferability of smooth solutions in Hamiltonian Variational Ansatz</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01982</link>
    <author>Antonio Anna Mele, Glen Bigan Mbeng, Giuseppe Ernesto Santoro, Mario Collura, Pietro Torta</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A large ongoing research effort focuses on Variational Quantum Algorithms (VQAs), representing leading candidates to achieve computational speed-ups on current quantum devices. The scalability of VQAs to a large number of qubits, beyond the simulation capabilities of classical computers, is still debated. Two major hurdles are the proliferation of low-quality variational local minima, and the exponential vanishing of gradients in the cost function landscape, a phenomenon referred to as barren plateaus. Here we show that by employing iterative search schemes one can effectively prepare the ground state of paradigmatic quantum many-body models, circumventing also the barren plateau phenomenon. This is accomplished by leveraging the transferability to larger system sizes of iterative solutions, displaying an intrinsic smoothness of the variational parameters, a result that does not extend to other solutions found via random-start local optimization. Our scheme could be directly tested on near-term quantum devices, running a refinement optimization in a favorable local landscape with non-vanishing gradients.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Ergodic theory of diagonal orthogonal covariant quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01145</link>
    <author>Satvik Singh, Nilanjana Datta, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the ergodic properties of quantum channels that are covariant with respect to diagonal orthogonal transformations. We prove that the ergodic behaviour of a channel in this class is essentially governed by a classical stochastic matrix. This allows us to exploit tools from classical ergodic theory to study quantum ergodicity of such channels. As an application of our analysis, we study dual unitary brickwork circuits which have recently been proposed as minimal models of quantum chaos in many-body systems. Upon imposing a local diagonal orthogonal invariance symmetry on these circuits, the long-term behaviour of spatio-temporal correlations between local observables in such circuits is completely determined by the ergodic properties of a channel that is covariant under diagonal orthogonal transformations. We utilize this fact to show that such symmetric dual unitary circuits exhibit a rich variety of ergodic behaviours, thus emphasizing their importance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Neural Network Classifiers: A Tutorial</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02806</link>
    <author>Weikang Li, Zhide Lu, Dong-Ling Deng</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Machine learning has achieved dramatic success over the past decade, with applications ranging from face recognition to natural language processing. Meanwhile, rapid progress has been made in the field of quantum computation including developing both powerful quantum algorithms and advanced quantum devices. The interplay between machine learning and quantum physics holds the intriguing potential for bringing practical applications to the modern society. Here, we focus on quantum neural networks in the form of parameterized quantum circuits. We will mainly discuss different structures and encoding strategies of quantum neural networks for supervised learning tasks, and benchmark their performance utilizing Yao.jl, a quantum simulation package written in Julia Language. The codes are efficient, aiming to provide convenience for beginners in scientific works such as developing powerful variational quantum learning models and assisting the corresponding experimental demonstrations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scrambling of Algebras in Open Quantum Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02033</link>
    <author>Faidon Andreadakis, Namit Anand, Paolo Zanardi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Many quantitative approaches to the dynamical scrambling of information in quantum systems involve the study of out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs). In this paper, we introduce an algebraic OTOC ($\mathcal{A}$-OTOC) that allows us to study information scrambling of generalized quantum subsystems under quantum channels. For closed quantum systems, this algebraic framework was recently employed to unify quantum information-theoretic notions of operator entanglement, coherence-generating power, and Loschmidt echo. The main focus of this work is to provide a natural generalization of these techniques to open quantum systems. We first show that, for unitary dynamics, the $\mathcal{A}$-OTOC quantifies a generalized notion of information scrambling, namely between a subalgebra of observables and its commutant. For open quantum systems, on the other hand, we find a competition between the global environmental decoherence and the local scrambling of information. We illustrate this interplay by analytically studying various illustrative examples of algebras and quantum channels. To complement our analytical results, we perform numerical simulations of two paradigmatic systems: the PXP model and the Heisenberg XXX model, under dephasing. Our numerical results reveal connections with many-body scars and the stability of decoherence-free subspaces.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Advantages and limitations of quantum routing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01766</link>
    <author>Aniruddha Bapat, Andrew M. Childs, Alexey V. Gorshkov, Eddie Schoute</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Swap gate is a ubiquitous tool for moving information on quantum hardware, yet it can be considered a classical operation because it does not entangle product states. Genuinely quantum operations could outperform Swap for the task of permuting qubits within an architecture, which we call routing. We consider quantum routing in two models: (1) allowing arbitrary two-qubit unitaries, or (2) allowing Hamiltonians with norm-bounded interactions. We lower bound the circuit depth or time of quantum routing in terms of spectral properties of graphs representing the architecture interaction constraints, and give a generalized upper bound for all simple connected $n$-vertex graphs. In particular, we give conditions for a superpolynomial classical-quantum routing separation, which exclude graphs with a small spectral gap and graphs of bounded degree. Finally, we provide examples of a quadratic separation between gate-based and Hamiltonian routing models with a constant number of local ancillas per qubit and of an $\Omega(n)$ speedup if we also allow fast local interactions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Emergence of Kac-Moody Symmetry in Critical Quantum Spin Chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.01656</link>
    <author>Ruoshui Wang, Yijian Zou, Guifre Vidal</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a critical quantum spin chain with a microscopic Lie-group symmetry, corresponding e.g. to $U(1)$ or $SU(2)$ spin isotropy, we numerically investigate the emergence of Kac-Moody symmetry at low energies and long distances. In that regime, one such critical quantum spin chain is described by a conformal field theory where the usual Virasoro algebra associated to conformal invariance is augmented with a Kac-Moody algebra associated to conserved currents. Specifically, we first propose a method to construct lattice operators corresponding to the Kac-Moody generators. We then numerically show that, when projected onto low energy states of the quantum spin chain, these operators indeed approximately fulfill the Kac-Moody algebra. The lattice version of the Kac-Moody generators allow us to compute the so-called level constant and to organize the low-energy eigenstates of the lattice Hamiltonian into Kac-Moody towers. We illustrate the proposal with the XXZ model and the Heisenberg model with a next-to-nearest-neighbor coupling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Emergence of Fermi's Golden Rule</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.00704</link>
    <author>Tobias Micklitz, Alan Morningstar, Alexander Altland, David A. Huse</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fermi's Golden Rule (FGR) applies in the limit where an initial quantum state is weakly coupled to a \it continuum of other final states overlapping its energy. Here we investigate what happens away from this limit, where the set of final states is discrete, with a nonzero mean level spacing; this question arises in a number of recently investigated many-body systems. For different symmetry classes, we analytically and/or numerically calculate the universal crossovers in the average decay of the initial state as the level spacing is varied, with the Golden Rule emerging in the limit of a continuum. Among the corrections to the exponential decay of the initial state given by FGR is the appearance of the spectral form factor in the long-time regime for small but nonzero level spacing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Minimising statistical errors in calibration of quantum-gate sets</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.03417</link>
    <author>Yaiza Aragonés-Soria, René Otten, Tobias Hangleiter, Pascal Cerfontaine, David Gross</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Calibration of quantum gates is a necessary hurdle to overcome on the way to a reliable quantum computer. In a recent paper, a protocol called Gate Set Calibration protocol (GSC) has been introduced and used to learn coherent errors from multi-qubit quantum gates. Here, we extend this study in a number of ways: First, we perform a statistical analysis of the measurement uncertainties. Second, we find explicit measurement settings that minimize this uncertainty, while also requiring that the protocol involves only a small number of distinct gates, aiding physical realizability. We numerically demonstrate that, just by adding two more single-qubit gates to GSC, the statistical error produced in the calibration of a CNOT gate is divided by a factor of more than two.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>