<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A lower bound on the space overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00119</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Alexander Müller-Hermes, Ala Shayeghi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The threshold theorem is a fundamental result in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation stating that arbitrarily long quantum computations can be performed with a polylogarithmic overhead provided the noise level is below a constant level. A recent work by Fawzi, Grospellier and Leverrier (FOCS 2018) building on a result by Gottesman (QIC 2013) has shown that the space overhead can be asymptotically reduced to a constant independent of the circuit provided we only consider circuits with a length bounded by a polynomial in the width. In this work, using a minimal model for quantum fault tolerance, we establish a general lower bound on the space overhead required to achieve fault tolerance. For any non-unitary qubit channel $\mathcal{N}$ and any quantum fault tolerance schemes against $\mathrm{i.i.d.}$ noise modeled by $\mathcal{N}$, we prove a lower bound of $\max\left\{\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})^{-1}n,\alpha_\mathcal{N} \log T\right\}$ on the number of physical qubits, for circuits of length $T$ and width $n$. Here, $\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})$ denotes the quantum capacity of $\mathcal{N}$ and $\alpha_\mathcal{N}>0$ is a constant only depending on the channel $\mathcal{N}$. In our model, we allow for qubits to be replaced by fresh ones during the execution of the circuit and we allow classical computation to be free and perfect. This improves upon results that assumed classical computations to be also affected by noise, and that sometimes did not allow for fresh qubits to be added. Along the way, we prove an exponential upper bound on the maximal length of fault-tolerant quantum computation with amplitude damping noise resolving a conjecture by Ben-Or, Gottesman, and Hassidim (2013).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum State Preparation with Optimal Circuit Depth: Implementations and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11495</link>
    <author>Xiao-Ming Zhang, Tongyang Li, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum state preparation is an important subroutine for quantum computing. We show that any $n$-qubit quantum state can be prepared with a $\Theta(n)$-depth circuit using only single- and two-qubit gates, although with a cost of an exponential amount of ancillary qubits. On the other hand, for sparse quantum states with $d\geqslant2$ non-zero entries, we can reduce the circuit depth to $\Theta(\log(nd))$ with $O(nd\log d)$ ancillary qubits. The algorithm for sparse states is exponentially faster than best-known results and the number of ancillary qubits is nearly optimal and only increases polynomially with the system size. We discuss applications of the results in different quantum computing tasks, such as Hamiltonian simulation, solving linear systems of equations, and realizing quantum random access memories, and find cases with exponential reductions of the circuit depth for all these three tasks. In particular, using our algorithm, we find a family of linear system solving problems enjoying exponential speedups, even compared to the best-known quantum and classical dequantization algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Finding fault-tolerant Clifford circuits using SMT solvers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12450</link>
    <author>Noah Shutty, Christopher Chamberland</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Universal fault-tolerant quantum computers will require the use of efficient protocols to implement encoded operations necessary in the execution of algorithms. In this work, we show how SMT solvers can be used to automate the construction of Clifford circuits with certain fault-tolerance properties and apply our techniques to a fault-tolerant magic state preparation protocol. Part of the protocol requires converting magic states encoded in the color code to magic states encoded in the surface code. Since the teleportation step involves decoding a color code merged with a surface code, we develop a new decoding algorithm applicable to such codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum machine learning with subspace states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00054</link>
    <author>Iordanis Kerenidis, Anupam Prakash</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new approach for quantum linear algebra based on quantum subspace states and present three new quantum machine learning algorithms. The first is a quantum determinant sampling algorithm that samples from the distribution $\Pr[S]= det(X_{S}X_{S}^{T})$ for $|S|=d$ using $O(nd)$ gates and with circuit depth $O(d\log n)$. The state of art classical algorithm for the task requires $O(d^{3})$ operations \citederezinski2019minimax. The second is a quantum singular value estimation algorithm for compound matrices $\mathcal{A}^{k}$, the speedup for this algorithm is potentially exponential. It decomposes a $\binom{n}{k}$ dimensional vector of order-$k$ correlations into a linear combination of subspace states corresponding to $k$-tuples of singular vectors of $A$. The third algorithm reduces exponentially the depth of circuits used in quantum topological data analysis from $O(n)$ to $O(\log n)$. Our basic tool are quantum subspace states, defined as $|Col(X)\rangle = \sum_{S\subset [n], |S|=d} det(X_{S}) |S\rangle$ for matrices $X \in \mathbb{R}^{n \times d}$ such that $X^{T} X = I_{d}$, that encode $d$-dimensional subspaces of $\mathbb{R}^{n}$. We develop two efficient state preparation techniques, the first using Givens circuits uses the representation of a subspace as a sequence of Givens rotations, while the second uses efficient implementations of unitaries $\Gamma(x) = \sum_{i} x_{i} Z^{\otimes (i-1)} \otimes X \otimes I^{n-i}$ with $O(\log n)$ depth circuits that we term Clifford loaders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An efficient quantum algorithm for lattice problems achieving subexponential approximation factor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.13450</link>
    <author>Lior Eldar, Sean Hallgren</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a quantum algorithm for solving the Bounded Distance Decoding (BDD) problem with a subexponential approximation factor on a class of integer lattices. The quantum algorithm uses a well-known but challenging-to-use quantum state on lattices as a type of approximate quantum eigenvector to randomly self-reduce the BDD instance to a random BDD instance which is solvable classically. The running time of the quantum algorithm is polynomial for one range of approximation factors and subexponential time for a second range of approximation factors. The subclass of lattices we study has a natural description in terms of the lattice's periodicity and finite abelian group rank. This view makes for a clean quantum algorithm in terms of finite abelian groups, uses very relatively little from lattice theory, and suggests exploring approximation algorithms for lattice problems in parameters other than dimension alone. A talk on this paper sparked many lively discussions and resulted in a new classical algorithm matching part of our result. We leave it as a challenge to give a classcial algorithm matching the general case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum cryptography with classical communication: parallel remote state preparation for copy-protection, verification, and more</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.13445</link>
    <author>Alexandru Gheorghiu, Tony Metger, Alexander Poremba</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum mechanical effects have enabled the construction of cryptographic primitives that are impossible classically. For example, quantum copy-protection allows for a program to be encoded in a quantum state in such a way that the program can be evaluated, but not copied. Many of these cryptographic primitives are two-party protocols, where one party, Bob, has full quantum computational capabilities, and the other party, Alice, is only required to send random BB84 states to Bob. In this work, we show how such protocols can generically be converted to ones where Alice is fully classical, assuming that Bob cannot efficiently solve the LWE problem. In particular, this means that all communication between (classical) Alice and (quantum) Bob is classical, yet they can still make use of cryptographic primitives that would be impossible if both parties were classical. We apply this conversion procedure to obtain quantum cryptographic protocols with classical communication for unclonable encryption, copy-protection, computing on encrypted data, and verifiable blind delegated computation. The key technical ingredient for our result is a protocol for classically-instructed parallel remote state preparation of BB84 states. This is a multi-round protocol between (classical) Alice and (quantum polynomial-time) Bob that allows Alice to certify that Bob must have prepared $n$ uniformly random BB84 states (up to a change of basis on his space). Furthermore, Alice knows which specific BB84 states Bob has prepared, while Bob himself does not. Hence, the situation at the end of this protocol is (almost) equivalent to one where Alice sent $n$ random BB84 states to Bob. This allows us to replace the step of preparing and sending BB84 states in existing protocols by our remote-state preparation protocol in a generic and modular way.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Correction with Quantum Autoencoders</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00555</link>
    <author>David F. Locher, Lorenzo Cardarelli, Markus Müller</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Active quantum error correction is a central ingredient to achieve robust quantum processors. In this paper we investigate the potential of quantum machine learning for quantum error correction. Specifically, we demonstrate how quantum neural networks, in the form of quantum autoencoders, can be trained to learn optimal strategies for active detection and correction of errors, including spatially correlated computational errors as well as qubit losses. We highlight that the denoising capabilities of quantum autoencoders are not limited to the protection of specific states but extend to the entire logical codespace. We also show that quantum neural networks can be used to discover new logical encodings that are optimally adapted to the underlying noise. Moreover, we find that, even in the presence of moderate noise in the quantum autoencoders themselves, they may still be successfully used to perform beneficial quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reducing the impact of time-correlated noise on zero-noise extrapolation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11792</link>
    <author>Kevin Schultz, Ryan LaRose, Andrea Mari, Gregory Quiroz, Nathan Shammah, B. David Clader, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Zero-noise extrapolation is a quantum error mitigation technique that has typically been studied under the ideal approximation that the noise acting on a quantum device is not time-correlated. In this work, we investigate the feasibility and performance of zero-noise extrapolation in the presence of time-correlated noise. We show that, in contrast to white noise, time-correlated noise is harder to mitigate via zero-noise extrapolation because it is difficult to scale the noise level without also modifying its spectral distribution. This limitation is particularly strong if "local" gate-level methods are applied for noise scaling. However, we find that "global" noise scaling methods, e.g., global unitary folding, can be sufficiently reliable even in the presence of time-correlated noise. We also introduce gate Trotterization as a new noise scaling technique that may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Encoding qubits in multimode grid states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.12337</link>
    <author>Baptiste Royer, Shraddha Sing, Steven M. Girvin</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Encoding logical quantum information in harmonic oscillator modes is a promising and hardware- efficient approach to the realization of a quantum computer. In this work, we propose to encode logical qubits in grid states of an ensemble of harmonic oscillator modes. We first discuss general results about these multimode bosonic codes; how to design them, how to practically implement them in different experimental platforms and how lattice symmetries can be leveraged to perform logical non-Clifford operations. We then introduce in detail two two-mode grid codes based on the hypercubic and D4 lattices, respectively, showing how to perform a universal set of logical operations. We demonstrate numerically that multimode grid codes have, compared to their single- mode counterpart, increased robustness against propagation of errors from ancillas used for error correction. Finally, we highlight some interesting links between multidimensional lattices and single- mode grid codes concatenated with qubit codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Differentiating and Integrating ZX Diagrams</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.13250</link>
    <author>Quanlong Wang, Richie Yeung</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>ZX-calculus has proved to be a useful tool for quantum technology with a wide range of successful applications. Most of these applications are of an algebraic nature. However, other tasks that involve differentiation and integration remain unreachable with current ZX techniques. Here we elevate ZX to an analytical perspective by realising differentiation and integration entirely within the framework of ZX-calculus. We explicitly illustrate the new analytic framework of ZX-calculus by applying it in context of quantum machine learning.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>