<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Verifiable Quantum Advantage without Structure</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02063</link>
    <author>Takashi Yamakawa, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show the following hold, unconditionally unless otherwise stated, relative to a random oracle with probability 1: - There are NP search problems solvable by BQP machines but not BPP machines. - There exist functions that are one-way, and even collision resistant, against classical adversaries but are easily inverted quantumly. Similar separations hold for digital signatures and CPA-secure public key encryption (the latter requiring the assumption of a classically CPA-secure encryption scheme). Interestingly, the separation does not necessarily extend to the case of other cryptographic objects such as PRGs. - There are unconditional publicly verifiable proofs of quantumness with the minimal rounds of interaction: for uniform adversaries, the proofs are non-interactive, whereas for non-uniform adversaries the proofs are two message public coin. - Our results do not appear to contradict the Aaronson-Ambanis conjecture. Assuming this conjecture, there exist publicly verifiable certifiable randomness, again with the minimal rounds of interaction. By replacing the random oracle with a concrete cryptographic hash function such as SHA2, we obtain plausible Minicrypt instantiations of the above results. Previous analogous results all required substantial structure, either in terms of highly structured oracles and/or algebraic assumptions in Cryptomania and beyond.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of variational quantum algorithms: a quantum optimal transport approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03455</link>
    <author>Giacomo De Palma, Milad Marvian, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The impressive progress in quantum hardware of the last years has raised the interest of the quantum computing community in harvesting the computational power of such devices. However, in the absence of error correction, these devices can only reliably implement very shallow circuits or comparatively deeper circuits at the expense of a nontrivial density of errors. In this work, we obtain extremely tight limitation bounds for standard NISQ proposals in both the noisy and noiseless regimes, with or without error-mitigation tools. The bounds limit the performance of both circuit model algorithms, such as QAOA, and also continuous-time algorithms, such as quantum annealing. In the noisy regime with local depolarizing noise $p$, we prove that at depths $L=\cO(p^{-1})$ it is exponentially unlikely that the outcome of a noisy quantum circuit outperforms efficient classical algorithms for combinatorial optimization problems like Max-Cut. Although previous results already showed that classical algorithms outperform noisy quantum circuits at constant depth, these results only held for the expectation value of the output. Our results are based on newly developed quantum entropic and concentration inequalities, which constitute a homogeneous toolkit of theoretical methods from the quantum theory of optimal mass transport whose potential usefulness goes beyond the study of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bi-PPT channels are entanglement breaking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01685</link>
    <author>Alexander Müller-Hermes, Satvik Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a recent paper, Hirche and Leditzky introduced the notion of bi-PPT channels which are quantum channels that stay completely positive under composition with a transposition and such that the same property holds for one of their complementary channels. They asked whether there are examples of such channels that are not antidegradable. We show that this is not the case, since bi-PPT channels are always entanglement breaking. We also show that degradable quantum channels staying completely positive under composition with a transposition are entanglement breaking.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum variational learning for quantum error-correcting codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03560</link>
    <author>Chenfeng Cao, Chao Zhang, Zipeng Wu, Markus Grassl, Bei Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error-correcting codes (QECCs) are believed to be a necessity for large-scale fault-tolerant quantum computation. In the past two decades, various methods of QECC constructions have been developed, leading to many good families of codes. However, the majority of these codes are not suitable for near-term quantum devices. Here we present VarQEC, a noise-resilient variational quantum algorithm to search for quantum codes with a hardware-efficient encoding circuit. The cost functions are inspired by the most general and fundamental requirements of a QECC, the Knill-Laflamme conditions. Given the target noise channel (or the target code parameters) and the hardware connectivity graph, we optimize a shallow variational quantum circuit to prepare the basis states of an eligible code. In principle, VarQEC can find quantum codes for any error model, whether additive or non-additive, degenerate or non-degenerate, pure or impure. We have verified its effectiveness by (re)discovering some symmetric and asymmetric codes, e.g., $((n,2^{n-6},3))_2$ for $n$ from 7 to 14. We also found new $((6,2,3))_2$ and $((7,2,3))_2$ codes that are not equivalent to any stabilizer code, and extensive numerical evidence with VarQEC suggests that a $((7,3,3))_2$ code does not exist. Furthermore, we found many new channel-adaptive codes for error models involving nearest-neighbor correlated errors. Our work sheds new light on the understanding of QECC in general, which may also help to enhance near-term device performance with channel-adaptive error-correcting codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Variational Ansatz for the Ground State of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02923</link>
    <author>Paul M. Schindler, Tommaso Guaita, Tao Shi, Eugene Demler, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an ansatz for the ground states of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model, a paradigmatic model for quantum spin glasses. Our ansatz, based on the concept of generalized coherent states, very well captures the fundamental aspects of the model, including the ground state energy and the position of the spin glass phase transition. It further enables us to study some previously unexplored features, such as the non-vanishing longitudinal field regime and the entanglement structure of the ground states. We find that the ground state entanglement can be captured by a simple ensemble of weighted graph states with normally distributed phase gates, leading to a volume law entanglement, contrasting with predictions based on entanglement monogamy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring magic on a quantum processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.00015</link>
    <author>Salvatore F.E. Oliviero, Lorenzo Leone, Alioscia Hamma, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic states are the resource that allows quantum computers to attain an advantage over classical computers. This resource consists in the deviation from a property called stabilizerness which in turn implies that stabilizer circuits can be efficiently simulated on a classical computer. Without magic, no quantum computer can do anything that a classical computer cannot do. Given the importance of magic for quantum computation, it would be useful to have a method for measuring the amount of magic in a quantum state. In this work, we propose and experimentally demonstrate a protocol for measuring magic based on randomized measurements. Our experiments are carried out on two IBM Quantum Falcon processors. This protocol can provide a characterization of the effectiveness of a quantum hardware in producing states that cannot be effectively simulated on a classical computer. We show how from these measurements one can construct realistic noise models affecting the hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Diagrammatic Analysis for Parameterized Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01307</link>
    <author>Tobias Stollenwerk, Stuart Hadfield</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Diagrammatic representations of quantum algorithms and circuits offer novel approaches to their design and analysis. In this work, we describe extensions of the ZX-calculus especially suitable for parameterized quantum circuits, in particular for computing observable expectation values as functions of or for fixed parameters, which are important algorithmic quantities in a variety of applications ranging from combinatorial optimization to quantum chemistry. We provide several new ZX-diagram rewrite rules and generalizations for this setting. In particular, we give formal rules for dealing with linear combinations of ZX-diagrams, where the relative complex-valued scale factors of each diagram must be kept track of, in contrast to most previously studied single-diagram realizations where these coefficients can be effectively ignored. This allows us to directly import a number useful relations from the operator analysis to ZX-calculus setting, including causal cone and quantum gate commutation rules. We demonstrate that the diagrammatic approach offers useful insights into algorithm structure and performance by considering several ansätze from the literature including realizations of hardware-efficient ansätze and QAOA. We find that by employing a diagrammatic representation, calculations across different ansätze can become more intuitive and potentially easier approach systematically than by alternative means. Finally, we outline how diagrammatic approaches may aid in the design and study of new and more effective quantum circuit ansätze.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gaussian matrix product states cannot efficiently describe critical systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02478</link>
    <author>Adrián Franco-Rubio, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gaussian fermionic matrix product states (GfMPS) form a class of ansatz quantum states for 1d systems of noninteracting fermions. We show, for a simple critical model of free hopping fermions, that: (i) any GfMPS approximation to its ground state must have bond dimension scaling superpolynomially with the system size, whereas (ii) there exists a non-Gaussian fermionic MPS approximation to this state with polynomial bond dimension. This proves that, in general, imposing Gaussianity at the level of the tensor network may significantly alter its capability to efficiently approximate critical Gaussian states. We also provide numerical evidence that the required bond dimension is subexponential, and thus can still be simulated with moderate resources.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Spectral estimation for stoquastic Hamiltonians: a comparison between classical imaginary-time evolution and quantum real-time evolution</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01113</link>
    <author>Maarten Stroeks, Jonas Helsen, Barbara Terhal</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a classical Monte Carlo (MC) scheme which efficiently estimates an imaginary-time, decaying signal for stoquastic (i.e. sign-problem-free) local Hamiltonians. The decay rates in this signal correspond to Hamiltonian eigenvalues (with associated eigenstates present in an initial state) and can be classically extracted using a classical signal processing method like ESPRIT. We compare the efficiency of this MC scheme to its quantum counterpart in which one extracts eigenvalues of a general local Hamiltonian from a real-time, oscillatory signal obtained through quantum phase estimation circuits, again using the ESPRIT method. We prove that the ESPRIT method can resolve S = poly(n) eigenvalues, assuming a 1/poly(n) gap between them, with poly(n) quantum and classical effort through the quantum phase estimation circuits. We prove that our Monte Carlo scheme plus the ESPRIT method can resolve S = O(1) eigenvalues, assuming a 1/poly(n) gap between them, with poly(n) purely classical effort for stoquastic Hamiltonians. These results thus quantify some opportunities and limitations of classical Monte Carlo methods for spectral estimation of stoquastic Hamiltonians. We numerically compare these MC and QPE eigenvalue estimation schemes by implementing them for an archetypal stoquastic Hamiltonian system: the transverse field Ising chain.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Simulation for High Energy Physics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03381</link>
    <author>Christian W. Bauer. Zohreh Davoudi, A. Baha Balantekin, Tanmoy Bhattacharya, Marcela Carena, Wibe A. de Jong, Patrick Draper, Aida El-Khadra, Nate Gemelke, Masanori Hanada, Dmitri Kharzeev, Henry Lamm, Ying-Ying Li, Junyu Liu, Mikhail Lukin, Yannick Meurice, Christopher Monroe, Benjamin Nachman, Guido Pagano, John Preskill, Enrico Rinaldi, et al (10)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It is for the first time that Quantum Simulation for High Energy Physics (HEP) is studied in the U.S. decadal particle-physics community planning, and in fact until recently, this was not considered a mainstream topic in the community. This fact speaks of a remarkable rate of growth of this subfield over the past few years, stimulated by the impressive advancements in Quantum Information Sciences (QIS) and associated technologies over the past decade, and the significant investment in this area by the government and private sectors in the U.S. and other countries. High-energy physicists have quickly identified problems of importance to our understanding of nature at the most fundamental level, from tiniest distances to cosmological extents, that are intractable with classical computers but may benefit from quantum advantage. They have initiated, and continue to carry out, a vigorous program in theory, algorithm, and hardware co-design for simulations of relevance to the HEP mission. This community whitepaper is an attempt to bring this exciting and yet challenging area of research to the spotlight, and to elaborate on what the promises, requirements, challenges, and potential solutions are over the next decade and beyond.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>