<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking the Planar Honeycomb Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11845</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney, Michael Newman</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We improve the planar honeycomb code by describing boundaries that need no additional physical connectivity, and by optimizing the shape of the qubit patch. We then benchmark the code using Monte Carlo sampling to estimate logical error rates and derive metrics including thresholds, lambdas, and teraquop qubit counts. We determine that the planar honeycomb code can create a logical qubit with one-in-a-trillion logical error rates using 7000 physical qubits at a 0.1% gate-level error rate (or 900 physical qubits given native two-qubit parity measurements). Our results cement the honeycomb code as a promising candidate for two-dimensional qubit architectures with sparse connectivity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Differential Privacy: An Information Theory Perspective</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10717</link>
    <author>Christoph Hirche, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Differential privacy has been an exceptionally successful concept when it comes to providing provable security guarantees for classical computations. More recently, the concept was generalized to quantum computations. While classical computations are essentially noiseless and differential privacy is often achieved by artificially adding noise, near-term quantum computers are inherently noisy and it was observed that this leads to natural differential privacy as a feature. In this work we discuss quantum differential privacy in an information theoretic framework by casting it as a quantum divergence. A main advantage of this approach is that differential privacy becomes a property solely based on the output states of the computation, without the need to check it for every measurement. This leads to simpler proofs and generalized statements of its properties as well as several new bounds for both, general and specific, noise models. In particular, these include common representations of quantum circuits and quantum machine learning concepts. Here, we focus on the difference in the amount of noise required to achieve certain levels of differential privacy versus the amount that would make any computation useless. Finally, we also generalize the classical concepts of local differential privacy, Rényi differential privacy and the hypothesis testing interpretation to the quantum setting, providing several new properties and insights.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of nearest-neighbour quantum networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.10886</link>
    <author>Frederik Hahn, Axel Dahlberg, Jens Eisert, Anna Pappa</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum communication research has in recent years shifted to include multi-partite networks for which questions of quantum network routing naturally emerge. To understand the potential for multi-partite routing, we focus on the most promising architectures for future quantum networks - those connecting nodes close to each other. Nearest-neighbour networks such as rings, lines, and grids, have been studied under different communication scenarios to facilitate the sharing of quantum resources, especially in the presence of bottlenecks. We here analyze the potential of nearest-neighbour quantum networks and identify some serious limitations, by demonstrating that rings and lines cannot overcome common bottleneck communication problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Performance of planar Floquet codes with Majorana-based qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11829</link>
    <author>Adam Paetznick, Christina Knapp, Nicolas Delfosse, Bela Bauer, Jeongwan Haah, Matthew B. Hastings, Marcus P. da Silva</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction is crucial for any quantum computing platform to achieve truly scalable quantum computation. The surface code and its variants have been considered the most promising quantum error correction scheme due to their high threshold, low overhead, and relatively simple structure that can naturally be implemented in many existing qubit architectures, such as superconducting qubits. The recent development of Floquet codes offers another promising approach. By going beyond the usual paradigm of stabilizer codes, Floquet codes achieve similar performance while being constructed entirely from two-qubit measurements. This makes them particularly suitable for platforms where two-qubit measurements can be implemented directly, such as measurement-only topological qubits based on Majorana zero modes (MZMs). Here, we explain how two variants of Floquet codes can be implemented on MZM-based architectures without any auxiliary qubits for syndrome measurement and with shallow syndrome extraction sequences. We then numerically demonstrate their favorable performance. In particular, we show that they improve the threshold for scalable quantum computation in MZM-based systems by an order of magnitude, and significantly reduce space and time overheads below threshold.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bounding quantum capacities via partial orders and complementarity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11688</link>
    <author>Christoph Hirche, Felix Leditzky</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum capacities are fundamental quantities that are notoriously hard to compute and can exhibit surprising properties such as superadditivity. Thus, a vast amount of literature is devoted to finding tight and computable bounds on these capacities. We add a new viewpoint by giving operationally motivated bounds on several capacities, including the quantum capacity and private capacity of a quantum channel and the one-way distillable entanglement and private key of a quantum state. These bounds are generally phrased in terms of capacity quantities involving the complementary channel or state. As a tool to obtain these bounds, we discuss partial orders on quantum channels and states, such as the less noisy and the more capable order. Our bounds help to further understand the interplay between different capacities, as they give operational limitations on superadditivity and the difference between capacities in terms of the information-theoretic properties of the complementary channel or state. They can also be used as a new approach towards numerically bounding capacities, as discussed with some examples.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hybrid Quantum-Classical Search Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11443</link>
    <author>Ansis Rosmanis</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Search is one of the most commonly used primitives in quantum algorithm design. It is known that quadratic speedups provided by Grover's algorithm are optimal, and no faster quantum algorithms for Search exist. While it is known that at least some quantum computation is required to achieve these speedups, the existing bounds do not rule out the possibility of an equally fast hybrid quantum-classical algorithm where most of the computation is classical. In this work, we study such hybrid algorithms and we show that classical computation, unless it by itself can solve the Search problem, cannot assist quantum computation. In addition, we generalize this result to algorithms with subconstant success probabilities.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimizing thermalizations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12616</link>
    <author>Kamil Korzekwa, Matteo Lostaglio</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a rigorous approach, based on the concept of continuous thermomajorisation, to algorithmically characterise the full set of energy occupations of a quantum system accessible from a given initial state through weak interactions with a heat bath. The algorithm can be deployed to solve complex optimization problems in out-of-equilibrium setups and it returns explicit elementary control sequences realizing optimal transformations. We illustrate this by finding optimal protocols in the context of cooling, work extraction and catalysis. The same tools also allow one to quantitatively assess the role played by memory effects in the performance of thermodynamic protocols. We obtained exhaustive solutions on a laptop machine for systems with dimension $d\leq 7$, but with heuristic methods one could access much higher $d$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>One-dimensional SPT phases protected by frieze symmetries</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12880</link>
    <author>Bram Vancraeynest-De Cuiper, Nicolas Dewolf, Jutho Haegeman, Frank Verstraete</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We undertake a systematic study of symmetry-protected topological gapped phases of quantum spin chains in the presence of the quasi-one-dimensional frieze space groups. Here, the spatial symmetries of the one-dimensional lattice are considered together with an additional 'vertical reflection', which we take to be an on-site $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry. We identify seventeen distinct non-trivial phases and define canonical forms. If time-reversal is combined with a shift over one site, then no new topological phases arise. We furthermore construct explicit renormalization-group fixed point wavefunctions for symmetry-protected topological phases with global on-site symmetries, and demonstrate how group cohomology can be computed using the Smith normal form</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>SupermarQ: A Scalable Quantum Benchmark Suite</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.11045</link>
    <author>Teague Tomesh, Pranav Gokhale, Victory Omole, Gokul Subramanian Ravi, Kaitlin N. Smith, Joshua Viszlai, Xin-Chuan Wu, Nikos Hardavellas, Margaret R. Martonosi, Frederic T. Chong</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The emergence of quantum computers as a new computational paradigm has been accompanied by speculation concerning the scope and timeline of their anticipated revolutionary changes. While quantum computing is still in its infancy, the variety of different architectures used to implement quantum computations make it difficult to reliably measure and compare performance. This problem motivates our introduction of SupermarQ, a scalable, hardware-agnostic quantum benchmark suite which uses application-level metrics to measure performance. SupermarQ is the first attempt to systematically apply techniques from classical benchmarking methodology to the quantum domain. We define a set of feature vectors to quantify coverage, select applications from a variety of domains to ensure the suite is representative of real workloads, and collect benchmark results from the IBM, IonQ, and AQT@LBNL platforms. Looking forward, we envision that quantum benchmarking will encompass a large cross-community effort built on open source, constantly evolving benchmark suites. We introduce SupermarQ as an important step in this direction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Physics solutions for machine learning privacy leaks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.12319</link>
    <author>Alejandro Pozas-Kerstjens, Senaida Hernández-Santana, José Ramón Pareja Monturiol, Marco Castrillón López, Giannicola Scarpa, Carlos E. González-Guillén, David Pérez-García</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Machine learning systems are becoming more and more ubiquitous in increasingly complex areas, including cutting-edge scientific research. The opposite is also true: the interest in better understanding the inner workings of machine learning systems motivates their analysis under the lens of different scientific disciplines. Physics is particularly successful in this, due to its ability to describe complex dynamical systems. While explanations of phenomena in machine learning based on physics are increasingly present, examples of direct application of notions akin to physics in order to improve machine learning systems are more scarce. Here we provide one such application in the problem of developing algorithms that preserve the privacy of the manipulated data, which is especially important in tasks such as the processing of medical records. We develop well-defined conditions to guarantee robustness to specific types of privacy leaks, and rigorously prove that such conditions are satisfied by tensor-network architectures. These are inspired by the efficient representation of quantum many-body systems, and have shown to compete and even surpass traditional machine learning architectures in certain cases. Given the growing expertise in training tensor-network architectures, these results imply that one may not have to be forced to make a choice between accuracy in prediction and ensuring the privacy of the information processed.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>