<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Bosonic coding: introduction and use cases</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05714</link>
    <author>Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bosonic or continuous-variable coding is a field concerned with robust quantum information processing and communication with electromagnetic signals or mechanical modes. I review bosonic quantum memories, characterizing them as either bosonic stabilizer or bosonic Fock-state codes. I then enumerate various applications of bosonic encodings, four of which circumvent no-go theorems due to the intrinsic infinite-dimensionality of bosonic systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Continuous-variable quantum state designs: theory and applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05127</link>
    <author>Joseph T. Iosue, Kunal Sharma, Michael J. Gullans, Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We generalize the notion of quantum state designs to infinite-dimensional spaces. We first prove that, under the definition of continuous-variable (CV) state $t$-designs from Comm. Math. Phys. 326, 755 (2014), no state designs exist for $t\geq2$. Similarly, we prove that no CV unitary $t$-designs exist for $t\geq 2$. We propose an alternative definition for CV state designs, which we call rigged $t$-designs, and provide explicit constructions for $t=2$. As an application of rigged designs, we develop a design-based shadow-tomography protocol for CV states. Using energy-constrained versions of rigged designs, we define an average fidelity for CV quantum channels and relate this fidelity to the CV entanglement fidelity. As an additional result of independent interest, we establish a connection between torus $2$-designs and complete sets of mutually unbiased bases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Assessing requirements to scale to practical quantum advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07629</link>
    <author>Michael E. Beverland, Prakash Murali, Matthias Troyer, Krysta M. Svore, Torsten Hoeffler, Vadym Kliuchnikov, Guang Hao Low, Mathias Soeken, Aarthi Sundaram, Alexander Vaschillo</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While quantum computers promise to solve some scientifically and commercially valuable problems thought intractable for classical machines, delivering on this promise will require a large-scale quantum machine. Understanding the impact of architecture design choices for a scaled quantum stack for specific applications, prior to full realization of the quantum system, is an important open challenge. To this end, we develop a framework for quantum resource estimation, abstracting the layers of the stack, to estimate resources required across these layers for large-scale quantum applications. Using a tool that implements this framework, we assess three scaled quantum applications and find that hundreds of thousands to millions of physical qubits are needed to achieve practical quantum advantage. We identify three qubit parameters, namely size, speed, and controllability, that are critical at scale to rendering these applications practical. A goal of our work is to accelerate progress towards practical quantum advantage by enabling the broader community to explore design choices across the stack, from algorithms to qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generating $k$ EPR-pairs from an n-party resource state</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06497</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Yash Sharma, Mario Szegedy, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Motivated by quantum network applications over classical channels, we initiate the study of $n$-party resource states from which LOCC protocols can create EPR-pairs between any $k$ disjoint pairs of parties. We give constructions of such states where $k$ is not too far from the optimal $n/2$ while the individual parties need to hold only a constant number of qubits. In the special case when each party holds only one qubit, we describe a family of $n$-qubit states with $k$ proportional to $\log n$ based on Reed-Muller codes, as well as small numerically found examples for $k=2$ and $k=3$. We also prove some lower bounds, for example showing that if $k=n/2$ then the parties must have at least $\Omega(\log\log n)$ qubits each.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Black-Hole Radiation Decoding is Quantum Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05491</link>
    <author>Zvika Brakerski</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose to study equivalence relations between phenomena in high-energy physics and the existence of standard cryptographic primitives, and show the first example where such an equivalence holds. A small number of prior works showed that high-energy phenomena can be explained by cryptographic hardness. Examples include using the existence of one-way functions to explain the hardness of decoding black-hole Hawking radiation (Harlow and Hayden 2013, Aaronson 2016), and using pseudorandom quantum states to explain the hardness of computing AdS/CFT dictionary (Bouland, Fefferman and Vazirani, 2020). In this work we show, for the former example of black-hole radiation decoding, that it also implies the existence of secure quantum cryptography. In fact, we show an existential equivalence between the hardness of black-hole radiation decoding and a variety of cryptographic primitives, including bit-commitment schemes and oblivious transfer protocols (using quantum communication). This can be viewed (with proper disclaimers, as we discuss) as providing a physical justification for the existence of secure cryptography. We conjecture that such connections may be found in other high-energy physics phenomena.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Refuting spectral compatibility of quantum marginals</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06349</link>
    <author>Felix Huber, Nikolai Wyderka</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The spectral variant of the quantum marginal problem asks: Given prescribed spectra for a set of quantum marginals, does there exist a compatible joint state? The main idea of this work is a symmetry-reduced semidefinite programming hierarchy for detecting incompatible spectra. The hierarchy can provide refutations that are dimension-free, certifying incompatibility in all local dimensions. It equally applies to the compatibility of local unitary invariants, to the sums of Hermitian matrices problem, to optimize trace polynomials on the positive cone, and to certify vanishing Kronecker coefficients.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadow tomography for continuous variables quantum systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07578</link>
    <author>Simon Becker, Nilanjana Datta, Ludovico Lami, Cambyse Rouzé</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this article we develop a continuous variable (CV) shadow tomography scheme with wide ranging applications in quantum optics. Our work is motivated by the increasing experimental and technological relevance of CV systems in quantum information, quantum communication, quantum sensing, quantum simulations, quantum computing and error correction. We introduce two experimentally realisable schemes for obtaining classical shadows of CV (possibly non-Gaussian) quantum states using only randomised Gaussian unitaries and easily implementable Gaussian measurements such as homodyne and heterodyne detection. For both schemes, we show that $N=\mathcal{O}\big(\operatorname{poly}\big(\frac{1}{\epsilon},\log\big(\frac{1}{\delta}\big),M_n^{r+\alpha},\log(m)\big)\big)$ samples of an unknown $m$-mode state $\rho$ suffice to learn the expected value of any $r$-local polynomial in the canonical observables of degree $\alpha$, both with high probability $1-\delta$ and accuracy $\epsilon$, as long as the state $\rho$ has moments of order $n>\alpha$ bounded by $M_n$. By simultaneously truncating states and operators in energy and phase space, we are able to overcome new mathematical challenges that arise due to the infinite-dimensionality of CV systems. We also provide a scheme to learn nonlinear functionals of the state, such as entropies over any small number of modes, by leveraging recent energy-constrained entropic continuity bounds. Finally, we provide numerical evidence of the efficiency of our protocols in the case of CV states of relevance in quantum information theory, including ground states of quadratic Hamiltonians of many-body systems and cat qubit states. We expect our scheme to provide good recovery in learning relevant states of 2D materials and photonic crystals.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The X-Cube Floquet Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05784</link>
    <author>Zhehao Zhang, David Aasen, Sagar Vijay</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Inspired by the coupled-layer construction of the X-Cube model, we introduce the X-Cube Floquet code, a dynamical quantum error-correcting code where the number of encoded logical qubits grows with system size. The X-Cube Floquet code is defined on a three-dimensional lattice, built from intersecting two-dimensional layers in the $xy$, $yz$, and $xz$ directions, and consists of a periodic sequence of two-qubit measurements which couple the layers together. Within a single Floquet cycle, the codespace switches between that of the X-Cube fracton order and layers of entangled, two-dimensional toric codes. The encoded logical qubits' dynamics are analyzed, and we argue that the new code has a non-zero error threshold. We provide a new Hamiltonian realization of the X-Cube model and, more generally, explore the phase diagram related to the sequence of measurements that define the X-Cube Floquet code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hardware optimized parity check gates for superconducting surface codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06382</link>
    <author>Matthew J. Reagor, Thomas C. Bohdanowicz, David Rodriguez Perez, Eyob A. Sete, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Error correcting codes use multi-qubit measurements to realize fault-tolerant quantum logic steps. In fact, the resources needed to scale-up fault-tolerant quantum computing hardware are largely set by this task. Tailoring next-generation processors for joint measurements, therefore, could result in improvements to speed, accuracy, or cost -- accelerating the development large-scale quantum computers. Here, we motivate such explorations by analyzing an unconventional surface code based on multi-body interactions between superconducting transmon qubits. Our central consideration, Hardware Optimized Parity (HOP) gates, achieves stabilizer-type measurements through simultaneous multi-qubit conditional phase accumulation. Despite the multi-body effects that underpin this approach, our estimates of logical faults suggest that this design can be at least as robust to realistic noise as conventional designs. We show a higher threshold of $1.25 \times 10^{-3}$ compared to the standard code's $0.79 \times 10^{-3}$. However, in the HOP code the logical error rate decreases more slowly with decreasing physical error rate. Our results point to a fruitful path forward towards extending gate-model platforms for error correction at the dawn of its empirical development.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Continuous-Variable Shadow Tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05149</link>
    <author>Srilekha Gandhari, Victor V. Albert, Thomas Gerrits, Jacob M. Taylor, Michael J. Gullans</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shadow tomography is a framework for constructing succinct descriptions of quantum states, called classical shadows, with powerful methods to bound the estimators used. We recast existing experimental protocols for continuous-variable tomography in the classical-shadow framework, obtaining rigorous bounds on the sample complexity for estimating density matrices from these protocols. We analyze the efficiency of homodyne, heterodyne, photon number resolving (PNR), and photon-parity protocols. To reach a desired precision on the classical shadow of an $N$-photon density matrix with a high probability, we show that homodyne detection requires an order $\mathcal{O}(N^5)$ measurements in the worst case, whereas PNR and photon-parity detection require $\mathcal{O}(N^4)$ measurements in the worst case (both up to logarithmic corrections). We benchmark these results against numerical simulation as well as experimental data from optical homodyne experiments. We find that numerical and experimental homodyne tomography significantly outperforms our bounds, exhibiting a more typical scaling of the number of measurements that is close to linear in $N$. We extend our single-mode results to an efficient construction of multimode shadows based on local measurements.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>