<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Verifiable Quantum Advantage without Structure</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02063</link>
    <author>Takashi Yamakawa, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show the following hold, unconditionally unless otherwise stated, relative to a random oracle with probability 1: - There are NP search problems solvable by BQP machines but not BPP machines. - There exist functions that are one-way, and even collision resistant, against classical adversaries but are easily inverted quantumly. Similar separations hold for digital signatures and CPA-secure public key encryption (the latter requiring the assumption of a classically CPA-secure encryption scheme). Interestingly, the separation does not necessarily extend to the case of other cryptographic objects such as PRGs. - There are unconditional publicly verifiable proofs of quantumness with the minimal rounds of interaction: for uniform adversaries, the proofs are non-interactive, whereas for non-uniform adversaries the proofs are two message public coin. - Our results do not appear to contradict the Aaronson-Ambanis conjecture. Assuming this conjecture, there exist publicly verifiable certifiable randomness, again with the minimal rounds of interaction. By replacing the random oracle with a concrete cryptographic hash function such as SHA2, we obtain plausible Minicrypt instantiations of the above results. Previous analogous results all required substantial structure, either in terms of highly structured oracles and/or algebraic assumptions in Cryptomania and beyond.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bi-PPT channels are entanglement breaking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01685</link>
    <author>Alexander Müller-Hermes, Satvik Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a recent paper, Hirche and Leditzky introduced the notion of bi-PPT channels which are quantum channels that stay completely positive under composition with a transposition and such that the same property holds for one of their complementary channels. They asked whether there are examples of such channels that are not antidegradable. We show that this is not the case, since bi-PPT channels are always entanglement breaking. We also show that degradable quantum channels staying completely positive under composition with a transposition are entanglement breaking.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Variational Ansatz for the Ground State of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02923</link>
    <author>Paul M. Schindler, Tommaso Guaita, Tao Shi, Eugene Demler, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an ansatz for the ground states of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model, a paradigmatic model for quantum spin glasses. Our ansatz, based on the concept of generalized coherent states, very well captures the fundamental aspects of the model, including the ground state energy and the position of the spin glass phase transition. It further enables us to study some previously unexplored features, such as the non-vanishing longitudinal field regime and the entanglement structure of the ground states. We find that the ground state entanglement can be captured by a simple ensemble of weighted graph states with normally distributed phase gates, leading to a volume law entanglement, contrasting with predictions based on entanglement monogamy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring magic on a quantum processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.00015</link>
    <author>Salvatore F.E. Oliviero, Lorenzo Leone, Alioscia Hamma, Seth Lloyd</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic states are the resource that allows quantum computers to attain an advantage over classical computers. This resource consists in the deviation from a property called stabilizerness which in turn implies that stabilizer circuits can be efficiently simulated on a classical computer. Without magic, no quantum computer can do anything that a classical computer cannot do. Given the importance of magic for quantum computation, it would be useful to have a method for measuring the amount of magic in a quantum state. In this work, we propose and experimentally demonstrate a protocol for measuring magic based on randomized measurements. Our experiments are carried out on two IBM Quantum Falcon processors. This protocol can provide a characterization of the effectiveness of a quantum hardware in producing states that cannot be effectively simulated on a classical computer. We show how from these measurements one can construct realistic noise models affecting the hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Diagrammatic Analysis for Parameterized Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01307</link>
    <author>Tobias Stollenwerk, Stuart Hadfield</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Diagrammatic representations of quantum algorithms and circuits offer novel approaches to their design and analysis. In this work, we describe extensions of the ZX-calculus especially suitable for parameterized quantum circuits, in particular for computing observable expectation values as functions of or for fixed parameters, which are important algorithmic quantities in a variety of applications ranging from combinatorial optimization to quantum chemistry. We provide several new ZX-diagram rewrite rules and generalizations for this setting. In particular, we give formal rules for dealing with linear combinations of ZX-diagrams, where the relative complex-valued scale factors of each diagram must be kept track of, in contrast to most previously studied single-diagram realizations where these coefficients can be effectively ignored. This allows us to directly import a number useful relations from the operator analysis to ZX-calculus setting, including causal cone and quantum gate commutation rules. We demonstrate that the diagrammatic approach offers useful insights into algorithm structure and performance by considering several ansätze from the literature including realizations of hardware-efficient ansätze and QAOA. We find that by employing a diagrammatic representation, calculations across different ansätze can become more intuitive and potentially easier approach systematically than by alternative means. Finally, we outline how diagrammatic approaches may aid in the design and study of new and more effective quantum circuit ansätze.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gaussian matrix product states cannot efficiently describe critical systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02478</link>
    <author>Adrián Franco-Rubio, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gaussian fermionic matrix product states (GfMPS) form a class of ansatz quantum states for 1d systems of noninteracting fermions. We show, for a simple critical model of free hopping fermions, that: (i) any GfMPS approximation to its ground state must have bond dimension scaling superpolynomially with the system size, whereas (ii) there exists a non-Gaussian fermionic MPS approximation to this state with polynomial bond dimension. This proves that, in general, imposing Gaussianity at the level of the tensor network may significantly alter its capability to efficiently approximate critical Gaussian states. We also provide numerical evidence that the required bond dimension is subexponential, and thus can still be simulated with moderate resources.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental quantum adversarial learning with programmable superconducting qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01738</link>
    <author>Wenhui Ren, Weikang Li, Shibo Xu, Ke Wang, Wenjie Jiang, Feitong Jin, Xuhao Zhu, Jiachen Chen, Zixuan Song, Pengfei Zhang, Hang Dong, Xu Zhang, Jinfeng Deng, Yu Gao, Chuanyu Zhang, Yaozu Wu, Bing Zhang, Qiujiang Guo, Hekang Li, Zhen Wang, et al (4)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing promises to enhance machine learning and artificial intelligence. Different quantum algorithms have been proposed to improve a wide spectrum of machine learning tasks. Yet, recent theoretical works show that, similar to traditional classifiers based on deep classical neural networks, quantum classifiers would suffer from the vulnerability problem: adding tiny carefully-crafted perturbations to the legitimate original data samples would facilitate incorrect predictions at a notably high confidence level. This will pose serious problems for future quantum machine learning applications in safety and security-critical scenarios. Here, we report the first experimental demonstration of quantum adversarial learning with programmable superconducting qubits. We train quantum classifiers, which are built upon variational quantum circuits consisting of ten transmon qubits featuring average lifetimes of 150 $\mu$s, and average fidelities of simultaneous single- and two-qubit gates above 99.94% and 99.4% respectively, with both real-life images (e.g., medical magnetic resonance imaging scans) and quantum data. We demonstrate that these well-trained classifiers (with testing accuracy up to 99%) can be practically deceived by small adversarial perturbations, whereas an adversarial training process would significantly enhance their robustness to such perturbations. Our results reveal experimentally a crucial vulnerability aspect of quantum learning systems under adversarial scenarios and demonstrate an effective defense strategy against adversarial attacks, which provide a valuable guide for quantum artificial intelligence applications with both near-term and future quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Spectral estimation for stoquastic Hamiltonians: a comparison between classical imaginary-time evolution and quantum real-time evolution</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01113</link>
    <author>Maarten Stroeks, Jonas Helsen, Barbara Terhal</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present a classical Monte Carlo (MC) scheme which efficiently estimates an imaginary-time, decaying signal for stoquastic (i.e. sign-problem-free) local Hamiltonians. The decay rates in this signal correspond to Hamiltonian eigenvalues (with associated eigenstates present in an initial state) and can be classically extracted using a classical signal processing method like ESPRIT. We compare the efficiency of this MC scheme to its quantum counterpart in which one extracts eigenvalues of a general local Hamiltonian from a real-time, oscillatory signal obtained through quantum phase estimation circuits, again using the ESPRIT method. We prove that the ESPRIT method can resolve S = poly(n) eigenvalues, assuming a 1/poly(n) gap between them, with poly(n) quantum and classical effort through the quantum phase estimation circuits. We prove that our Monte Carlo scheme plus the ESPRIT method can resolve S = O(1) eigenvalues, assuming a 1/poly(n) gap between them, with poly(n) purely classical effort for stoquastic Hamiltonians. These results thus quantify some opportunities and limitations of classical Monte Carlo methods for spectral estimation of stoquastic Hamiltonians. We numerically compare these MC and QPE eigenvalue estimation schemes by implementing them for an archetypal stoquastic Hamiltonian system: the transverse field Ising chain.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Peptide conformational sampling using the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.01821</link>
    <author>Sami Boulebnane, Xavier Lucas, Agnes Meyder, Stanislaw Adaszewski, Ashley Montanaro</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Protein folding -- the problem of predicting the spatial structure of a protein given its sequence of amino-acids -- has attracted considerable research effort in biochemistry in recent decades. In this work, we explore the potential of quantum computing to solve a simplified version of protein folding. More precisely, we numerically investigate the performance of a variational quantum algorithm, the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA), in sampling low-energy conformations of short peptides. We start by benchmarking the algorithm on an even simpler problem: sampling self-avoiding walks, which is a necessary condition for a valid protein conformation. Motivated by promising results achieved by QAOA on this problem, we then apply the algorithm to a more complete version of protein folding, including a simplified physical potential. In this case, based on numerical simulations on 20 qubits, we find less promising results: deep quantum circuits are required to achieve accurate results, and the performance of QAOA can be matched by random sampling up to a small overhead. Overall, these results cast serious doubt on the ability of QAOA to address the protein folding problem in the near term, even in an extremely simplified setting. We believe that the approach and conclusions presented in this work could offer valuable methodological insights on how to systematically evaluate variational quantum optimization algorithms on real-world problems beyond protein folding.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complexity and entanglement in non-local computation and holography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.00908</link>
    <author>Alex May</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Does gravity constrain computation? We study this question using the AdS/CFT correspondence, where computation in the presence of gravity can be related to non-gravitational physics in the boundary theory. In AdS/CFT, computations which happen locally in the bulk are implemented in a particular non-local form in the boundary, which in general requires distributed entanglement. In particular, we argue that the area of a particular surface called the ridge, associated to a bulk subregion, is equal to the mutual information available in the boundary to perform the computation non-locally. We further argue the complexity of the local operation controls the amount of entanglement needed to implement it non-locally, and that in particular the complexity and entanglement cost are related by a polynomial. If this relationship holds, gravity constrains the complexity of operations within the scattering region to be polynomial in the area of the ridge.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>