<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.00921</link>
    <author>Zhenyu Cai, Ryan Babbush, Simon C. Benjamin, Suguru Endo, William J. Huggins, Ying Li, Jarrod R. McClean, Thomas E. O'Brien</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For quantum computers to successfully solve real-world problems, it is necessary to tackle the challenge of noise: the errors which occur in elementary physical components due to unwanted or imperfect interactions. The theory of quantum fault tolerance can provide an answer in the long term, but in the coming era of `NISQ' machines we must seek to mitigate errors rather than completely remove them. This review surveys the diverse methods that have been proposed for quantum error mitigation, assesses their in-principle efficacy, and then describes the hardware demonstrations achieved to date. We identify the commonalities and limitations among the methods, noting how mitigation methods can be chosen according to the primary type of noise present, including algorithmic errors. Open problems in the field are identified and we discuss the prospects for realising mitigation-based devices that can deliver quantum advantage with an impact on science and business.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning many-body Hamiltonians with Heisenberg-limited scaling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03030</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Yu Tong, Di Fang, Yuan Su</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Learning a many-body Hamiltonian from its dynamics is a fundamental problem in physics. In this work, we propose the first algorithm to achieve the Heisenberg limit for learning an interacting $N$-qubit local Hamiltonian. After a total evolution time of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-1})$, the proposed algorithm can efficiently estimate any parameter in the $N$-qubit Hamiltonian to $\epsilon$-error with high probability. The proposed algorithm is robust against state preparation and measurement error, does not require eigenstates or thermal states, and only uses $\mathrm{polylog}(\epsilon^{-1})$ experiments. In contrast, the best previous algorithms, such as recent works using gradient-based optimization or polynomial interpolation, require a total evolution time of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ and $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ experiments. Our algorithm uses ideas from quantum simulation to decouple the unknown $N$-qubit Hamiltonian $H$ into noninteracting patches, and learns $H$ using a quantum-enhanced divide-and-conquer approach. We prove a matching lower bound to establish the asymptotic optimality of our algorithm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from classical LTCs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02999</link>
    <author>Zhiyang He, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide a completely self-contained construction of a family of NLTS Hamiltonians [Freedman and Hastings, 2014] based on ideas from [Anshu, Breuckmann, and Nirkhe, 2022], [Cross, He, Natarajan, Szegedy, and Zhu, 2022] and [Eldar and Harrow, 2017]. Crucially, it does not require optimal-parameter quantum LDPC codes and can be built from simple classical LTCs such as the repetition code on an expander graph. Furthermore, it removes the constant-rate requirement from the construction of Anshu, Breuckmann, and Nirkhe.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum communication complexity of linear regression</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.01601</link>
    <author>Ashley Montanaro, Changpeng Shao</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Dequantized algorithms show that quantum computers do not have exponential speedups for many linear algebra problems in terms of time and query complexity. In this work, we show that quantum computers can have exponential speedups in terms of communication complexity for some fundamental linear algebra problems. We mainly focus on solving linear regression and Hamiltonian simulation. In the quantum case, the task is to prepare the quantum state of the result. To allow for a fair comparison, in the classical case the task is to sample from the result. We investigate these two problems in two-party and multiparty models, propose near-optimal quantum protocols and prove quantum/classical lower bounds. In this process, we propose an efficient quantum protocol for quantum singular value transformation, which is a powerful technique for designing quantum algorithms. As a result, for many linear algebra problems where quantum computers lose exponential speedups in terms of time and query complexity, it is possible to have exponential speedups in terms of communication complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Floquet codes without parent subsystem codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02468</link>
    <author>Margarita Davydova, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Shankar Balasubramanian</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a new class of error-correcting dynamic codes in two and three dimensions that has no explicit connection to any parent subsystem code. The two-dimensional code, which we call the CSS Floquet code, is geometrically similar to that of the honeycomb code by Hastings and Haah, and also dynamically embeds an instantaneous toric code. However, unlike the honeycomb code it possesses an explicit CSS structure and its gauge checks do not form a subsystem code. Nevertheless, we show that our dynamic protocol conserves logical information and possesses a threshold for error correction. We generalize this construction to three dimensions and obtain a code that fault-tolerantly alternates between realizing two type-I fracton models, the checkerboard and the X-cube model. Finally, we show the compatibility of our CSS Floquet code protocol and the honeycomb code by showing the possibility of randomly switching between the two protocols without information loss while still measuring error syndromes. We call this more general aperiodic structure `dynamic tree codes', which we also generalize to three dimensions. Under a certain correlated randomness constraint, this code is error correcting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Thermal State Preparation via Rounding Promises</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.01670</link>
    <author>Patrick Rall, Chunhao Wang, Pawel Wocjan</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A promising avenue for the preparation of Gibbs states on a quantum computer is to simulate the physical thermalization process. The Davies generator describes the dynamics of an open quantum system that is in contact with a heat bath. Crucially, it does not require simulation of the heat bath itself, only the system we hope to thermalize. Using the state-of-the-art techniques for quantum simulation of the Lindblad equation, we devise a technique for the preparation of Gibbs states via thermalization as specified by the Davies generator. In doing so, we encounter a severe technical challenge: implementation of the Davies generator demands the ability to estimate the energy of the system unambiguously. That is, each energy of the system must be deterministically mapped to a unique estimate. Previous work showed that this is only possible if the system satisfies an unphysical 'rounding promise' assumption. We solve this problem by engineering a random ensemble of rounding promises that simultaneously solves three problems: First, each rounding promise admits preparation of a 'promised' thermal state via a Davies generator. Second, these Davies generators have a similar mixing time as the ideal Davies generator. Third, the average of these promised thermal states approximates the ideal thermal state.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Distributed Quantum Interactive Proofs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.01390</link>
    <author>François Le Gall, Masayuki Miyamoto, Harumichi Nishimura</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The study of distributed interactive proofs was initiated by Kol, Oshman, and Saxena [PODC 2018] as a generalization of distributed decision mechanisms (proof-labeling schemes, etc.), and has received a lot of attention in recent years. In distributed interactive proofs, the nodes of an $n$-node network $G$ can exchange short messages (called certificates) with a powerful prover. The goal is to decide if the input (including $G$ itself) belongs to some language, with as few turns of interaction and as few bits exchanged between nodes and the prover as possible. There are several results showing that the size of certificates can be reduced drastically with a constant number of interactions compared to non-interactive distributed proofs. In this paper, we introduce the quantum counterpart of distributed interactive proofs: certificates can now be quantum bits, and the nodes of the network can perform quantum computation. The first result of this paper shows that by using quantum distributed interactive proofs, the number of interactions can be significantly reduced. More precisely, our result shows that for any constant~$k$, the class of languages that can be decided by a $k$-turn classical (i.e., non-quantum) distributed interactive protocol with $f(n)$-bit certificate size is contained in the class of languages that can be decided by a $5$-turn distributed quantum interactive protocol with $O(f(n))$-bit certificate size. We also show that if we allow to use shared randomness, the number of turns can be reduced to 3-turn. Since no similar turn-reduction \emphclassical technique is currently known, our result gives evidence of the power of quantum computation in the setting of distributed interactive proofs as well.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Perturbation theory with quantum signal processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.00718</link>
    <author>Kosuke Mitarai, Wataru Mizukami</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Perturbation theory is an important technique for reducing computational cost and providing physical insights in simulating quantum systems with classical computers. Here, we provide a quantum algorithm to obtain perturbative energies on quantum computers. The benefit of using quantum computers is that we can start the perturbation from a Hamiltonian that is classically hard to solve. The proposed algorithm uses quantum signal processing (QSP) to achieve this goal. Along with the perturbation theory, we construct a technique for ground state preparation with detailed computational cost analysis, which can be of independent interest. We also estimate a rough computational cost of the algorithm for simple chemical systems such as water clusters and polyacene molecules. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first of such estimates for practical applications of QSP. Unfortunately, we find that the proposed algorithm, at least in its current form, does not exhibit practical numbers despite of the efficiency of QSP compared to conventional quantum algorithms. However, perturbation theory itself is an attractive direction to explore because of its physical interpretability; it provides us insights about what interaction gives an important contribution to the properties of systems. This is in sharp contrast to the conventional approaches based on the quantum phase estimation algorithm, where we can only obtain values of energy. From this aspect, this work is a first step towards ``explainable'' quantum simulation on fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A perturbative gadget for delaying the onset of barren plateaus in variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03099</link>
    <author>Simon Cichy, Paul K. Faehrmann, Sumeet Khatri, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms are being explored as a promising approach to finding useful applications for noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers. However, cost functions corresponding to many problems of interest are inherently global, defined by Hamiltonians with many-body interactions. Consequently, the optimization landscape can exhibit exponentially vanishing gradients, so-called barren plateaus, rendering optimal solutions difficult to find. Strategies for mitigating barren plateaus are therefore needed to make variational quantum algorithms trainable and capable of running on larger-scale quantum devices. In this work, we contribute the toolbox of perturbative gadgets to the portfolio of methods being explored in the quest for making noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices useful. Specifically, we introduce a novel perturbative gadget, tailored to variational quantum algorithms, that can be used to avoid barren plateaus. Our perturbative gadget encodes an arbitrary many-body Hamiltonian corresponding to a global cost function into the low-energy subspace of a three-body Hamiltonian. Our construction requires $rk$ additional qubits for a $k$-body Hamiltonian comprising $r$ terms. We provide rigorous guarantees on the optimization of the local cost function defined by our three-body gadget Hamiltonian with respect to the original cost function, and we prove that this local cost function exhibits non-vanishing gradients, thus delaying the onset of barren plateaus. We then provide numerical demonstrations to show the functioning of our approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hello Quantum World! A rigorous but accessible first-year university course in quantum information science</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.02868</link>
    <author>Sophia E. Economou, Edwin Barnes</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Addressing workforce shortages within the Quantum Information Science and Engineering (QISE) community requires attracting and retaining students from diverse backgrounds early on in their undergraduate education. Here, we describe a course we developed called Hello Quantum World! that introduces a broad range of fundamental quantum information and computation concepts in a rigorous way but without requiring any knowledge of mathematics beyond high-school algebra nor any prior knowledge of quantum mechanics. Some of the topics covered include superposition, entanglement, quantum gates, teleportation, quantum algorithms, and quantum error correction. The course is designed for first-year undergraduate students, both those pursuing a degree in QISE and those who are seeking to be `quantum-aware'.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>