<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Sparse random Hamiltonians are quantumly easy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03394</link>
    <author>Chi-Fang Chen, Alexander M. Dalzell, Mario Berta, Fernando G.S.L. Brandão, Joel A. Tropp</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 08 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A candidate application for quantum computers is to simulate the low-temperature properties of quantum systems. For this task, there is a well-studied quantum algorithm that performs quantum phase estimation on an initial trial state that has a nonnegligible overlap with a low-energy state. However, it is notoriously hard to give theoretical guarantees that such a trial state can be prepared efficiently. Moreover, the heuristic proposals that are currently available, such as with adiabatic state preparation, appear insufficient in practical cases. This paper shows that, for most random sparse Hamiltonians, the maximally mixed state is a sufficiently good trial state, and phase estimation efficiently prepares states with energy arbitrarily close to the ground energy. Furthermore, any low-energy state must have nonnegligible quantum circuit complexity, suggesting that low-energy states are classically nontrivial and phase estimation is the optimal method for preparing such states (up to polynomial factors). These statements hold for two models of random Hamiltonians: (i) a sum of random signed Pauli strings and (ii) a random signed $d$-sparse Hamiltonian. The main technical argument is based on some new results in nonasymptotic random matrix theory. In particular, a refined concentration bound for the spectral density is required to obtain complexity guarantees for these random Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-Tolerant Connection of Error-Corrected Qubits with Noisy Links</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01296</link>
    <author>Joshua Ramette, Josiah Sinclair, Nikolas P. Breuckmann, Vladan Vuletić</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>One of the most promising routes towards scalable quantum computing is a modular approach. We show that distinct surface code patches can be connected in a fault-tolerant manner even in the presence of substantial noise along their connecting interface. We quantify analytically and numerically the combined effect of errors across the interface and bulk. We show that the system can tolerate 14 times higher noise at the interface compared to the bulk, with only a small effect on the code's threshold and sub-threshold behavior, reaching threshold with $\sim 1 \%$ bulk errors and $\sim 10 \%$ interface errors. This implies that fault-tolerant scaling of error-corrected modular devices is within reach using existing technology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Qubit-Efficient Randomized Quantum Algorithms for Linear Algebra</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01873</link>
    <author>Samson Wang, Sam McArdle, Mario Berta</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a class of randomized quantum algorithms for the task of sampling from matrix functions, without the use of quantum block encodings or any other coherent oracle access to the matrix elements. As such, our use of qubits is purely algorithmic, and no additional qubits are required for quantum data structures. For $N\times N$ Hermitian matrices, the space cost is $\log(N)+1$ qubits and depending on the structure of the matrices, the gate complexity can be comparable to state-of-the-art methods that use quantum data structures of up to size $O(N^2)$, when considering equivalent end-to-end problems. Within our framework, we present a quantum linear system solver that allows one to sample properties of the solution vector, as well as an algorithm for sampling properties of ground states of Hamiltonians. As a concrete application, we combine these two sub-routines to present a scheme for calculating Green's functions of quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal lower bound on topological entanglement entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.00689</link>
    <author>Isaac H. Kim, Michael Levin, Ting-Chun Lin, Daniel Ranard, Bowen Shi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement entropies of two-dimensional gapped ground states are expected to satisfy an area law, with a constant correction term known as the topological entanglement entropy (TEE). In many models, the TEE takes a universal value that characterizes the underlying topological phase. However, the TEE is not truly universal: it can differ even for two states related by constant-depth circuits, which are necessarily in the same phase. The difference between the TEE and the value predicted by the anyon theory is often called the spurious topological entanglement entropy. We show that this spurious contribution is always nonnegative, thus the value predicted by the anyon theory provides a universal lower bound. This observation also leads to a definition of TEE which is invariant under constant-depth quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Relaxing Hardware Requirements for Surface Code Circuits using Time-dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.02192</link>
    <author>Matt McEwen, Dave Bacon, Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The typical time-independent view of quantum error correction (QEC) codes hides significant freedom in the decomposition into circuits that are executable on hardware. Using the concept of detecting regions, we design time-dynamic QEC circuits directly instead of designing static QEC codes to decompose into circuits. In particular, we improve on the standard circuit constructions for the surface code, presenting new circuits that can embed on a hexagonal grid instead of a square grid, that can use ISWAP gates instead of CNOT or CZ gates, that can exchange qubit data and measure roles, and that move logical patches around the physical qubit grid while executing. All these constructions use no additional entangling gate layers and display essentially the same logical performance, having teraquop footprints within 25% of the standard surface code circuit. We expect these circuits to be of great interest to quantum hardware engineers, because they achieve essentially the same logical performance as standard surface code circuits while relaxing demands on hardware.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Computational Separation Between Quantum No-cloning and No-teleportation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01858</link>
    <author>Barak Nehoran, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Two of the fundamental no-go theorems of quantum information are the no-cloning theorem (that it is impossible to make copies of general quantum states) and the no-teleportation theorem (the prohibition on sending quantum states over classical channels without pre-shared entanglement). They are known to be equivalent, in the sense that a collection of quantum states is clonable if and only if it is teleportable. Our main result suggests that this is not the case when computational efficiency is considered. We give a collection of quantum states and oracles relative to which these states are efficiently clonable but not efficiently teleportable. Given that the opposite scenario is impossible (states that can be teleported can always trivially be cloned), this gives the most complete oracle separation possible between these two important no-go properties. In doing so, we introduce a related quantum no-go property, reconstructibility, which refers to the ability to construct a quantum state from a uniquely identifying classical description. We show the stronger result of a collection of quantum states that are efficiently clonable but not efficiently reconstructible. This novel no-go property only exists in relation to computational efficiency, as it is trivial for unbounded computation. It thus opens up the possibility of further computational no-go properties that have not yet been studied because they do not exist outside the computational context.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Experimental demonstration of the advantage of adaptive quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.03029</link>
    <author>Michael Foss-Feig, Arkin Tikku, Tsung-Cheng Lu, Karl Mayer, Mohsin Iqbal, Thomas M. Gatterman, Justin A. Gerber, Kevin Gilmore, Dan Gresh, Aaron Hankin, Nathan Hewitt, Chandler V. Horst, Mitchell Matheny, Tanner Mengle, Brian Neyenhuis, Henrik Dreyer, David Hayes, Timothy H. Hsieh, Isaac H. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Adaptive quantum circuits employ unitary gates assisted by mid-circuit measurement, classical computation on the measurement outcome, and the conditional application of future unitary gates based on the result of the classical computation. In this paper, we experimentally demonstrate that even a noisy adaptive quantum circuit of constant depth can achieve a task that is impossible for any purely unitary quantum circuit of identical depth: the preparation of long-range entangled topological states with high fidelity. We prepare a particular toric code ground state with fidelity of at least $76.9\pm 1.3\%$ using a constant depth ($d=4$) adaptive circuit, and rigorously show that no unitary circuit of the same depth and connectivity could prepare this state with fidelity greater than $50\%$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Can shallow quantum circuits scramble local noise into global white noise?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.00881</link>
    <author>Jonathan Foldager, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Shallow quantum circuits are believed to be the most promising candidates for achieving early practical quantum advantage - this has motivated the development of a broad range of error mitigation techniques whose performance generally improves when the quantum state is well approximated by a global depolarising (white) noise model. While it has been crucial for demonstrating quantum supremacy that random circuits scramble local noise into global white noise - a property that has been proved rigorously - we investigate to what degree practical shallow quantum circuits scramble local noise into global white noise. We define two key metrics as (a) density matrix eigenvalue uniformity and (b) commutator norm. While the former determines the distance from white noise, the latter determines the performance of purification based error mitigation. We derive analytical approximate bounds on their scaling and find in most cases they nicely match numerical results. On the other hand, we simulate a broad class of practical quantum circuits and find that white noise is in certain cases a bad approximation posing significant limitations on the performance of some of the simpler error mitigation schemes. On a positive note, we find in all cases that the commutator norm is sufficiently small guaranteeing a very good performance of purification-based error mitigation. Lastly, we identify techniques that may decrease both metrics, such as increasing the dimensionality of the dynamical Lie algebra by gate insertions or randomised compiling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bulk-to-boundary anyon fusion from microscopic models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.01835</link>
    <author>Julio C. Magdalena de la Fuente, Jens Eisert, Andreas Bauer</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Topological quantum error correction based on the manipulation of the anyonic defects constitutes one of the most promising frameworks towards realizing fault-tolerant quantum devices. Hence, it is crucial to understand how these defects interact with external defects such as boundaries or domain walls. Motivated by this line of thought, in this work, we study the fusion events between anyons in the bulk and at the boundary in fixed-point models of 2+1-dimensional non-chiral topological order defined by arbitrary fusion categories. Our construction uses generalized tube algebra techniques to construct a bi-representation of bulk and boundary defects. We explicitly derive a formula to calculate the fusion multiplicities of a bulk-to-boundary fusion event for twisted quantum double models and calculate some exemplary fusion events for Abelian models and the (twisted) quantum double model of S3, the simplest non-Abelian group-theoretical model. Moreover, we use the folding trick to study the anyonic behavior at non-trivial domain walls between twisted S3 and twisted Z2 as well as Z3 models. A recurring theme in our construction is an isomorphism relating twisted cohomology groups to untwisted ones. The results of this work can directly be applied to study logical operators in two-dimensional topological error correcting codes with boundaries described by a twisted gauge theory of a finite group.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Extending Matchgate Simulation Methods to Universal Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.02654</link>
    <author>Avinash Mocherla, Lingling Lao, Dan E. Browne</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Matchgates are a family of parity-preserving two-qubit gates, nearest-neighbour circuits of which are known to be classically simulable in polynomial time. In this work, we present a simulation method to classically simulate an $\boldsymbol{n}$-qubit circuit containing $\boldsymbol{N}$ matchgates and $\boldsymbol{m}$ universality-enabling gates in the setting of single-qubit Pauli measurements and product state inputs. The universality-enabling gates we consider include the SWAP, CZ and CPhase gates. We find in the worst and average cases, the scaling when $\boldsymbol{m \, < \, \lfloor \frac{n}{2} \rfloor -1}$ is given by $\sim \mathcal{O}(\boldsymbol{N(\frac{n}{m+1})^{2m+2}})$ and $\sim \mathcal{O}( \boldsymbol{\frac{N}{m+1}(\frac{n}{m+1})^{2m+2}})$, respectively. For $\boldsymbol{m \, \geq \, \lfloor \frac{n}{2} \rfloor -1}$, we find the scaling is exponential in $\boldsymbol{n}$, but always outperforms a dense statevector simulator in the asymptotic limit.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>