<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Free-Fermion Subsystem Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07254</link>
    <author>Adrian Chapman, Steven T. Flammia, Alicia J. Kollár</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider quantum error-correcting subsystem codes whose gauge generators realize a translation-invariant, free-fermion-solvable spin model. In this setting, errors are suppressed by a Hamiltonian whose terms are the gauge generators of the code and whose exact spectrum and eigenstates can be found via a generalized Jordan-Wigner transformation. Such solutions are characterized by the frustration graph of the Hamiltonian: the graph whose vertices are Hamiltonian terms, which are neighboring if the terms anticommute. We provide methods for embedding a given frustration graph in the anticommutation relations of a spin model and present the first known example of an exactly solvable spin model with a two-dimensional free-fermion description and exact topological qubits. This model can be viewed as a free-fermionized version of the two-dimensional Bacon-Shor code. Using graph-theoretic tools to study the unit cell, we give an efficient algorithm for deciding if a given translation-invariant spin model is solvable, and explicitly construct the solution. Further, we examine the energetics of these exactly solvable models from the graph-theoretic perspective and show that the relevant gaps of the spin model correspond to known graph-theoretic quantities: the skew energy and the median eigenvalue of an oriented graph. Finally, we numerically search for models which have large spectral gaps above the ground state spin configuration and thus exhibit particularly robust thermal suppression of errors. These results suggest that optimal models will have low dimensionality and odd coordination numbers, and that the primary limit to energetic error suppression is the skew energy difference between different symmetry sectors rather than single-particle excitations of the free fermions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A circuit-level protocol and analysis for twist-based lattice surgery</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05678</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Lattice surgery is a measurement-based technique for performing fault-tolerant quantum computation in two dimensions. When using the surface code, the most general lattice surgery operations require lattice irregularities called twist defects. However, implementing twist-based lattice surgery may require additional resources, such as extra device connectivity, and could lower the threshold and overall performance for the surface code. Here we provide an explicit twist-based lattice surgery protocol and its requisite connectivity layout. We also provide new stabilizer measurement circuits for measuring twist defects which are compatible with our chosen gate scheduling. We undertake the first circuit-level error correction simulations during twist-based lattice surgery using a biased depolarizing noise model. Our results indicate a slight decrease in the threshold for timelike logical failures compared to lattice surgery protocols with no twist defects in the bulk. However, comfortably below threshold (i.e. with CNOT infidelities below $5 \times 10^{-3}$), the performance degradation is mild and in fact preferable over proposed alternative twist-free schemes. Lastly, we provide an efficient scheme for measuring $Y$ operators along boundaries of surface codes which bypasses certain steps that were required in previous schemes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Algorithms for Approximating Quantum Partition Functions at Low Temperature</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06533</link>
    <author>Tyler Helmuth, Ryan L. Mann</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish an efficient approximation algorithm for the partition functions of a class of quantum spin systems at low temperature, which can be viewed as stable quantum perturbations of classical spin systems. Our algorithm is based on combining the contour representation of quantum spin systems of this type due to Borgs, Kotecký, and Ueltschi with the algorithmic framework developed by Helmuth, Perkins, and Regts, and Borgs et al.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Depth optimization of CZ, CNOT, and Clifford circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05215</link>
    <author>Dmitri Maslov, Ben Zindorf</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We seek to develop better upper bound guarantees on the depth of quantum CZ gate, CNOT gate, and Clifford circuits than those reported previously. We focus on the number of qubits $n\,{\leq}\,$1,345,000 [1], which represents the most practical use case. Our upper bound on the depth of CZ circuits is $\lfloor n/2 + 0.4993{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.0191{\cdot}\log(n) - 10.9139\rfloor$, improving best known depth by a factor of roughly 2. We extend the constructions used to prove this upper bound to obtain depth upper bound of $\lfloor n + 1.9496{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.5075{\cdot}\log(n) - 23.4269 \rfloor$ for CNOT gate circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $4/3$ over state of the art, and depth upper bound of $\lfloor 2n + 2.9487{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 8.4909{\cdot}\log(n) - 44.4798\rfloor$ for Clifford circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $5/3$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cut query algorithms with star contraction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05674</link>
    <author>Simon Apers, Yuval Efron, Paweł Gawrychowski, Troy Lee, Sagnik Mukhopadhyay, Danupon Nanongkai</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the complexity of determining the edge connectivity of a simple graph with cut queries. We show that (i) there is a bounded-error randomized algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $O(n)$ cut queries, and (ii) there is a bounded-error quantum algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $\~O(\sqrt{n})$ cut queries. We prove these results using a new technique called "star contraction" to randomly contract edges of a graph while preserving non-trivial minimum cuts. In star contraction vertices randomly contract an edge incident on a small set of randomly chosen vertices. In contrast to the related 2-out contraction technique of Ghaffari, Nowicki, and Thorup [SODA'20], star contraction only contracts vertex-disjoint star subgraphs, which allows it to be efficiently implemented via cut queries. The $O(n)$ bound from item (i) was not known even for the simpler problem of connectivity, and improves the $O(n\log^3 n)$ bound by Rubinstein, Schramm, and Weinberg [ITCS'18]. The bound is tight under the reasonable conjecture that the randomized communication complexity of connectivity is $\Omega(n\log n)$, an open question since the seminal work of Babai, Frankl, and Simon [FOCS'86]. The bound also excludes using edge connectivity on simple graphs to prove a superlinear randomized query lower bound for minimizing a symmetric submodular function. Item (ii) gives a nearly-quadratic separation with the randomized complexity and addresses an open question of Lee, Santha, and Zhang [SODA'21]. The algorithm can also be viewed as making $\~O(\sqrt{n})$ matrix-vector multiplication queries to the adjacency matrix. Finally, we demonstrate the use of star contraction outside of the cut query setting by designing a one-pass semi-streaming algorithm for computing edge connectivity in the vertex arrival setting. This contrasts with the edge arrival setting where two passes are required.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On Lieb-Robinson Bounds for the Double Bracket Flow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07141</link>
    <author>Matthew B. Hastings</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the possibility of developing a Lieb-Robinson bound for the double bracket flow. This is a differential equation $$\partial_B H(B)=[[V,H(B)],H(B)]$$ which may be used to diagonalize Hamiltonians. Here, $V$ is fixed and $H(0)=H$. We argue (but do not prove) that $H(B)$ need not converge to a limit for nonzero real $B$ in the infinite volume limit, even assuming several conditions on $H(0)$. However, we prove Lieb-Robinson bounds for all $B$ for the double-bracket flow for free fermion systems, but the range increases \emphexponentially with the control parameter $B$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Uniform continuity bound for sandwiched Rényi conditional entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05534</link>
    <author>Ashutosh Marwah, Frédéric Dupuis</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove a simple uniform continuity bound for the sandwiched Rényi conditional entropy for $\alpha \in [1/2, 1) \cup (1, \infty]$, which is independent of the dimension of the conditioning system.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Test-measured Rényi divergences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05477</link>
    <author>Milán Mosonyi, Fumio Hiai</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One possibility of defining a quantum Rényi $\alpha$-divergence of two quantum states is to optimize the classical Rényi $\alpha$-divergence of their post-measurement probability distributions over all possible measurements (measured Rényi divergence), and maybe regularize these quantities over multiple copies of the two states (regularized measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence). A key observation behind the theorem for the strong converse exponent of asymptotic binary quantum state discrimination is that the regularized measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence coincides with the sandwiched Rényi $\alpha$-divergence when $\alpha>1$. Moreover, it also follows from the same theorem that to achieve this, it is sufficient to consider $2$-outcome measurements (tests) for any number of copies (this is somewhat surprising, as achieving the measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence for $n$ copies might require a number of measurement outcomes that diverges in $n$, in general). In view of this, it seems natural to expect the same when $\alpha<1$; however, we show that this is not the case. In fact, we show that even for commuting states (classical case) the regularized quantity attainable using $2$-outcome measurements is in general strictly smaller than the Rényi $\alpha$-divergence (which is unique in the classical case). In the general quantum case this shows that the above ``regularized test-measured'' Rényi $\alpha$-divergence is not even a quantum extension of the classical Rényi divergence when $\alpha<1$, in sharp contrast to the $\alpha>1$ case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Characterizing Long-Range Entanglement in a Mixed State Through an Emergent Order on the Entangling Surface</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07792</link>
    <author>Tsung-Cheng Lu, Sagar Vijay</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Topologically-ordered phases of matter at non-zero temperature are conjectured to exhibit universal patterns of long-range entanglement which may be detected by a mixed-state entanglement measure known as entanglement negativity. We show that the entanglement negativity in certain topological orders can be understood through the properties of an emergent symmetry-protected topological (SPT) order which is localized on the entanglement bipartition. This connection leads to an understanding of ($i$) universal contributions to the entanglement negativity which diagnose finite-temperature topological order, and ($ii$) the behavior of the entanglement negativity across certain phase transitions in which thermal fluctuations eventually destroy long-range entanglement across the bipartition surface. Within this correspondence, the universal patterns of entanglement in the finite-temperature topological order are related to the stability of an emergent SPT order against a symmetry-breaking field. SPT orders protected by higher-form symmetries -- which arise, for example, in the description of the entanglement negativity for $\mathbb{Z}_{2}$ topological order in $d=4$ spatial dimensions -- remain robust even in the presence of a weak symmetry-breaking perturbation, leading to long-range entanglement at non-zero temperature for certain topological orders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decoding techniques applied to the compilation of CNOT circuits for NISQ architectures</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06457</link>
    <author>Timothée Goubault de Brugière, Marc Baboulin, Benoît Valiron, Simon Martiel, Cyril Allouche</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Current proposals for quantum compilers require the synthesis and optimization of linear reversible circuits and among them CNOT circuits. Since these circuits represent a significant part of the cost of running an entire quantum circuit, we aim at reducing their size. In this paper we present a new algorithm for the synthesis of CNOT circuits based on the solution of the syndrome decoding problem. Our method addresses the case of ideal hardware with an all-to-all qubit connectivity and the case of near-term quantum devices with restricted connectivity. For both cases, we present benchmarks showing that our algorithm outperforms existing algorithms.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>