<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A lower bound on the space overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00119</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Alexander Müller-Hermes, Ala Shayeghi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The threshold theorem is a fundamental result in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation stating that arbitrarily long quantum computations can be performed with a polylogarithmic overhead provided the noise level is below a constant level. A recent work by Fawzi, Grospellier and Leverrier (FOCS 2018) building on a result by Gottesman (QIC 2013) has shown that the space overhead can be asymptotically reduced to a constant independent of the circuit provided we only consider circuits with a length bounded by a polynomial in the width. In this work, using a minimal model for quantum fault tolerance, we establish a general lower bound on the space overhead required to achieve fault tolerance. For any non-unitary qubit channel $\mathcal{N}$ and any quantum fault tolerance schemes against $\mathrm{i.i.d.}$ noise modeled by $\mathcal{N}$, we prove a lower bound of $\max\left\{\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})^{-1}n,\alpha_\mathcal{N} \log T\right\}$ on the number of physical qubits, for circuits of length $T$ and width $n$. Here, $\mathrm{Q}(\mathcal{N})$ denotes the quantum capacity of $\mathcal{N}$ and $\alpha_\mathcal{N}>0$ is a constant only depending on the channel $\mathcal{N}$. In our model, we allow for qubits to be replaced by fresh ones during the execution of the circuit and we allow classical computation to be free and perfect. This improves upon results that assumed classical computations to be also affected by noise, and that sometimes did not allow for fresh qubits to be added. Along the way, we prove an exponential upper bound on the maximal length of fault-tolerant quantum computation with amplitude damping noise resolving a conjecture by Ben-Or, Gottesman, and Hassidim (2013).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bias-tailored quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01702</link>
    <author>Joschka Roffe, Lawrence Z. Cohen, Armanda O. Quintivalle, Daryus Chandra, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bias-tailoring allows quantum error correction codes to exploit qubit noise asymmetry. Recently, it was shown that a modified form of the surface code, the XZZX code, exhibits considerably improved performance under biased noise. In this work, we demonstrate that quantum low density parity check codes can be similarly bias-tailored. We introduce a bias-tailored lifted product code construction that provides the framework to expand bias-tailoring methods beyond the family of 2D topological codes. We present examples of bias-tailored lifted product codes based on classical quasi-cyclic codes and numerically assess their performance using a belief propagation plus ordered statistics decoder. Our Monte Carlo simulations, performed under asymmetric noise, show that bias-tailored codes achieve several orders of magnitude improvement in their error suppression relative to depolarising noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Practical Guide to the Numerical Implementation of Tensor Networks I: Contractions, Decompositions and Gauge Freedom</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.02138</link>
    <author>Glen Evenbly</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an overview of the key ideas and skills necessary to begin implementing tensor network methods numerically, which is intended to facilitate the practical application of tensor network methods for researchers that are already versed with their theoretical foundations. These skills include an introduction to the contraction of tensor networks, to optimal tensor decompositions, and to the manipulation of gauge degrees of freedom in tensor networks. The topics presented are of key importance to many common tensor network algorithms such as DMRG, TEBD, TRG, PEPS and MERA.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum machine learning with subspace states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00054</link>
    <author>Iordanis Kerenidis, Anupam Prakash</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new approach for quantum linear algebra based on quantum subspace states and present three new quantum machine learning algorithms. The first is a quantum determinant sampling algorithm that samples from the distribution $\Pr[S]= det(X_{S}X_{S}^{T})$ for $|S|=d$ using $O(nd)$ gates and with circuit depth $O(d\log n)$. The state of art classical algorithm for the task requires $O(d^{3})$ operations \citederezinski2019minimax. The second is a quantum singular value estimation algorithm for compound matrices $\mathcal{A}^{k}$, the speedup for this algorithm is potentially exponential. It decomposes a $\binom{n}{k}$ dimensional vector of order-$k$ correlations into a linear combination of subspace states corresponding to $k$-tuples of singular vectors of $A$. The third algorithm reduces exponentially the depth of circuits used in quantum topological data analysis from $O(n)$ to $O(\log n)$. Our basic tool are quantum subspace states, defined as $|Col(X)\rangle = \sum_{S\subset [n], |S|=d} det(X_{S}) |S\rangle$ for matrices $X \in \mathbb{R}^{n \times d}$ such that $X^{T} X = I_{d}$, that encode $d$-dimensional subspaces of $\mathbb{R}^{n}$. We develop two efficient state preparation techniques, the first using Givens circuits uses the representation of a subspace as a sequence of Givens rotations, while the second uses efficient implementations of unitaries $\Gamma(x) = \sum_{i} x_{i} Z^{\otimes (i-1)} \otimes X \otimes I^{n-i}$ with $O(\log n)$ depth circuits that we term Clifford loaders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mitigating the quantum hype</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01925</link>
    <author>Olivier Ezratty</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We are in the midst of quantum hype with some excessive claims of quantum computing potential, many vendors' and even some research organizations' exaggerations, and a funding frenzy for very low technology readiness level startups. Governments are contributing to this hype with their large quantum initiatives and their technology sovereignty aspirations. Technology hypes are not bad per se since they create emulation, drive innovations and also contribute to attracting new talents. It works as scientists and vendors deliver progress and innovation on a continuous basis after a so-called peak of expectations. It fails with exaggerated overpromises and underdeliveries that last too long. It can cut short research and innovation funding in the mid to long term. After looking at the shape and form of technology and science hypes and driving some lessons from past technology hypes, we investigate the current quantum hype phenomenon and identify some of its specifics. We find that, although there is some significant uncertainty on the potential to create real scalable quantum computers, the scientific and vendor fields are relatively solid compared to other technology hypes. Also, quantum technologies comprise other fields like quantum telecommunications and quantum sensing with a higher technology readiness level, which are less prone to hype. We then make some proposals to mitigate the potential negative effects of the current quantum hype including recommendations on scientific communication to strengthen the trust in quantum science, vendor behavior improvements, benchmarking methodologies, public education and putting in place a responsible research and innovation approach. All-in-all, it is about restoring the role of science and scientists in the current debates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Correction with Quantum Autoencoders</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00555</link>
    <author>David F. Locher, Lorenzo Cardarelli, Markus Müller</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Active quantum error correction is a central ingredient to achieve robust quantum processors. In this paper we investigate the potential of quantum machine learning for quantum error correction. Specifically, we demonstrate how quantum neural networks, in the form of quantum autoencoders, can be trained to learn optimal strategies for active detection and correction of errors, including spatially correlated computational errors as well as qubit losses. We highlight that the denoising capabilities of quantum autoencoders are not limited to the protection of specific states but extend to the entire logical codespace. We also show that quantum neural networks can be used to discover new logical encodings that are optimally adapted to the underlying noise. Moreover, we find that, even in the presence of moderate noise in the quantum autoencoders themselves, they may still be successfully used to perform beneficial quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improved quantum algorithms for linear and nonlinear differential equations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01054</link>
    <author>Hari Krovi</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present substantially generalized and improved quantum algorithms over prior work for inhomogeneous linear and nonlinear ordinary differential equations (ODE). In Berry et al., (2017), a quantum algorithm for a certain class of linear ODEs is given, where the matrix involved needs to be diagonalizable. The quantum algorithm for linear ODEs presented here extends to many classes of non-diagonalizable matrices. The algorithm here can also be exponentially faster for certain classes of diagonalizable matrices. Our linear ODE algorithm is then applied to nonlinear differential equations using Carleman linearization (an approach taken recently by us in Liu et al., (2021)). The improvement over that result is two-fold. First, we obtain an exponentially better dependence on error. This kind of logarithmic dependence on error has also been achieved by Xue et al., (2021), but only for homogeneous nonlinear equations. Second, the present algorithm can handle any sparse, invertible matrix (that models dissipation) if it has a negative log-norm (including non-diagonalizable matrices), whereas Liu et al., (2021) and Xue et al., (2021) additionally require normality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>High-temperature thermalization implies the emergence of quantum state designs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01669</link>
    <author>Henrik Wilming, Ingo Roth</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It was recently observed that in certain thermalizing many-body systems, measuring the complement of a subsystem that thermalized to infinite temperature in a suitable orthonormal basis gives rise to approximate quantum state k-designs as post-measurement states on the subsystem. We prove that this emergence of approximate k-designs holds true in every large system where some small subsystem is close to being maximally mixed. On a technical level we show that any high-dimensional purification of an approximately maximally mixed state induces an approximate quantum state k-design when measured in a suitable orthonormal basis. Moreover, we show that this is true with overwhelming probability for measurement bases chosen uniformly at random from the Haar measure.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum-inspired classical algorithm for molecular vibronic spectra</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.01861</link>
    <author>Changhun Oh, Youngrong Lim, Yat Wong, Bill Fefferman, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Molecular vibronic spectra is an essential property of molecules, which is an important tool to analyze chemical components and study molecular structures. Computing molecular vibronic spectra has been a challenging task, and its best-known classical algorithm scales combinatorially in the system size. Recently, a quantum simulator, specifically Gaussian boson sampling, has been proposed to generate the spectra efficiently. Thus, molecular vibronic spectra is a candidate of tasks for which a quantum device provides a computational advantage. In this work, we propose a quantum-inspired classical algorithm for molecular vibronic spectra. We find an exact solution of the Fourier components of molecular vibronic spectra at zero temperature using the positive $P$-representation method. Thus, we can obtain the molecular vibronic spectra exactly by the inverse Fourier transformation for the solution for a given resolution. We also show that the same method applies to a finite temperature case. Therefore, computing molecular vibronic spectra, which can be mapped to a Gaussian boson sampling, does not require a quantum device. We then generalize the method beyond the Gaussian framework and find that the Fourier components are written as a loop hafnian, the exact computation of which is known to be \#P-hard. It presents an interesting theoretical separation between non-Gaussian boson sampling and Gaussian boson sampling. Meanwhile, since running an actual boson sampling circuit would incur an $1/\text{poly}(N)$ additive error for $N$ samples, we also study the possibility of achieving the same accuracy using a classical algorithm. Interestingly, when there is no squeezing in the process, one may use Gurvits's algorithm to compute the Fourier components within an additive error. We finally provide possible approaches to approximate the Fourier components and discuss their limitations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Order preserving maps on quantum measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.00725</link>
    <author>Teiko Heinosaari, Maria Anastasia Jivulescu, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the partially ordered set of equivalence classes of quantum measurements endowed with the post-processing partial order. The post-processing order is fundamental as it enables to compare measurements by their intrinsic noise and it gives grounds to define the important concept of quantum incompatibility. Our approach is based on mapping this set into a simpler partially ordered set using an order preserving map and investigating the resulting image. The aim is to ignore unnecessary details while keeping the essential structure, thereby simplifying e.g. detection of incompatibility. One possible choice is the map based on Fisher information introduced by Huangjun Zhu, known to be an order morphism taking values in the cone of positive semidefinite matrices. We explore the properties of that construction and improve Zhu's incompatibility criterion by adding a constraint depending on the number of measurement outcomes. We generalize this type of construction to other ordered vector spaces and we show that this map is optimal among all quadratic maps.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>