<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Lower Bounds on Learning Pauli Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09192</link>
    <author>Omar Fawzi, Aadil Oufkir, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding the noise affecting a quantum device is of fundamental importance for scaling quantum technologies. A particularly important class of noise models is that of Pauli channels, as randomized compiling techniques can effectively bring any quantum channel to this form and are significantly more structured than general quantum channels. In this paper, we show fundamental lower bounds on the sample complexity for learning Pauli channels in diamond norm with unentangled measurements. We consider both adaptive and non-adaptive strategies. In the non-adaptive setting, we show a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{3n}\epsilon^{-2})$ to learn an $n$-qubit Pauli channel. In particular, this shows that the recently introduced learning procedure by Flammia and Wallman is essentially optimal. In the adaptive setting, we show a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{2.5n}\epsilon^{-2})$ for $\epsilon=\mathcal{O}(2^{-n})$, and a lower bound of $\Omega(2^{2n}\epsilon^{-2} )$ for any $\epsilon > 0$. This last lower bound even applies for arbitrarily many sequential uses of the channel, as long as they are only interspersed with other unital operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error Correction of Quantum Algorithms: Arbitrarily Accurate Recovery Of Noisy Quantum Signal Processing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08542</link>
    <author>Andrew K. Tan, Yuan Liu, Minh C. Tran, Isaac L. Chuang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The intrinsic probabilistic nature of quantum systems makes error correction or mitigation indispensable for quantum computation. While current error-correcting strategies focus on correcting errors in quantum states or quantum gates, these fine-grained error-correction methods can incur significant overhead for quantum algorithms of increasing complexity. We present a first step in achieving error correction at the level of quantum algorithms by combining a unified perspective on modern quantum algorithms via quantum signal processing (QSP). An error model of under- or over-rotation of the signal processing operator parameterized by $\epsilon < 1$ is introduced. It is shown that while Pauli $Z$-errors are not recoverable without additional resources, Pauli $X$ and $Y$ errors can be arbitrarily suppressed by coherently appending a noisy `recovery QSP.' Furthermore, it is found that a recovery QSP of length $O(2^k c^{k^2} d)$ is sufficient to correct any length-$d$ QSP with $c$ unique phases to $k^{th}$-order in error $\epsilon$. Allowing an additional assumption, a lower bound of $\Omega(cd)$ is shown, which is tight for $k = 1$, on the length of the recovery sequence. Our algorithmic-level error correction method is applied to Grover's fixed-point search algorithm as a demonstration.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Exponential Separation Between Quantum Query Complexity and the Polynomial Degree</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09218</link>
    <author>Andris Ambainis, Aleksandrs Belovs</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>While it is known that there is at most a polynomial separation between quantum query complexity and the polynomial degree for total functions, the precise relationship between the two is not clear for partial functions. In this paper, we demonstrate an exponential separation between exact polynomial degree and approximate quantum query complexity for a partial Boolean function. For an unbounded alphabet size, we have a constant versus polynomial separation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Direct Reduction from the Polynomial to the Adversary Method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10317</link>
    <author>Aleksandrs Belovs</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The polynomial and the adversary methods are the two main tools for proving lower bounds on query complexity of quantum algorithms. Both methods have found a large number of applications, some problems more suitable for one method, some for the other. It is known though that the adversary method, in its general negative-weighted version, is tight for bounded-error quantum algorithms, whereas the polynomial method is not. By the tightness of the former, for any polynomial lower bound, there ought to exist a corresponding adversary lower bound. However, direct reduction was not known. In this paper, we give a simple and direct reduction from the polynomial method (in the form of a dual polynomial) to the adversary method. This shows that any lower bound in the form of a dual polynomial is actually an adversary lower bound of a specific form.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing quantum satisfiability</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10699</link>
    <author>Ashley Montanaro, Changpeng Shao, Dominic Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 26 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum k-SAT (the problem of determining whether a k-local Hamiltonian is frustration-free) is known to be QMA_1-complete for k >= 3, and hence likely hard for quantum computers to solve. Building on a classical result of Alon and Shapira, we show that quantum k-SAT can be solved in randomised polynomial time given the `property testing' promise that the instance is either satisfiable (by any state) or far from satisfiable by a product state; by `far from satisfiable by a product state' we mean that \epsilon n^k constraints must be removed before a product state solution exists, for some fixed \epsilon > 0. The proof has two steps: we first show that for a satisfiable instance of quantum k-SAT, most subproblems on a constant number of qubits are satisfiable by a product state. We then show that for an instance of quantum k-SAT which is far from satisfiable by a product state, most subproblems are unsatisfiable by a product state. Given the promise, quantum k-SAT may therefore be solved by checking satisfiability by a product state on randomly chosen subsystems of constant size.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entropy Uncertainty Relations and Strong Sub-additivity of Quantum Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08402</link>
    <author>Li Gao, Marius Junge, Nicholas LaRacuente</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We prove an entropic uncertainty relation for two quantum channels, extending the work of Frank and Lieb for quantum measurements. This is obtained via a generalized strong super-additivity (SSA) of quantum entropy. Motivated by Petz's algebraic SSA inequality, we also obtain a generalized SSA for quantum relative entropy. As a special case, it gives an improved data processing inequality.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable Quantum Error Correction for Surface Codes using FPGA</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.08419</link>
    <author>Namitha Liyanage, Yue Wu, Alexander Deters, Lin Zhong</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A fault-tolerant quantum computer must decode and correct errors faster than they appear. The faster errors can be corrected, the more time the computer can do useful work. The Union-Find (UF) decoder is promising with an average time complexity slightly higher than $O(d^3)$. We report a distributed version of the UF decoder that exploits parallel computing resources for further speedup. Using an FPGA-based implementation, we empirically show that this distributed UF decoder has a sublinear average time complexity with regard to $d$, given $O(d^3)$ parallel computing resources. The decoding time per measurement round decreases as $d$ increases, a first time for a quantum error decoder. The implementation employs a scalable architecture called Helios that organizes parallel computing resources into a hybrid tree-grid structure. Using Xilinx's cycle-accurate simulator, we present cycle-accurate decoding time for $d$ up to 15, with the phenomenological noise model with $p=0.1\%$. We are able to implement $d$ up to 7 with a Xilinx ZC106 FPGA, for which an average decoding time is 120 ns per measurement round. Since the decoding time per measurement round of Helios decreases with $d$, Helios can decode a surface code of arbitrarily large $d$ without a growing backlog.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sketching phase diagrams using low-depth variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09369</link>
    <author>Jan Lukas Bosse, Raul Santos, Ashley Montanaro</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Mapping out phase diagrams of quantum systems using classical simulations can be challenging or intractable due to the computational resources required to simulate even small quantum systems far away from the thermodynamic limit. We investigate using quantum computers and the Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) for this task. In contrast to the task of preparing the exact ground state using VQE, sketching phase diagrams might require less quantum resources and accuracy, because low fidelity approximations to the ground state may be enough to correctly identify different phases. We used classical numerical simulations of low-depth VQE circuits to compute order parameters for four well-studied spin and fermion models which represent a mix of 1D and 2D, and exactly-solvable and classically hard systems. We find that it is possible to predict the location of phase transitions up to reasonable accuracy using states produced by VQE even when their overlap with the true ground state is small. Further, we introduce a model-agnostic predictor of phase transitions based on the speed with which the VQE energy improves with respect to the circuit depth, and find that in some cases this is also able to predict phase transitions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the (Im)plausibility of Public-Key Quantum Money from Collision-Resistant Hash Functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.09236</link>
    <author>Prabhanjan Ananth, Zihan Hu, Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Public-key quantum money is a cryptographic proposal for using highly entangled quantum states as currency that is publicly verifiable yet resistant to counterfeiting due to the laws of physics. Despite significant interest, constructing provably-secure public-key quantum money schemes based on standard cryptographic assumptions has remained an elusive goal. Even proposing plausibly-secure candidate schemes has been a challenge. These difficulties call for a deeper and systematic study of the structure of public-key quantum money schemes and the assumptions they can be based on. Motivated by this, we present the first black-box separation of quantum money and cryptographic primitives. Specifically, we show that collision-resistant hash functions cannot be used as a black-box to construct public-key quantum money schemes where the banknote verification makes classical queries to the hash function. Our result involves a novel combination of state synthesis techniques from quantum complexity theory and simulation techniques, including Zhandry's compressed oracle technique.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The superadditivity effects of quantum capacity decrease with the dimension for qudit depolarizing channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.10132</link>
    <author>Josu Etxezarreta Martinez, Antonio deMarti iOlius, Pedro M. Crespo</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 25 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum channel capacity is a fundamental quantity in order to understand how good can quantum information be transmitted or corrected when subjected to noise. However, it is generally not known how to compute such quantities, since the quantum channel coherent information is not additive for all channels, implying that it must be maximized over an unbounded number of channel uses. This leads to the phenomenon known as superadditivity, which refers to the fact that the regularized coherent information of $n$ channel uses exceeds one-shot coherent information. In this letter, we study how the gain in quantum capacity of qudit depolarizing channels relates to the dimension of the systems considered. We make use of an argument based on the no-cloning bound in order to proof that the possible superaditive effects decrease as a function of the dimension for such family of channels. In addition, we prove that the capacity of the qudit depolarizing channel coincides with the coherent information when $d\rightarrow\infty$. We conclude that when high dimensional qudits experiencing depolarizing noise are considered, the coherent information of the channel is not only an achievable rate but essentially the maximum possible rate for any quantum block code.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>