<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A polynomial-time classical algorithm for noisy random circuit sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03999</link>
    <author>Dorit Aharonov, Xun Gao, Zeph Landau, Yunchao Liu, Umesh Vazirani</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a polynomial time classical algorithm for sampling from the output distribution of a noisy random quantum circuit in the regime of anti-concentration to within inverse polynomial total variation distance. This gives strong evidence that, in the presence of a constant rate of noise per gate, random circuit sampling (RCS) cannot be the basis of a scalable experimental violation of the extended Church-Turing thesis. Our algorithm is not practical in its current form, and does not address finite-size RCS based quantum supremacy experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailoring three-dimensional topological codes for biased noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02116</link>
    <author>Eric Huang, Arthur Pesah, Christopher T. Chubb, Michael Vasmer, Arpit Dua</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tailored topological stabilizer codes in two dimensions have been shown to exhibit high storage threshold error rates and improved subthreshold performance under biased Pauli noise. Three-dimensional (3D) topological codes can allow for several advantages including a transversal implementation of non-Clifford logical gates, single-shot decoding strategies, parallelized decoding in the case of fracton codes as well as construction of fractal lattice codes. Motivated by this, we tailor 3D topological codes for enhanced storage performance under biased Pauli noise. We present Clifford deformations of various 3D topological codes, such that they exhibit a threshold error rate of $50\%$ under infinitely biased Pauli noise. Our examples include the 3D surface code on the cubic lattice, the 3D surface code on a checkerboard lattice that lends itself to a subsystem code with a single-shot decoder, the 3D color code, as well as fracton models such as the X-cube model, the Sierpinski model and the Haah code. We use the belief propagation with ordered statistics decoder (BP-OSD) to study threshold error rates at finite bias. We also present a rotated layout for the 3D surface code, which uses roughly half the number of physical qubits for the same code distance under appropriate boundary conditions. Imposing coprime periodic dimensions on this rotated layout leads to logical operators of weight $O(n)$ at infinite bias and a corresponding $\exp[-O(n)]$ subthreshold scaling of the logical failure rate, where $n$ is the number of physical qubits in the code. Even though this scaling is unstable due to the existence of logical representations with $O(1)$ low-rate Pauli errors, the number of such representations scales only polynomially for the Clifford-deformed code, leading to an enhanced effective distance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Homomorphic Logical Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03625</link>
    <author>Shilin Huang, Tomas Jochym-O'Connor, Theodore J. Yoder</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shor and Steane ancilla are two well-known methods for fault-tolerant logical measurements, which are successful on small codes and their concatenations. On large quantum low-density-parity-check (LDPC) codes, however, Shor and Steane measurements have impractical time and space overhead respectively. In this work, we widen the choice of ancilla codes by unifying Shor and Steane measurements into a single framework, called homomorphic measurements. For any Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) code with the appropriate ancilla code, one can avoid repetitive measurements or complicated ancilla state preparation procedures such as distillation, which overcomes the difficulties of both Shor and Steane methods. As an example, we utilize the theory of covering spaces to construct homomorphic measurement protocols for arbitrary $X$- or $Z$-type logical Pauli operators on surface codes in general, including the toric code and hyperbolic surface codes. Conventional surface code decoders, such as minimum-weight perfect matching, can be directly applied to our constructions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Invertible subalgebras</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.02086</link>
    <author>Jeongwan Haah</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce invertible subalgebras of local operator algebras on lattices. An invertible subalgebra is defined to be one such that every local operator can be locally expressed by elements of the inveritible subalgebra and those of the commutant. On a two-dimensional lattice, an invertible subalgebra hosts a chiral anyon theory by a commuting Hamiltonian, which is believed not to be possible on a full local operator algebra. We prove that the stable equivalence classes of $D$-dimensional invertible subalgebras form an abelian group under tensor product, isomorphic to the group of all $D+1$ dimensional QCA modulo blending equivalence and shifts. In an appendix, we consider a metric on the group of all QCA on infinite lattices and prove that the metric completion contains the time evolution by local Hamiltonians, which is only approximately locality-preserving. Our metric topology is strictly finer than the strong topology.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning quantum processes without input control</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.05005</link>
    <author>Marco Fanizza, Yihui Quek, Matteo Rosati</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a general statistical learning theory for processes that take as input a classical random variable and output a quantum state. This is a practically motivated setting where the learner wants to find an approximate representation of an unknown quantum process, without having control on the classical inputs that govern the process itself, e.g., in learning astronomical processes, studying disordered systems and biological processes not controlled by the observer. We provide an algorithm for learning with high probability in this setting with a finite amount of samples, even if the concept class is infinite. To do this, we review and adapt existing algorithms for shadow tomography and hypothesis selection, and combine their guarantees with the uniform convergence on the data of the loss functions of interest. As a by-product we obtain sufficient conditions for performing shadow tomography of classical-quantum states with a number of copies which depend only on the dimension of the quantum register. We give concrete examples of processes that can be learned in this manner, based on quantum circuits or physically motivated scenarios like systems subject to Hamiltonians with random perturbations or data-dependent phase-shifts.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Pauli topological subsystem codes from Abelian anyon theories</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03798</link>
    <author>Tyler D. Ellison, Yu-An Chen, Arpit Dua, Wilbur Shirley, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Dominic J. Williamson</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We construct Pauli topological subsystem codes characterized by arbitrary two-dimensional Abelian anyon theories--this includes anyon theories with degenerate braiding relations and those without a gapped boundary to the vacuum. Our work both extends the classification of two-dimensional Pauli topological subsystem codes to systems of composite-dimensional qudits and establishes that the classification is at least as rich as that of Abelian anyon theories. We exemplify the construction with topological subsystem codes defined on four-dimensional qudits based on the $\mathbb{Z}_4^{(1)}$ anyon theory with degenerate braiding relations and the chiral semion theory--both of which cannot be captured by topological stabilizer codes. The construction proceeds by "gauging out" certain anyon types of a topological stabilizer code. This amounts to defining a gauge group generated by the stabilizer group of the topological stabilizer code and a set of anyonic string operators for the anyon types that are gauged out. The resulting topological subsystem code is characterized by an anyon theory containing a proper subset of the anyons of the topological stabilizer code. We thereby show that every Abelian anyon theory is a subtheory of a stack of toric codes and a certain family of twisted quantum doubles that generalize the double semion anyon theory. We further prove a number of general statements about the logical operators of translation invariant topological subsystem codes and define their associated anyon theories in terms of higher-form symmetries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Certificate games</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03396</link>
    <author>Sourav Chakraborty, Anna Gál, Sophie Laplante, Rajat Mittal, Anupa Sunny</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce and study Certificate Game complexity, a measure of complexity based on the probability of winning a game where two players are given inputs with different function values and are asked to output $i$ such that $x_i\neq y_i$ (zero-communication setting). We give upper and lower bounds for private coin, public coin, shared entanglement and non-signaling strategies, and give some separations. We show that complexity in the public coin model is upper bounded by Randomized query and Certificate complexity. On the other hand, it is lower bounded by fractional and randomized certificate complexity, making it a good candidate to prove strong lower bounds on randomized query complexity. Complexity in the private coin model is bounded from below by zero-error randomized query complexity. The quantum measure highlights an interesting and surprising difference between classical and quantum query models. Whereas the public coin certificate game complexity is bounded from above by randomized query complexity, the quantum certificate game complexity can be quadratically larger than quantum query complexity. We use non-signaling, a notion from quantum information, to give a lower bound of $n$ on the quantum certificate game complexity of the $OR$ function, whose quantum query complexity is $\Theta(\sqrt{n})$, then go on to show that this ``non-signaling bottleneck'' applies to all functions with high sensitivity, block sensitivity or fractional block sensitivity. We consider the single-bit version of certificate games (inputs of the two players have Hamming distance $1$). We prove that the single-bit version of certificate game complexity with shared randomness is equal to sensitivity up to constant factors, giving a new characterization of sensitivity. The single-bit version with private randomness is equal to $\lambda^2$, where $\lambda$ is the spectral sensitivity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Overcoming leakage in scalable quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.04728</link>
    <author>Kevin C. Miao, Matt McEwen, Juan Atalaya, Dvir Kafri, Leonid P. Pryadko, Andreas Bengtsson, Alex Opremcak, Kevin J. Satzinger, Zijun Chen, Paul V. Klimov, Chris Quintana, Rajeev Acharya, Kyle Anderson, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Joseph C. Bardin, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, et al (97)</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Leakage of quantum information out of computational states into higher energy states represents a major challenge in the pursuit of quantum error correction (QEC). In a QEC circuit, leakage builds over time and spreads through multi-qubit interactions. This leads to correlated errors that degrade the exponential suppression of logical error with scale, challenging the feasibility of QEC as a path towards fault-tolerant quantum computation. Here, we demonstrate the execution of a distance-3 surface code and distance-21 bit-flip code on a Sycamore quantum processor where leakage is removed from all qubits in each cycle. This shortens the lifetime of leakage and curtails its ability to spread and induce correlated errors. We report a ten-fold reduction in steady-state leakage population on the data qubits encoding the logical state and an average leakage population of less than $1 \times 10^{-3}$ throughout the entire device. The leakage removal process itself efficiently returns leakage population back to the computational basis, and adding it to a code circuit prevents leakage from inducing correlated error across cycles, restoring a fundamental assumption of QEC. With this demonstration that leakage can be contained, we resolve a key challenge for practical QEC at scale.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Reducing the qubit requirement of Jordan-Wigner encodings of $N$-mode, $K$-fermion systems from $N$ to $\lceil \log_2 {N \choose K} \rceil$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.04501</link>
    <author>Brent Harrison, Dylan Nelson, Daniel Adamiak, James Whitfield</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>To simulate a fermionic system on a quantum computer, it is necessary to encode the state of the fermions onto qubits. Fermion-to-qubit mappings such as the Jordan-Wigner and Bravyi-Kitaev transformations do this using $N$ qubits to represent systems of $N$ fermionic modes. In this work, we demonstrate that for particle number conserving systems of $K$ fermions and $N$ modes, the qubit requirement can be reduced to the information theoretic minimum of $\lceil \log_2 {N \choose K} \rceil$. This will improve the feasibility of simulation of molecules and many-body systems on near-term quantum computers with limited qubit number.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An interpretation of Union-Find Decoder on Weighted Graphs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03288</link>
    <author>Yue Wu, Namitha Liyanage, Lin Zhong</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Union-Find (UF) and Minimum-Weight Perfect Matching (MWPM) are popular decoder designs for surface codes. The former has significantly lower time complexity than the latter but is considered somewhat inferior, in terms of decoding accuracy. In this work we present an interpretation of UF decoders that explains why UF and MWPM decoders perform closely in some cases: the UF decoder is an approximate implementation of the blossom algorithm used for MWPM. This interpretation allows a generalization of UF decoders for weighted decoding graphs and explains why UF decoders achieve high accuracy for certain surface codes.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>