<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Lecture Notes on Quantum Algorithms for Scientific Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08309</link>
    <author>Lin Lin</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This is a set of lecture notes used in a graduate topic class in applied mathematics called ``Quantum Algorithms for Scientific Computation'' at the Department of Mathematics, UC Berkeley during the fall semester of 2021. These lecture notes focus only on quantum algorithms closely related to scientific computation, and in particular, matrix computation. The main purpose of the lecture notes is to introduce quantum phase estimation (QPE) and ``post-QPE'' methods such as block encoding, quantum signal processing, and quantum singular value transformation, and to demonstrate their applications in solving eigenvalue problems, linear systems of equations, and differential equations. The intended audience is the broad computational science and engineering (CSE) community interested in using fault-tolerant quantum computers to solve challenging scientific computing problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Clifford-deformed Surface Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07802</link>
    <author>Arpit Dua, Aleksander Kubica, Liang Jiang, Steven T. Flammia, Michael J. Gullans</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Various realizations of Kitaev's surface code perform surprisingly well for biased Pauli noise. Attracted by these potential gains, we study the performance of Clifford-deformed surface codes (CDSCs) obtained from the surface code by the application of single-qubit Clifford operators. We first analyze CDSCs on the $3\times 3$ square lattice and find that depending on the noise bias, their logical error rates can differ by orders of magnitude. To explain the observed behavior, we introduce the effective distance $d'$, which reduces to the standard distance for unbiased noise. To study CDSC performance in the thermodynamic limit, we focus on random CDSCs. Using the statistical mechanical mapping for quantum codes, we uncover a phase diagram that describes random CDSCs with $50\%$ threshold at infinite bias. In the high-threshold region, we further demonstrate that typical code realizations at finite bias outperform the thresholds and subthreshold logical error rates of the best known translationally invariant codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Free-Fermion Subsystem Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07254</link>
    <author>Adrian Chapman, Steven T. Flammia, Alicia J. Kollár</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider quantum error-correcting subsystem codes whose gauge generators realize a translation-invariant, free-fermion-solvable spin model. In this setting, errors are suppressed by a Hamiltonian whose terms are the gauge generators of the code and whose exact spectrum and eigenstates can be found via a generalized Jordan-Wigner transformation. Such solutions are characterized by the frustration graph of the Hamiltonian: the graph whose vertices are Hamiltonian terms, which are neighboring if the terms anticommute. We provide methods for embedding a given frustration graph in the anticommutation relations of a spin model and present the first known example of an exactly solvable spin model with a two-dimensional free-fermion description and exact topological qubits. This model can be viewed as a free-fermionized version of the two-dimensional Bacon-Shor code. Using graph-theoretic tools to study the unit cell, we give an efficient algorithm for deciding if a given translation-invariant spin model is solvable, and explicitly construct the solution. Further, we examine the energetics of these exactly solvable models from the graph-theoretic perspective and show that the relevant gaps of the spin model correspond to known graph-theoretic quantities: the skew energy and the median eigenvalue of an oriented graph. Finally, we numerically search for models which have large spectral gaps above the ground state spin configuration and thus exhibit particularly robust thermal suppression of errors. These results suggest that optimal models will have low dimensionality and odd coordination numbers, and that the primary limit to energetic error suppression is the skew energy difference between different symmetry sectors rather than single-particle excitations of the free fermions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Low-overhead quantum computing with the color code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07806</link>
    <author>Felix Thomsen, Markus S. Kesselring, Stephen D. Bartlett, Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Fault-tolerant quantum computation demands significant resources: large numbers of physical qubits must be checked for errors repeatedly to protect quantum data as logic gates are implemented in the presence of noise. We demonstrate that an approach based on the color code can lead to considerable reductions in the resource overheads compared with conventional methods, while remaining compatible with a two-dimensional layout. We propose a lattice surgery scheme that exploits the color code's rich structure to perform arbitrary pairs of commuting logical Pauli measurements in parallel while keeping the space cost low. Compared to lattice surgery schemes based on the surface code with the same code distance, our approach yields about a $3\times$ improvement in the space-time overhead. Even when taking into account the color code's lower error threshold using current decoders, the overhead is reduced by $10\%$ at a physical error rate of $10^{-3}$ and by $50\%$ at $10^{-4}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Probabilistic error cancellation with sparse Pauli-Lindblad models on noisy quantum processors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.09866</link>
    <author>Ewout van den Berg, Zlatko K. Minev, Abhinav Kandala, Kristan Temme</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Error-mitigation techniques can enable access to accurate estimates of physical observables that are otherwise biased by noise in pre-fault-tolerant quantum computers. One particularly general error-mitigation technique is probabilistic error cancellation (PEC), which effectively inverts a well-characterized noise channel to produce noise-free estimates of observables. Experimental realizations of this technique, however, have been impeded by the challenge of learning correlated noise in large quantum circuits. In this work, we present a practical protocol for learning a sparse noise model that scales to large quantum devices and is efficient to learn and invert. These advances enable us to demonstrate PEC on a superconducting quantum processor with crosstalk errors, thereby revealing a path to error-mitigated quantum computation with noise-free observables at larger circuit volumes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Avoiding barren plateaus using classical shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08194</link>
    <author>Stefan H. Sack, Raimel A. Medina, Alexios A. Michailidis, Richard Kueng, Maksym Serbyn</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms are promising algorithms for achieving quantum advantage on near-term devices. The quantum hardware is used to implement a variational wave function and measure observables, whereas the classical computer is used to store and update the variational parameters. The optimization landscape of expressive variational ansätze is however dominated by large regions in parameter space, known as barren plateaus, with vanishing gradients which prevents efficient optimization. In this work we propose a general algorithm to avoid barren plateaus in the initialization and throughout the optimization. To this end we define a notion of weak barren plateaus (WBP) based on the entropies of local reduced density matrices. The presence of WBPs can be efficiently quantified using recently introduced shadow tomography of the quantum state with a classical computer. We demonstrate that avoidance of WBPs suffices to ensure sizable gradients in the initialization. In addition, we demonstrate that decreasing the gradient step size, guided by the entropies allows to avoid WBPs during the optimization process. This paves the way for efficient barren plateau free optimization on near-term devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On Lieb-Robinson Bounds for the Double Bracket Flow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07141</link>
    <author>Matthew B. Hastings</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the possibility of developing a Lieb-Robinson bound for the double bracket flow. This is a differential equation $$\partial_B H(B)=[[V,H(B)],H(B)]$$ which may be used to diagonalize Hamiltonians. Here, $V$ is fixed and $H(0)=H$. We argue (but do not prove) that $H(B)$ need not converge to a limit for nonzero real $B$ in the infinite volume limit, even assuming several conditions on $H(0)$. However, we prove Lieb-Robinson bounds for all $B$ for the double-bracket flow for free fermion systems, but the range increases \emphexponentially with the control parameter $B$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable High-Performance Fluxonium Quantum Processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.09374</link>
    <author>Long B. Nguyen, Gerwin Koolstra, Yosep Kim, Alexis Morvan, Trevor Chistolini, Shraddha Singh, Konstantin N. Nesterov, Christian Jünger, Larry Chen, Zahra Pedramrazi, Bradley K. Mitchell, John Mark Kreikebaum, Shruti Puri, David I. Santiago, Irfan Siddiqi Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The technological development of hardware heading toward universal fault-tolerant quantum computation requires a large-scale processing unit with high performance. While fluxonium qubits are promising with high coherence and large anharmonicity, their scalability has not been systematically explored. In this work, we propose a superconducting quantum information processor based on compact high-coherence fluxoniums with suppressed crosstalk, reduced design complexity, improved operational efficiency, high-fidelity gates, and resistance to parameter fluctuations. In this architecture, the qubits are readout dispersively using individual resonators connected to a common bus and manipulated via combined on-chip RF and DC control lines, both of which can be designed to have low crosstalk. A multi-path coupling approach enables exchange interactions between the high-coherence computational states and at the same time suppresses the spurious static ZZ rate, leading to fast and high-fidelity entangling gates. We numerically investigate the cross resonance controlled-NOT and the differential AC-Stark controlled-Z operations, revealing low gate error for qubit-qubit detuning bandwidth of up to 1 GHz. Our study on frequency crowding indicates high fabrication yield for quantum processors consisting of over thousands of qubits. In addition, we estimate low resource overhead to suppress logical error rate using the XZZX surface code. These results promise a scalable quantum architecture with high performance for the pursuit of universal quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multicore Quantum Computing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08861</link>
    <author>Hamza Jnane, Brennan Undseth, Zhenyu Cai, Simon C Benjamin, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Any architecture for practical quantum computing must be scalable. An attractive approach is to create multiple cores, computing regions of fixed size that are well-spaced but interlinked with communication channels. This exploded architecture can relax the demands associated with a single monolithic device: the complexity of control, cooling and power infrastructure as well as the difficulties of cross-talk suppression and near-perfect component yield. Here we explore interlinked multicore architectures through analytic and numerical modelling. While elements of our analysis are relevant to diverse platforms, our focus is on semiconductor electron spin systems in which numerous cores may exist on a single chip. We model shuttling and microwave-based interlinks and estimate the achievable fidelities, finding values that are encouraging but markedly inferior to intra-core operations. We therefore introduce optimsed entanglement purification to enable high-fidelity communication, finding that $99.5\%$ is a very realistic goal. We then assess the prospects for quantum advantage using such devices in the NISQ-era and beyond: we simulate recently proposed exponentially-powerful error mitigation schemes in the multicore environment and conclude that these techniques impressively suppress imperfections in both the inter- and intra-core operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Evaluating Generalization in Classical and Quantum Generative Models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08770</link>
    <author>Kaitlin Gili, Marta Mauri, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Defining and accurately measuring generalization in generative models remains an ongoing challenge and a topic of active research within the machine learning community. This is in contrast to discriminative models, where there is a clear definition of generalization, i.e., the model's classification accuracy when faced with unseen data. In this work, we construct a simple and unambiguous approach to evaluate the generalization capabilities of generative models. Using the sample-based generalization metrics proposed here, any generative model, from state-of-the-art classical generative models such as GANs to quantum models such as Quantum Circuit Born Machines, can be evaluated on the same ground on a concrete well-defined framework. In contrast to other sample-based metrics for probing generalization, we leverage constrained optimization problems (e.g., cardinality constrained problems) and use these discrete datasets to define specific metrics capable of unambiguously measuring the quality of the samples and the model's generalization capabilities for generating data beyond the training set but still within the valid solution space. Additionally, our metrics can diagnose trainability issues such as mode collapse and overfitting, as we illustrate when comparing GANs to quantum-inspired models built out of tensor networks. Our simulation results show that our quantum-inspired models have up to a $68 \times$ enhancement in generating unseen unique and valid samples compared to GANs, and a ratio of 61:2 for generating samples with better quality than those observed in the training set. We foresee these metrics as valuable tools for rigorously defining practical quantum advantage in the domain of generative modeling.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>