<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The Physics of Quantum Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08064</link>
    <author>John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Rapid ongoing progress in quantum information science makes this an apt time for a Solvay Conference focused on The Physics of Quantum Information. Here I review four intertwined themes encompassed by this topic: Quantum computer science, quantum hardware, quantum matter, and quantum gravity. Though the time scale for broad practical impact of quantum computation is still uncertain, in the near future we can expect noteworthy progress toward scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing, and discoveries enabled by programmable quantum simulators. In the longer term, controlling highly complex quantum matter will open the door to profound scientific advances and powerful new technologies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal algorithms for learning quantum phase states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07851</link>
    <author>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Sergey Bravyi, Arkopal Dutt, Theodore J. Yoder</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the complexity of learning $n$-qubit quantum phase states. A degree-$d$ phase state is defined as a superposition of all $2^n$ basis vectors $x$ with amplitudes proportional to $(-1)^{f(x)}$, where $f$ is a degree-$d$ Boolean polynomial over $n$ variables. We show that the sample complexity of learning an unknown degree-$d$ phase state is $\Theta(n^d)$ if we allow separable measurements and $\Theta(n^{d-1})$ if we allow entangled measurements. Our learning algorithm based on separable measurements has runtime $\textsf{poly}(n)$ (for constant $d$) and is well-suited for near-term demonstrations as it requires only single-qubit measurements in the Pauli $X$ and $Z$ bases. We show similar bounds on the sample complexity for learning generalized phase states with complex-valued amplitudes. We further consider learning phase states when $f$ has sparsity-$s$, degree-$d$ in its $\mathbb{F}_2$ representation (with sample complexity $O(2^d sn)$), $f$ has Fourier-degree-$t$ (with sample complexity $O(2^{2t})$), and learning quadratic phase states with $\varepsilon$-global depolarizing noise (with sample complexity $O(n^{1+\varepsilon})$). These learning algorithms give us a procedure to learn the diagonal unitaries of the Clifford hierarchy and IQP circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Mean estimation when you have the source code; or, quantum Monte Carlo methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.07544</link>
    <author>Robin Kothari, Ryan O'Donnell</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Suppose $\boldsymbol{y}$ is a real random variable, and one is given access to ``the code'' that generates it (for example, a randomized or quantum circuit whose output is $\boldsymbol{y}$). We give a quantum procedure that runs the code $O(n)$ times and returns an estimate $\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}}$ for $\mu = \mathrm{E}[\boldsymbol{y}]$ that with high probability satisfies $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/n$, where $\sigma = \mathrm{stddev}[\boldsymbol{y}]$. This dependence on $n$ is optimal for quantum algorithms. One may compare with classical algorithms, which can only achieve the quadratically worse $|\widehat{\boldsymbol{\mu}} - \mu| \leq \sigma/\sqrt{n}$. Our method improves upon previous works, which either made additional assumptions about $\boldsymbol{y}$, and/or assumed the algorithm knew an a priori bound on $\sigma$, and/or used additional logarithmic factors beyond $O(n)$. The central subroutine for our result is essentially Grover's algorithm but with complex phases.ally Grover's algorithm but with complex phases.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadows of fermions with particle number symmetry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08964</link>
    <author>Guang Hao Low</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider classical shadows of fermion wavefunctions with $\eta$ particles occupying $n$ modes. We prove that of all $k$-reduced density matrices may be simultaneously estimated to an average variance of $\epsilon^{2}$ using at most $\binom{\eta}{k}\big(1-\frac{\eta-k}{n}\big)^{k}\frac{1+n}{1+n-k}/\epsilon^{2}$ measurements in random single-particle bases that conserve particle number, and provide an estimator that is computationally efficient. This is a super-exponential improvement over the $\binom{n}{k}\sqrt{\pi k}/\epsilon^{2}$ scaling of prior approaches as $n$ can be arbitrarily larger than $\eta$ in natural problems. Our method, in the worst-case of half-filling, still provides a factor of $4^{k}$ advantage in sample complexity, and also estimates all $\eta$-reduced density matrices, applicable to estimating overlaps with all single Slater determinants, with at most $\frac{4}{3}/\epsilon^{2}$ samples, which is additionally independent of $\eta$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal sample lower bounds for quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09178</link>
    <author>Ryuji Takagi, Hiroyasu Tajima, Mile Gu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Although numerous quantum error-mitigation protocols have been proposed as means to suppress noise effects on intermediate-scale quantum devices, their general potential and limitations have still been elusive. In particular, to understand the ultimate feasibility of quantum error mitigation, it is crucial to characterize the fundamental sampling cost -- how many times an arbitrary mitigation protocol must run a noisy quantum device. Here, we establish universal lower bounds on the sampling cost for quantum error mitigation to achieve the desired accuracy with high probability. Our bounds apply to general mitigation protocols, including the ones involving nonlinear postprocessing. We further show that the number of samples required for a wide class of protocols to mitigate errors in layered circuits must grow exponentially with the circuit depth for various noise models, revealing the fundamental obstacles in showing useful applications of noisy near-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universal cost bound of quantum error mitigation based on quantum estimation theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09385</link>
    <author>Kento Tsubouchi, Takahiro Sagawa, Nobuyuki Yoshioka</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation is an art to combat noise in quantum computers that are not fully fault tolerant. While a wide variety of techniques has been proposed with surging number of experimental applications, little is known concerning the unified understanding on their fundamental aspects. In this paper, we perform a theoretical analysis on the cost of quantum error mitigation using the quantum estimation theory. The applicability of quantum estimation theory is extended so that we can analyze the quantum Fisher information of layered noisy quantum circuits equipped with a wide range of quantum error mitigation methods. By showing that the quantum Fisher information decays exponentially with the circuit depth, we derive for a general class of Markovian noise that unbiased estimation of an observable encounters an exponential growth in the lower bound on the measurement cost, or more precisely the required number of copies of noisy quantum state. As two practical and illustrative examples, we discuss the case when the noise channel is solely the global or local depolarizing noise. We explicitly express the lower bound in terms of their noise rates, and further find that we can asymptotically saturate the bound by a simple mitigation technique for the global depolarizing noise. Our results not only reveal the physical limitations of quantum error mitigation, but may also provide a new criteria for performance evaluation of quantum error mitigation techniques.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A hybrid framework for estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08416</link>
    <author>You Zhou, Zhenhuan Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states, such as the moment $\tr(\rho^m)$, is of fundamental and practical interest in quantum science and technology. Here we show a quantum-classical hybrid framework to measure them, where the quantum part is constituted by the generalized swap test, and the classical part is realized by postprocessing the result from randomized measurements. This hybrid framework utilizes the partial coherent power of the intermediate-scale quantum processor and, at the same time, dramatically reduces the number of quantum measurements and the cost of classical postprocessing. We demonstrate the advantage of our framework in the tasks of state-moment estimation and quantum error mitigation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Early Days of Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09964</link>
    <author>Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I recount some of my memories of the early development of quantum computation, including the discovery of the factoring algorithm, of error correcting codes, and of fault tolerance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Long-distance transmon coupler with CZ gate fidelity above $99.8\%$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09460</link>
    <author>Fabian Marxer, Antti Vepsäläinen, Shan W. Jolin, Jani Tuorila, Alessandro Landra, Caspar Ockeloen-Korppi, Wei Liu, Olli Ahonen, Adrian Auer, Lucien Belzane, Ville Bergholm, Chun Fai Chan, Kok Wai Chan, Tuukka Hiltunen, Juho Hotari, Eric Hyyppä, Joni Ikonen, David Janzso, Miikka Koistinen, Janne Kotilahti, et al (19)</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tunable coupling of superconducting qubits has been widely studied due to its importance for isolated gate operations in scalable quantum processor architectures. Here, we demonstrate a tunable qubit-qubit coupler based on a floating transmon device which allows us to place qubits at least 2 mm apart from each other while maintaining over 50 MHz coupling between the coupler and the qubits. In the introduced tunable-coupler design, both the qubit-qubit and the qubit-coupler couplings are mediated by two waveguides instead of relying on direct capacitive couplings between the components, reducing the impact of the qubit-qubit distance on the couplings. This leaves space for each qubit to have an individual readout resonator and a Purcell filter needed for fast high-fidelity readout. In addition, the large qubit-qubit distance reduces unwanted non-nearest neighbor coupling and allows multiple control lines to cross over the structure with minimal crosstalk. Using the proposed flexible and scalable architecture, we demonstrate a controlled-$Z$ gate with $(99.81 \pm 0.02)\%$ fidelity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The grammar of the Ising model: A new complexity hierarchy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08301</link>
    <author>Tobias Reinhart, Gemma De las Cuevas</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>How complex is an Ising model? Usually, this is measured by the computational complexity of its ground state energy problem. Yet, this complexity measure only distinguishes between planar and non-planar interaction graphs, and thus fails to capture properties such as the average node degree, the number of long range interactions, or the dimensionality of the lattice. Herein, we introduce a new complexity measure for Ising models and thoroughly classify Ising models with respect to it. Specifically, given an Ising model we consider the decision problem corresponding to the function graph of its Hamiltonian, and classify this problem in the Chomsky hierarchy. We prove that the language of this decision problem is (i) regular if and only if the Ising model is finite, (ii) constructive context free if and only if the Ising model is linear and its edge language is regular, (iii) constructive context sensitive if and only if the edge language of the Ising model is context sensitive, and (iv) decidable if and only if the edge language of the Ising model is decidable. We apply this theorem to show that the 1d Ising model, the Ising model on generalised ladder graphs, and the Ising model on layerwise complete graphs are constructive context free, while the 2d Ising model, the all-to-all Ising model, and the Ising model on perfect binary trees are constructive context sensitive. We also provide a grammar for the 1d and 2d Ising model. This work is a first step in the characterisation of physical interactions in terms of grammars.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>