<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Out-of-distribution generalization for learning quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10268</link>
    <author>Matthias C. Caro, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Nicholas Ezzell, Joe Gibbs, Andrew T. Sornborger, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Generalization bounds are a critical tool to assess the training data requirements of Quantum Machine Learning (QML). Recent work has established guarantees for in-distribution generalization of quantum neural networks (QNNs), where training and testing data are assumed to be drawn from the same data distribution. However, there are currently no results on out-of-distribution generalization in QML, where we require a trained model to perform well even on data drawn from a distribution different from the training distribution. In this work, we prove out-of-distribution generalization for the task of learning an unknown unitary using a QNN and for a broad class of training and testing distributions. In particular, we show that one can learn the action of a unitary on entangled states using only product state training data. We numerically illustrate this by showing that the evolution of a Heisenberg spin chain can be learned using only product training states. Since product states can be prepared using only single-qubit gates, this advances the prospects of learning quantum dynamics using near term quantum computers and quantum experiments, and further opens up new methods for both the classical and quantum compilation of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Partitioning qubits in hypergraph product codes to implement logical gates</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10812</link>
    <author>Armanda O. Quintavalle, Paul Webster, Michael Vasmer</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The promise of high-rate low-density parity check (LDPC) codes to substantially reduce the overhead of fault-tolerant quantum computation depends on constructing efficient, fault-tolerant implementations of logical gates on such codes. Transversal gates are the simplest type of fault-tolerant gate, but the potential of transversal gates on LDPC codes has hitherto been largely neglected. We investigate the transversal gates that can be implemented in hypergraph product codes, a class of LDPC codes. Our analysis is aided by the construction of a symplectic canonical basis for the logical operators of hypergraph product codes, a result that may be of independent interest. We show that in these codes transversal gates can implement Hadamard (up to logical SWAP gates) and control-Z on all logical qubits. Moreover, we show that sequences of transversal operations, interleaved with error correction, allow implementation of entangling gates between arbitrary pairs of logical qubits in the same code block. We thereby demonstrate that transversal gates can be used as the basis for universal quantum computing on LDPC codes, when supplemented with state injection.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complexity phase transitions in instantaneous quantum polynomial-time circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08898</link>
    <author>Chae-Yeun Park, Michael J. Kastoryano</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study a subclass of the Instantaneous Quantum Polynomial-time (IQP) circuit with a varying density of two-qubit gates. We identify two phase transitions as a function of the gate density. At the first transition, the coherent Gibbs representation of the output state transitions from quasilocal to extended, and becomes completely non-local after the second transition, resembling that of Haar random states. We introduce several new diagnostics to argue that learning the distribution after the first transition already becomes classically intractable, even though its output distribution is far from random. Our work thus opens a novel pathway for exploring quantum advantage in more practical setups whose outcome distributions are more structured than random states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical algorithms for many-body quantum systems at finite energies</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.09439</link>
    <author>Yilun Yang, J. Ignacio Cirac, Mari Carmen Bañuls</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate quantum inspired algorithms to compute physical observables of quantum many-body systems at finite energies. They are based on the quantum algorithms proposed in [Lu et al. PRX Quantum 2, 020321 (2021)], which use the quantum simulation of the dynamics of such systems, as well as classical filtering and sampling techniques. Here, we replace the quantum simulation by standard classical methods based on matrix product states and operators. As a result, we can address significantly larger systems than those reachable by exact diagonalization or by other algorithms. We demonstrate the performance with spin chains up to 80 sites.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Maximal entanglement velocity implies dual unitarity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10341</link>
    <author>Tianci Zhou, Aram W. Harrow</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A global quantum quench can be modeled by a quantum circuit with local unitary gates. In general, entanglement grows linearly at a rate given by entanglement velocity, which is upper bounded by the growth of the light cone. We show that the unitary interactions achieving the maximal rate must remain unitary if we exchange the space and time directions -- a property known as dual unitarity. Our results are robust: approximate maximal entanglement velocity also implies approximate dual unitarity. We further show that maximal entanglement velocity is always accompanied by a specific dynamical pattern of entanglement, which yields simpler analyses of several known exactly solvable models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dynamical simulation via quantum machine learning with provable generalization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10269</link>
    <author>Joe Gibbs, Zoë Holmes, Matthias C. Caro, Nicholas Ezzell, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Lukasz Cincio, Andrew T. Sornborger, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Much attention has been paid to dynamical simulation and quantum machine learning (QML) independently as applications for quantum advantage, while the possibility of using QML to enhance dynamical simulations has not been thoroughly investigated. Here we develop a framework for using QML methods to simulate quantum dynamics on near-term quantum hardware. We use generalization bounds, which bound the error a machine learning model makes on unseen data, to rigorously analyze the training data requirements of an algorithm within this framework. This provides a guarantee that our algorithm is resource-efficient, both in terms of qubit and data requirements. Our numerics exhibit efficient scaling with problem size, and we simulate 20 times longer than Trotterization on IBMQ-Bogota.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable measures of magic for quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10061</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, M. S. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic characterizes the degree of non-stabilizerness of quantum states. It is a crucial resource for quantum computing and a necessary condition for quantum advantage. However, quantifying magic beyond a few qubits has been a major challenge. Here, we introduce Bell magic to efficiently measure magic for any number of qubits. Our method can be easily implemented in experiments together with a cost-free error mitigation scheme. We experimentally demonstrate the transition of classically simulable stabilizer states into intractable quantum states on the IonQ quantum computer. For applications, Bell magic distinguishes stabilizer and magical states with a low measurement cost. Further, variational quantum algorithms can maximize the magic of quantum states via the shift-rule. Our results pave the way to benchmark the non-classical power of quantum computers, quantum simulators and quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A general framework for the composition of quantum homomorphic encryption \& quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10471</link>
    <author>Yingkai Ouyang, Peter P. Rohde</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two essential primitives for universal, cloud-based quantum computation with security based on the laws of quantum mechanics, are quantum homomorphic encryption with information-theoretic security and quantum error correction. The former enables information-theoretic security of outsourced quantum computation, while the latter allows reliable and scalable quantum computations in the presence of errors. Previously these ingredients have been considered in isolation from one another. By establishing group-theoretic requirements that these two ingredients must satisfy, we provide a general framework for composing them. Namely, a quantum homomorphic encryption scheme enhanced with quantum error correction can directly inherit its properties from its constituent quantum homomorphic encryption and quantum error correction schemes. We apply our framework to both discrete- and continuous-variable models for quantum computation, such as Pauli-key and permutation-key encryptions in the qubit model, and displacement-key encryptions in a continuous-variable model based on Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Training variational quantum circuits with CoVaR: covariance root finding with classical shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08494</link>
    <author>Gregory Boyd, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Exploiting near-term quantum computers and achieving practical value is a considerable and exciting challenge. Most prominent candidates as variational algorithms typically aim to find the ground state of a Hamiltonian by minimising a single classical (energy) surface which is sampled from by a quantum computer. Here we introduce a method we call CoVaR, an alternative means to exploit the power of variational circuits: We find eigenstates by finding joint roots of a polynomially growing number of properties of the quantum state as covariance functions between the Hamiltonian and an operator pool of our choice. The most remarkable feature of our CoVaR approach is that it allows us to fully exploit the extremely powerful classical shadow techniques, i.e., we simultaneously estimate a very large number $>10^4-10^7$ of covariances. We randomly select covariances and estimate analytical derivatives at each iteration applying a stochastic Levenberg-Marquardt step via a large but tractable linear system of equations that we solve with a classical computer. We prove that the cost in quantum resources per iteration is comparable to a standard gradient estimation, however, we observe in numerical simulations a very significant improvement by many orders of magnitude in convergence speed. CoVaR is directly analogous to stochastic gradient-based optimisations of paramount importance to classical machine learning while we also offload significant but tractable work onto the classical processor.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Fisher information-based incompatibility criterion for quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.09963</link>
    <author>Qing-Hua Zhang, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new incompatibility criterion for quantum channels, based on the notion of (quantum) Fisher information. Our construction is based on a similar criterion for quantum measurements put forward by H.~Zhu. We then study the power of the incompatibility criterion in different scenarios. Firstly, we prove the first analytical conditions for the incompatibility of two Schur channels. Then, we study the incompatibility structure of a tuple of depolarizing channels, comparing the newly introduced criterion with the known results from asymmetric quantum cloning.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>