<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Short Proofs of Linear Growth of Quantum Circuit Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05668</link>
    <author>Zhi Li</author>
    <pubDate>May 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The complexity of a quantum gate, defined as the minimal number of elementary gates to build it, is an important concept in quantum information and computation. It is shown recently that the complexity of quantum gates built from random quantum circuits almost surely grows linearly with the number of building blocks. In this article, we provide two short proofs of this fact. We also discuss a discrete version of quantum circuit complexity growth.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An optimal oracle separation of classical and quantum hybrid schemes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.04633</link>
    <author>Atsuya Hasegawa, François Le Gall</author>
    <pubDate>May 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, Chia, Chung and Lai (STOC 2020) and Coudron and Menda (STOC 2020) have shown that there exists an oracle $\mathcal{O}$ such that $\mathsf{BQP}^\mathcal{O} \neq (\mathsf{BPP^{BQNC}})^\mathcal{O} \cup (\mathsf{BQNC^{BPP}})^\mathcal{O}$. In fact, Chia et al. proved a stronger statement: for any depth parameter $d$, there exists an oracle that separates quantum depth $d$ and $2d+1$, when polynomial-time classical computation is allowed. This implies that relative to an oracle, doubling quantum depth gives classical and quantum hybrid schemes more computational power. In this paper, we show that for any depth parameter $d$, there exists an oracle that separates quantum depth $d$ and $d+1$, when polynomial-time classical computation is allowed. This gives an optimal oracle separation of classical and quantum hybrid schemes. To prove our result, we consider $d$-Bijective Shuffling Simon's Problem (which is a variant of $d$-Shuffling Simon's Problem considered by Chia et al.) and an oracle inspired by an "in-place" permutation oracle.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fundamental limitations on optimization in variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05056</link>
    <author>Hao-Kai Zhang, Chengkai Zhu, Geng Liu, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Exploring quantum applications of near-term quantum devices is a rapidly growing field of quantum information science with both theoretical and practical interests. A leading paradigm to establish such near-term quantum applications is variational quantum algorithms (VQAs). These algorithms use a classical optimizer to train a parameterized quantum circuit to accomplish certain tasks, where the circuits are usually randomly initialized. In this work, we prove that for a broad class of such random circuits, the variation range of the cost function via adjusting any local quantum gate within the circuit vanishes exponentially in the number of qubits with a high probability. This result can unify the restrictions on gradient-based and gradient-free optimizations in a natural manner and reveal extra harsh constraints on the training landscapes of VQAs. Hence a fundamental limitation on the trainability of VQAs is unraveled, indicating the essence of the optimization hardness in the Hilbert space with exponential dimension. We further showcase the validity of our results with numerical simulations of representative VQAs. We believe that these results would deepen our understanding of the scalability of VQAs and shed light on the search for near-term quantum applications with advantages.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical verification of quantum depth</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.04656</link>
    <author>Nai-Hui Chia, Shih-Han Hung</author>
    <pubDate>May 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present two protocols for classical verification of quantum depth. Our protocols allow a purely classical verifier to distinguish devices with different quantum circuit depths even in the presence of classical computation. We show that a device with quantum circuit depth at most d will be rejected by the verifier even if the prover applies additional polynomial-time classical computation to cheat. On the other hand, the verifier accepts a device which has quantum circuit depth d' for some d'>d. In our first protocol, we introduce an additional untrusted quantum machine which shares entanglements with the target machine. Applying a robust self-test, our first protocol certifies the depth of the target machine with information theoretic security and nearly optimal separation. The protocol relies on the oracle separation problem for quantum depth by Chia, Chung and Lai [STOC 2020] and a transformation from an oracle separation problem to a two-player non-local game. Our second protocol certifies the quantum depth of a single device based on quantum hardness of learning with errors. The protocol relies on the noisy trapdoor claw-free function family and the idea of pointer chasing to force the prover to keep quantum coherence until all preceding message exchanges are completed. To our knowledge, we give the first constructions for distinguishing hybrid quantum-classical computers with different circuit depths in unrelativized models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum contextuality provides communication complexity advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.03308</link>
    <author>Shashank Gupta, Debashis Saha, Zhen-Peng Xu, Adán Cabello, A. S. Majumdar</author>
    <pubDate>May 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Despite the conceptual importance of contextuality in quantum mechanics, there is a hitherto limited number of applications requiring contextuality but not entanglement. Here, we show that for any quantum state and observables of sufficiently small dimension producing contextuality, there exists a communication task with quantum advantage. Conversely, any quantum advantage in this task admits a proof of contextuality whenever an additional condition holds. We further show that given any set of observables allowing for quantum state-independent contextuality, there exists a class of communication tasks wherein the difference between classical and quantum communication complexities increases as the number of inputs grows. Finally, we show how to convert each of these communication tasks into a semi-device independent protocol for quantum key distribution.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Arkhipov's theorem, graph minors, and linear system nonlocal games</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.04645</link>
    <author>Connor Paddock, Vincent Russo, Turner Silverthorne, William Slofstra</author>
    <pubDate>May 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The perfect quantum strategies of a linear system game correspond to certain representations of its solution group. We study the solution groups of graph incidence games, which are linear system games in which the underlying linear system is the incidence system of a (non-properly) two-coloured graph. While it is undecidable to determine whether a general linear system game has a perfect quantum strategy, for graph incidence games this problem is solved by Arkhipov's theorem, which states that the graph incidence game of a connected graph has a perfect quantum strategy if and only if it either has a perfect classical strategy, or the graph is nonplanar. Arkhipov's criterion can be rephrased as a forbidden minor condition on connected two-coloured graphs. We extend Arkhipov's theorem by showing that, for graph incidence games of connected two-coloured graphs, every quotient closed property of the solution group has a forbidden minor characterization. We rederive Arkhipov's theorem from the group theoretic point of view, and then find the forbidden minors for two new properties: finiteness and abelianness. Our methods are entirely combinatorial, and finding the forbidden minors for other quotient closed properties seems to be an interesting combinatorial problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Repeated Averages on Graphs</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.04535</link>
    <author>Ramis Movassagh, Mario Szegedy, Guanyang Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Sourav Chatterjee, Persi Diaconis, Allan Sly and Lingfu Zhang, prompted by a question of Ramis Movassagh, renewed the study of a process proposed in the early 1980s by Jean Bourgain. A state vector $v \in \mathbb R^n$, labeled with the vertices of a connected graph, $G$, changes in discrete time steps following the simple rule that at each step a random edge $(i,j)$ is picked and $v_i$ and $v_j$ are both replaced by their average $(v_i+v_j)/2$. It is easy to see that the value associated with each vertex converges to $1/n$. The question was how quickly will $v$ be $\epsilon$-close to uniform in the $L^{1}$ norm in the case of the complete graph, $K_{n}$, when $v$ is initialized as a standard basis vector that takes the value 1 on one coordinate, and zeros everywhere else. They have established a sharp cutoff of $\frac{1}{2\log 2}n\log n + O(n\sqrt{\log n})$. Our main result is to prove, that $\frac{(1-\epsilon)}{2\log2}n\log n-O(n)$ is a general lower bound for all connected graphs on $n$ nodes. We also get sharp magnitude of $t_{\epsilon,1}$ for several important families of graphs, including star, expander, dumbbell, and cycle. In order to establish our results we make several observations about the process, such as the worst case initialization is always a standard basis vector. Our results add to the body of work of Aldous, Aldous and Lanoue, Quattropani and Sau, Cao, Olshevsky and Tsitsiklis, and others. The renewed interest is due to an analogy to a question related to the Google's supremacy circuit. For the proof of our main theorem we employ a concept that we call 'augmented entropy function' which may find independent interest in the computer science and probability theory communities.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>isQ: Towards a Practical Software Stack for Quantum Programming</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.03866</link>
    <author>Jingzhe Guo, Huazhe Lou, Riling Li, Wang Fang, Junyi Liu, Peixun Long, Shenggang Ying, Mingsheng Ying</author>
    <pubDate>May 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce isQ, a new software stack for quantum programming in an imperative programming language, also named isQ. The aim of isQ is to make the programmers write quantum programs as conveniently as possible. In particular: 1) The isQ language and its compiler contain many features, including some not well supported by (most) other quantum programming platforms, e.g. classical control flow such as recursion; decomposition of selfdefined unitary gates; and oracle programming and its circuit realization. 2) To make it flexible, an isQ program can be compiled into several kinds of intermediate representation, including OpenQASM 3.0, QIR and QCIS (specially tailored for the superconducting quantum hardware at USTC). 3) Besides interfacing isQ with true superconducting hardware, a QIR simulator is also developed for demonstration and testing of isQ programs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An invitation to topological orders and category theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05565</link>
    <author>Liang Kong, Zhi-Hao Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>May 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Although it has been a well-known fact, for more than two decades, that category theory is needed for the study of topological orders, it is still a non-trivial challenge for students and working physicists to master the abstract language of category theory. In this work, for those who have no background in category theory, we explain in great details how the structure of a (braided) fusion category naturally emerges from lattice models and physical intuitions. Moreover, we show that nearly all mathematical notions and constructions in fusion categories and its representation theory, such as (monoidal) functors, Drinfeld center, module categories, Morita equivalence, condensation completion and fusion 2-categories, naturally emerge from lattice models and physical intuitions. In this process, we also introduce some basic notions and important results of topological orders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational Quantum Optimization of Nonlocality in Noisy Quantum Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02891</link>
    <author>Brian Doolittle, Tom Bromley, Nathan Killoran, Eric Chitambar</author>
    <pubDate>May 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The inherent noise and complexity of quantum communication networks leads to challenges in designing quantum network protocols using classical methods. To address this issue, we develop a variational quantum optimization framework that simulates quantum networks on quantum hardware and optimizes the network using differential programming techniques. We use our hybrid framework to optimize nonlocality in noisy quantum networks. On the noisy IBM quantum computers, we demonstrate our framework's ability to maximize quantum nonlocality. On a classical simulator with a static noise model, we investigate the noise robustness of quantum nonlocality with respect to unital and nonunital channels. In both cases, we find that our optimization methods can reproduce known results, while uncovering interesting phenomena. When unital noise is present we find numerical evidence suggesting that maximally entangled state preparations yield maximal nonlocality. When nonunital noise is present we find that nonmaximally entangled states can yield maximal nonlocality. Thus, we show that variational quantum optimization is a practical design tool for quantum networks in the near-term. In the long-term, our variational quantum optimization techniques show promise of scaling beyond classical approaches and can be deployed on quantum network hardware to optimize quantum communication protocols against their inherent noise.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>