<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A smallest computable entanglement monotone</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00835</link>
    <author>J. Eisert, M. M. Wilde</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Rains relative entropy of a bipartite quantum state is the tightest known upper bound on its distillable entanglement - which has a crisp physical interpretation of entanglement as a resource - and it is efficiently computable by convex programming. It has not been known to be a selective entanglement monotone in its own right. In this work, we strengthen the interpretation of the Rains relative entropy by showing that it is monotone under the action of selective operations that completely preserve the positivity of the partial transpose, reasonably quantifying entanglement. That is, we prove that Rains relative entropy of an ensemble generated by such an operation does not exceed the Rains relative entropy of the initial state in expectation, giving rise to the smallest, most conservative known computable selective entanglement monotone. Additionally, we show that this is true not only for the original Rains relative entropy, but also for Rains relative entropies derived from various Renyi relative entropies. As an application of these findings, we prove, in both the non-asymptotic and asymptotic settings, that the probabilistic approximate distillable entanglement of a state is bounded from above by various Rains relative entropies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Testing matrix product states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01824</link>
    <author>Mehdi Soleimanifar, John Wright</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Devising schemes for testing the amount of entanglement in quantum systems has played a crucial role in quantum computing and information theory. Here, we study the problem of testing whether an unknown state $|\psi\rangle$ is a matrix product state (MPS) in the property testing model. MPS are a class of physically-relevant quantum states which arise in the study of quantum many-body systems. A quantum state $|\psi_{1,...,n}\rangle$ comprised of $n$ qudits is said to be an MPS of bond dimension $r$ if the reduced density matrix $\psi_{1,...,k}$ has rank $r$ for each $k \in \{1,...,n\}$. When $r=1$, this corresponds to the set of product states. For larger values of $r$, this yields a more expressive class of quantum states, which are allowed to possess limited amounts of entanglement. In the property testing model, one is given $m$ identical copies of $|\psi\rangle$, and the goal is to determine whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ or whether $|\psi\rangle$ is far from all such states. For the case of product states, we study the product test, a simple two-copy test previously analyzed by Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010), and a key ingredient in their proof that $\mathsf{QMA(2)}=\mathsf{QMA}(k)$ for $k \geq 2$. We give a new and simpler analysis of the product test which achieves an optimal bound for a wide range of parameters, answering open problems of Harrow and Montanaro (FOCS 2010) and Montanaro and de Wolf (2016). For the case of $r\geq 2$, we give an efficient algorithm for testing whether $|\psi\rangle$ is an MPS of bond dimension $r$ using $m = O(n r^2)$ copies, independent of the dimensions of the qudits, and we show that $\Omega(n^{1/2})$ copies are necessary for this task. This lower bound shows that a dependence on the number of qudits $n$ is necessary, in sharp contrast to the case of product states where a constant number of copies suffices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Practical and Efficient Hamiltonian Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00190</link>
    <author>Wenjun Yu, Jinzhao Sun, Zeyao Han, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>With the fast development of quantum technology, the size of quantum systems we can digitally manipulate and analogly probe increase drastically. In order to have a better control and understanding of the quantum hardware, an important task is to characterize the interaction, i.e., to learn the Hamiltonian, which determines both static or dynamic properties of the system. Conventional Hamiltonian learning methods either require costly process tomography or adopt impractical assumptions, such as prior information of the Hamiltonian structure and the ground or thermal states of the system. In this work, we present a practical and efficient Hamiltonian learning method that circumvents these limitations. The proposed method can efficiently learn any Hamiltonian that is sparse on the Pauli basis using only short time dynamics and local operations without any information of the Hamiltonian or preparing any eigenstates or thermal states. The method has scalable complexity and vanishing failure probability regarding the qubit number. Meanwhile, it is free from state preparation and measurement error and robust against a certain amount of circuit and shot noise. We numerically test the scaling and the estimation accuracy of the method for transverse field Ising Hamiltonian with random interaction strengths and molecular Hamiltonians, both with varying sizes. All these results verify the practicality and efficacy of the method, paving the way for a systematic understanding of large quantum systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limits on Parameter Estimation of Quantum Channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01738</link>
    <author>Vishal Katariya</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The aim of this thesis is to develop a theoretical framework to study parameter estimation of quantum channels. We study the task of estimating unknown parameters encoded in a channel in the sequential setting. A sequential strategy is the most general way to use a channel multiple times. Our goal is to establish lower bounds (called Cramer-Rao bounds) on the estimation error. The bounds we develop are universally applicable; i.e., they apply to all permissible quantum dynamics. We consider the use of catalysts to enhance the power of a channel estimation strategy. This is termed amortization. The power of a channel for a parameter estimation is determined by its Fisher information. Thus, we study how much a catalyst quantum state can enhance the Fisher information of a channel by defining the amortized Fisher information. We establish our bounds by proving that for certain Fisher information quantities, catalyst states do not improve the performance of a sequential estimation protocol compared to a parallel one. The technical term for this is an amortization collapse. We use this to establish bounds when estimating one parameter, or multiple parameters simultaneously. Our bounds apply universally and we also cast them as optimization problems. For the single parameter case, we establish bounds for general quantum channels using both the symmetric logarithmic derivative (SLD) Fisher information and the right logarithmic derivative (RLD) Fisher information. The task of estimating multiple parameters simultaneously is more involved than the single parameter case, because the Cramer-Rao bounds take the form of matrix inequalities. We establish a scalar Cramer-Rao bound for multiparameter channel estimation using the RLD Fisher information. For both single and multiparameter estimation, we provide a no-go condition for the so-called Heisenberg scaling using our RLD-based bound.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Oracle separations of hybrid quantum-classical circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01904</link>
    <author>Atul Singh Arora, Alexandru Gheorghiu, Uttam Singh</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An important theoretical problem in the study of quantum computation, that is also practically relevant in the context of near-term quantum devices, is to understand the computational power of hybrid models, that combine poly-time classical computation with short-depth quantum computation. Here, we consider two such models: CQ_d which captures the scenario of a polynomial-time classical algorithm that queries a d-depth quantum computer many times; and QC_d which is more analogous to measurement-based quantum computation and captures the scenario of a d-depth quantum computer with the ability to change the sequence of gates being applied depending on measurement outcomes processed by a classical computation. Chia, Chung & Lai (STOC 2020) and Coudron & Menda (STOC 2020) showed that these models (with d=log^O(1) (n)) are strictly weaker than BQP (the class of problems solvable by poly-time quantum computation), relative to an oracle, disproving a conjecture of Jozsa in the relativised world. We show that, despite the similarities between CQ_d and QC_d, the two models are incomparable, i.e. CQ_d $\nsubseteq$ QC_d and QC_d $\nsubseteq$ CQ_d relative to an oracle. In other words, there exist problems that one model can solve but not the other and vice versa. We do this by considering new oracle problems that capture the distinctions between the two models and by introducing the notion of an intrinsically stochastic oracle, an oracle whose responses are inherently randomised, which is used for our second result. While we leave showing the second separation relative to a standard oracle as an open problem, we believe the notion of stochastic oracles could be of independent interest for studying complexity classes which have resisted separation in the standard oracle model. Our constructions also yield simpler oracle separations between the hybrid models and BQP, compared to earlier works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Benchmarking Characterization Methods for Noisy Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02243</link>
    <author>Megan L. Dahlhauser, Travis S. Humble</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Effective methods for characterizing the noise in quantum computing devices are essential for programming and debugging circuit performance. Existing approaches vary in the information obtained as well as the amount of quantum and classical resources required, with more information generally requiring more resources. Here we benchmark the characterization methods of gate set tomography, Pauli channel noise reconstruction, and empirical direct characterization for developing models that describe noisy quantum circuit performance on a 27-qubit superconducting transmon device. We evaluate these models by comparing the accuracy of noisy circuit simulations with the corresponding experimental observations. We find that the agreement of noise model to experiment does not correlate with the information gained by characterization and that the underlying circuit strongly influences the best choice of characterization approach. Empirical direct characterization scales best of the methods we tested and produced the most accurate characterizations across our benchmarks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Information Scrambling in Quantum Many-body Scarred Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.01777</link>
    <author>Dong Yuan, Shun-Yao Zhang, Yu Wang, L.-M. Duan, Dong-Ling Deng</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum many-body scarred systems host special non-thermal eigenstates which support periodic revival dynamics and weakly break the ergodicity. In this paper, we study the quantum information scrambling dynamics in quantum many-body scarred systems, with a focus on the "PXP" model. We use the out-of-time-ordered correlator (OTOC) and Holevo information as measures of the information scrambling, and apply an efficient numerical method based on matrix product operators to compute them up to 41 spins. We find that both the OTOC and Holevo information exhibit a linear light cone and periodic oscillations inside the light cone for initial states within the scarred subspace, which is in sharp contrast to thermal or many-body localized systems. To explain the formation of the linear light cone structure, we provide a perturbation-type calculation based on a phenomenological model. In addition, we demonstrate that the OTOC and Holevo information dynamics of the "PXP" model can be measured using the Rydberg-atom quantum simulators with current experimental technologies, and numerically identify the measurable signatures using experimental parameters.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Analytical calculation formulas for capacities of classical and classical-quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.02450</link>
    <author>Masahito Hayashi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive an analytical calculation formula for the channel capacity of a classical channel without any iteration while its existing algorithms require iterations and the number of iteration depends on the required precision level. Hence, our formula is its first analytical formula without any iteration. We apply the obtained formula to examples and see how the obtained formula works in these examples. Then, we extend it to the channel capacity of a classical-quantum (cq-) channel. Many existing studies proposed algorithms for a cq-channel and all of them require iterations. Our extended analytical algorithm have also no iteration and output the exactly optimum values.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Topological quantum computation is hyperbolic</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00857</link>
    <author>Eric Samperton</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that a topological quantum computer based on the evaluation of a Witten-Reshetikhin-Turaev TQFT invariant of knots can always be arranged so that the knot diagrams one compiles are hyperbolic. Furthermore, the diagrams can be arranged to have additional nice properties, such as being alternating with minimal crossing number. Various complexity-theoretic hardness results regarding the calculation of quantum invariants of knots follow as corollaries. In particular, we argue that the hyperbolic geometry of knots is unlikely to be useful for topological quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum error mitigation via matrix product operators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00752</link>
    <author>Yuchen Guo, Shuo Yang</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the era of noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices, the number of controllable hardware qubits is insufficient to implement quantum error correction (QEC). As an alternative, quantum error mitigation (QEM) can suppress the error of measurement results via repeated experiments and postprocessing of data. Typical techniques for error mitigation, e.g., the quasi-probability decomposition method, incur exponentially increasing costs with system size $N_q$ in order to model and mitigate errors for each gate. Here, we introduce a QEM method based on the matrix product operator (MPO) representation of a quantum circuit, which can characterize the noise channel of the entire circuit with polynomial complexity. Our QEM technique is demonstrated on a $\rm{depth}=4$ fully parallel quantum circuit of up to $N_q=10$ qubits. The circuit error is mitigated by several orders of magnitude with only a small bond dimension for the noise channel. Our method dramatically reduces the computational cost and can be generalized to models beyond localized and Markovian noise.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>