<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence between fermion-to-qubit mappings in two spatial dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05153</link>
    <author>Yu-An Chen, Yijia Xu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We argue that all locality-preserving mappings between fermionic observables and Pauli matrices on a two-dimensional lattice can be generated from the exact bosonization in Ref. [1], whose gauge constraints project onto the subspace of the toric code with emergent fermions. Starting from the exact bosonization and applying Clifford finite-depth generalized local unitary (gLU) transformation, we can achieve all possible fermion-to-qubit mappings (up to the re-pairing of Majorana fermions). In particular, we discover a new super-compact encoding using 1.25 qubits per fermion on the square lattice, which is lower than any method in the literature. We prove the existence of fermion-to-qubit mappings with qubit-fermion ratios $r=1+ \frac{1}{2k}$ for positive integers $k$, where the proof utilizes the trivialness of quantum cellular automata (QCA) in two spatial dimensions. When the ratio approaches 1, the fermion-to-qubit mapping reduces to the 1d Jordan-Wigner transformation along a certain path in the two-dimensional lattice. Finally, we explicitly demonstrate that the Bravyi-Kitaev superfast simulation, the Verstraete-Cirac auxiliary method, Kitaev's exactly solved model, the Majorana loop stabilizer codes, and the compact fermion-to-qubit mapping can all be obtained from the exact bosonization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Depth optimization of CZ, CNOT, and Clifford circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05215</link>
    <author>Dmitri Maslov, Ben Zindorf</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We seek to develop better upper bound guarantees on the depth of quantum CZ gate, CNOT gate, and Clifford circuits than those reported previously. We focus on the number of qubits $n\,{\leq}\,$1,345,000 [1], which represents the most practical use case. Our upper bound on the depth of CZ circuits is $\lfloor n/2 + 0.4993{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.0191{\cdot}\log(n) - 10.9139\rfloor$, improving best known depth by a factor of roughly 2. We extend the constructions used to prove this upper bound to obtain depth upper bound of $\lfloor n + 1.9496{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.5075{\cdot}\log(n) - 23.4269 \rfloor$ for CNOT gate circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $4/3$ over state of the art, and depth upper bound of $\lfloor 2n + 2.9487{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 8.4909{\cdot}\log(n) - 44.4798\rfloor$ for Clifford circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $5/3$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum networks self-test all entangled states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05032</link>
    <author>Ivan Šupić, Joseph Bowles, Marc-Olivier Renou, Antonio Acín, Matty J. Hoban</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Certifying quantum properties with minimal assumptions is a fundamental problem in quantum information science. Self-testing is a method to infer the underlying physics of a quantum experiment only from the measured statistics. While all bipartite pure entangled states can be self-tested, little is known about how to self-test quantum states of an arbitrary number of systems. Here, we introduce a framework for network-assisted self-testing and use it to self-test any pure entangled quantum state of an arbitrary number of systems. The scheme requires the preparation of a number of singlets that scales linearly with the number of systems, and the implementation of standard projective and Bell measurements, all feasible with current technology. When all the network constraints are exploited, the obtained self-testing certification is stronger than what is achievable in any Bell-type scenario. Our work does not only solve an open question in the field, but also shows how properly designed networks offer new opportunities for the certification of quantum phenomena.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Consilience between QBism and Phenomenology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04734</link>
    <author>Hans Christian von Baeyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two decades after its creation, the interpretation of quantum mechanics called QBism is entering a new phase. Since it shares a personalist, subjective world-view with phenomenology, the philosophical study of human experience, there is a growing interest in the relationship between the two subjects. I call attention to the little-known philosopher Samuel Todes, whose phenomenology focused on the essential role of the human body in our understanding of the world. After reviewing this radical proposal, and illustrating it with some examples, I recommend it as an interesting mediator between the communities of physicists and phenomenologists. In addition, I argue that it may prove useful for promoting the public understanding of QBism.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Uniform continuity bound for sandwiched Rényi conditional entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05534</link>
    <author>Ashutosh Marwah, Frédéric Dupuis</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove a simple uniform continuity bound for the sandwiched Rényi conditional entropy for $\alpha \in [1/2, 1) \cup (1, \infty]$, which is independent of the dimension of the conditioning system.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Test-measured Rényi divergences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05477</link>
    <author>Milán Mosonyi, Fumio Hiai</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One possibility of defining a quantum Rényi $\alpha$-divergence of two quantum states is to optimize the classical Rényi $\alpha$-divergence of their post-measurement probability distributions over all possible measurements (measured Rényi divergence), and maybe regularize these quantities over multiple copies of the two states (regularized measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence). A key observation behind the theorem for the strong converse exponent of asymptotic binary quantum state discrimination is that the regularized measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence coincides with the sandwiched Rényi $\alpha$-divergence when $\alpha>1$. Moreover, it also follows from the same theorem that to achieve this, it is sufficient to consider $2$-outcome measurements (tests) for any number of copies (this is somewhat surprising, as achieving the measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence for $n$ copies might require a number of measurement outcomes that diverges in $n$, in general). In view of this, it seems natural to expect the same when $\alpha<1$; however, we show that this is not the case. In fact, we show that even for commuting states (classical case) the regularized quantity attainable using $2$-outcome measurements is in general strictly smaller than the Rényi $\alpha$-divergence (which is unique in the classical case). In the general quantum case this shows that the above ``regularized test-measured'' Rényi $\alpha$-divergence is not even a quantum extension of the classical Rényi divergence when $\alpha<1$, in sharp contrast to the $\alpha>1$ case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Towards real-world quantum networks: a review</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04802</link>
    <author>Shi-Hai Wei, Bo Jing, Xue-Ying Zhang, Jin-Yu Liao, Chen-Zhi Yuan, Bo-Yu Fan, Chen Lyu, Dian-Li Zhou, You Wang, Guang-Wei Deng, Hai-Zhi Song, Daniel Oblak, Guang-Can Guo, Qiang Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum networks play an extremely important role in quantum information science, with application to quantum communication, computation, metrology and fundamental tests. One of the key challenges for implementing a quantum network is to distribute entangled flying qubits to spatially separated nodes, at which quantum interfaces or transducers map the entanglement onto stationary qubits. The stationary qubits at the separated nodes constitute quantum memories realized in matter while the flying qubits constitute quantum channels realized in photons. Dedicated efforts around the world for more than twenty years have resulted in both major theoretical and experimental progress towards entangling quantum nodes and ultimately building a global quantum network. Here, we review the development of quantum networks and the experimental progress over the past two decades leading to the current state of the art for generating entanglement of quantum nodes based on various physical systems such as single atoms, cold atomic ensembles, trapped ions, diamonds with Nitrogen-Vacancy centers, solid-state host doped with rare-earth ions, etc. Along the way we discuss the merits and compare the potential of each of these systems towards realizing a quantum network.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Universality and sharp matrix concentration inequalities</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05142</link>
    <author>Tatiana Brailovskaya, Ramon van Handel</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that, under mild assumptions, the spectrum of a sum of independent random matrices is close to that of the Gaussian random matrix whose entries have the same mean and covariance. This nonasymptotic universality principle both explains the phenomenon behind classical matrix concentration inequalities such as the matrix Bernstein inequality, and yields new sharp matrix concentration inequalities for general sums of independent random matrices when combined with the recent Gaussian theory of Bandeira, Boedihardjo, and Van Handel. As an application of our main results, we prove strong asymptotic freeness of a very general class of random matrix models with non-Gaussian, nonhomogeneous, and dependent entries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A local-realistic theory for fermions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04553</link>
    <author>Nicetu Tibau Vidal, Vlatko Vedral, Chiara Marletto</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a local model for general fermionic systems, which we express in the Heisenberg picture. To this end, we shall use a recently proposed formalism, the so-called "Raymond-Robichaud" construction, which allows one to construct an explicitly local model for any dynamical theory that satisfies no-signalling, in terms of equivalence classes of transformations that can be attached to each individual subsystem. By following the rigorous use of the parity superselection rule for fermions, we show how this construction removes the usual difficulties that fermionic systems display in regard to the definition of local states and local transformations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decompositional Quantum Graph Neural Network</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05158</link>
    <author>Xing Ai, Zhihong Zhang, Luzhe Sun, Junchi Yan, Edwin Hancock</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum machine learning is a fast emerging field that aims to tackle machine learning using quantum algorithms and quantum computing. Due to the lack of physical qubits and an effective means to map real-world data from Euclidean space to Hilbert space, most of these methods focus on quantum analogies or process simulations rather than devising concrete architectures based on qubits. In this paper, we propose a novel hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for graph-structured data, which we refer to as the Decompositional Quantum Graph Neural Network (DQGNN). DQGNN implements the GNN theoretical framework using the tensor product and unity matrices representation, which greatly reduces the number of model parameters required. When controlled by a classical computer, DQGNN can accommodate arbitrarily sized graphs by processing substructures from the input graph using a modestly-sized quantum device. The architecture is based on a novel mapping from real-world data to Hilbert space. This mapping maintains the distance relations present in the data and reduces information loss. Experimental results show that the proposed method outperforms competitive state-of-the-art models with only 1.68\% parameters compared to those models.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>