<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Real-time quantum error correction beyond break-even</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09116</link>
    <author>V. V. Sivak, A. Eickbusch, B. Royer, S. Singh, I. Tsioutsios, S. Ganjam, A. Miano, B. L. Brock, A. Z. Ding, L. Frunzio, S. M. Girvin, R. J. Schoelkopf, M. H. Devoret</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ambition of harnessing the quantum for computation is at odds with the fundamental phenomenon of decoherence. The purpose of quantum error correction (QEC) is to counteract the natural tendency of a complex system to decohere. This cooperative process, which requires participation of multiple quantum and classical components, creates a special type of dissipation that removes the entropy caused by the errors faster than the rate at which these errors corrupt the stored quantum information. Previous experimental attempts to engineer such a process faced an excessive generation of errors that overwhelmed the error-correcting capability of the process itself. Whether it is practically possible to utilize QEC for extending quantum coherence thus remains an open question. We answer it by demonstrating a fully stabilized and error-corrected logical qubit whose quantum coherence is significantly longer than that of all the imperfect quantum components involved in the QEC process, beating the best of them with a coherence gain of $G = 2.27 \pm 0.07$. We achieve this performance by combining innovations in several domains including the fabrication of superconducting quantum circuits and model-free reinforcement learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the complexity of implementing Trotter steps</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09133</link>
    <author>Guang Hao Low, Yuan Su, Yu Tong, Minh C. Tran</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum dynamics can be simulated on a quantum computer by exponentiating elementary terms from the Hamiltonian in a sequential manner. However, such an implementation of Trotter steps has gate complexity depending on the total Hamiltonian term number, comparing unfavorably to algorithms using more advanced techniques. We develop methods to perform faster Trotter steps with complexity sublinear in the number of terms. We achieve this for a class of Hamiltonians whose interaction strength decays with distance according to power law. Our methods include one based on a recursive block encoding and one based on an average-cost simulation, overcoming the normalization-factor barrier of these advanced quantum simulation techniques. We also realize faster Trotter steps when certain blocks of Hamiltonian coefficients have low rank. Combining with a tighter error analysis, we show that it suffices to use $\left(\eta^{1/3}n^{1/3}+\frac{n^{2/3}}{\eta^{2/3}}\right)n^{1+o(1)}$ gates to simulate uniform electron gas with $n$ spin orbitals and $\eta$ electrons in second quantization in real space, asymptotically improving over the best previous work. We obtain an analogous result when the external potential of nuclei is introduced under the Born-Oppenheimer approximation. We prove a circuit lower bound when the Hamiltonian coefficients take a continuum range of values, showing that generic $n$-qubit $2$-local Hamiltonians with commuting terms require at least $\Omega(n^2)$ gates to evolve with accuracy $\epsilon=\Omega(1/poly(n))$ for time $t=\Omega(\epsilon)$. Our proof is based on a gate-efficient reduction from the approximate synthesis of diagonal unitaries within the Hamming weight-$2$ subspace, which may be of independent interest. Our result thus suggests the use of Hamiltonian structural properties as both necessary and sufficient to implement Trotter steps with lower gate complexity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Assessing requirements to scale to practical quantum advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07629</link>
    <author>Michael E. Beverland, Prakash Murali, Matthias Troyer, Krysta M. Svore, Torsten Hoeffler, Vadym Kliuchnikov, Guang Hao Low, Mathias Soeken, Aarthi Sundaram, Alexander Vaschillo</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While quantum computers promise to solve some scientifically and commercially valuable problems thought intractable for classical machines, delivering on this promise will require a large-scale quantum machine. Understanding the impact of architecture design choices for a scaled quantum stack for specific applications, prior to full realization of the quantum system, is an important open challenge. To this end, we develop a framework for quantum resource estimation, abstracting the layers of the stack, to estimate resources required across these layers for large-scale quantum applications. Using a tool that implements this framework, we assess three scaled quantum applications and find that hundreds of thousands to millions of physical qubits are needed to achieve practical quantum advantage. We identify three qubit parameters, namely size, speed, and controllability, that are critical at scale to rendering these applications practical. A goal of our work is to accelerate progress towards practical quantum advantage by enabling the broader community to explore design choices across the stack, from algorithms to qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generating $k$ EPR-pairs from an n-party resource state</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06497</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Yash Sharma, Mario Szegedy, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Motivated by quantum network applications over classical channels, we initiate the study of $n$-party resource states from which LOCC protocols can create EPR-pairs between any $k$ disjoint pairs of parties. We give constructions of such states where $k$ is not too far from the optimal $n/2$ while the individual parties need to hold only a constant number of qubits. In the special case when each party holds only one qubit, we describe a family of $n$-qubit states with $k$ proportional to $\log n$ based on Reed-Muller codes, as well as small numerically found examples for $k=2$ and $k=3$. We also prove some lower bounds, for example showing that if $k=n/2$ then the parties must have at least $\Omega(\log\log n)$ qubits each.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A (simple) classical algorithm for estimating Betti numbers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09618</link>
    <author>Simon Apers, Sayantan Sen, Dániel Szabó</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a simple algorithm for estimating the $k$-th normalized Betti number of a simplicial complex over $n$ elements using the path integral Monte Carlo method. For a general simplicial complex, the running time of our algorithm is $n^{O(\frac{1}{\gamma}\log\frac{1}{\varepsilon})}$ with $\gamma$ measuring the spectral gap of the combinatorial Laplacian and $\varepsilon \in (0,1)$ the additive precision. In the case of a clique complex, the running time of our algorithm improves to $(n/\lambda_{\max})^{O(\frac{1}{\gamma}\log\frac{1}{\varepsilon})}$ with $\lambda_{\max} \geq k$ the maximum eigenvalue of the combinatorial Laplacian. Our algorithm provides a classical benchmark for a line of quantum algorithms for estimating Betti numbers, and it matches their running time on clique complexes when the spectral gap is constant and $k \in \Omega(n)$ or $\lambda_{\max} \in \Omega(n)$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive surface code for quantum error correction in the presence of temporary or permanent defects</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08468</link>
    <author>Adam Siegel, Armands Strikis, Thomas Flatters, Simon Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Whether it is at the fabrication stage or during the course of the quantum computation, e.g. because of high-energy events like cosmic rays, the qubits constituting an error correcting code may be rendered inoperable. Such defects may correspond to individual qubits or to clusters and could potentially disrupt the code sufficiently to generate logical errors. In this paper, we explore a novel adaptive approach for surface code quantum error correction on a defective lattice. We show that combining an appropriate defect detection algorithm and a quarantine of the identified zone allows one to preserve the advantage of quantum error correction at finite code sizes, at the cost of a qubit overhead that scales with the size of the defect. Our numerics indicate that the code's threshold need not be significantly affected; for example, for a certain scenario where small defects repeatedly arise in each logical qubit, the noise threshold is $2.7\%$ (versus the defect-free case of $2.9\%$). These results pave the way to the experimental implementation of large-scale quantum computers where defects will be inevitable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadow tomography for continuous variables quantum systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07578</link>
    <author>Simon Becker, Nilanjana Datta, Ludovico Lami, Cambyse Rouzé</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this article we develop a continuous variable (CV) shadow tomography scheme with wide ranging applications in quantum optics. Our work is motivated by the increasing experimental and technological relevance of CV systems in quantum information, quantum communication, quantum sensing, quantum simulations, quantum computing and error correction. We introduce two experimentally realisable schemes for obtaining classical shadows of CV (possibly non-Gaussian) quantum states using only randomised Gaussian unitaries and easily implementable Gaussian measurements such as homodyne and heterodyne detection. For both schemes, we show that $N=\mathcal{O}\big(\operatorname{poly}\big(\frac{1}{\epsilon},\log\big(\frac{1}{\delta}\big),M_n^{r+\alpha},\log(m)\big)\big)$ samples of an unknown $m$-mode state $\rho$ suffice to learn the expected value of any $r$-local polynomial in the canonical observables of degree $\alpha$, both with high probability $1-\delta$ and accuracy $\epsilon$, as long as the state $\rho$ has moments of order $n>\alpha$ bounded by $M_n$. By simultaneously truncating states and operators in energy and phase space, we are able to overcome new mathematical challenges that arise due to the infinite-dimensionality of CV systems. We also provide a scheme to learn nonlinear functionals of the state, such as entropies over any small number of modes, by leveraging recent energy-constrained entropic continuity bounds. Finally, we provide numerical evidence of the efficiency of our protocols in the case of CV states of relevance in quantum information theory, including ground states of quadratic Hamiltonians of many-body systems and cat qubit states. We expect our scheme to provide good recovery in learning relevant states of 2D materials and photonic crystals.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Digital simulation of non-Abelian anyons with 68 programmable superconducting qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09802</link>
    <author>Shibo Xu, Zheng-Zhi Sun, Ke Wang, Liang Xiang, Zehang Bao, Zitian Zhu, Fanhao Shen, Zixuan Song, Pengfei Zhang, Wenhui Ren, Xu Zhang, Hang Dong, Jinfeng Deng, Jiachen Chen, Yaozu Wu, Ziqi Tan, Yu Gao, Feitong Jin, Xuhao Zhu, Chuanyu Zhang, et al (14)</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Non-Abelian anyons are exotic quasiparticle excitations hosted by certain topological phases of matter [1-2]. They break the fermion-boson dichotomy and obey non-Abelian braiding statistics [3-5]: their interchanges yield unitary operations, rather than merely a phase factor, in a space spanned by topologically degenerate wavefunctions. They are the building blocks of topological quantum computing [1, 6-9]. However, experimental observation of non-Abelian anyons and their characterizing braiding statistics have remained elusive hitherto, in spite of various theoretical proposals [10-21]. Here, we report such an observation with up to 68 programmable superconducting qubits arranged on a two-dimensional lattice. By implementing the toric-code model with twists through quantum circuits, we demonstrate that twists exchange electric and magnetic charges and behave as a particular type of non-Abelian anyons -- the Ising anyons. In particular, we show experimentally that these anyons follow the fusion rules and non-Abelian braiding statistics of the Ising type, and can indeed be used to encode topological logical qubits. Furthermore, we demonstrate how to implement both single- and two-qubit logical gates through applying a sequence of elementary Pauli gates on the underlying physical qubits and then measuring some nonlocal observables. Our results establish a versatile digital approach to realize and manipulate non-Abelian anyons, thus paving an alternative way to topological quantum computing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An efficient combination of quantum error correction and authentication</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09686</link>
    <author>Yfke Dulek, Garazi Muguruza, Florian Speelman</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>When sending quantum information over a channel, we want to ensure that the message remains intact. Quantum error correction and quantum authentication both aim to protect (quantum) information, but approach this task from two very different directions: error-correcting codes protect against probabilistic channel noise and are meant to be very robust against small errors, while authentication codes prevent adversarial attacks and are designed to be very sensitive against any error, including small ones. In practice, when sending an authenticated state over a noisy channel, one would have to wrap it in an error-correcting code to counterbalance the sensitivity of the underlying authentication scheme. We study the question of whether this can be done more efficiently by combining the two functionalities in a single code. To illustrate the potential of such a combination, we design the threshold code, a modification of the trap authentication code which preserves that code's authentication properties, but which is naturally robust against depolarizing channel noise. We show that the threshold code needs polylogarithmically fewer qubits to achieve the same level of security and robustness, compared to the naive composition of the trap code with any concatenated CSS code. We believe our analysis opens the door to combining more general error-correction and authentication codes, which could improve the practicality of the resulting scheme.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error bounds for Lie Group representations in quantum mechanics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08582</link>
    <author>Lauritz van Luijk, Niklas Galke, Alexander Hahn, Daniel Burgarth</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide state-dependent error bounds for strongly continuous unitary representations of connected Lie groups. That is, we bound the difference of two unitaries applied to a state in terms of the energy with respect to a reference Hamiltonian associated to the representation and a left-invariant metric distance on the group. Our method works for any connected Lie group and the metric is independent of the chosen representation. The approach also applies to projective representations and allows us to provide bounds on the energy constrained diamond norm distance of any suitably continuous channel representation of the group.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>