<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Modern applications of machine learning in quantum sciences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04198</link>
    <author>Anna Dawid, Julian Arnold, Borja Requena, Alexander Gresch, Marcin Płodzień, Kaelan Donatella, Kim Nicoli, Paolo Stornati, Rouven Koch, Miriam Büttner, Robert Okuła, Gorka Muñoz-Gil, Rodrigo A. Vargas-Hernández, Alba Cervera-Lierta, Juan Carrasquilla, Vedran Dunjko, Marylou Gabrié, Patrick Huembeli, Evert van Nieuwenburg, Filippo Vicentini, et al (9)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In these Lecture Notes, we provide a comprehensive introduction to the most recent advances in the application of machine learning methods in quantum sciences. We cover the use of deep learning and kernel methods in supervised, unsupervised, and reinforcement learning algorithms for phase classification, representation of many-body quantum states, quantum feedback control, and quantum circuits optimization. Moreover, we introduce and discuss more specialized topics such as differentiable programming, generative models, statistical approach to machine learning, and quantum machine learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of variational quantum algorithms: a quantum optimal transport approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03455</link>
    <author>Giacomo De Palma, Milad Marvian, Cambyse Rouzé, Daniel Stilck França</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The impressive progress in quantum hardware of the last years has raised the interest of the quantum computing community in harvesting the computational power of such devices. However, in the absence of error correction, these devices can only reliably implement very shallow circuits or comparatively deeper circuits at the expense of a nontrivial density of errors. In this work, we obtain extremely tight limitation bounds for standard NISQ proposals in both the noisy and noiseless regimes, with or without error-mitigation tools. The bounds limit the performance of both circuit model algorithms, such as QAOA, and also continuous-time algorithms, such as quantum annealing. In the noisy regime with local depolarizing noise $p$, we prove that at depths $L=\cO(p^{-1})$ it is exponentially unlikely that the outcome of a noisy quantum circuit outperforms efficient classical algorithms for combinatorial optimization problems like Max-Cut. Although previous results already showed that classical algorithms outperform noisy quantum circuits at constant depth, these results only held for the expectation value of the output. Our results are based on newly developed quantum entropic and concentration inequalities, which constitute a homogeneous toolkit of theoretical methods from the quantum theory of optimal mass transport whose potential usefulness goes beyond the study of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Routing with Teleportation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04185</link>
    <author>Dhruv Devulapalli, Eddie Schoute, Aniruddha Bapat, Andrew M. Childs, Alexey V. Gorshkov</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problem of implementing arbitrary permutations of qubits under interaction constraints in quantum systems that allow for arbitrarily fast local operations and classical communication (LOCC). In particular, we show examples of speedups over swap-based and more general unitary routing methods by distributing entanglement and using LOCC to perform quantum teleportation. We further describe an example of an interaction graph for which teleportation gives a logarithmic speedup in the worst-case routing time over swap-based routing. We also study limits on the speedup afforded by quantum teleportation - showing an $O(\sqrt{N \log N})$ upper bound on the separation in routing time for any interaction graph - and give tighter bounds for some common classes of graphs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum variational learning for quantum error-correcting codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03560</link>
    <author>Chenfeng Cao, Chao Zhang, Zipeng Wu, Markus Grassl, Bei Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error-correcting codes (QECCs) are believed to be a necessity for large-scale fault-tolerant quantum computation. In the past two decades, various methods of QECC constructions have been developed, leading to many good families of codes. However, the majority of these codes are not suitable for near-term quantum devices. Here we present VarQEC, a noise-resilient variational quantum algorithm to search for quantum codes with a hardware-efficient encoding circuit. The cost functions are inspired by the most general and fundamental requirements of a QECC, the Knill-Laflamme conditions. Given the target noise channel (or the target code parameters) and the hardware connectivity graph, we optimize a shallow variational quantum circuit to prepare the basis states of an eligible code. In principle, VarQEC can find quantum codes for any error model, whether additive or non-additive, degenerate or non-degenerate, pure or impure. We have verified its effectiveness by (re)discovering some symmetric and asymmetric codes, e.g., $((n,2^{n-6},3))_2$ for $n$ from 7 to 14. We also found new $((6,2,3))_2$ and $((7,2,3))_2$ codes that are not equivalent to any stabilizer code, and extensive numerical evidence with VarQEC suggests that a $((7,3,3))_2$ code does not exist. Furthermore, we found many new channel-adaptive codes for error models involving nearest-neighbor correlated errors. Our work sheds new light on the understanding of QECC in general, which may also help to enhance near-term device performance with channel-adaptive error-correcting codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Cleaning Lemma of Quantum Coding Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04699</link>
    <author>Gleb Kalachev, Sergey Sadov</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The term "Cleaning Lemma" refers to a family of similar propositions that have been used in Quantum Coding Theory to estimate the minimum distance of a code in terms of its length and dimension. We show that the mathematical core is a simple fact of linear algebra of inner product spaces; moreover, it admits a further reduction to a combinatorial, lattice-theoretical level. Several concrete variants of the Cleaning Lemma and some additional propositions are derived as corollaries of the proposed approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Variational Ansatz for the Ground State of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02923</link>
    <author>Paul M. Schindler, Tommaso Guaita, Tao Shi, Eugene Demler, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an ansatz for the ground states of the Quantum Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model, a paradigmatic model for quantum spin glasses. Our ansatz, based on the concept of generalized coherent states, very well captures the fundamental aspects of the model, including the ground state energy and the position of the spin glass phase transition. It further enables us to study some previously unexplored features, such as the non-vanishing longitudinal field regime and the entanglement structure of the ground states. We find that the ground state entanglement can be captured by a simple ensemble of weighted graph states with normally distributed phase gates, leading to a volume law entanglement, contrasting with predictions based on entanglement monogamy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Gaussian matrix product states cannot efficiently describe critical systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02478</link>
    <author>Adrián Franco-Rubio, J. Ignacio Cirac</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gaussian fermionic matrix product states (GfMPS) form a class of ansatz quantum states for 1d systems of noninteracting fermions. We show, for a simple critical model of free hopping fermions, that: (i) any GfMPS approximation to its ground state must have bond dimension scaling superpolynomially with the system size, whereas (ii) there exists a non-Gaussian fermionic MPS approximation to this state with polynomial bond dimension. This proves that, in general, imposing Gaussianity at the level of the tensor network may significantly alter its capability to efficiently approximate critical Gaussian states. We also provide numerical evidence that the required bond dimension is subexponential, and thus can still be simulated with moderate resources.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Simulation for High Energy Physics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03381</link>
    <author>Christian W. Bauer. Zohreh Davoudi, A. Baha Balantekin, Tanmoy Bhattacharya, Marcela Carena, Wibe A. de Jong, Patrick Draper, Aida El-Khadra, Nate Gemelke, Masanori Hanada, Dmitri Kharzeev, Henry Lamm, Ying-Ying Li, Junyu Liu, Mikhail Lukin, Yannick Meurice, Christopher Monroe, Benjamin Nachman, Guido Pagano, John Preskill, Enrico Rinaldi, et al (10)</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It is for the first time that Quantum Simulation for High Energy Physics (HEP) is studied in the U.S. decadal particle-physics community planning, and in fact until recently, this was not considered a mainstream topic in the community. This fact speaks of a remarkable rate of growth of this subfield over the past few years, stimulated by the impressive advancements in Quantum Information Sciences (QIS) and associated technologies over the past decade, and the significant investment in this area by the government and private sectors in the U.S. and other countries. High-energy physicists have quickly identified problems of importance to our understanding of nature at the most fundamental level, from tiniest distances to cosmological extents, that are intractable with classical computers but may benefit from quantum advantage. They have initiated, and continue to carry out, a vigorous program in theory, algorithm, and hardware co-design for simulations of relevance to the HEP mission. This community whitepaper is an attempt to bring this exciting and yet challenging area of research to the spotlight, and to elaborate on what the promises, requirements, challenges, and potential solutions are over the next decade and beyond.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matrix multiplication via matrix groups</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.03826</link>
    <author>Jonah Blasiak, Henry Cohn, Joshua A. Grochow, Kevin Pratt, Chris Umans</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 11 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In 2003, Cohn and Umans proposed a group-theoretic approach to bounding the exponent of matrix multiplication. Previous work within this approach ruled out certain families of groups as a route to obtaining $\omega = 2$, while other families of groups remain potentially viable. In this paper we turn our attention to matrix groups, whose usefulness within this framework was relatively unexplored. We first show that groups of Lie type cannot prove $\omega=2$ within the group-theoretic approach. This is based on a representation-theoretic argument that identifies the second-smallest dimension of an irreducible representation of a group as a key parameter that determines its viability in this framework. Our proof builds on Gowers' result concerning product-free sets in quasirandom groups. We then give another barrier that rules out certain natural matrix group constructions that make use of subgroups that are far from being self-normalizing. Our barrier results leave open several natural paths to obtain $\omega = 2$ via matrix groups. To explore these routes we propose working in the continuous setting of Lie groups, in which we develop an analogous theory. Obtaining the analogue of $\omega=2$ in this potentially easier setting is a key challenge that represents an intermediate goal short of actually proving $\omega = 2$. We give two constructions in the continuous setting, each of which evades one of our two barriers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Entanglement-invertible channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.04493</link>
    <author>Dominic Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In a well-known result \citeWerner2001, Werner classified all \emphtight quantum teleportation and dense coding schemes, showing that they correspond to \emphunitary error bases. Here tightness is a certain dimensional restriction: the quantum system to be teleported and the entangled resource must be of dimension d, and the measurement must have d^2 outcomes. In this work we generalise this classification so as to remove the dimensional restriction altogether, thereby resolving an open problem raised in that work. In fact, we classify not just teleportation and dense coding schemes, but \emphentanglement-reversible channels. These are channels between finite-dimensional C^*-algebras which are reversible with the aid of an entangled resource state, generalising ordinary reversibility of a channel. In Werner's classification, a bijective correspondence between tight teleportation and dense coding schemes was shown: swapping Alice and Bob's operations turns a teleportation scheme into a dense coding scheme and vice versa. We observe that this property generalises ordinary invertibility of a channel; we call it \emphentanglement-invertibility. We show that entanglement-invertible channels are precisely the \emphquantum bijections previously studied in the setting of quantum combinatorics \citeMusto2018, which are classified in terms of the representation theory of the quantum permutation group.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>