<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>On a gap in the proof of the generalised quantum Stein's lemma and its consequences for the reversibility of quantum resources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02813</link>
    <author>Mario Berta, Fernando G. S. L. Brandão, Gilad Gour, Ludovico Lami, Martin B. Plenio, Bartosz Regula, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the proof of the generalised quantum Stein's lemma [Brandão & Plenio, Commun. Math. Phys. 295, 791 (2010)] is not correct due to a gap in the argument leading to Lemma III.9. Hence, the main achievability result of Brandão & Plenio is not known to hold. This puts into question a number of established results in the literature, in particular the reversibility of quantum entanglement [Brandão & Plenio, Commun. Math. Phys. 295, 829 (2010); Nat. Phys. 4, 873 (2008)] and of general quantum resources [Brandão & Gour, Phys. Rev. Lett. 115, 070503 (2015)] under asymptotically resource non-generating operations. We discuss potential ways to recover variants of the newly unsettled results using other approaches.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive constant-depth circuits for manipulating non-abelian anyons</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01933</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Isaac Kim, Alexander Kliesch, Robert Koenig</author>
    <pubDate>May 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider Kitaev's quantum double model based on a finite group $G$ and describe quantum circuits for (a) preparation of the ground state, (b) creation of anyon pairs separated by an arbitrary distance, and (c) non-destructive topological charge measurement. We show that for any solvable group $G$ all above tasks can be realized by constant-depth adaptive circuits with geometrically local unitary gates and mid-circuit measurements. Each gate may be chosen adaptively depending on previous measurement outcomes. Constant-depth circuits are well suited for implementation on a noisy hardware since it may be possible to execute the entire circuit within the qubit coherence time. Thus our results could facilitate an experimental study of exotic phases of matter with a non-abelian particle statistics. We also show that adaptiveness is essential for our circuit construction. Namely, task (b) cannot be realized by non-adaptive constant-depth local circuits for any non-abelian group $G$. This is in a sharp contrast with abelian anyons which can be created and moved over an arbitrary distance by a depth-$1$ circuit composed of generalized Pauli gates.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Group-Invariant Quantum Machine Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02261</link>
    <author>Martin Larocca, Frederic Sauvage, Faris M. Sbahi, Guillaume Verdon, Patrick J. Coles, M. Cerezo</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Machine Learning (QML) models are aimed at learning from data encoded in quantum states. Recently, it has been shown that models with little to no inductive biases (i.e., with no assumptions about the problem embedded in the model) are likely to have trainability and generalization issues, especially for large problem sizes. As such, it is fundamental to develop schemes that encode as much information as available about the problem at hand. In this work we present a simple, yet powerful, framework where the underlying invariances in the data are used to build QML models that, by construction, respect those symmetries. These so-called group-invariant models produce outputs that remain invariant under the action of any element of the symmetry group $\mathfrak{G}$ associated to the dataset. We present theoretical results underpinning the design of $\mathfrak{G}$-invariant models, and exemplify their application through several paradigmatic QML classification tasks including cases when $\mathfrak{G}$ is a continuous Lie group and also when it is a discrete symmetry group. Notably, our framework allows us to recover, in an elegant way, several well known algorithms for the literature, as well as to discover new ones. Taken together, we expect that our results will help pave the way towards a more geometric and group-theoretic approach to QML model design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum contextuality provides communication complexity advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.03308</link>
    <author>Shashank Gupta, Debashis Saha, Zhen-Peng Xu, Adán Cabello, A. S. Majumdar</author>
    <pubDate>May 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Despite the conceptual importance of contextuality in quantum mechanics, there is a hitherto limited number of applications requiring contextuality but not entanglement. Here, we show that for any quantum state and observables of sufficiently small dimension producing contextuality, there exists a communication task with quantum advantage. Conversely, any quantum advantage in this task admits a proof of contextuality whenever an additional condition holds. We further show that given any set of observables allowing for quantum state-independent contextuality, there exists a class of communication tasks wherein the difference between classical and quantum communication complexities increases as the number of inputs grows. Finally, we show how to convert each of these communication tasks into a semi-device independent protocol for quantum key distribution.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Soft Syndrome Decoding of Quantum LDPC Codes for Joint Correction of Data and Syndrome Errors</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02341</link>
    <author>Nithin Raveendran, Narayanan Rengaswamy, Asit Kumar Pradhan, Bane Vasić</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum errors are primarily detected and corrected using the measurement of syndrome information which itself is an unreliable step in practical error correction implementations. Typically, such faulty or noisy syndrome measurements are modeled as a binary measurement outcome flipped with some probability. However, the measured syndrome is in fact a discretized value of the continuous voltage or current values obtained in the physical implementation of the syndrome extraction. In this paper, we use this "soft" or analog information without the conventional discretization step to benefit the iterative decoders for decoding quantum low-density parity-check (QLDPC) codes. Syndrome-based iterative belief propagation decoders are modified to utilize the syndrome-soft information to successfully correct both data and syndrome errors simultaneously, without repeated measurements. We demonstrate the advantages of extracting the soft information from the syndrome in our improved decoders, not only in terms of comparison of thresholds and logical error rates for quasi-cyclic lifted-product QLDPC code families, but also for faster convergence of iterative decoders. In particular, the new BP decoder with noisy syndrome performs as good as the standard BP decoder under ideal syndrome.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Magic of the ground state of the transverse field Ising model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02247</link>
    <author>Salvatore F.E. Oliviero, Lorenzo Leone, Alioscia Hamma</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Ground states of quantum many-body systems are both entangled and possess a kind of quantum complexity as their preparation requires universal resources that go beyond the Clifford group and stabilizer states. These resources - sometimes dubbed as magic - are also the crucial ingredient for quantum advantage. We study the behavior of the stabilizer Rényi entropy in the integrable transverse field Ising spin chain. We show that the locality of interactions results in a localized stabilizer Rényi entropy in the gapped phase thus making this quantity computable in terms of local quantities in the gapped phase, while measurements involving $L$ spins are necessary at the critical point to obtain an error scaling with $O(L^{-1})$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational Quantum Optimization of Nonlocality in Noisy Quantum Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02891</link>
    <author>Brian Doolittle, Tom Bromley, Nathan Killoran, Eric Chitambar</author>
    <pubDate>May 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The inherent noise and complexity of quantum communication networks leads to challenges in designing quantum network protocols using classical methods. To address this issue, we develop a variational quantum optimization framework that simulates quantum networks on quantum hardware and optimizes the network using differential programming techniques. We use our hybrid framework to optimize nonlocality in noisy quantum networks. On the noisy IBM quantum computers, we demonstrate our framework's ability to maximize quantum nonlocality. On a classical simulator with a static noise model, we investigate the noise robustness of quantum nonlocality with respect to unital and nonunital channels. In both cases, we find that our optimization methods can reproduce known results, while uncovering interesting phenomena. When unital noise is present we find numerical evidence suggesting that maximally entangled state preparations yield maximal nonlocality. When nonunital noise is present we find that nonmaximally entangled states can yield maximal nonlocality. Thus, we show that variational quantum optimization is a practical design tool for quantum networks in the near-term. In the long-term, our variational quantum optimization techniques show promise of scaling beyond classical approaches and can be deployed on quantum network hardware to optimize quantum communication protocols against their inherent noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complete flow-preserving rewrite rules for MBQC patterns with Pauli measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02009</link>
    <author>Tommy McElvanney, Miriam Backens</author>
    <pubDate>May 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the one-way model of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), computation proceeds via measurements on some standard resource state. So-called flow conditions ensure that the overall computation is deterministic in a suitable sense, with Pauli flow being the most general of these. Existing work on rewriting MBQC patterns while preserving the existence of flow has focused on rewrites that reduce the number of qubits. In this work, we show that introducing new $Z$-measured qubits, connected to any subset of the existing qubits, preserves the existence of Pauli flow. Furthermore, we give a unique canonical form for stabilizer ZX-diagrams inspired by recent work of Hu & Khesin [arXiv:2109.10210]. We prove that any MBQC-like stabilizer ZX-diagram with Pauli flow can be rewritten into this canonical form using only rules which preserve the existence of Pauli flow and that each of these rules can be reversed while also preserving the existence of Pauli flow. Hence we have complete graphical rewriting for MBQC-like stabilizer ZX-diagrams with Pauli flow.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>isQ: Towards a Practical Software Stack for Quantum Programming</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.03866</link>
    <author>Jingzhe Guo, Huazhe Lou, Riling Li, Wang Fang, Junyi Liu, Peixun Long, Shenggang Ying, Mingsheng Ying</author>
    <pubDate>May 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce isQ, a new software stack for quantum programming in an imperative programming language, also named isQ. The aim of isQ is to make the programmers write quantum programs as conveniently as possible. In particular: 1) The isQ language and its compiler contain many features, including some not well supported by (most) other quantum programming platforms, e.g. classical control flow such as recursion; decomposition of selfdefined unitary gates; and oracle programming and its circuit realization. 2) To make it flexible, an isQ program can be compiled into several kinds of intermediate representation, including OpenQASM 3.0, QIR and QCIS (specially tailored for the superconducting quantum hardware at USTC). 3) Besides interfacing isQ with true superconducting hardware, a QIR simulator is also developed for demonstration and testing of isQ programs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational quantum algorithm for unconstrained black box binary optimization: Application to feature selection</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.03045</link>
    <author>Christa Zoufal, Ryan V. Mishmash, Nitin Sharma, Niraj Kumar, Aashish Sheshadri, Amol Deshmukh, Noelle Ibrahim, Julien Gacon, Stefan Woerner</author>
    <pubDate>May 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a variational quantum algorithm to solve unconstrained black box binary optimization problems, i.e., problems in which the objective function is given as black box. This is in contrast to the typical setting of quantum algorithms for optimization where a classical objective function is provided as a given Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization problem and mapped to a sum of Pauli operators. Furthermore, we provide theoretical justification for our method based on convergence guarantees of quantum imaginary time evolution. To investigate the performance of our algorithm and its potential advantages, we tackle a challenging real-world optimization problem: feature selection. This refers to the problem of selecting a subset of relevant features to use for constructing a predictive model such as fraud detection. Optimal feature selection -- when formulated in terms of a generic loss function -- offers little structure on which to build classical heuristics, thus resulting primarily in 'greedy methods'. This leaves room for (near-term) quantum algorithms to be competitive to classical state-of-the-art approaches. We apply our quantum-optimization-based feature selection algorithm, termed VarQFS, to build a predictive model for a credit risk data set with 20 and 59 input features (qubits) and train the model using quantum hardware and tensor-network-based numerical simulations, respectively. We show that the quantum method produces competitive and in certain aspects even better performance compared to traditional feature selection techniques used in today's industry.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>