<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Real-time quantum error correction beyond break-even</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.09116</link>
    <author>V. V. Sivak, A. Eickbusch, B. Royer, S. Singh, I. Tsioutsios, S. Ganjam, A. Miano, B. L. Brock, A. Z. Ding, L. Frunzio, S. M. Girvin, R. J. Schoelkopf, M. H. Devoret</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The ambition of harnessing the quantum for computation is at odds with the fundamental phenomenon of decoherence. The purpose of quantum error correction (QEC) is to counteract the natural tendency of a complex system to decohere. This cooperative process, which requires participation of multiple quantum and classical components, creates a special type of dissipation that removes the entropy caused by the errors faster than the rate at which these errors corrupt the stored quantum information. Previous experimental attempts to engineer such a process faced an excessive generation of errors that overwhelmed the error-correcting capability of the process itself. Whether it is practically possible to utilize QEC for extending quantum coherence thus remains an open question. We answer it by demonstrating a fully stabilized and error-corrected logical qubit whose quantum coherence is significantly longer than that of all the imperfect quantum components involved in the QEC process, beating the best of them with a coherence gain of $G = 2.27 \pm 0.07$. We achieve this performance by combining innovations in several domains including the fabrication of superconducting quantum circuits and model-free reinforcement learning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Assessing requirements to scale to practical quantum advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07629</link>
    <author>Michael E. Beverland, Prakash Murali, Matthias Troyer, Krysta M. Svore, Torsten Hoeffler, Vadym Kliuchnikov, Guang Hao Low, Mathias Soeken, Aarthi Sundaram, Alexander Vaschillo</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>While quantum computers promise to solve some scientifically and commercially valuable problems thought intractable for classical machines, delivering on this promise will require a large-scale quantum machine. Understanding the impact of architecture design choices for a scaled quantum stack for specific applications, prior to full realization of the quantum system, is an important open challenge. To this end, we develop a framework for quantum resource estimation, abstracting the layers of the stack, to estimate resources required across these layers for large-scale quantum applications. Using a tool that implements this framework, we assess three scaled quantum applications and find that hundreds of thousands to millions of physical qubits are needed to achieve practical quantum advantage. We identify three qubit parameters, namely size, speed, and controllability, that are critical at scale to rendering these applications practical. A goal of our work is to accelerate progress towards practical quantum advantage by enabling the broader community to explore design choices across the stack, from algorithms to qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Generating $k$ EPR-pairs from an n-party resource state</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06497</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Yash Sharma, Mario Szegedy, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Motivated by quantum network applications over classical channels, we initiate the study of $n$-party resource states from which LOCC protocols can create EPR-pairs between any $k$ disjoint pairs of parties. We give constructions of such states where $k$ is not too far from the optimal $n/2$ while the individual parties need to hold only a constant number of qubits. In the special case when each party holds only one qubit, we describe a family of $n$-qubit states with $k$ proportional to $\log n$ based on Reed-Muller codes, as well as small numerically found examples for $k=2$ and $k=3$. We also prove some lower bounds, for example showing that if $k=n/2$ then the parties must have at least $\Omega(\log\log n)$ qubits each.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Refuting spectral compatibility of quantum marginals</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06349</link>
    <author>Felix Huber, Nikolai Wyderka</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The spectral variant of the quantum marginal problem asks: Given prescribed spectra for a set of quantum marginals, does there exist a compatible joint state? The main idea of this work is a symmetry-reduced semidefinite programming hierarchy for detecting incompatible spectra. The hierarchy can provide refutations that are dimension-free, certifying incompatibility in all local dimensions. It equally applies to the compatibility of local unitary invariants, to the sums of Hermitian matrices problem, to optimize trace polynomials on the positive cone, and to certify vanishing Kronecker coefficients.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical shadow tomography for continuous variables quantum systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.07578</link>
    <author>Simon Becker, Nilanjana Datta, Ludovico Lami, Cambyse Rouzé</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this article we develop a continuous variable (CV) shadow tomography scheme with wide ranging applications in quantum optics. Our work is motivated by the increasing experimental and technological relevance of CV systems in quantum information, quantum communication, quantum sensing, quantum simulations, quantum computing and error correction. We introduce two experimentally realisable schemes for obtaining classical shadows of CV (possibly non-Gaussian) quantum states using only randomised Gaussian unitaries and easily implementable Gaussian measurements such as homodyne and heterodyne detection. For both schemes, we show that $N=\mathcal{O}\big(\operatorname{poly}\big(\frac{1}{\epsilon},\log\big(\frac{1}{\delta}\big),M_n^{r+\alpha},\log(m)\big)\big)$ samples of an unknown $m$-mode state $\rho$ suffice to learn the expected value of any $r$-local polynomial in the canonical observables of degree $\alpha$, both with high probability $1-\delta$ and accuracy $\epsilon$, as long as the state $\rho$ has moments of order $n>\alpha$ bounded by $M_n$. By simultaneously truncating states and operators in energy and phase space, we are able to overcome new mathematical challenges that arise due to the infinite-dimensionality of CV systems. We also provide a scheme to learn nonlinear functionals of the state, such as entropies over any small number of modes, by leveraging recent energy-constrained entropic continuity bounds. Finally, we provide numerical evidence of the efficiency of our protocols in the case of CV states of relevance in quantum information theory, including ground states of quadratic Hamiltonians of many-body systems and cat qubit states. We expect our scheme to provide good recovery in learning relevant states of 2D materials and photonic crystals.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Adaptive surface code for quantum error correction in the presence of temporary or permanent defects</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08468</link>
    <author>Adam Siegel, Armands Strikis, Thomas Flatters, Simon Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Whether it is at the fabrication stage or during the course of the quantum computation, e.g. because of high-energy events like cosmic rays, the qubits constituting an error correcting code may be rendered inoperable. Such defects may correspond to individual qubits or to clusters and could potentially disrupt the code sufficiently to generate logical errors. In this paper, we explore a novel adaptive approach for surface code quantum error correction on a defective lattice. We show that combining an appropriate defect detection algorithm and a quarantine of the identified zone allows one to preserve the advantage of quantum error correction at finite code sizes, at the cost of a qubit overhead that scales with the size of the defect. Our numerics indicate that the code's threshold need not be significantly affected; for example, for a certain scenario where small defects repeatedly arise in each logical qubit, the noise threshold is $2.7\%$ (versus the defect-free case of $2.9\%$). These results pave the way to the experimental implementation of large-scale quantum computers where defects will be inevitable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hardware optimized parity check gates for superconducting surface codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06382</link>
    <author>Matthew J. Reagor, Thomas C. Bohdanowicz, David Rodriguez Perez, Eyob A. Sete, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Error correcting codes use multi-qubit measurements to realize fault-tolerant quantum logic steps. In fact, the resources needed to scale-up fault-tolerant quantum computing hardware are largely set by this task. Tailoring next-generation processors for joint measurements, therefore, could result in improvements to speed, accuracy, or cost -- accelerating the development large-scale quantum computers. Here, we motivate such explorations by analyzing an unconventional surface code based on multi-body interactions between superconducting transmon qubits. Our central consideration, Hardware Optimized Parity (HOP) gates, achieves stabilizer-type measurements through simultaneous multi-qubit conditional phase accumulation. Despite the multi-body effects that underpin this approach, our estimates of logical faults suggest that this design can be at least as robust to realistic noise as conventional designs. We show a higher threshold of $1.25 \times 10^{-3}$ compared to the standard code's $0.79 \times 10^{-3}$. However, in the HOP code the logical error rate decreases more slowly with decreasing physical error rate. Our results point to a fruitful path forward towards extending gate-model platforms for error correction at the dawn of its empirical development.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error bounds for Lie Group representations in quantum mechanics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.08582</link>
    <author>Lauritz van Luijk, Niklas Galke, Alexander Hahn, Daniel Burgarth</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide state-dependent error bounds for strongly continuous unitary representations of connected Lie groups. That is, we bound the difference of two unitaries applied to a state in terms of the energy with respect to a reference Hamiltonian associated to the representation and a left-invariant metric distance on the group. Our method works for any connected Lie group and the metric is independent of the chosen representation. The approach also applies to projective representations and allows us to provide bounds on the energy constrained diamond norm distance of any suitably continuous channel representation of the group.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Protecting Expressive Circuits with a Quantum Error Detection Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06703</link>
    <author>Chris N. Self, Marcello Benedetti, David Amaro</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error correction opens the way for quantum computers to speed up relevant tasks like simulating quantum systems. However, fully fault-tolerant quantum error correction is too resource intensive for existing quantum computers. In this context we develop the $[[k+2,k,2]]$ quantum error detection code, for implementations on existing trapped-ion computers. Encoding $k$ logical qubits into $k+2$ physical qubits, this code presents fault-tolerant state initialisation and syndrome measurement circuits that can detect any single-qubit error. It provides a universal set of local and global logical rotations that, notably, have physical support on only two qubits. A high-fidelity -- though non fault-tolerant -- compilation of this universal gate set is possible thanks to the two-qubit physical rotations present in trapped-ion computers with all-to-all connectivity. Given the particular structure of the logical operators, we nickname it the Iceberg code. On the 12-qubit Quantinuum H1-2 hardware we demonstrate the protection of circuits of 8 logical qubits with up to 256 layers, saturate the logical quantum volume of $2^8$, and show the positive effect of increasing the frequency of syndrome measurements within the circuit. These results illustrate the practical usefulness of the Iceberg code to protect expressive circuits on existing trapped-ion quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Parallel repetition of local simultaneous state discrimination</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.06456</link>
    <author>Llorenç Escolà Farràs, Jaròn Has, Maris Ozols, Christian Schaffner, Mehrdad Tahmasbi</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Local simultaneous state discrimination (LSSD) is a recently introduced problem in quantum information processing. Its classical version is a non-local game played by non-communicating players against a referee. Based on a known probability distribution, the referee generates one input for each of the players and keeps one secret value. The players have to guess the referee's value and win if they all do so. For this game, we investigate the advantage of no-signalling strategies over classical ones. We show numerically that for three players and binary values, no-signalling strategies cannot provide any improvement over classical ones. For a certain LSSD game based on a binary symmetric channel, we show that no-signalling strategies are strictly better when multiple simultaneous instances of the game are played. Good classical strategies for this game can be defined by codes, and good no-signalling strategies by list-decoding schemes. We expand this example game to a class of games defined by an arbitrary channel, and extend the idea of using codes and list decoding to define strategies for multiple simultaneous instances of these games. Finally, we give an expression for the limit of the exponent of the classical winning probability, and show that no-signalling strategies based on list-decoding schemes achieve this limit.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>