<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum complexity of the Kronecker coefficients</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11454</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Anirban Chowdhury, David Gosset, Vojtech Havlicek, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Whether or not the Kronecker coefficients of the symmetric group count some set of combinatorial objects is a longstanding open question. In this work we show that a given Kronecker coefficient is proportional to the rank of a projector that can be measured efficiently using a quantum computer. In other words a Kronecker coefficient counts the dimension of the vector space spanned by the accepting witnesses of a QMA verifier, where QMA is the quantum analogue of NP. This implies that approximating the Kronecker coefficients to within a given relative error is not harder than a certain natural class of quantum approximate counting problems that captures the complexity of estimating thermal properties of quantum many-body systems. A second consequence is that deciding positivity of Kronecker coefficients is contained in QMA, complementing a recent NP-hardness result of Ikenmeyer, Mulmuley and Walter. We obtain similar results for the related problem of approximating row sums of the character table of the symmetric group. Finally, we discuss an efficient quantum algorithm that approximates normalized Kronecker coefficients to inverse-polynomial additive error.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Theory of Direct Randomized Benchmarking</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.13853</link>
    <author>Anthony M. Polloreno, Arnaud Carignan-Dugas, Jordan Hines, Robin Blume-Kohout, Kevin Young, Timothy Proctor</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Randomized benchmarking (RB) protocols are widely used to measure an average error rate for a set of quantum logic gates. However, the standard version of RB is limited because it only benchmarks a processor's native gates indirectly, by using them in composite $n$-qubit Clifford gates. Standard RB's reliance on $n$-qubit Clifford gates restricts it to the few-qubit regime, because the fidelity of a typical composite $n$-qubit Clifford gate decreases rapidly with increasing $n$. Furthermore, although standard RB is often used to infer the error rate of native gates, by rescaling standard RB's error per Clifford to an error per native gate, this is an unreliable extrapolation. Direct RB is a method that addresses these limitations of standard RB, by directly benchmarking a customizable gate set, such as a processor's native gates. Here we provide a detailed introduction to direct RB, we discuss how to design direct RB experiments, and we present two complementary theories for direct RB. The first of these theories uses the concept of error propagation or scrambling in random circuits to show that direct RB is reliable for gates that experience stochastic Pauli errors. We prove that the direct RB decay is a single exponential, and that the decay rate is equal to the average infidelity of the benchmarked gates, under broad circumstances. This theory shows that group twirling is not required for reliable RB. Our second theory proves that direct RB is reliable for gates that experience general gate-dependent Markovian errors, using similar techniques to contemporary theories for standard RB. Our two theories for direct RB have complementary regimes of applicability, and they provide complementary perspectives on why direct RB works. Together these theories provide comprehensive guarantees on the reliability of direct RB.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Block-encoding structured matrices for data input in quantum computing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.10949</link>
    <author>Christoph Sünderhauf, Earl Campbell, Joan Camps</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>The cost of data input can dominate the run-time of quantum algorithms. Here, we consider data input of arithmetically structured matrices via block encoding circuits, the input model for the quantum singular value transform and related algorithms. We demonstrate how to construct block encoding circuits based on an arithmetic description of the sparsity and pattern of repeated values of a matrix. We present schemes yielding different subnormalisations of the block encoding; a comparison shows that the best choice depends on the specific matrix. The resulting circuits reduce flag qubit number according to sparsity, and data loading cost according to repeated values, leading to an exponential improvement for certain matrices. We give examples of applying our block encoding schemes to a few families of matrices, including Toeplitz and tridiagonal matrices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum trapdoor functions from classical one-way functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.12821</link>
    <author>Andrea Coladangelo</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce the notion of a quantum trapdoor function. This is an efficiently computable unitary that takes as input a "public" quantum state and a classical string $x$, and outputs a quantum state. This map is such that (i) it is hard to invert, in the sense that it is hard to recover $x$ given the output state (and many copies of the public state), and (ii) there is a classical trapdoor that allows efficient inversion. We show that a quantum trapdoor function can be constructed from any quantum-secure one-way function. A direct consequence of this result is that, assuming just the existence of quantum-secure one-way functions, there exist: (i) a public-key encryption scheme with a quantum public key, and (ii) a two-message key-exchange protocol, assuming an appropriate notion of a quantum authenticated channel.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum spherical codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11593</link>
    <author>Shubham P. Jain, Joseph T. Iosue, Alexander Barg, Victor V. Albert</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a framework for constructing quantum codes defined on spheres by recasting such codes as quantum analogues of the classical spherical codes. We apply this framework to bosonic coding, obtaining multimode extensions of the cat codes that can outperform previous constructions while requiring a similar type of overhead. Our polytope-based cat codes consist of sets of points with large separation that at the same time form averaging sets known as spherical designs. We also recast concatenations of qubit CSS codes with cat codes as quantum spherical codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Guidable Local Hamiltonian Problems with Implications to Heuristic Ansätze State Preparation and the Quantum PCP Conjecture</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11578</link>
    <author>Jordi Weggemans, Marten Folkertsma, Chris Cade</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 24 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce 'Merlinized' versions of the recently defined Guided Local Hamiltonian problem, which we call 'Guidable Local Hamiltonian' problems. Unlike their guided counterparts, these problems do not have a guiding state provided as a part of the input, but merely come with the promise that one exists and that it satisfies certain constraints. We consider in particular two classes of guiding states: those that can be prepared efficiently by a quantum circuit; and those belonging to a class of quantum states we call classically evaluatable, which have a short classical description from which it is possible to efficiently compute expectation values of local observables classically. We show that guidable local Hamiltonian problems for both classes of guiding states are $\mathsf{QCMA}$-complete in the inverse-polynomial precision setting, but lie within $\mathsf{NP}$ (or $\mathsf{NqP}$) in certain parameter regimes when the guiding state is classically evaluatable. We discuss the implications of these results to heuristic ansätze state preparation and the quantum PCP conjecture. Our completeness results show that, from a complexity-theoretic perspective, classical ansätze prepared by classical heuristics are just as powerful as quantum ansätze prepared by quantum heuristics, so long as one has access to quantum phase estimation. In relation to the quantum PCP conjecture, we (i) define a PCP for $\mathsf{QCMA}$ and show that it is equal to $\mathsf{NP}$ under quantum reductions; (ii) show several no-go results for the existence of quantum gap amplification procedures that preserve certain ground state properties; and (iii) propose two conjectures that can be viewed as stronger versions of the NLTS theorem. Finally, we show that many of our results can be directly modified to obtain similar results for the class $\mathsf{MA}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Field Theory and The Sum-of-Squares for Quantum Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.14006</link>
    <author>M. B. Hastings</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>This is a collection of various result and notes, addressing the sum-of-squares hierarchy for spin and fermion systems using some ideas from quantum field theory, including higher order perturbation theory, critical phenomena, nonlocal coupling in time, and auxiliary field Monte Carlo. This paper should be seen as a sequel to Refs. 1,2. Additionally in this paper, we consider the difficulty of approximating the ground state energy of the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model using other methods. We provide limitations on the power of the Lanczos method, starting with a Gausian wavefunction, and on the power of a sum of Gaussian wavefunctions (in this case under an assumption).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>(Non-)Universality in symmetric quantum circuits: Why Abelian symmetries are special</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.12466</link>
    <author>Iman Marvian</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 27 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this work, we develop the theory of symmetric quantum circuits with Abelian symmetries. It has been recently shown that general unitary transformations that respect a global symmetry can not be realized by composing unitaries that respect the same symmetry but do not act on all the subsystems in the system. For a general symmetry group, such as SU(d), the locality of interactions imposes different types of constraints on the realizable unitaries. For instance, the unitary realized in a subspace with one irreducible representation (charge) of the symmetry dictates the realized unitaries in multiple other sectors with inequivalent representations of the symmetry. Furthermore, in certain sectors rather than all unitaries that respect the symmetry, the realizable unitaries are the symplectic, or the orthogonal subgroups of this group. We show that none of the aforementioned restrictions appear in the case of Abelian symmetries: While the locality of interactions still imposes additional constraints on the realizable unitaries, they are of the following two types: (i) constraints on the relative phases between subspaces with different charges, and (ii) constraints due to the presence of multiple invariant subspaces inside a subspace with a given charge, which results in extra conserved observables. The latter type of constraint can be removed by k-local symmetric unitaries with sufficiently large k (independent of the system size), whereas to remove the former constraints, in general, one needs an ancillary qudit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Implementing Linear Combination of Unitaries on Intermediate-term Quantum Computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.13555</link>
    <author>Shantanav Chakraborty</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 28 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Over the years, the framework of Linear combination of unitaries (LCU) has been extremely useful for designing a plethora of quantum algorithms. In this work, we explore whether this widely applicable paradigm can be implemented on quantum computers that will be available immediately after the current NISQ stage. To this end, we develop three variants of LCU and apply each, to quantum algorithms of practical interest. First, we develop a physically motivated, continuous-time analogue of LCU (``Analog LCU''). This technique, implementable on hybrid qubit-qumode systems, is simpler than its discrete-time counterpart. We use this method to develop analog quantum algorithms for ground state preparation and quantum linear systems. We also develop a randomized quantum algorithm to sample from functions of Hamiltonians applied to quantum states (``Single-Ancilla LCU''). This approach repeatedly samples from a short-depth quantum circuit and uses only a single ancilla qubit. We use this to estimate expectation values of observables in the ground states of a Hamiltonian, and in the solution of quantum linear systems. This method is suitable for early fault-tolerant quantum computers. Our third approach stems from the observation that for several applications, it suffices to replace LCU with randomized sampling of unitaries according to the distribution of the LCU coefficients (``Ancilla-free LCU''). This is particularly useful when one is interested in the projection of a quantum state implemented by an LCU procedure in some subspace of interest. We demonstrate that this technique applies to the spatial search problem and helps establish a relationship between discrete and continuous-time quantum walks with their classical counterparts. Our work demonstrates that generic quantum algorithmic paradigms, such as LCU, can potentially be implemented on intermediate-term quantum devices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Complexity of Learning (Pseudo)random Dynamics of Black Holes and Other Chaotic Systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2302.11013</link>
    <author>Lisa Yang, Netta Engelhardt</author>
    <pubDate>Feb 23 2023</pubDate>
    <description>It has been recently proposed that the naive semiclassical prediction of non-unitary black hole evaporation can be understood in the fundamental description of the black hole as a consequence of ignorance of high-complexity information. Validity of this conjecture implies that any algorithm which is polynomially bounded in computational complexity cannot accurately reconstruct the black hole dynamics. In this work, we prove that such bounded quantum algorithms cannot accurately predict (pseudo)random unitary dynamics, even if they are given access to an arbitrary set of polynomially complex observables under this time evolution; this shows that "learning" a (pseudo)random unitary is computationally hard. We use the common simplification of modeling black holes and more generally chaotic systems via (pseudo)random dynamics. The quantum algorithms that we consider are completely general, and their attempted guess for the time evolution of black holes is likewise unconstrained: it need not be a linear operator, and may be as general as an arbitrary (e.g. decohering) quantum channel.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>