<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Thrifty shadow estimation: re-using quantum circuits and bounding tails</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06240</link>
    <author>Jonas Helsen, Michael Walter</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Randomized shadow estimation is a recent protocol that allows estimating exponentially many expectation values of a quantum state from ``classical shadows'', obtained by applying random quantum circuits and computational basis measurements. In this paper we study the statistical efficiency of this approach in light of near-term quantum computing. In particular, we propose and analyze a more practically-implementable variant of the protocol, thrifty shadow estimation, in which quantum circuits are reused many times instead of having to be freshly generated for each measurement (as in the original protocol). We show that the effect of this reuse strongly depends on the family of quantum circuits that is chosen. In particular, it is maximally effective when sampling Haar random unitaries, and maximally ineffective when sampling Clifford circuits (even though the Clifford group forms a three-design). To interpolate between these two extremes, we provide an efficiently simulable family of quantum circuits inspired by a recent construction of approximate t-designs. Finally we consider tail bounds for shadow estimation and discuss when median-of-means estimation can be replaced with standard mean estimation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>High-threshold quantum computing by fusing one-dimensional cluster states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06775</link>
    <author>Stefano Paesani, Benjamin J. Brown</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a measurement-based model for fault-tolerant quantum computation that can be realised with one-dimensional cluster states and fusion measurements only; basic resources that are readily available with scalable photonic hardware. Our simulations demonstrate high thresholds compared with other measurement-based models realized with basic entangled resources and two-qubit fusion measurements. Its high tolerance to noise indicates that our practical construction offers a promising route to scalable quantum computing with quantum emitters and linear-optical elements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A graph-state based synthesis framework for Clifford isometries</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06928</link>
    <author>Timothée Goubault de Brugière, Simon Martiel, Christophe Vuillot</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We tackle the problem of Clifford isometry compilation, i.e, how to synthesize a Clifford isometry into an executable quantum circuit. We propose a simple framework for synthesis that only exploits the elementary properties of the Clifford group and one equation of the symplectic group. We highlight the versatility of our framework by showing that several normal forms of the literature are natural corollaries. We report an improvement of the two-qubit depth necessary for the execution of a Clifford circuit on an LNN architecture. We also apply our framework to the synthesis of graph states and the codiagonalization of Pauli rotations and we improve the 2-qubit count and 2-qubit depth of circuits taken from quantum chemistry experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>General guarantees for randomized benchmarking with random quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06181</link>
    <author>Markus Heinrich, Martin Kliesch, Ingo Roth</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In its many variants, randomized benchmarking (RB) is a broadly used technique for assessing the quality of gate implementations on quantum computers. A detailed theoretical understanding and general guarantees exist for the functioning and interpretation of RB protocols if the gates under scrutiny are drawn uniformly at random from a compact group. In contrast, many practically attractive and scalable RB protocols implement random quantum circuits with local gates randomly drawn from some gate-set. Despite their abundance in practice, for those non-uniform RB protocols, general guarantees under experimentally plausible assumptions are missing. In this work, we derive such guarantees for a large class of RB protocols for random circuits that we refer to as filtered RB. Prominent examples include linear cross-entropy benchmarking, character benchmarking, Pauli-noise tomography and variants of simultaneous RB. Building upon recent results for random circuits, we show that many relevant filtered RB schemes can be realized with random quantum circuits in linear depth, and we provide explicit small constants for common instances. We further derive general sample complexity bounds for filtered RB. We show filtered RB to be sample-efficient for several relevant groups, including protocols addressing higher-order cross-talk. Our theory for non-uniform filtered RB is, in principle, flexible enough to design new protocols for non-universal and analog quantum simulators.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Grothendieck inequalities characterize converses to the polynomial method</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08559</link>
    <author>Jop Briët, Francisco Escudero Gutiérrez, Sander Gribling</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A surprising 'converse to the polynomial method' of Aaronson et al. (CCC'16) shows that any bounded quadratic polynomial can be computed exactly in expectation by a 1-query algorithm up to a universal multiplicative factor related to the famous Grothendieck constant. Here we show that such a result does not generalize to quartic polynomials and 2-query algorithms, even when we allow for additive approximations. We also show that the additive approximation implied by their result is tight for bounded bilinear forms, which gives a new characterization of the Grothendieck constant in terms of 1-query quantum algorithms. Along the way we provide reformulations of the completely bounded norm of a form, and its dual norm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Bounds on Renyi entropy growth in many-body quantum systems</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.07444</link>
    <author>Zhengyan Darius Shi</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove rigorous bounds on the growth of $\alpha$-Renyi entropies $S_{\alpha}(t)$ (the Von Neumann entropy being the special case $\alpha = 1$) associated with any subsystem $A$ of a general lattice quantum many-body system with finite onsite Hilbert space dimension. For completely non-local Hamiltonians, we show that the instantaneous growth rates $|S'_{\alpha}(t)|$ (with $\alpha \neq 1$) can be exponentially larger than $|S'_1(t)|$ as a function of the subsystem size $|A|$. For $D$-dimensional systems with geometric locality, we prove bounds on $|S'_{\alpha}(t)|$ that depend on the decay rate of interactions with distance. When $\alpha = 1$, the bound is $|A|$-independent for all power-law decaying interactions $V(r) \sim r^{-w}$ with $w > 2D+1$. But for $\alpha > 1$, the bound is $|A|$-independent only when the interactions are finite-range or decay faster than $V(r) \sim e^{- c\, r^D}$ for some $c$ depending on the local Hilbert space dimension. Using similar arguments, we also prove bounds on $k$-local systems with or without geometric locality. A central theme of this work is that the value of $\alpha$ strongly influences the interplay between locality and entanglement growth. In other words, the Von Neumann entropy and the $\alpha$-Renyi entropies cannot be regarded as proxies for each other in studies of entanglement dynamics. We compare these bounds with analytic and numerical results on Hamiltonians with varying degrees of locality and find concrete examples that almost saturate the bound for non-local dynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Minimum Fourth-Order Trotterization Formula for a Time-Dependent Hamiltonian</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06788</link>
    <author>Tatsuhiko N. Ikeda, Asir Abrar, Isaac L. Chuang, Sho Sugiura</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>When a time propagator $e^{\delta t A}$ for duration $\delta t$ consists of two noncommuting parts $A=X+Y$, Trotterization approximately decomposes the propagator into a product of exponentials of $X$ and $Y$. Various Trotterization formulas have been utilized in quantum and classical computers, but much less is known for the Trotterization with the time-dependent generator $A(t)$. Its difficulty is that the propagator becomes a time-ordered exponential $\mathcal{T}\exp(\int_\mu^{\mu+\delta t}A(s)ds)$ for more than the second-order formula. Here, for $A(t)$ given by the sum of two operators $X$ and $Y$ with time-dependent coefficients $A(t) = x(t) X + y(t) Y$, we obtain a fourth-order Trotterization formula, whose error is $O(\delta t^5)$. The formula consists of seven exponentials of $X$ and $Y$, and we prove that there is no fourth-order Trotterization formula with fewer than seven exponentials. Its error consists of the contribution $\Gamma_5$ known for the time-independent formula plus a new contribution $\Upsilon_5$ which is intrinsic to the time dependence of $A(t)$. Finally, we numerically demonstrate that for the Hamiltonian tested our formula has errors as small as the time-dependent fourth-order Suzuki formula involving eleven exponentials.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>From time-reversal symmetry to quantum Bayes' rules</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08088</link>
    <author>Arthur J. Parzygnat, James Fullwood</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Bayes' rule $\mathbb{P}(B|A)\mathbb{P}(A)=\mathbb{P}(A|B)\mathbb{P}(B)$ is one of the simplest yet most profound, ubiquitous, and far-reaching results of classical probability theory, with applications in decision making, artificial intelligence, weather forecasts, betting strategies, and more generally statistical inference. Many attempts have been made to extend this rule to quantum systems, the significance of which we are only beginning to understand. In this work, we develop a systematic framework for defining Bayes' rule in the quantum setting, and we show that a vast majority of the proposed quantum Bayes' rules appearing in the literature are all instances of our definition. Moreover, our Bayes' rule is based upon a simple relationship between the notions of \emphstate over time and a time-reversal symmetry map, both of which are introduced here.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Non-local finite-depth circuits for constructing SPT states and quantum cellular automata</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.06844</link>
    <author>David T. Stephen, Arpit Dua, Ali Lavasani, Rahul Nandkishore</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Whether a given target state can be prepared by starting with a simple product state and acting with a finite-depth quantum circuit, is a key question in quantum condensed matter physics, quantum information, and quantum computation. It underpins classifications of topological phases, as well as the understanding of topological quantum codes, and has obvious relevance for device implementations. Traditionally, this question assumes that the quantum circuit is made up of unitary gates which are geometrically local. Inspired by the advent of noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices, we reconsider this question with $k$-local gates, i.e. gates that act on no more than $k$ degrees of freedom but are not restricted to be geometrically local. We show that symmetry-protected topological states (SPTs) can be produced by starting with a product state and acting with a finite-depth circuit of symmetric $k$-local gates, and are thus $k$-local trivial. These conclusions apply both to SPTs protected by global symmetries and subsystem symmetries, but seemingly not to higher-form symmetries. We also show that arbitrary translationally-invariant quantum cellular automata on periodic lattices in any dimension can be implemented by finite-depth $k$-local circuits. We conclude by discussing the implications for other phases, such as fracton phases, and surveying future directions. Our analysis opens a new experimentally motivated conceptual direction examining the feasibility of state preparation and the stability of phases without the assumption of geometric locality and has broad implications for condensed matter physics, quantum information, and quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classically Simulating Quantum Supremacy IQP Circuits trough a Random Graph Approach</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2212.08609</link>
    <author>Julien Codsi, John van de Wetering</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Supremacy is a demonstration of a computation by a quantum computer that can not be performed by the best classical computer in a reasonable time. A well-studied approach to demonstrating this on near-term quantum computers is to use random circuit sampling. It has been suggested that a good candidate for demonstrating quantum supremacy with random circuit sampling is to use \emphIQP circuits. These are quantum circuits where the unitary it implements is diagonal. In this paper we introduce improved techniques for classically simulating random IQP circuits. We find a simple algorithm to calculate an amplitude of an $n$-qubit IQP circuit with dense random two-qubit interactions in time $O(\frac{\log^2 n}{n} 2^n )$, which for sparse circuits (where each qubit interacts with $O(\log n)$ other qubits) runs in $o(2^n/\text{poly}(n))$ for any given polynomial. Using a more complicated stabiliser decomposition approach we improve the algorithm for dense circuits to $O\left(\frac{(\log n)^{4-\beta}}{n^{2-\beta}} 2^n \right)$ where $\beta \approx 0.396$. We benchmarked our algorithm and found that we can simulate up to 50-qubit circuits in a couple of minutes on a laptop. We estimate that 70-qubit circuits are within reach for a large computing cluster.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>