<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Foundations for learning from noisy quantum experiments</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.13691</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Steven T. Flammia, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding what can be learned from experiments is central to scientific progress. In this work, we use a learning-theoretic perspective to study the task of learning physical operations in a quantum machine when all operations (state preparation, dynamics, and measurement) are a priori unknown. We prove that, without any prior knowledge, if one can explore the full quantum state space by composing the operations, then every operation can be learned. When one cannot explore the full state space but all operations are approximately known and noise in Clifford gates is gate-independent, we find an efficient algorithm for learning all operations up to a single unlearnable parameter characterizing the fidelity of the initial state. For learning a noise channel on Clifford gates to a fixed accuracy, our algorithm uses quadratically fewer experiments than previously known protocols. Under more general conditions, the true description of the noise can be unlearnable; for example, we prove that no benchmarking protocol can learn gate-dependent Pauli noise on Clifford+T gates even under perfect state preparation and measurement. Despite not being able to learn the noise, we show that a noisy quantum computer that performs entangled measurements on multiple copies of an unknown state can yield a large advantage in learning properties of the state compared to a noiseless device that measures individual copies and then processes the measurement data using a classical computer. Concretely, we prove that noisy quantum computers with two-qubit gate error rate $\epsilon$ can achieve a learning task using $N$ copies of the state, while $N^{\Omega(1/\epsilon)}$ copies are required classically.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Preparing Arbitrary Continuous Functions in Quantum Registers With Logarithmic Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00519</link>
    <author>Arthur G. Rattew, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers will be able solve important problems with significant polynomial and exponential speedups over their classical counterparts, for instance in option pricing in finance, and in real-space molecular chemistry simulations. However, key applications can only achieve their potential speedup if their inputs are prepared efficiently. We effectively solve the important problem of efficiently preparing quantum states following arbitrary continuous (as well as more general) functions with complexity logarithmic in the desired resolution, and with rigorous error bounds. This is enabled by the development of a fundamental subroutine based off of the simulation of rank-1 projectors. Combined with diverse techniques from quantum information processing, this subroutine enables us to present a broad set of tools for solving practical tasks, such as state preparation, numerical integration of Lipschitz continuous functions, and superior sampling from probability density functions. As a result, our work has significant implications in a wide range of applications, for instance in financial forecasting, and in quantum simulation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Stability Experiments: The Overlooked Dual of Memory Experiments</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.13834</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>May 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Topological quantum computations are built on a foundation of two basic tasks: preserving logical observables through time and moving logical observables through space. Memory experiments, which check how well logical observables are preserved through time, are a well established benchmark. Strangely, there is no corresponding well established benchmark for moving logical observables through space. This paper tries to fill that gap with "stability experiments", which check how well a quantum error correction system can determine the product of a large region of stabilizers. Stability experiments achieve this by testing on a region that is locally a normal code but globally has a known product of stabilizers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Dictionaries without QRAM</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.13835</link>
    <author>Craig Gidney</author>
    <pubDate>May 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This paper presents an efficient gate-level implementation of a quantum dictionary: a data structure that can store a superposition of mappings from keys to values. The dictionary is stored as a fixed-length list of sorted address-value pairs, where the length of the list is the maximum number of entries that can be put in the dictionary. An addressed value can be extracted from (or injected into) the dictionary using $C \cdot (V + 2.5A) + O(V + A + C)$ expected Toffoli gates and $O(V + A)$ auxiliary qubits (where $C$ is the maximum capacity, $A$ is the address width, and $V$ is the value width).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Propagation of errors and quantitative quantum simulation with quantum advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.13644</link>
    <author>S. Flannigan, N. Pearson, G. H. Low, A. Buyskikh, I. Bloch, P. Zoller, M. Troyer, A. J. Daley</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The rapid development in hardware for quantum computing and simulation has led to much interest in problems where these devices can exceed the capabilities of existing classical computers and known methods. Approaching this for problems that go beyond testing the performance of a quantum device is an important step, and quantum simulation of many-body quench dynamics is one of the most promising candidates for early practical quantum advantage. We analyse the requirements for quantitatively reliable quantum simulation beyond the capabilities of existing classical methods for analogue quantum simulators with neutral atoms in optical lattices and trapped ions. Considering the primary sources of error in analogue devices and how they propagate after a quench in studies of the Hubbard or long-range transverse field Ising model, we identify the level of error expected in quantities we extract from experiments. We conclude for models that are directly implementable that regimes of practical quantum advantage are attained in current experiments with analogue simulators. We also identify the hardware requirements to reach the same level of accuracy with future fault-tolerant digital quantum simulation. Verification techniques are already available to test the assumptions we make here, and demonstrating these in experiments will be an important next step.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Divisible Codes for Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.13176</link>
    <author>Jingzhen Hu, Qingzhong Liang, Robert Calderbank</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Divisible codes are defined by the property that codeword weights share a common divisor greater than one. They are used to design signals for communications and sensing, and this paper explores how they can be used to protect quantum information as it is transformed by logical gates. Given a CSS code $\mathcal{C}$, we derive conditions that are both necessary and sufficient for a transversal diagonal physical operator $U_Z$ to preserve $\mathcal{C}$ and induce $U_L$. The group of $Z$-stabilizers in a CSS code $\mathcal{C}$ is determined by the dual of a classical $[n, k_1]$ binary code $\mathcal{C}_1$, and the group of $X$-stabilizers is determined by a classical $[n, k_2]$ binary code $\mathcal{C}_2$ that is contained in $\mathcal{C}_1$. The requirement that a diagonal physical operator $U_Z$ fixes a CSS code $\mathcal{C}$ leads to constraints on the congruence of weights in cosets of $\mathcal{C}_2$. These constraints are a perfect fit to divisible codes, and represent an opportunity to take advantage of the extensive literature on classical codes with two or three weights. We construct new families of CSS codes using cosets of the first order Reed Muller code defined by quadratic forms. We provide a simple alternative to the standard method of deriving the coset weight distributions (based on Dickson normal form) that may be of independent interest. Finally, we develop an approach to circumventing the Eastin-Knill Theorem which states that no QECC can implement a universal set of logical gates through transversal gates alone. The essential idea is to design stabilizer codes in layers, with $N_1$ inner qubits and $N_2$ outer qubits, and to assemble a universal set of fault tolerant gates on the inner qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>What is the temperature of a quantum state?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.00017</link>
    <author>Patryk Lipka-Bartosik, Martí Perarnau-Llobet, Nicolas Brunner</author>
    <pubDate>May 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Temperature is usually defined for physical systems at thermal equilibrium. Nevertheless one may wonder if it would be possible to attribute a meaningful notion of temperature to an arbitrary quantum state, beyond simply the thermal (Gibbs) state. In this work, we propose such a notion of temperature considering an operational task, inspired by the Zeroth Law of thermodynamics. Specifically, we define two effective temperatures for quantifying the ability of a quantum system to cool down or heat up a thermal environment. In this way we can associate an operationally meaningful notion of temperature to any quantum density matrix. We provide general expressions for these effective temperatures, for both single- and many-copy systems, establishing connections to concepts previously discussed in the literature. Finally, we consider a more sophisticated scenario where the heat exchange between the system and the thermal environment is assisted by a quantum reference frame. This leads to an effect of "coherent quantum catalysis", where the use of a coherent catalyst allows for exploiting quantum energetic coherences in the system, now leading to much colder or hotter effective temperatures.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Symbolic synthesis of Clifford circuits and beyond</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.14205</link>
    <author>Matthew Amy, Owen Bennett-Gibbs, Neil J. Ross</author>
    <pubDate>May 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Path sums are a convenient symbolic formalism for quantum operations with applications to the simulation, optimization, and verification of quantum protocols. Unlike quantum circuits, path sums are not limited to unitary operations, but can express arbitrary linear ones. Two problems, therefore, naturally arise in the study of path sums: the unitarity problem and the extraction problem. The former is the problem of deciding whether a given path sum represents a unitary operator. The latter is the problem of constructing a quantum circuit, given a path sum promised to represent a unitary operator. We show that the unitarity problem is co-NP-hard in general, but that it is in P when restricted to Clifford path sums. We then provide an algorithm to synthesize a Clifford circuit from a unitary Clifford path sum. The circuits produced by our extraction algorithm are of the form $C_1HC_2$, where $C_1$ and $C_2$ are Hadamard-free circuits and $H$ is a layer of Hadamard gates. We also provide a heuristic generalization of our extraction algorithm to arbitrary path sums. While this algorithm is not guaranteed to succeed, it often succeeds and typically produces natural looking circuits. Alongside applications to the optimization and decompilation of quantum circuits, we demonstrate the capability of our algorithm by synthesizing the standard quantum Fourier transform directly from a path sum.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient quantum algorithm for nonlinear reaction-diffusion equations and energy estimation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01141</link>
    <author>Dong An, Di Fang, Stephen Jordan, Jin-Peng Liu, Guang Hao Low, Jiasu Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Nonlinear differential equations exhibit rich phenomena in many fields but are notoriously challenging to solve. Recently, Liu et al. [1] demonstrated the first efficient quantum algorithm for dissipative quadratic differential equations under the condition $R < 1$, where $R$ measures the ratio of nonlinearity to dissipation using the $\ell_2$ norm. Here we develop an efficient quantum algorithm based on [1] for reaction-diffusion equations, a class of nonlinear partial differential equations (PDEs). To achieve this, we improve upon the Carleman linearization approach introduced in [1] to obtain a faster convergence rate under the condition $R_D < 1$, where $R_D$ measures the ratio of nonlinearity to dissipation using the $\ell_{\infty}$ norm. Since $R_D$ is independent of the number of spatial grid points $n$ while $R$ increases with $n$, the criterion $R_D<1$ is significantly milder than $R<1$ for high-dimensional systems and can stay convergent under grid refinement for approximating PDEs. As applications of our quantum algorithm we consider the Fisher-KPP and Allen-Cahn equations, which have interpretations in classical physics. In particular, we show how to estimate the mean square kinetic energy in the solution by postprocessing the quantum state that encodes it to extract derivative information.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A fast quantum algorithm for computing matrix permanent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.01328</link>
    <author>Joonsuk Huh</author>
    <pubDate>May 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Computing a matrix permanent is known to be a classically intractable problem. This paper presents the first polynomial time quantum algorithm for computing permanents of arbitrary $N$-dimensional square matrices with multiplicative error and additive error protocols. We transformed the well-known classical algorithm, Ryser's formula, into sums of quantum overlap integrals to develop the quantum algorithm. This requires $\mathcal{O}(N)$ and $\mathcal{O}(N^{3})$ evaluations of the real part of the quantum overlap integrals for real and complex matrices, respectively, with polynomial depth quantum circuits of $\mathcal{O}(N)$ qubits. The existence of the polynomial time multiplicative error estimation of a matrix permanent would strongly imply that quantum computers can access the #P-hard problem. Our quantum algorithm attains the milestone of opening a new direction in quantum computing and computational complexity theory. It could resolve crucial computational complexity issues like locating the bounded error quantum polynomial time (BQP) relative to the polynomial hierarchy, which has been a big complexity question. Depending on the size of a matrix norm of interest, we can also obtain an exponentially small additive error estimation and better estimation against Gurvits' classical sampling algorithm. The additive error protocol is practically implementable in noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices. Moreover, our quantum algorithm directly shows the computational complexity connection between the matrix permanent and the real-time partition function of the quantum Ising Hamiltonian.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>