<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>The XP Stabiliser Formalism: a Generalisation of the Pauli Stabiliser Formalism with Arbitrary Phases</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00103</link>
    <author>Mark A. Webster, Benjamin J. Brown, Stephen D. Bartlett</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose an extension to the Pauli stabiliser formalism that includes fractional $2\pi/N$ rotations around the $Z$ axis for some integer $N$. The resulting generalised stabiliser formalism - denoted the XP stabiliser formalism - allows for a wider range of states and codespaces to be represented. We describe the states which arise in the formalism, and demonstrate an equivalence between XP stabiliser states and 'weighted hypergraph states' - a generalisation of both hypergraph and weighted graph states. Given an arbitrary set of XP operators, we present algorithms for determining the codespace and logical operators for an XP code. Finally, we consider whether measurements of XP operators on XP codes can be classically simulated.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Is quantum advantage the right goal for quantum machine learning?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01340</link>
    <author>Maria Schuld, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Machine learning is frequently listed among the most promising applications for quantum computing. This is in fact a curious choice: Today's machine learning algorithms are notoriously powerful in practice, but remain theoretically difficult to study. Quantum computing, in contrast, does not offer practical benchmarks on realistic scales, and theory is the main tool we have to judge whether it could become relevant for a problem. In this perspective we explain why it is so difficult to say something about the practical power of quantum computers for machine learning with the tools we are currently using. We argue that these challenges call for a critical debate on whether quantum advantage and the narrative of "beating" classical machine learning should continue to dominate the literature the way it does, and provide a few examples for alternative research questions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Tanner codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.13641</link>
    <author>Anthony Leverrier, Gilles Zémor</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Tanner codes are long error correcting codes obtained from short codes and a graph, with bits on the edges and parity-check constraints from the short codes enforced at the vertices of the graph. Combining good short codes together with a spectral expander graph yields the celebrated expander codes of Sipser and Spielman, which are asymptotically good classical LDPC codes. In this work we apply this prescription to the left-right Cayley complex that lies at the heart of the recent construction of a $c^3$ locally testable code by Dinur et al. Specifically, we view this complex as two graphs that share the same set of edges. By defining a Tanner code on each of those graphs we obtain two classical codes that together define a quantum code. This construction can be seen as a simplified variant of the Panteleev and Kalachev asymptotically good quantum LDPC code, with improved estimates for its minimum distance. This quantum code is closely related to the Dinur et al. code in more than one sense: indeed, we prove a theorem that simultaneously gives a linearly growing minimum distance for the quantum code and recovers the local testability of the Dinur et al. code.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical Verification of Quantum Computations in Linear Time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.13997</link>
    <author>Jiayu Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the quantum computation verification problem, a quantum server wants to convince a client that the output of evaluating a quantum circuit $C$ is some result that it claims. This problem is considered very important both theoretically and practically in quantum computation [arXiv:1709.06984], [arXiv:1704.04487], [arXiv:1209.0449]. The client is considered to be limited in computational power, and one desirable property is that the client can be completely classical, which leads to the classical verification of quantum computation (CVQC) problem. In terms of total time complexity of both the client and the server, the fastest single-server CVQC protocol so far has complexity $O(poly(\kappa)|C|^3)$ where $|C|$ is the size of the circuit to be verified, given by Mahadev [arXiv:1804.01082]. In this work, by developing new techniques, we give a new CVQC protocol with complexity $O(poly(\kappa)|C|)$, which is significantly faster than existing protocols. Our protocol is secure in the quantum random oracle model [arXiv:1008.0931] assuming the existence of noisy trapdoor claw-free functions [arXiv:1804.00640], which are both extensively used assumptions in quantum cryptography. Along the way, we also give a new classical channel remote state preparation protocol for states in $\{|+_\theta\rangle=\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}(|0\rangle+e^{i\theta\pi/4}|1\rangle):\theta\in \{0,1\cdots 7\}\}$, another basic primitive in quantum cryptography. Our protocol allows for parallel verifiable preparation of $L$ independently random states in this form (up to a constant overall error and a possibly unbounded server-side isometry), and runs in only $O(poly(\kappa)L)$ time and constant rounds; for comparison, existing works (even for possibly simpler state families) all require very large or unestimated time and round complexities [arXiv:1904.06320][arXiv:1904.06303][arXiv:2201.13445][arXiv:2201.13430].</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Influence in Completely Bounded Block-multilinear Forms and Classical Simulation of Quantum Algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00212</link>
    <author>Nikhil Bansal, Makrand Sinha, Ronald de Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Aaronson-Ambainis conjecture (Theory of Computing '14) says that every low-degree bounded polynomial on the Boolean hypercube has an influential variable. This conjecture, if true, would imply that the acceptance probability of every $d$-query quantum algorithm can be well-approximated almost everywhere (i.e., on almost all inputs) by a $\mathrm{poly}(d)$-query classical algorithm. We prove a special case of the conjecture: in every completely bounded degree-$d$ block-multilinear form with constant variance, there always exists a variable with influence at least $1/\mathrm{poly}(d)$. In a certain sense, such polynomials characterize the acceptance probability of quantum query algorithms, as shown by Arunachalam, Briët and Palazuelos (SICOMP '19). As a corollary we obtain efficient classical almost-everywhere simulation for a particular class of quantum algorithms that includes for instance $k$-fold Forrelation. Our main technical result relies on connections to free probability theory.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The quantum low-rank approximation problem</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00811</link>
    <author>Nic Ezzell, Zoë Holmes, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a quantum version of the famous low-rank approximation problem. Specifically, we consider the distance $D(\rho,\sigma)$ between two normalized quantum states, $\rho$ and $\sigma$, where the rank of $\sigma$ is constrained to be at most $R$. For both the trace distance and Hilbert-Schmidt distance, we analytically solve for the optimal state $\sigma$ that minimizes this distance. For the Hilbert-Schmidt distance, the unique optimal state is $\sigma = \tau_R +N_R$, where $\tau_R = \Pi_R \rho \Pi_R$ is given by projecting $\rho$ onto its $R$ principal components with projector $\Pi_R$, and $N_R$ is a normalization factor given by $N_R = \frac{1- \text{Tr}(\tau_R)}{R}\Pi_R$. For the trace distance, this state is also optimal but not uniquely optimal, and we provide the full set of states that are optimal. We briefly discuss how our results have application for performing principal component analysis (PCA) via variational optimization on quantum computers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum circuit compilation and hybrid computation using Pauli-based computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01789</link>
    <author>F.C.R. Peres, Ernesto F. Galvão</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Pauli-based computation (PBC) is driven by a sequence of adaptively chosen, non-destructive measurements of Pauli observables. Any quantum circuit written in terms of the Clifford+$T$ gate set and having $t$ $T$ gates can be compiled into a PBC on $t$ qubits. Here we propose practical ways of implementing PBC as adaptive quantum circuits, and provide code to do the required classical side-processing. Our first scheme reduces the number of quantum gates to $O(t^2)$ (from a previous $O(t^3 / \log t)$ scaling) at the cost of one extra auxiliary qubit, with a possible reduction of the depth to $O(t \log t$), at the cost of $t$ additional auxiliary qubits (second scheme). We compile examples of random and hidden-shift quantum circuits into adaptive PBC circuits. We also simulate hybrid quantum computation, where a classical computer effectively extends the working memory of a small quantum computer by $k$ virtual qubits, at a cost exponential in $k$. Our results demonstrate the practical advantage of PBC techniques for circuit compilation and hybrid computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Boson bunching is not maximized by indistinguishable particles</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01306</link>
    <author>Benoît Seron, Leonardo Novo, Nicolas J. Cerf</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Boson bunching is amongst the most remarkable features of quantum physics. A celebrated example in optics is the Hong-Ou-Mandel effect, where the bunching of two photons arises from a destructive quantum interference between the trajectories where they both either cross a beam splitter or are reflected. This effect takes its roots in the indistinguishability of identical photons. Hence, it is generally admitted -- and experimentally verified -- that bunching vanishes as soon as photons can be distinguished, e.g., when they occupy distinct time bins or have different polarizations. Here we disproof this alleged straightforward link between indistinguishability and bunching by exploiting a recent finding in the theory of matrix permanents. We exhibit a family of optical circuits where the bunching of photons into two modes can be significantly boosted by making them partially distinguishable via an appropriate polarization pattern. This boosting effect is already visible in a 7-photon interferometric process, making the observation of this phenomenon within reach of current photonic technology. This unexpected behavior questions our understanding of multiparticle interference in the grey zone between indistinguishable bosons and classical particles.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal quantum dataset for learning a unitary transformation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00546</link>
    <author>Zhan Yu, Xuanqiang Zhao, Benchi Zhao, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Unitary transformations formulate the time evolution of quantum states. How to learn a unitary transformation efficiently is a fundamental problem in quantum machine learning. The most natural and leading strategy is to train a quantum machine learning model based on a quantum dataset. Although presence of more training data results in better models, using too much data reduces the efficiency of training. In this work, we solve the problem on the minimum size of sufficient quantum datasets for learning a unitary transformation exactly, which reveals the power and limitation of quantum data. First, we prove that the minimum size of dataset with pure states is $2^n$ for learning an $n$-qubit unitary transformation. To fully explore the capability of quantum data, we introduce a quantum dataset consisting of $n+1$ mixed states that are sufficient for exact training. The main idea is to simplify the structure utilizing decoupling, which leads to an exponential improvement on the size over the datasets with pure states. Furthermore, we show that the size of quantum dataset with mixed states can be reduced to a constant, which yields an optimal quantum dataset for learning a unitary. We showcase the applications of our results in oracle compiling and Hamiltonian simulation. Notably, to accurately simulate a 3-qubit one-dimensional nearest-neighbor Heisenberg model, our circuit only uses $48$ elementary quantum gates, which is significantly less than $4320$ gates in the circuit constructed by the Trotter-Suzuki product formula.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Maximum Flow and Minimum-Cost Flow in Almost-Linear Time</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.00671</link>
    <author>Li Chen, Rasmus Kyng, Yang P. Liu, Richard Peng, Maximilian Probst Gutenberg, Sushant Sachdeva</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give an algorithm that computes exact maximum flows and minimum-cost flows on directed graphs with $m$ edges and polynomially bounded integral demands, costs, and capacities in $m^{1+o(1)}$ time. Our algorithm builds the flow through a sequence of $m^{1+o(1)}$ approximate undirected minimum-ratio cycles, each of which is computed and processed in amortized $m^{o(1)}$ time using a dynamic data structure. Our framework extends to an algorithm running in $m^{1+o(1)}$ time for computing flows that minimize general edge-separable convex functions to high accuracy. This gives an almost-linear time algorithm for several problems including entropy-regularized optimal transport, matrix scaling, $p$-norm flows, and isotonic regression.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>