<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum many-body systems in thermal equilibrium</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08349</link>
    <author>Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The thermal or equilibrium ensemble is one of the most ubiquitous states of matter. For models comprised of many locally interacting quantum particles, it describes a wide range of physical situations, relevant to condensed matter physics, high energy physics, quantum chemistry and quantum computing, among others. We give a pedagogical overview of some of the most important universal features about the physics and complexity of these states, which have the locality of the Hamiltonian at its core. We focus on mathematically rigorous statements, many of them inspired by ideas and tools from quantum information theory. These include bounds on their correlations, the form of the subsystems, various statistical properties, and the performance of classical and quantum algorithms. We also include a summary of a few of the most important technical tools, as well as some self-contained proofs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Out-of-distribution generalization for learning quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10268</link>
    <author>Matthias C. Caro, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Nicholas Ezzell, Joe Gibbs, Andrew T. Sornborger, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Generalization bounds are a critical tool to assess the training data requirements of Quantum Machine Learning (QML). Recent work has established guarantees for in-distribution generalization of quantum neural networks (QNNs), where training and testing data are assumed to be drawn from the same data distribution. However, there are currently no results on out-of-distribution generalization in QML, where we require a trained model to perform well even on data drawn from a distribution different from the training distribution. In this work, we prove out-of-distribution generalization for the task of learning an unknown unitary using a QNN and for a broad class of training and testing distributions. In particular, we show that one can learn the action of a unitary on entangled states using only product state training data. We numerically illustrate this by showing that the evolution of a Heisenberg spin chain can be learned using only product training states. Since product states can be prepared using only single-qubit gates, this advances the prospects of learning quantum dynamics using near term quantum computers and quantum experiments, and further opens up new methods for both the classical and quantum compilation of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Complexity phase transitions in instantaneous quantum polynomial-time circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08898</link>
    <author>Chae-Yeun Park, Michael J. Kastoryano</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study a subclass of the Instantaneous Quantum Polynomial-time (IQP) circuit with a varying density of two-qubit gates. We identify two phase transitions as a function of the gate density. At the first transition, the coherent Gibbs representation of the output state transitions from quasilocal to extended, and becomes completely non-local after the second transition, resembling that of Haar random states. We introduce several new diagnostics to argue that learning the distribution after the first transition already becomes classically intractable, even though its output distribution is far from random. Our work thus opens a novel pathway for exploring quantum advantage in more practical setups whose outcome distributions are more structured than random states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Dynamical simulation via quantum machine learning with provable generalization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10269</link>
    <author>Joe Gibbs, Zoë Holmes, Matthias C. Caro, Nicholas Ezzell, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Lukasz Cincio, Andrew T. Sornborger, Patrick J. Coles</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Much attention has been paid to dynamical simulation and quantum machine learning (QML) independently as applications for quantum advantage, while the possibility of using QML to enhance dynamical simulations has not been thoroughly investigated. Here we develop a framework for using QML methods to simulate quantum dynamics on near-term quantum hardware. We use generalization bounds, which bound the error a machine learning model makes on unseen data, to rigorously analyze the training data requirements of an algorithm within this framework. This provides a guarantee that our algorithm is resource-efficient, both in terms of qubit and data requirements. Our numerics exhibit efficient scaling with problem size, and we simulate 20 times longer than Trotterization on IBMQ-Bogota.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical algorithms for many-body quantum systems at finite energies</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.09439</link>
    <author>Yilun Yang, J. Ignacio Cirac, Mari Carmen Bañuls</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We investigate quantum inspired algorithms to compute physical observables of quantum many-body systems at finite energies. They are based on the quantum algorithms proposed in [Lu et al. PRX Quantum 2, 020321 (2021)], which use the quantum simulation of the dynamics of such systems, as well as classical filtering and sampling techniques. Here, we replace the quantum simulation by standard classical methods based on matrix product states and operators. As a result, we can address significantly larger systems than those reachable by exact diagonalization or by other algorithms. We demonstrate the performance with spin chains up to 80 sites.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Scalable measures of magic for quantum computers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.10061</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, M. S. Kim</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Magic characterizes the degree of non-stabilizerness of quantum states. It is a crucial resource for quantum computing and a necessary condition for quantum advantage. However, quantifying magic beyond a few qubits has been a major challenge. Here, we introduce Bell magic to efficiently measure magic for any number of qubits. Our method can be easily implemented in experiments together with a cost-free error mitigation scheme. We experimentally demonstrate the transition of classically simulable stabilizer states into intractable quantum states on the IonQ quantum computer. For applications, Bell magic distinguishes stabilizer and magical states with a low measurement cost. Further, variational quantum algorithms can maximize the magic of quantum states via the shift-rule. Our results pave the way to benchmark the non-classical power of quantum computers, quantum simulators and quantum many-body systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Beyond i.i.d. in the Resource Theory of Asymmetry: An Information-Spectrum Approach for Quantum Fisher Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08439</link>
    <author>Koji Yamaguchi, Hiroyasu Tajima</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Energetic coherence is a valuable resource for various operations, including precise measurement of time and acceleration of quantum manipulations. Recently, it has been shown that the theory of energetic coherence, called the resource theory of asymmetry, has a thermodynamic structure, as do entanglement theory and quantum thermodynamics. In the so-called i.i.d. regime, where identical copies of a state are converted into identical copies of another state, the convertibility is entirely determined by the amount of energetic coherence measured by the quantum Fisher information (QFI). This fact means that QFI takes the place of entropy in thermodynamics and entanglement entropy in entanglement theory. So far, such a correspondence between energetic coherence and entropy is known only in the i.i.d. regime. In entanglement theory and quantum thermodynamics in the non-i.i.d. regime, entropy-related quantities based on the information-spectrum method reveal a non-equilibrium thermodynamics structure. Still, it has been an open question whether a similar structure exists for energetic coherence. In this Letter, we solve this problem by constructing an information-spectrum method applicable to the quantum Fisher information content. As a result, we establish a general theory of the pure-state convertibility in the non-i.i.d. regime of the resource theory of asymmetry. The given theory reveals a non-equilibrium thermodynamic structure of energetic coherence in the non-i.i.d. regime, based on QFI rather than entropy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Training variational quantum circuits with CoVaR: covariance root finding with classical shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08494</link>
    <author>Gregory Boyd, Bálint Koczor</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Exploiting near-term quantum computers and achieving practical value is a considerable and exciting challenge. Most prominent candidates as variational algorithms typically aim to find the ground state of a Hamiltonian by minimising a single classical (energy) surface which is sampled from by a quantum computer. Here we introduce a method we call CoVaR, an alternative means to exploit the power of variational circuits: We find eigenstates by finding joint roots of a polynomially growing number of properties of the quantum state as covariance functions between the Hamiltonian and an operator pool of our choice. The most remarkable feature of our CoVaR approach is that it allows us to fully exploit the extremely powerful classical shadow techniques, i.e., we simultaneously estimate a very large number $>10^4-10^7$ of covariances. We randomly select covariances and estimate analytical derivatives at each iteration applying a stochastic Levenberg-Marquardt step via a large but tractable linear system of equations that we solve with a classical computer. We prove that the cost in quantum resources per iteration is comparable to a standard gradient estimation, however, we observe in numerical simulations a very significant improvement by many orders of magnitude in convergence speed. CoVaR is directly analogous to stochastic gradient-based optimisations of paramount importance to classical machine learning while we also offload significant but tractable work onto the classical processor.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Fisher information-based incompatibility criterion for quantum channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.09963</link>
    <author>Qing-Hua Zhang, Ion Nechita</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new incompatibility criterion for quantum channels, based on the notion of (quantum) Fisher information. Our construction is based on a similar criterion for quantum measurements put forward by H.~Zhu. We then study the power of the incompatibility criterion in different scenarios. Firstly, we prove the first analytical conditions for the incompatibility of two Schur channels. Then, we study the incompatibility structure of a tuple of depolarizing channels, comparing the newly introduced criterion with the known results from asymmetric quantum cloning.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Volumetric Benchmarking of Error Mitigation with Qermit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.09725</link>
    <author>Cristina Cirstoiu, Silas Dilkes, Daniel Mills, Seyon Sivarajah, Ross Duncan</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The detrimental effect of noise accumulates as quantum computers grow in size. In the case where devices are too small or noisy to perform error correction, error mitigation may be used. Error mitigation does not increase the fidelity of quantum states, but instead aims to reduce the approximation error in quantities of concern, such as expectation values of observables. However, it is as yet unclear which circuit types, and devices of which characteristics, benefit most from the use of error mitigation. Here we develop a methodology to assess the performance of quantum error mitigation techniques. Our benchmarks are volumetric in design, and are performed on different superconducting hardware devices. Extensive classical simulations are also used for comparison. We use these benchmarks to identify disconnects between the predicted and practical performance of error mitigation protocols, and to identify the situations in which their use is beneficial. To perform these experiments, and for the benefit of the wider community, we introduce Qermit - an open source python package for quantum error mitigation. Qermit supports a wide range of error mitigation methods, is easily extensible and has a modular graph-based software design that facilitates composition of error mitigation protocols and subroutines.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>