<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Sample Complexity Lower Bound for Quantum State Tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11185</link>
    <author>Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that $\Omega(rd/\epsilon)$ copies of an unknown rank-$r$, dimension-$d$ quantum mixed state are necessary in order to learn a classical description with $1 - \epsilon$ fidelity. This improves upon the tomography lower bounds obtained by Haah, et al. and Wright.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13228</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas Breuckmann, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of non-trivial complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). We prove this conjecture by showing that the recently discovered families of constant-rate and linear-distance QLDPC codes correspond to NLTS local Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Laziness, Barren Plateau, and Noise in Machine Learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.09313</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Zexi Lin, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We define \emphlaziness to describe a large suppression of variational parameter updates for neural networks, classical or quantum. In the quantum case, the suppression is exponential in the number of qubits for randomized variational quantum circuits. We discuss the difference between laziness and \emphbarren plateau in quantum machine learning created by quantum physicists in \citemcclean2018barren for the flatness of the loss function landscape during gradient descent. We address a novel theoretical understanding of those two phenomena in light of the theory of neural tangent kernels. For noiseless quantum circuits, without the measurement noise, the loss function landscape is complicated in the overparametrized regime with a large number of trainable variational angles. Instead, around a random starting point in optimization, there are large numbers of local minima that are good enough and could minimize the mean square loss function, where we still have quantum laziness, but we do not have barren plateaus. However, the complicated landscape is not visible within a limited number of iterations, and low precision in quantum control and quantum sensing. Moreover, we look at the effect of noises during optimization by assuming intuitive noise models, and show that variational quantum algorithms are noise-resilient in the overparametrization regime. Our work precisely reformulates the quantum barren plateau statement towards a precision statement and justifies the statement in certain noise models, injects new hope toward near-term variational quantum algorithms, and provides theoretical connections toward classical machine learning. Our paper provides conceptual perspectives about quantum barren plateaus, together with discussions about the gradient descent dynamics in \citetogether.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical surrogates for quantum learning models</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11740</link>
    <author>Franz J. Schreiber, Jens Eisert, Johannes Jakob Meyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The advent of noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers has put the search for possible applications to the forefront of quantum information science. One area where hopes for an advantage through near-term quantum computers are high is quantum machine learning, where variational quantum learning models based on parametrized quantum circuits are discussed. In this work, we introduce the concept of a classical surrogate, a classical model which can be efficiently obtained from a trained quantum learning model and reproduces its input-output relations. As inference can be performed classically, the existence of a classical surrogate greatly enhances the applicability of a quantum learning strategy. However, the classical surrogate also challenges possible advantages of quantum schemes. As it is possible to directly optimize the ansatz of the classical surrogate, they create a natural benchmark the quantum model has to outperform. We show that large classes of well-analyzed re-uploading models have a classical surrogate. We conducted numerical experiments and found that these quantum models show no advantage in performance or trainability in the problems we analyze. This leaves only generalization capability as possible point of quantum advantage and emphasizes the dire need for a better understanding of inductive biases of quantum learning models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11246</link>
    <author>Cica Gustiani, Richard Meister, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational methods offer a highly promising route to exploiting quantum computers for chemistry tasks. Here we employ methods described in a sister paper to the present report, entitled ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits, in order to solve problems using adaptively evolving quantum circuits. Consistent with prior authors we find that this approach can outperform human-designed circuits such as the coupled-cluster or hardware-efficient ansätze, and we make comparisons for larger instances up to 14 qubits. Moreover we introduce a novel approach to constraining the circuit evolution in the physically relevant subspace, finding that this greatly improves performance and compactness of the circuits. We consider both static and dynamics properties of molecular systems. The emulation environments used is QuESTlink; all resources are open source and linked from this paper.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Computing Quantum Monte Carlo</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.10431</link>
    <author>Yukun Zhang, Yifei Huang, Jinzhao Sun, Dingshun Lv, Xiao Yuan</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computing and quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) are respectively the most powerful quantum and classical computing methods for understanding many-body quantum systems. Here, we propose a hybrid quantum-classical algorithm that integrates these two methods, inheriting their distinct features in efficient representation and manipulation of quantum states and overcoming their limitations. We introduce upper bounds to non-stoquaticity indicators (NSI), which measure the sign problem, the most notable limitation of QMC. We show that our algorithm could greatly mitigate the sign problem, which decreases NSIs with the assist of quantum computing. Meanwhile, the use of quantum Monte Carlo also increases the power of noisy quantum circuits, allowing accurate computation with much shallower circuits. We numerically test and verify the method for the N2 molecule (12 qubits) and the Hubbard model (16 qubits). Our work paves the way to solving practical problems with intermediate-scale and early-fault tolerant quantum computers, with potential applications in chemistry, condensed matter physics, materials, high energy physics, etc.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exploring ab initio machine synthesis of quantum circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11245</link>
    <author>Richard Meister, Cica Gustiani, Simon C. Benjamin</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Gate-level quantum circuits are often derived manually from higher level algorithms. While this suffices for small implementations and demonstrations, ultimately automatic circuit design will be required to realise complex algorithms using hardware-specific operations and connectivity. Here we explore methods for the ab initio creation of circuits within a machine, either a classical computer or a hybrid quantum-classical device. We consider a range of techniques including: methods for introducing new gate structures, optimisation of parameterised circuits and choices of cost functions, and efficient removal of low-value gates exploiting the quantum geometric tensor and other heuristics. Using these principles we tackle the tasks of automatic encoding of unitary processes and translation (recompilation) of a circuit from one form to another. Using emulated quantum computers with various noise-free gate sets we provide simple examples involving up to 10 qubits, corresponding to 20 qubits in the augmented space we use. Further applications of specific relevance to chemistry modelling are considered in a sister paper, 'Exploiting subspace constraints and ab initio variational methods for quantum chemistry'.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random tensor networks with nontrivial links</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.10482</link>
    <author>Newton Cheng, Cécilia Lancien, Geoff Penington, Michael Walter, Freek Witteveen</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Random tensor networks are a powerful toy model for understanding the entanglement structure of holographic quantum gravity. However, unlike holographic quantum gravity, their entanglement spectra are flat. It has therefore been argued that a better model consists of random tensor networks with link states that are not maximally entangled, i.e., have nontrivial spectra. In this work, we initiate a systematic study of the entanglement properties of these networks. We employ tools from free probability, random matrix theory, and one-shot quantum information theory to study random tensor networks with bounded and unbounded variation in link spectra, and in cases where a subsystem has one or multiple minimal cuts. If the link states have bounded spectral variation, the limiting entanglement spectrum of a subsystem with two minimal cuts can be expressed as a free product of the entanglement spectra of each cut, along with a Marchenko-Pastur distribution. For a class of states with unbounded spectral variation, analogous to semiclassical states in quantum gravity, we relate the limiting entanglement spectrum of a subsystem with two minimal cuts to the distribution of the minimal entanglement across the two cuts. In doing so, we draw connections to previous work on split transfer protocols, entanglement negativity in random tensor networks, and Euclidean path integrals in quantum gravity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Simple Proof of PreciseQMA = PSPACE</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.09230</link>
    <author>Yulong Li</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give an alternative proof of PreciseQMA = PSPACE, first proved by Fefferman and Lin (Innov. Theor. Comp. Sci. 2018), where PreciseQMA is the class Quantum Merlin-Arthur with inverse exponential completeness-soundness gap. We adapt the proof of Quantum Cook-Levin Theorem to prove the inclusion PSPACE in PreciseQMA.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Near-Term Quantum Algorithm for Computing Molecular and Materials Properties based on Recursive Variational Series Methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.09881</link>
    <author>Phillip W. K. Jensen, Peter D. Johnson, Alexander A. Kunitsa</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 22 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Determining properties of molecules and materials is one of the premier applications of quantum computing. A major question in the field is: how might we use imperfect near-term quantum computers to solve problems of practical value? We propose a quantum algorithm to estimate properties of molecules using near-term quantum devices. The method is a recursive variational series estimation method, where we expand an operator of interest in terms of Chebyshev polynomials, and evaluate each term in the expansion using a variational quantum algorithm. We test our method by computing the one-particle Green's function in energy domain and the autocorrelation function in time domain, finding some advantages to this approach over existing methods.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>