<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Unconditional Quantum Advantage for Sampling with Shallow Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.00995</link>
    <author>Adam Bene Watts, Natalie Parham</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 04 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Recent work by Bravyi, Gosset, and Koenig showed that there exists a search problem that a constant-depth quantum circuit can solve, but that any constant-depth classical circuit with bounded fan-in cannot. They also pose the question: can we achieve a similar proof of separation for an input-independent sampling task? In this paper, we show that the answer to this question is yes. We introduce a distribution $D_{n}$ and give a constant-depth, $n$ qubit, quantum circuit that samples from a distribution close to $D_{n}$ in total variation distance. For any $\delta < 1$ we also prove, unconditionally, that any classical circuit with bounded fan-in gates that takes as input $n + n^\delta$ uniformly random bits and produces output close to $D_{n}$ in total variation distance has depth $\Omega(\log \log n)$. This gives an unconditional proof that constant-depth quantum circuits can sample from distributions which can't be reproduced by constant-depth bounded fan-in classical circuits, even up to additive error. The distribution $D_n$ and classical circuit lower bounds are based on work of Viola, in which he shows a different (but related) distribution cannot be sampled from approximately by constant-depth bounded fan-in classical circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal lower bounds for Quantum Learning via Information Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02227</link>
    <author>Shima Bab Hadiashar, Ashwin Nayak, Pulkit Sinha</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Although a concept class may be learnt more efficiently using quantum samples as compared with classical samples in certain scenarios, Arunachalam and de Wolf (JMLR, 2018) proved that quantum learners are asymptotically no more efficient than classical ones in the quantum PAC and Agnostic learning models. They established lower bounds on sample complexity via quantum state identification and Fourier analysis. In this paper, we derive optimal lower bounds for quantum sample complexity in both the PAC and agnostic models via an information-theoretic approach. The proofs are arguably simpler, and the same ideas can potentially be used to derive optimal bounds for other problems in quantum learning theory. We then turn to a quantum analogue of the Coupon Collector problem, a classic problem from probability theory also of importance in the study of PAC learning. Arunachalam, Belovs, Childs, Kothari, Rosmanis, and de Wolf (TQC, 2020) characterized the quantum sample complexity of this problem up to constant factors. First, we show that the information-theoretic approach mentioned above provably does not yield the optimal lower bound. As a by-product, we get a natural ensemble of pure states in arbitrarily high dimensions which are not easily (simultaneously) distinguishable, while the ensemble has close to maximal Holevo information. Second, we discover that the information-theoretic approach yields an asymptotically optimal bound for an approximation variant of the problem. Finally, we derive a sharp lower bound for the Quantum Coupon Collector problem, with the exact leading order term, via the Holevo-Curlander bounds on the distinguishability of an ensemble. All the aspects of the Quantum Coupon Collector problem we study rest on properties of the spectrum of the associated Gram matrix, which may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tailoring fusion-based error correction for high thresholds to biased fusion failures</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.00019</link>
    <author>Kaavya Sahay, Jahan Claes, Shruti Puri</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce fault-tolerant (FT) architectures for error correction with the XZZX cluster state based on performing measurements of two-qubit Pauli operators $Z\otimes Z$ and $X\otimes X$, or fusions, on a collection of few-body entangled resource states. Our construction is tailored to be effective against noise that predominantly causes faulty $X\otimes X$ measurements during fusions. This feature offers practical advantage in linear optical quantum computing with dual-rail photonic qubits, where failed fusions only erase $X\otimes X$ measurement outcomes. By applying our construction to this platform, we find a record high FT threshold to fusion failures exceeding $25\%$ in the experimentally relevant regime of non-zero loss rate per photon, considerably simplifying hardware requirements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fault-tolerant error correction for a universal non-Abelian topological quantum computer at finite temperature</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.00054</link>
    <author>Alexis Schotte, Lander Burgelman, Guanyu Zhu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We study fault-tolerant error correction in a quantum memory constructed as a two-dimensional model of Fibonacci anyons on a torus, in the presence of thermal noise represented by pair-creation processes and measurement errors. The correction procedure is based on the cellular automaton decoders originating in the works of Gács and Harrington. Through numerical simulations, we observe that this code behaves fault-tolerantly and that threshold behavior is likely present. Hence, we provide strong evidence for the existence of a fault-tolerant universal non-Abelian topological quantum computer.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum simulation of exact electron dynamics can be more efficient than classical mean-field methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.01203</link>
    <author>Ryan Babbush, William J. Huggins, Dominic W. Berry, Shu Fay Ung, Andrew Zhao, David R. Reichman, Hartmut Neven, Andrew D. Baczewski, Joonho Lee</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 04 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum algorithms for simulating electronic ground states are slower than popular classical mean-field algorithms such as Hartree-Fock and density functional theory, but offer higher accuracy. Accordingly, quantum computers have been predominantly regarded as competitors to only the most accurate and costly classical methods for treating electron correlation. However, here we tighten bounds showing that certain first quantized quantum algorithms enable exact time evolution of electronic systems with exponentially less space and polynomially fewer operations in basis set size than conventional real-time time-dependent Hartree-Fock and density functional theory. Although the need to sample observables in the quantum algorithm reduces the speedup, we show that one can estimate all elements of the $k$-particle reduced density matrix with a number of samples scaling only polylogarithmically in basis set size. We also introduce a more efficient quantum algorithm for first quantized mean-field state preparation that is likely cheaper than the cost of time evolution. We conclude that quantum speedup is most pronounced for finite temperature simulations and suggest several practically important electron dynamics problems with potential quantum advantage.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>One-Way Ticket to Las Vegas and the Quantum Adversary</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.02003</link>
    <author>Aleksandrs Belovs, Duyal Yolcu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a new definition of quantum Las Vegas query complexity. We show that it is exactly equal to the quantum adversary bound. This is achieved by a new and very simple way of transforming a feasible solution to the adversary optimisation problem into a quantum query algorithm. This allows us to generalise the bound to include unidirectional access, multiple input oracles, and input oracles that are not unitary. As an application, we demonstrate a separation between unidirectional and bidirectional access to an input oracle for a rather natural unitary permutation inversion problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measuring out quasi-local integrals of motion from entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.01787</link>
    <author>B. Lu, C. Bertoni, S. J. Thomson, J. Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Quasi-local integrals of motion are a key concept underpinning the modern understanding of many-body localisation, an intriguing phenomenon in which interactions and disorder come together. Despite the existence of several numerical ways to compute them - and astoundingly in the light of the observation that much of the phenomenology of many properties can be derived from them - it is not obvious how to directly measure aspects of them in real quantum simulations; in fact, the smoking gun of their experimental observation is arguably still missing. In this work, we propose a way to extract the real-space properties of such quasi-local integrals of motion based on a spatially-resolved entanglement probe able to distinguish Anderson from many-body localisation from non-equilibrium dynamics. We complement these findings with a new rigorous entanglement bound and compute the relevant quantities using tensor networks. We demonstrate that the entanglement gives rise to a well-defined length scale that can be measured in experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On unital qubit channels</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.01358</link>
    <author>Chi-Kwong Li, Man-Duen Choi</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 05 2023</pubDate>
    <description>A canonical form for unital qubit channels under local unitary transforms is obtained. In particular, it is shown that the eigenvalues of the Choi matrix of a unital quantum channel are complete invariant of the canonical form. It follows immediately that every unital qubit channel is the average of four unitary channels. More generally, a unital qubit channel can be expressed as the convex combination of unitary channels with convex coefficients $p_1, \dots, p_m$ as long as $(p_1, \dots, p_m)$ is majorized by the vector of eigenvalues of the Choi matrix of the channel. By the fact that every unital map $\Phi$ on $2\times 2$ matrices preserving trace and Hermitian matrices corresponds to a linear map $\phi$ on ${\mathbb R}^3$ that will transform the Bloch (unit) sphere in ${\mathbb R}^3$ to an ellipsoid ${\mathcal E}$, it is shown that $\Phi$ is a unital qubit channel if and only if $\phi$ is a convex combination of special orthogonal matrices.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimal one-shot entanglement sharing</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.01781</link>
    <author>Vikesh Siddhu, John Smolin</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 06 2023</pubDate>
    <description>Sharing entanglement across quantum interconnects is fundamental for quantum information processing. We discuss a practical setting where this interconnect, modeled by a quantum channel, is used once with the aim of sharing high fidelity entanglement. For any channel, we provide methods to easily find both this maximum fidelity and optimal inputs that achieve it. Unlike most metrics for sharing entanglement, this maximum fidelity can be shown to be multiplicative. This ensures a complete understanding in the sense that the maximum fidelity and optimal inputs found in our one-shot setting extend even when the channel is used multiple times, possibly with other channels. Optimal inputs need not be fully entangled. We find the minimum entanglement in these optimal inputs can even vary discontinuously with channel noise. Generally, noise parameters are hard to identify and remain unknown for most channels. However, for all qubit channels with qubit environments, we provide a rigorous noise parametrization which we explain in-terms of no-cloning. This noise parametrization and a channel representation we call the standard Kraus decomposition have pleasing properties that make them both useful more generally.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matching upper bounds on symmetric predicates in quantum communication complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.00370</link>
    <author>Daiki Suruga</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 03 2023</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we focus on the quantum communication complexity of functions of the form $f \circ G = f(G(X_1, Y_1), \ldots, G(X_n, Y_n))$ where $f: \{0, 1\}^n \to \{0, 1\}$ is a symmetric function, $G: \{0, 1\}^j \times \{0, 1\}^k \to \{0, 1\}$ is any function and Alice (resp. Bob) is given $(X_i)_{i \leq n}$ (resp. $(Y_i)_{i \leq n}$). Recently, Chakraborty et al. [STACS 2022] showed that the quantum communication complexity of $f \circ G$ is $O(Q(f)\mathrm{QCC}_\mathrm{E}(G))$ when the parties are allowed to use shared entanglement, where $Q(f)$ is the query complexity of $f$ and $\mathrm{QCC}_\mathrm{E}(G)$ is the exact communication complexity of $G$. In this paper, we first show that the same statement holds \emphwithout shared entanglement, which generalizes their result. Based on the improved result, we next show tight upper bounds on $f \circ \mathrm{AND}_2$ for any symmetric function $f$ (where $\textrm{AND}_2 : \{0, 1\} \times \{0, 1\} \to \{0, 1\}$ denotes the 2-bit AND function) in both models: with shared entanglement and without shared entanglement. This matches the well-known lower bound by Razborov~[Izv. Math. 67(1) 145, 2003] when shared entanglement is allowed and improves Razborov's bound when shared entanglement is not allowed.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>