<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Time-energy uncertainty relation for noisy quantum metrology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13707</link>
    <author>Philippe Faist, Mischa P. Woods, Victor V. Albert, Joseph M. Renes, Jens Eisert, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Detection of weak forces and precise measurement of time are two of the many applications of quantum metrology to science and technology. We consider a quantum system initialized in a pure state and whose evolution is goverened by a Hamiltonian $H$; a measurement can later estimate the time $t$ for which the system has evolved. In this work, we introduce and study a fundamental trade-off which relates the amount by which noise reduces the accuracy of a quantum clock to the amount of information about the energy of the clock that leaks to the environment. Specifically, we consider an idealized scenario in which Alice prepares an initial pure state of the clock, allows the clock to evolve for a time $t$ that is not precisely known, and then transmits the clock through a noisy channel to Bob. The environment (Eve) receives any information that is lost. We prove that Bob's loss of quantum Fisher information (QFI) about $t$ is equal to Eve's gain of QFI about a complementary energy parameter. We also prove a more general trade-off that applies when Bob and Eve wish to estimate the values of parameters associated with two non-commuting observables. We derive the necessary and sufficient conditions for the accuracy of the clock to be unaffected by the noise. These are a subset of the Knill-Laflamme error-correction conditions; states satisfying these conditions are said to form a metrological code. We provide a scheme to construct metrological codes in the stabilizer formalism. We show that there are metrological codes that cannot be written as a quantum error-correcting code with similar distance in which the Hamiltonian acts as a logical operator, potentially offering new schemes for constructing states that do not lose any sensitivity upon application of a noisy channel. We discuss applications of our results to sensing using a many-body state subject to erasure or amplitude-damping noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matchgate Shadows for Fermionic Quantum Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13723</link>
    <author>Kianna Wan, William J. Huggins, Joonho Lee, Ryan Babbush</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>"Classical shadows" are estimators of an unknown quantum state, constructed from suitably distributed random measurements on copies of that state [Nature Physics 16, 1050-1057]. Here, we analyze classical shadows obtained using random matchgate circuits, which correspond to fermionic Gaussian unitaries. We prove that the first three moments of the Haar distribution over the continuous group of matchgate circuits are equal to those of the discrete uniform distribution over only the matchgate circuits that are also Clifford unitaries; thus, the latter forms a "matchgate 3-design." This implies that the classical shadows resulting from the two ensembles are functionally equivalent. We show how one can use these matchgate shadows to efficiently estimate inner products between an arbitrary quantum state and fermionic Gaussian states, as well as the expectation values of local fermionic operators and various other quantities, thus surpassing the capabilities of prior work. As a concrete application, this enables us to apply wavefunction constraints that control the fermion sign problem in the quantum-classical auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm (QC-AFQMC) [Nature 603, 416-420], without the exponential post-processing cost incurred by the original approach.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lower bounds for learning quantum states with single-copy measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14438</link>
    <author>Angus Lowe, Ashwin Nayak</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the problems of quantum tomography and shadow tomography using measurements performed on individual, identical copies of an unknown $d$-dimensional state. We first revisit a known lower bound due to Haah et al. (2017) on quantum tomography with accuracy $\epsilon$ in trace distance, when the measurements choices are independent of previously observed outcomes (i.e., they are nonadaptive). We give a succinct proof of this result. This leads to stronger lower bounds when the learner uses measurements with a constant number of outcomes. In particular, this rigorously establishes the optimality of the folklore ``Pauli tomography" algorithm in terms of its sample complexity. We also derive novel bounds of $\Omega(r^2 d/\epsilon^2)$ and $\Omega(r^2 d^2/\epsilon^2)$ for learning rank $r$ states using arbitrary and constant-outcome measurements, respectively, in the nonadaptive case. In addition to the sample complexity, a resource of practical significance for learning quantum states is the number of different measurements used by an algorithm. We extend our lower bounds to the case where the learner performs possibly adaptive measurements from a fixed set of $\exp(O(d))$ measurements. This implies in particular that adaptivity does not give us any advantage using single-copy measurements that are efficiently implementable. We also obtain a similar bound in the case where the goal is to predict the expectation values of a given sequence of observables, a task known as shadow tomography. Finally, in the case of adaptive, single-copy measurements implementable with polynomial-size circuits, we prove that a straightforward strategy based on computing sample means of the given observables is optimal.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simulating quantum circuits using efficient tensor network contraction algorithms with subexponential upper bound</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01498</link>
    <author>Thorsten B. Wahl, Sergii Strelchuk</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive a rigorous upper bound on the classical computation time of finite-ranged tensor network contractions in $d \geq 2$ dimensions. By means of the Sphere Separator Theorem, we are able to take advantage of the structure of quantum circuits to speed up contractions to show that quantum circuits of single-qubit and finite-ranged two-qubit gates can be classically simulated in subexponential time in the number of gates. In many practically relevant cases this beats standard simulation schemes. Moreover, our algorithm leads to speedups of several orders of magnitude over naive contraction schemes for two-dimensional quantum circuits on as little as an $8 \times 8$ lattice. We obtain similarly efficient contraction schemes for Google's Sycamore-type quantum circuits, instantaneous quantum polynomial-time circuits and non-homogeneous (2+1)-dimensional random quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fast erasure decoder for a class of quantum LDPC codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01002</link>
    <author>Nicholas Connolly, Vivien Londe, Anthony Leverrier, Nicolas Delfosse</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We propose a decoder for the correction of erasures with hypergraph product codes, which form one of the most popular families of quantum LDPC codes. Our numerical simulations show that this decoder provides a close approximation of the maximum likelihood decoder that can be implemented in O(N^2) bit operations where N is the length of the quantum code. A probabilistic version of this decoder can be implemented in O(N^1.5) bit operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exact and efficient Lanczos method on a quantum computer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.00567</link>
    <author>William Kirby, Mario Motta, Antonio Mezzacapo</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an algorithm that uses block encoding on a quantum computer to exactly construct a Krylov space, which can be used as the basis for the Lanczos method to estimate extremal eigenvalues of Hamiltonians. While the classical Lanczos method has exponential cost in the system size to represent the Krylov states for quantum systems, our efficient quantum algorithm achieves this in polynomial time and memory. The construction presented is exact in the sense that the resulting Krylov space is identical to that of the Lanczos method, so the only approximation with respect to the Lanczos method is due to finite sample noise. This is possible because, unlike previous quantum versions of the Lanczos method, our algorithm does not require simulating real or imaginary time evolution. We provide an explicit error bound for the resulting ground state energy estimate in the presence of noise. For this method to be successful, the only requirement on the input problem is that the overlap of the initial state with the true ground state must be $\Omega(1/\text{poly}(n))$ for $n$ qubits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14280</link>
    <author>Matthew P. A. Fisher, Vedika Khemani, Adam Nahum, Sagar Vijay</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum circuits -- built from local unitary gates and local measurements -- are a new playground for quantum many-body physics and a tractable setting to explore universal collective phenomena far-from-equilibrium. These models have shed light on longstanding questions about thermalization and chaos, and on the underlying universal dynamics of quantum information and entanglement. In addition, such models generate new sets of questions and give rise to phenomena with no traditional analog, such as new dynamical phases in quantum systems that are monitored by an external observer. Quantum circuit dynamics is also topical in view of experimental progress in building digital quantum simulators that allow control of precisely these ingredients. Randomness in the circuit elements allows a high level of theoretical control, with a key theme being mappings between real-time quantum dynamics and effective classical lattice models or dynamical processes. Many of the universal phenomena that can be identified in this tractable setting apply to much wider classes of more structured many-body dynamics.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Data Center: Theories and Applications</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14336</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Connor T. Hann, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In this paper, we propose the Quantum Data Center (QDC), an architecture combining Quantum Random Access Memory (QRAM) and quantum networks. We give a precise definition of QDC, and discuss its possible realizations and extensions. We discuss applications of QDC in quantum computation, quantum communication, and quantum sensing, with a primary focus on QDC for $T$-gate resources, QDC for multi-party private quantum communication, and QDC for distributed sensing through data compression. We show that QDC will provide efficient, private, and fast services as a future version of data centers.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fermionic tomography and learning</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.14787</link>
    <author>Bryan O'Gorman</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shadow tomography via classical shadows is a state-of-the-art approach for estimating properties of a quantum state. We present a simplified, combinatorial analysis of a recently proposed instantiation of this approach based on the ensemble of unitaries that are both fermionic Gaussian and Clifford. Using this analysis, we derive a corrected expression for the variance of the estimator. We then show how this leads to efficient estimation protocols for the fidelity with a pure fermionic Gaussian state (provably) and for an $X$-like operator of the form ($|\mathbf 0\rangle\langle\psi|$ + h.c.) (via numerical evidence). We also construct much smaller ensembles of measurement bases that yield the exact same quantum channel, which may help with compilation. We use these tools to show that an $n$-electron, $m$-mode Slater determinant can be learned to within $\epsilon$ fidelity given $O(n^2 m^7 \log(m / \delta) / \epsilon^2)$ samples of the Slater determinant.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Techniques for combining fast local decoders with global decoders under circuit-level noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01178</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Luis Goncalves, Prasahnt Sivarajah, Eric Peterson, Sebastian Grimberg</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Implementing algorithms on a fault-tolerant quantum computer will require fast decoding throughput and latency times to prevent an exponential increase in buffer times between the applications of gates. In this work we begin by quantifying these requirements. We then introduce the construction of local neural network (NN) decoders using three-dimensional convolutions. These local decoders are adapted to circuit-level noise and can be applied to surface code volumes of arbitrary size. Their application removes errors arising from a certain number of faults, which serves to substantially reduce the syndrome density. Remaining errors can then be corrected by a global decoder, such as Blossom or Union Find, with their implementation significantly accelerated due to the reduced syndrome density. However, in the circuit-level setting, the corrections applied by the local decoder introduce many vertical pairs of highlighted vertices. To obtain a low syndrome density in the presence of vertical pairs, we consider a strategy of performing a syndrome collapse which removes many vertical pairs and reduces the size of the decoding graph used by the global decoder. We also consider a strategy of performing a vertical cleanup, which consists of removing all local vertical pairs prior to implementing the global decoder. Lastly, we estimate the cost of implementing our local decoders on Field Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGAs).</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>