<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Equivalence between fermion-to-qubit mappings in two spatial dimensions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05153</link>
    <author>Yu-An Chen, Yijia Xu</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We argue that all locality-preserving mappings between fermionic observables and Pauli matrices on a two-dimensional lattice can be generated from the exact bosonization in Ref. [1], whose gauge constraints project onto the subspace of the toric code with emergent fermions. Starting from the exact bosonization and applying Clifford finite-depth generalized local unitary (gLU) transformation, we can achieve all possible fermion-to-qubit mappings (up to the re-pairing of Majorana fermions). In particular, we discover a new super-compact encoding using 1.25 qubits per fermion on the square lattice, which is lower than any method in the literature. We prove the existence of fermion-to-qubit mappings with qubit-fermion ratios $r=1+ \frac{1}{2k}$ for positive integers $k$, where the proof utilizes the trivialness of quantum cellular automata (QCA) in two spatial dimensions. When the ratio approaches 1, the fermion-to-qubit mapping reduces to the 1d Jordan-Wigner transformation along a certain path in the two-dimensional lattice. Finally, we explicitly demonstrate that the Bravyi-Kitaev superfast simulation, the Verstraete-Cirac auxiliary method, Kitaev's exactly solved model, the Majorana loop stabilizer codes, and the compact fermion-to-qubit mapping can all be obtained from the exact bosonization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A circuit-level protocol and analysis for twist-based lattice surgery</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05678</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Lattice surgery is a measurement-based technique for performing fault-tolerant quantum computation in two dimensions. When using the surface code, the most general lattice surgery operations require lattice irregularities called twist defects. However, implementing twist-based lattice surgery may require additional resources, such as extra device connectivity, and could lower the threshold and overall performance for the surface code. Here we provide an explicit twist-based lattice surgery protocol and its requisite connectivity layout. We also provide new stabilizer measurement circuits for measuring twist defects which are compatible with our chosen gate scheduling. We undertake the first circuit-level error correction simulations during twist-based lattice surgery using a biased depolarizing noise model. Our results indicate a slight decrease in the threshold for timelike logical failures compared to lattice surgery protocols with no twist defects in the bulk. However, comfortably below threshold (i.e. with CNOT infidelities below $5 \times 10^{-3}$), the performance degradation is mild and in fact preferable over proposed alternative twist-free schemes. Lastly, we provide an efficient scheme for measuring $Y$ operators along boundaries of surface codes which bypasses certain steps that were required in previous schemes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Algorithms for Approximating Quantum Partition Functions at Low Temperature</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06533</link>
    <author>Tyler Helmuth, Ryan L. Mann</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish an efficient approximation algorithm for the partition functions of a class of quantum spin systems at low temperature, which can be viewed as stable quantum perturbations of classical spin systems. Our algorithm is based on combining the contour representation of quantum spin systems of this type due to Borgs, Kotecký, and Ueltschi with the algorithmic framework developed by Helmuth, Perkins, and Regts, and Borgs et al.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Depth optimization of CZ, CNOT, and Clifford circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05215</link>
    <author>Dmitri Maslov, Ben Zindorf</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We seek to develop better upper bound guarantees on the depth of quantum CZ gate, CNOT gate, and Clifford circuits than those reported previously. We focus on the number of qubits $n\,{\leq}\,$1,345,000 [1], which represents the most practical use case. Our upper bound on the depth of CZ circuits is $\lfloor n/2 + 0.4993{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.0191{\cdot}\log(n) - 10.9139\rfloor$, improving best known depth by a factor of roughly 2. We extend the constructions used to prove this upper bound to obtain depth upper bound of $\lfloor n + 1.9496{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 3.5075{\cdot}\log(n) - 23.4269 \rfloor$ for CNOT gate circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $4/3$ over state of the art, and depth upper bound of $\lfloor 2n + 2.9487{\cdot}\log^2(n) + 8.4909{\cdot}\log(n) - 44.4798\rfloor$ for Clifford circuits, offering an improvement by a factor of roughly $5/3$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum networks self-test all entangled states</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05032</link>
    <author>Ivan Šupić, Joseph Bowles, Marc-Olivier Renou, Antonio Acín, Matty J. Hoban</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Certifying quantum properties with minimal assumptions is a fundamental problem in quantum information science. Self-testing is a method to infer the underlying physics of a quantum experiment only from the measured statistics. While all bipartite pure entangled states can be self-tested, little is known about how to self-test quantum states of an arbitrary number of systems. Here, we introduce a framework for network-assisted self-testing and use it to self-test any pure entangled quantum state of an arbitrary number of systems. The scheme requires the preparation of a number of singlets that scales linearly with the number of systems, and the implementation of standard projective and Bell measurements, all feasible with current technology. When all the network constraints are exploited, the obtained self-testing certification is stronger than what is achievable in any Bell-type scenario. Our work does not only solve an open question in the field, but also shows how properly designed networks offer new opportunities for the certification of quantum phenomena.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cut query algorithms with star contraction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05674</link>
    <author>Simon Apers, Yuval Efron, Paweł Gawrychowski, Troy Lee, Sagnik Mukhopadhyay, Danupon Nanongkai</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the complexity of determining the edge connectivity of a simple graph with cut queries. We show that (i) there is a bounded-error randomized algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $O(n)$ cut queries, and (ii) there is a bounded-error quantum algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $\~O(\sqrt{n})$ cut queries. We prove these results using a new technique called "star contraction" to randomly contract edges of a graph while preserving non-trivial minimum cuts. In star contraction vertices randomly contract an edge incident on a small set of randomly chosen vertices. In contrast to the related 2-out contraction technique of Ghaffari, Nowicki, and Thorup [SODA'20], star contraction only contracts vertex-disjoint star subgraphs, which allows it to be efficiently implemented via cut queries. The $O(n)$ bound from item (i) was not known even for the simpler problem of connectivity, and improves the $O(n\log^3 n)$ bound by Rubinstein, Schramm, and Weinberg [ITCS'18]. The bound is tight under the reasonable conjecture that the randomized communication complexity of connectivity is $\Omega(n\log n)$, an open question since the seminal work of Babai, Frankl, and Simon [FOCS'86]. The bound also excludes using edge connectivity on simple graphs to prove a superlinear randomized query lower bound for minimizing a symmetric submodular function. Item (ii) gives a nearly-quadratic separation with the randomized complexity and addresses an open question of Lee, Santha, and Zhang [SODA'21]. The algorithm can also be viewed as making $\~O(\sqrt{n})$ matrix-vector multiplication queries to the adjacency matrix. Finally, we demonstrate the use of star contraction outside of the cut query setting by designing a one-pass semi-streaming algorithm for computing edge connectivity in the vertex arrival setting. This contrasts with the edge arrival setting where two passes are required.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Uniform continuity bound for sandwiched Rényi conditional entropy</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05534</link>
    <author>Ashutosh Marwah, Frédéric Dupuis</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We prove a simple uniform continuity bound for the sandwiched Rényi conditional entropy for $\alpha \in [1/2, 1) \cup (1, \infty]$, which is independent of the dimension of the conditioning system.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the Consilience between QBism and Phenomenology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.04734</link>
    <author>Hans Christian von Baeyer</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Two decades after its creation, the interpretation of quantum mechanics called QBism is entering a new phase. Since it shares a personalist, subjective world-view with phenomenology, the philosophical study of human experience, there is a growing interest in the relationship between the two subjects. I call attention to the little-known philosopher Samuel Todes, whose phenomenology focused on the essential role of the human body in our understanding of the world. After reviewing this radical proposal, and illustrating it with some examples, I recommend it as an interesting mediator between the communities of physicists and phenomenologists. In addition, I argue that it may prove useful for promoting the public understanding of QBism.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Test-measured Rényi divergences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05477</link>
    <author>Milán Mosonyi, Fumio Hiai</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>One possibility of defining a quantum Rényi $\alpha$-divergence of two quantum states is to optimize the classical Rényi $\alpha$-divergence of their post-measurement probability distributions over all possible measurements (measured Rényi divergence), and maybe regularize these quantities over multiple copies of the two states (regularized measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence). A key observation behind the theorem for the strong converse exponent of asymptotic binary quantum state discrimination is that the regularized measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence coincides with the sandwiched Rényi $\alpha$-divergence when $\alpha>1$. Moreover, it also follows from the same theorem that to achieve this, it is sufficient to consider $2$-outcome measurements (tests) for any number of copies (this is somewhat surprising, as achieving the measured Rényi $\alpha$-divergence for $n$ copies might require a number of measurement outcomes that diverges in $n$, in general). In view of this, it seems natural to expect the same when $\alpha<1$; however, we show that this is not the case. In fact, we show that even for commuting states (classical case) the regularized quantity attainable using $2$-outcome measurements is in general strictly smaller than the Rényi $\alpha$-divergence (which is unique in the classical case). In the general quantum case this shows that the above ``regularized test-measured'' Rényi $\alpha$-divergence is not even a quantum extension of the classical Rényi divergence when $\alpha<1$, in sharp contrast to the $\alpha>1$ case.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decoding techniques applied to the compilation of CNOT circuits for NISQ architectures</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.06457</link>
    <author>Timothée Goubault de Brugière, Marc Baboulin, Benoît Valiron, Simon Martiel, Cyril Allouche</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Current proposals for quantum compilers require the synthesis and optimization of linear reversible circuits and among them CNOT circuits. Since these circuits represent a significant part of the cost of running an entire quantum circuit, we aim at reducing their size. In this paper we present a new algorithm for the synthesis of CNOT circuits based on the solution of the syndrome decoding problem. Our method addresses the case of ideal hardware with an all-to-all qubit connectivity and the case of near-term quantum devices with restricted connectivity. For both cases, we present benchmarks showing that our algorithm outperforms existing algorithms.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>