<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Computational advantage of quantum random sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04079</link>
    <author>Dominik Hangleiter, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum random sampling is the leading proposal for demonstrating a computational advantage of quantum computers over classical computers. Recently, first large-scale implementations of quantum random sampling have arguably surpassed the boundary of what can be simulated on existing classical hardware. In this article, we comprehensively review the theoretical underpinning of quantum random sampling in terms of computational complexity and verifiability, as well as the practical aspects of its experimental implementation using superconducting and photonic devices and its classical simulation. We discuss in detail open questions in the field and provide perspectives for the road ahead, including potential applications of quantum random sampling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The learnability of Pauli noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06362</link>
    <author>Senrui Chen, Yunchao Liu, Matthew Otten, Alireza Seif, Bill Fefferman, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, several noise benchmarking algorithms have been developed to characterize noisy quantum gates on today's quantum devices. A well-known issue in benchmarking is that not everything about quantum noise is learnable due to the existence of gauge freedom, leaving open the question of what information about noise is learnable and what is not, which has been unclear even for a single CNOT gate. Here we give a precise characterization of the learnability of Pauli noise channels attached to Clifford gates, showing that learnable information corresponds to the cycle space of the pattern transfer graph of the gate set, while unlearnable information corresponds to the cut space. This implies the optimality of cycle benchmarking, in the sense that it can learn all learnable information about Pauli noise. We experimentally demonstrate noise characterization of IBM's CNOT gate up to 2 unlearnable degrees of freedom, for which we obtain bounds using physical constraints. In addition, we give an attempt to characterize the unlearnable information by assuming perfect initial state preparation. However, based on the experimental data, we conclude that this assumption is inaccurate as it yields unphysical estimates, and we obtain a lower bound on state preparation noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tight Bounds for State Tomography with Incoherent Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05265</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Brice Huang, Jerry Li, Allen Liu, Mark Sellke</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the classic question of state tomography: given copies of an unknown quantum state $\rho\in\mathbb{C}^{d\times d}$, output $\widehat{\rho}$ for which $\|\rho - \widehat{\rho}\|_{\mathsf{tr}} \le \varepsilon$. When one is allowed to make coherent measurements entangled across all copies, $\Theta(d^2/\varepsilon^2)$ copies are necessary and sufficient [Haah et al. '17, O'Donnell-Wright '16]. Unfortunately, the protocols achieving this rate incur large quantum memory overheads that preclude implementation on current or near-term devices. On the other hand, the best known protocol using incoherent (single-copy) measurements uses $O(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17], and multiple papers have posed it as an open question to understand whether or not this rate is tight. In this work, we fully resolve this question, by showing that any protocol using incoherent measurements, even if they are chosen adaptively, requires $\Omega(d^3/\varepsilon^2)$ copies, matching the upper bound of [Kueng-Rauhut-Terstiege '17]. We do so by a new proof technique which directly bounds the "tilt" of the posterior distribution after measurements, which yields a surprisingly short proof of our lower bound, and which we believe may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Advantage in Cryptography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04078</link>
    <author>Renato Renner, Ramona Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Ever since its inception, cryptography has been caught in a vicious circle: Cryptographers keep inventing methods to hide information, and cryptanalysts break them, prompting cryptographers to invent even more sophisticated encryption schemes, and so on. But could it be that quantum information technology breaks this circle? At first sight, it looks as if it just lifts the competition between cryptographers and cryptanalysts to the next level. Indeed, quantum computers will render most of today's public key cryptosystems insecure. Nonetheless, there are good reasons to believe that cryptographers will ultimately prevail over cryptanalysts. Quantum cryptography allows us to build communication schemes whose secrecy relies only on the laws of physics as well as some minimum assumptions about the cryptographic hardware - leaving basically no room for an attack. While we are not yet there, this article provides an overview of the principles and state of the art of quantum cryptography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Resources Required to Block-Encode a Matrix of Classical Data</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.03505</link>
    <author>B. David Clader, Alexander M. Dalzell, Nikitas Stamatopoulos, Grant Salton, Mario Berta, William J. Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide modular circuit-level implementations and resource estimates for several methods of block-encoding a dense $N\times N$ matrix of classical data to precision $\epsilon$; the minimal-depth method achieves a $T$-depth of $\mathcal{O}{(\log (N/\epsilon))},$ while the minimal-count method achieves a $T$-count of $\mathcal{O}{(N\log(1/\epsilon))}$. We examine resource tradeoffs between the different approaches, and we explore implementations of two separate models of quantum random access memory (QRAM). As part of this analysis, we provide a novel state preparation routine with $T$-depth $\mathcal{O}{(\log (N/\epsilon))}$, improving on previous constructions with scaling $\mathcal{O}{(\log^2 (N/\epsilon))}$. Our results go beyond simple query complexity and provide a clear picture into the resource costs when large amounts of classical data are assumed to be accessible to quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Provably efficient variational generative modeling of quantum many-body systems via quantum-probabilistic information geometry</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04663</link>
    <author>Faris M. Sbahi, Antonio J. Martinez, Sahil Patel, Dmitri Saberi, Jae Hyeon Yoo, Geoffrey Roeder, Guillaume Verdon</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The dual tasks of quantum Hamiltonian learning and quantum Gibbs sampling are relevant to many important problems in physics and chemistry. In the low temperature regime, algorithms for these tasks often suffer from intractabilities, for example from poor sample- or time-complexity. With the aim of addressing such intractabilities, we introduce a generalization of quantum natural gradient descent to parameterized mixed states, as well as provide a robust first-order approximating algorithm, Quantum-Probabilistic Mirror Descent. We prove data sample efficiency for the dual tasks using tools from information geometry and quantum metrology, thus generalizing the seminal result of classical Fisher efficiency to a variational quantum algorithm for the first time. Our approaches extend previously sample-efficient techniques to allow for flexibility in model choice, including to spectrally-decomposed models like Quantum Hamiltonian-Based Models, which may circumvent intractable time complexities. Our first-order algorithm is derived using a novel quantum generalization of the classical mirror descent duality. Both results require a special choice of metric, namely, the Bogoliubov-Kubo-Mori metric. To test our proposed algorithms numerically, we compare their performance to existing baselines on the task of quantum Gibbs sampling for the transverse field Ising model. Finally, we propose an initialization strategy leveraging geometric locality for the modelling of sequences of states such as those arising from quantum-stochastic processes. We demonstrate its effectiveness empirically for both real and imaginary time evolution while defining a broader class of potential applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Average-case hardness of estimating probabilities of random quantum circuits with a linear scaling in the error exponent</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05642</link>
    <author>Hari Krovi</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the hardness of computing additive approximations to output probabilities of random quantum circuits. We consider three random circuit families, namely, Haar random, $p=1$ QAOA, and random IQP circuits. Our results are as follows. For Haar random circuits with $m$ gates, we improve on prior results by showing $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hardness of average-case additive approximations to an imprecision of $2^{-O(m)}$. Efficient classical simulation of such problems would imply the collapse of the polynomial hierarchy. For constant depth circuits i.e., when $m=O(n)$, this linear scaling in the exponent is within a constant of the scaling required to show hardness of sampling. Prior to our work, such a result was shown only for Boson Sampling in Bouland et al (2021). We also use recent results in polynomial interpolation to show $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hardness under $\mathsf{BPP}$ reductions rather than $\mathsf{BPP}^{\mathsf{NP}}$ reductions. This improves the results of prior work for Haar random circuits both in terms of the error scaling and the power of reductions. Next, we consider random $p=1$ QAOA and IQP circuits and show that in the average-case, it is $\mathsf{coC_=P}$ hard to approximate the output probability to within an additive error of $2^{-O(n)}$. For $p=1$ QAOA circuits, this work constitutes the first average-case hardness result for the problem of approximating output probabilities for random QAOA circuits, which include Sherrington-Kirkpatrick and Erdös-Renyi graphs. For IQP circuits, a consequence of our results is that approximating the Ising partition function with imaginary couplings to an additive error of $2^{-O(n)}$ is hard even in the average-case, which extends prior work on worst-case hardness of multiplicative approximation to Ising partition functions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Cone-Restricted Information Theory</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04300</link>
    <author>Ian George, Eric Chitambar</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The max-relative entropy and the conditional min-entropy it induces have become central to one-shot information theory. Both may be expressed in terms of a conic program over the positive semidefinite cone. Recently, it was shown that the same conic program altered to be over the separable cone admits an operational interpretation in terms of communicating classical information over a quantum channel. In this work, we generalize this framework of replacing the cone to determine which results in quantum information theory rely upon the positive semidefinite cone and which can be generalized. We show the fully quantum Stein's lemma and asymptotic equipartition property break down if the cone exponentially increases in resourcefulness but never approximates the positive semidefinite cone. However, we show for CQ states, the separable cone is sufficient to recover the asymptotic theory, thereby drawing a strong distinction between the fully and partial quantum settings. We present parallel results for the extended conditional min-entropy. In doing so, we extend the notion of k-superpositive channels to superchannels. We also present operational uses of this framework. We first show the cone restricted min-entropy of a Choi operator captures a measure of entanglement-assisted noiseless classical communication using restricted measurements. We show that quantum majorization results naturally generalize to other cones. As a novel example, we introduce a new min-entropy-like quantity that captures the quantum majorization of quantum channels in terms of bistochastic pre-processing. Lastly, we relate this framework to general conic norms and their non-additivity. Throughout this work we emphasize the introduced measures' relationship to general convex resource theories. In particular, we look at both resource theories that capture locality and resource theories of coherence/Abelian symmetries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Connections between graphs and matrix spaces</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04815</link>
    <author>Yinan Li, Youming Qiao, Avi Wigderson, Yuval Wigderson, Chuanqi Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a bipartite graph $G$, the graphical matrix space $\mathcal{S}_G$ consists of matrices whose non-zero entries can only be at those positions corresponding to edges in $G$. Tutte (J. London Math. Soc., 1947), Edmonds (J. Res. Nat. Bur. Standards Sect. B, 1967) and Lovász (FCT, 1979) observed connections between perfect matchings in $G$ and full-rank matrices in $\mathcal{S}_G$. Dieudonné (Arch. Math., 1948) proved a tight upper bound on the dimensions of those matrix spaces containing only singular matrices. The starting point of this paper is a simultaneous generalization of these two classical results: we show that the largest dimension over subspaces of $\mathcal{S}_G$ containing only singular matrices is equal to the maximum size over subgraphs of $G$ without perfect matchings, based on Meshulam's proof of Dieudonné's result (Quart. J. Math., 1985). Starting from this result, we go on to establish more connections between properties of graphs and matrix spaces. For example, we establish connections between acyclicity and nilpotency, between strong connectivity and irreducibility, and between isomorphism and conjugacy/congruence. For each connection, we study three types of correspondences, namely the basic correspondence, the inherited correspondence (for subgraphs and subspaces), and the induced correspondence (for induced subgraphs and restrictions). Some correspondences lead to intriguing generalizations of classical results, such as for Dieudonné's result mentioned above, and for a celebrated theorem of Gerstenhaber regarding the largest dimension of nil matrix spaces (Amer. J. Math., 1958). Finally, we show some implications of our results to quantum information and present open problems in computational complexity motivated by these results.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On the probabilistic quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.05232</link>
    <author>Ryszard Kukulski, Łukasz Pawela, Zbigniew Puchała</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Probabilistic quantum error correction is an error-correcting procedure which uses postselection to determine if the encoded information was successfully restored. In this work, we deeply analyze probabilistic version of the error-correcting procedure for general noise. We generalized the Knill-Laflamme conditions for probabilistically correctable errors. We show that for some noise channels, we should encode the information into a mixed state to maximize the probability of successful error correction. Finally, we investigate an advantage of the probabilistic error-correcting procedure over the deterministic one. Reducing the probability of successful error correction allows for correcting errors generated by a broader class of noise channels. Significantly, if the errors are caused by a unitary interaction with an auxiliary qubit system, we can probabilistically restore a qubit state by using only one additional physical qubit.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>