<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Implementing Fault-tolerant Entangling Gates on the Five-qubit Code and the Color Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01863</link>
    <author>C. Ryan-Anderson, N. C. Brown, M. S. Allman, B. Arkin, G. Asa-Attuah, C. Baldwin, J. Berg, J. G. Bohnet, S. Braxton, N. Burdick, J. P. Campora, A. Chernoguzov, J. Esposito, B. Evans, D. Francois, J. P. Gaebler, T. M. Gatterman, J. Gerber, K. Gilmore, D. Gresh, et al (17)</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We compare two different implementations of fault-tolerant entangling gates on logical qubits. In one instance, a twelve-qubit trapped-ion quantum computer is used to implement a non-transversal logical CNOT gate between two five qubit codes. The operation is evaluated with varying degrees of fault tolerance, which are provided by including quantum error correction circuit primitives known as flagging and pieceable fault tolerance. In the second instance, a twenty-qubit trapped-ion quantum computer is used to implement a transversal logical CNOT gate on two [[7,1,3]] color codes. The two codes were implemented on different but similar devices, and in both instances, all of the quantum error correction primitives, including the determination of corrections via decoding, are implemented during runtime using a classical compute environment that is tightly integrated with the quantum processor. For different combinations of the primitives, logical state fidelity measurements are made after applying the gate to different input states, providing bounds on the process fidelity. We find the highest fidelity operations with the color code, with the fault-tolerant SPAM operation achieving fidelities of 0.99939(15) and 0.99959(13) when preparing eigenstates of the logical X and Z operators, which is higher than the average physical qubit SPAM fidelities of 0.9968(2) and 0.9970(1) for the physical X and Z bases, respectively. When combined with a logical transversal CNOT gate, we find the color code to perform the sequence--state preparation, CNOT, measure out--with an average fidelity bounded by [0.9957,0.9963]. The logical fidelity bounds are higher than the analogous physical-level fidelity bounds, which we find to be [0.9850,0.9903], reflecting multiple physical noise sources such as SPAM errors for two qubits, several single-qubit gates, a two-qubit gate and some amount of memory error.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simulating quantum circuits using efficient tensor network contraction algorithms with subexponential upper bound</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01498</link>
    <author>Thorsten B. Wahl, Sergii Strelchuk</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We derive a rigorous upper bound on the classical computation time of finite-ranged tensor network contractions in $d \geq 2$ dimensions. By means of the Sphere Separator Theorem, we are able to take advantage of the structure of quantum circuits to speed up contractions to show that quantum circuits of single-qubit and finite-ranged two-qubit gates can be classically simulated in subexponential time in the number of gates. In many practically relevant cases this beats standard simulation schemes. Moreover, our algorithm leads to speedups of several orders of magnitude over naive contraction schemes for two-dimensional quantum circuits on as little as an $8 \times 8$ lattice. We obtain similarly efficient contraction schemes for Google's Sycamore-type quantum circuits, instantaneous quantum polynomial-time circuits and non-homogeneous (2+1)-dimensional random quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Correcting non-independent and non-identically distributed errors with surface codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.02191</link>
    <author>Konstantin Tiurev, Peter-Jan H. S. Derks, Joschka Roffe, Jens Eisert, Jan-Michael Reiner</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A common approach to studying the performance of quantum error correcting codes is to assume independent and identically distributed single-qubit errors. However, realistic errors in experimental multi-qubit devices are typically neither independent nor identical across qubits. In this work, we develop and investigate the properties of topological surface codes tailored to a known noise channel by locally adapted Clifford conjugations. We show that the surface code locally tailored to non-uniform single-qubit noise in conjunction with a scalable matching decoder yields improved error thresholds and exponentially suppressed sub-threshold failure rates when compared to the Calderbank-Shor-Steane surface code. Furthermore, we study the behaviour of the tailored surface code under local two-qubit noise and show the role that code degeneracy plays in correcting such noise. The proposed methods do not require additional overhead in terms of the number of qubits and use a standard matching decoder, hence come at no extra cost compared to the standard surface-code error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Fundamental Limitation on the Detectability of Entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.02518</link>
    <author>Pengyu Liu, Zhenhuan Liu, Shu Chen, Xiongfeng Ma</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Entanglement detection is essential in quantum information science and quantum many-body physics. It has been proved that entanglement exists almost surely for a random quantum state, while the realizations of effective entanglement criteria usually consume exponential resources, and efficient criteria often perform poorly without prior knowledge. This fact implies a fundamental limitation might exist in the detectability of entanglement. In this work, we formalize this limitation as a fundamental trade-off between the efficiency and effectiveness of entanglement criteria via a systematic method to theoretically evaluate the detection capability of entanglement criteria. For a system coupled to an environment, we prove that any entanglement criterion needs exponentially many observables to detect the entanglement effectively when restricted to single-copy operations. Otherwise, the detection capability of the criterion will decay double-exponentially. Furthermore, if multi-copy joint measurements are allowed, the effectiveness of entanglement detection can be exponentially improved, which implies a quantum advantage in entanglement detection problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Techniques for combining fast local decoders with global decoders under circuit-level noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01178</link>
    <author>Christopher Chamberland, Luis Goncalves, Prasahnt Sivarajah, Eric Peterson, Sebastian Grimberg</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Implementing algorithms on a fault-tolerant quantum computer will require fast decoding throughput and latency times to prevent an exponential increase in buffer times between the applications of gates. In this work we begin by quantifying these requirements. We then introduce the construction of local neural network (NN) decoders using three-dimensional convolutions. These local decoders are adapted to circuit-level noise and can be applied to surface code volumes of arbitrary size. Their application removes errors arising from a certain number of faults, which serves to substantially reduce the syndrome density. Remaining errors can then be corrected by a global decoder, such as Blossom or Union Find, with their implementation significantly accelerated due to the reduced syndrome density. However, in the circuit-level setting, the corrections applied by the local decoder introduce many vertical pairs of highlighted vertices. To obtain a low syndrome density in the presence of vertical pairs, we consider a strategy of performing a syndrome collapse which removes many vertical pairs and reduces the size of the decoding graph used by the global decoder. We also consider a strategy of performing a vertical cleanup, which consists of removing all local vertical pairs prior to implementing the global decoder. Lastly, we estimate the cost of implementing our local decoders on Field Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGAs).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning quantum systems via out-of-time-order correlators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.02254</link>
    <author>Thomas Schuster, Murphy Niu, Jordan Cotler, Thomas O'Brien, Jarrod R. McClean, Masoud Mohseni</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Learning the properties of dynamical quantum systems underlies applications ranging from nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy to quantum device characterization. A central challenge in this pursuit is the learning of strongly-interacting systems, where conventional observables decay quickly in time and space, limiting the information that can be learned from their measurement. In this work, we introduce a new class of observables into the context of quantum learning -- the out-of-time-order correlator -- which we show can substantially improve the learnability of strongly-interacting systems by virtue of displaying informative physics at large times and distances. We identify two general scenarios in which out-of-time-order correlators provide a significant advantage for learning tasks in locally-interacting systems: (i) when experimental access to the system is spatially-restricted, for example via a single "probe" degree of freedom, and (ii) when one desires to characterize weak interactions whose strength is much less than the typical interaction strength. We numerically characterize these advantages across a variety of learning problems, and find that they are robust to both read-out error and decoherence. Finally, we introduce a binary classification task that can be accomplished in constant time with out-of-time-order measurements. In a companion paper, we prove that this task is exponentially hard with any adaptive learning protocol that only involves time-ordered operations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Information-theoretic Hardness of Out-of-time-order Correlators</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.02256</link>
    <author>Jordan Cotler, Thomas Schuster, Masoud Mohseni</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We establish that there are properties of quantum many-body dynamics which are efficiently learnable if we are given access to out-of-time-order correlators (OTOCs), but which require exponentially many operations in the system size if we can only measure time-ordered correlators. This implies that any experimental protocol which reconstructs OTOCs solely from time-ordered correlators must be, in certain cases, exponentially inefficient. Our proofs leverage and generalize recent techniques in quantum learning theory. Along the way, we elucidate a general definition of time-ordered versus out-of-time-order experimental measurement protocols, which can be considered as classes of adaptive quantum learning algorithms. Moreover, our results provide a theoretical foundation for novel applications of OTOCs in quantum simulations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Duality theory for Clifford tensor powers</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01688</link>
    <author>Felipe Montealegre-Mora, David Gross</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The representation theory of the Clifford group is playing an increasingly prominent role in quantum information theory, including in such diverse use cases as the construction of protocols for quantum system certification, quantum simulation, and quantum cryptography. In these applications, the tensor powers of the defining representation seem particularly important. The representation theory of these tensor powers is understood in two regimes. 1. For odd qudits in the case where the power t is not larger than the number of systems n: Here, a duality theory between the Clifford group and certain discrete orthogonal groups can be used to make fairly explicit statements about the occurring irreps (this theory is related to Howe duality and the eta-correspondence). 2. For qubits: Tensor powers up to t=4 have been analyzed on a case-by-case basis. In this paper, we provide a unified framework for the duality approach that also covers qubit systems. To this end, we translate the notion of rank of symplectic representations to representations of the qubit Clifford group, and generalize the eta correspondence between symplectic and orthogonal groups to a correspondence between the Clifford and certain orthogonal-stochastic groups. As a sample application, we provide a protocol to efficiently implement the complex conjugate of a black-box Clifford unitary evolution.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Is there evidence for exponential quantum advantage in quantum chemistry?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.02199</link>
    <author>Seunghoon Lee, Joonho Lee, Huanchen Zhai, Yu Tong, Alexander M. Dalzell, Ashutosh Kumar, Phillip Helms, Johnnie Gray, Zhi-Hao Cui, Wenyuan Liu, Michael Kastoryano, Ryan Babbush, John Preskill, David R. Reichman, Earl T. Campbell, Edward F. Valeev, Lin Lin, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The idea to use quantum mechanical devices to simulate other quantum systems is commonly ascribed to Feynman. Since the original suggestion, concrete proposals have appeared for simulating molecular and materials chemistry through quantum computation, as a potential "killer application". Indications of potential exponential quantum advantage in artificial tasks have increased interest in this application, thus, it is critical to understand the basis for potential exponential quantum advantage in quantum chemistry. Here we gather the evidence for this case in the most common task in quantum chemistry, namely, ground-state energy estimation. We conclude that evidence for such an advantage across chemical space has yet to be found. While quantum computers may still prove useful for quantum chemistry, it may be prudent to assume exponential speedups are not generically available for this problem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tensor types and their use in physics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.01135</link>
    <author>Andreas Bauer, Alexander Nietner</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The content of this paper can be roughly organized into a three-level hierarchy of generality. At the first, most general level, we introduce a new language which allows us to express various categorical structures in a systematic and explicit manner in terms of so-called 2-schemes. Although 2-schemes can formalize categorical structures such as symmetric monoidal categories, they are not limited to this, and can be used to define structures with no categorical analogue. Most categorical structures come with an effective graphical calculus such as string diagrams for symmetric monoidal categories, and the same is true more generally for interesting 2-schemes. In this work, we focus on one particular non-categorical 2-scheme, whose instances we refer to as tensor types. At the second level of the hierarchy, we work out different flavors of this 2-scheme in detail. The effective graphical calculus of tensor types is that of tensor networks or Penrose diagrams, that is, string diagrams without a flow of time. As such, tensor types are similar to compact closed categories, though there are various small but potentially important differences. Also, the two definitions use completely different mechanisms despite both being examples of 2-schemes. At the third level of the hierarchy, we provide a long list of different families of concrete tensor types, in a way which makes them accessible to concrete computations, motivated by their potential use in physics. Different tensor types describe different types of physical models, such as classical or quantum physics, deterministic or statistical physics, many-body or single-body physics, or matter with or without symmetries or fermions.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>