<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>What is nonclassical about uncertainty relations?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11779</link>
    <author>Lorenzo Catani, Matthew Leifer, Giovanni Scala, David Schmid, Robert W. Spekkens</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Uncertainty relations express limits on the extent to which the outcomes of distinct measurements on a single state can be made jointly predictable. The existence of nontrivial uncertainty relations in quantum theory is generally considered to be a way in which it entails a departure from the classical worldview. However, this view is undermined by the fact that there exist operational theories which exhibit nontrivial uncertainty relations but which are consistent with the classical worldview insofar as they admit of a generalized-noncontextual ontological model. This prompts the question of what aspects of uncertainty relations, if any, cannot be realized in this way and so constitute evidence of genuine nonclassicality. We here consider uncertainty relations describing the tradeoff between the predictability of a pair of binary-outcome measurements (e.g., measurements of Pauli X and Pauli Z observables in quantum theory). We show that, for a class of theories satisfying a particular symmetry property, the functional form of this predictability tradeoff is constrained by noncontextuality to be below a linear curve. Because qubit quantum theory has the relevant symmetry property, the fact that it has a quadratic tradeoff between these predictabilities is a violation of this noncontextual bound, and therefore constitutes an example of how the functional form of an uncertainty relation can witness contextuality. We also deduce the implications for a selected group of operational foils to quantum theory and consider the generalization to three measurements.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantifying Nonstabilizerness of Matrix Product States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13076</link>
    <author>Tobias Haug, Lorenzo Piroli</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Nonstabilizerness, also known as magic, quantifies the number of non-Clifford operations needed in order to prepare a quantum state. As typical measures either involve minimization procedures or a computational cost exponential in the number of qubits $N$, it is notoriously hard to characterize for many-body states. In this work, we show that nonstabilizerness, as quantified by the recently introduced Stabilizer Rényi Entropies (SREs), can be computed efficiently for matrix product states (MPSs). Specifically, given an MPS of bond-dimension $\chi$ and integer Rényi index $n>1$, we show that the SRE can be expressed in terms of the norm of an MPS with bond-dimension $\chi^{2n}$. For translation-invariant states, this allows us to extract magic from a single tensor, the transfer matrix, while for generic MPSs this construction yields a computational cost linear in $N$ and polynomial in $\chi$. We exploit this observation to revisit the study of ground-state magic in the quantum Ising chain, providing accurate numerical results up to large system sizes. We analyze the SRE near criticality and investigate its dependence on the local computational basis. We show that it is in general not maximal at the critical point, and interpret our findings in terms of ``long-range magic''.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Preparing Many Copies of a Quantum State in the Black-Box Model</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11014</link>
    <author>Yassine Hamoudi</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We describe a simple quantum algorithm for preparing $K$ copies of an $N$-dimensional quantum state whose amplitudes are given by a quantum oracle. Our result extends a previous work of Grover, who showed how to prepare one copy in time $O(\sqrt{N})$. In comparison with the naive $O(K\sqrt{N})$ solution obtained by repeating this procedure~$K$ times, our algorithm achieves the optimal running time of $\theta(\sqrt{KN})$. Our technique uses a refinement of the quantum rejection sampling method employed by Grover. As a direct application, we obtain a similar speed-up for obtaining $K$ independent samples from a distribution whose probability vector is given by a quantum oracle.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Publicly verifiable quantum money from random lattices</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13135</link>
    <author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu, Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Publicly verifiable quantum money is a protocol for the preparation of quantum states that can be efficiently verified by any party for authenticity but is computationally infeasible to counterfeit. We develop a cryptographic scheme for publicly verifiable quantum money based on Gaussian superpositions over random lattices. We introduce a verification-of-authenticity procedure based on the lattice discrete Fourier transform, and subsequently prove the unforgeability of our quantum money under the hardness of the short vector problem from lattice-based cryptography.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Resources for bosonic quantum computational advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11781</link>
    <author>Ulysse Chabaud, Mattia Walschaers</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers promise to dramatically outperform their classical counterparts. However, the non-classical resources enabling such computational advantages are challenging to pinpoint, as it is not a single resource but the subtle interplay of many that can be held responsible for these potential advantages. In this work, we show that every bosonic quantum computation can be recast into a continuous-variable sampling computation where all computational resources are contained in the input state. Using this reduction, we derive a general classical algorithm for the strong simulation of bosonic computations, whose complexity scales with the non-Gaussian stellar rank of both the input state and the measurement setup. We further study the conditions for an efficient classical simulation of the associated continuous-variable sampling computations and identify an operational notion of non-Gaussian entanglement based on the lack of passive separability, thus clarifying the interplay of bosonic quantum computational resources such as squeezing, non-Gaussianity and entanglement.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A Faster Quantum Algorithm for Semidefinite Programming via Robust IPM Framework</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11154</link>
    <author>Baihe Huang, Shunhua Jiang, Zhao Song, Runzhou Tao, Ruizhe Zhang</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This paper studies a fundamental problem in convex optimization, which is to solve semidefinite programming (SDP) with high accuracy. This paper follows from existing robust SDP-based interior point method analysis due to [Huang, Jiang, Song, Tao and Zhang, FOCS 2022]. While, the previous work only provides an efficient implementation in the classical setting. This work provides a novel quantum implementation. We give a quantum second-order algorithm with high-accuracy in both the optimality and the feasibility of its output, and its running time depending on $\log(1/\epsilon)$ on well-conditioned instances. Due to the limitation of quantum itself or first-order method, all the existing quantum SDP solvers either have polynomial error dependence or low-accuracy in the feasibility.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection: Hardness based on a Weak Quantum Conjecture</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.11068</link>
    <author>Andris Ambainis, Harry Buhrman, Koen Leijnse, Subhasree Patro, Florian Speelman</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Classically, for many computational problems one can conclude time lower bounds conditioned on the hardness of one or more of key problems: k-SAT, 3SUM and APSP. More recently, similar results have been derived in the quantum setting conditioned on the hardness of k-SAT and 3SUM. This is done using fine-grained reductions, where the approach is to (1) select a key problem $X$ that, for some function $T$, is conjectured to not be solvable by any $O(T(n)^{1-\epsilon})$ time algorithm for any constant $\epsilon > 0$ (in a fixed model of computation), and (2) reduce $X$ in a fine-grained way to these computational problems, thus giving (mostly) tight conditional time lower bounds for them. Interestingly, for Delta-Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection, classical hardness results have been derived conditioned on hardness of all three mentioned key problems. More precisely, it is proven that an $n^{3-\epsilon}$ time classical algorithm for either of these two graph problems would imply faster classical algorithms for k-SAT, 3SUM and APSP, which makes Delta-Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection worthwhile to study. In this paper, we show that an $n^{1.5-\epsilon}$ time quantum algorithm for either of these two graph problems would imply faster quantum algorithms for k-SAT, 3SUM, and APSP. We first formulate a quantum hardness conjecture for APSP and then present quantum reductions from k-SAT, 3SUM, and APSP to Delta-Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection. Additionally, based on the quantum APSP conjecture, we are also able to prove quantum lower bounds for a matrix problem and many graph problems. The matching upper bounds follow trivially for most of them, except for Delta-Matching Triangles and Triangle Collection for which we present quantum algorithms that require careful use of data structures and Ambainis' variable time search.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Do Quantum Circuit Born Machines Generalize?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13645</link>
    <author>Kaitlin Gili, Mohamed Hibat-Allah, Marta Mauri, Chris Ballance, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In recent proposals of quantum circuit models for generative tasks, the discussion about their performance has been limited to their ability to reproduce a known target distribution. For example, expressive model families such as Quantum Circuit Born Machines (QCBMs) have been almost entirely evaluated on their capability to learn a given target distribution with high accuracy. While this aspect may be ideal for some tasks, it limits the scope of a generative model's assessment to its ability to memorize data rather than generalize. As a result, there has been little understanding of a model's generalization performance and the relation between such capability and the resource requirements, e.g., the circuit depth and the amount of training data. In this work, we leverage upon a recently proposed generalization evaluation framework to begin addressing this knowledge gap. We first investigate the QCBM's learning process of a cardinality-constrained distribution and see an increase in generalization performance while increasing the circuit depth. In the 12-qubit example presented here, we observe that with as few as 30% of the valid patterns as the training set, the QCBM exhibits the best generalization performance toward generating unseen and valid patterns. Lastly, we assess the QCBM's ability to generalize not only to valid features, but to high-quality bitstrings distributed according to an adequately biased distribution. We see that the QCBM is able to effectively learn the bias and generate unseen samples with higher quality than those in the training set. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work in the literature that presents the QCBM's generalization performance as an integral evaluation metric for quantum generative models, and demonstrates the QCBM's ability to generalize to high-quality, desired novel samples.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The minimal communication cost for simulating entangled qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.12457</link>
    <author>Martin J. Renner, Marco Túlio Quintino</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyse the amount of classical communication required to reproduce the statistics of local projective measurements on a general pair of entangled qubits, $|\Psi_{AB}>=\sqrt{p}\ |00>+\sqrt{1-p}\ |11>$ ($1/2\leq p \leq 1$). We construct a classical protocol that perfectly simulates local projective measurements on all entangled qubit pairs by communicating one classical trit. Additionally, when $\frac{2p(1-p)}{2p-1} \log{\left(\frac{p}{1-p}\right)}+2(1-p)\leq1$, approximately $0.835 \leq p \leq 1$, we present a classical protocol that requires only a single bit of communication. The latter model even allows a perfect classical simulation with an average communication cost that approaches zero in the limit where the degree of entanglement approaches zero ($p \to 1$). This proves that the communication cost for simulating weakly entangled qubit pairs is strictly smaller than for the maximally entangled one.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matchgate Shadows for Fermionic Quantum Simulation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13723</link>
    <author>Kianna Wan, William J. Huggins, Joonho Lee, Ryan Babbush</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>"Classical shadows" are estimators of an unknown quantum state, constructed from suitably distributed random measurements on copies of that state [Nature Physics 16, 1050-1057]. Here, we analyze classical shadows obtained using random matchgate circuits, which correspond to fermionic Gaussian unitaries. We prove that the first three moments of the Haar distribution over the continuous group of matchgate circuits are equal to those of the discrete uniform distribution over only the matchgate circuits that are also Clifford unitaries; thus, the latter forms a "matchgate 3-design." This implies that the classical shadows resulting from the two ensembles are functionally equivalent. We show how one can use these matchgate shadows to efficiently estimate inner products between an arbitrary quantum state and fermionic Gaussian states, as well as the expectation values of local fermionic operators and various other quantities, thus surpassing the capabilities of prior work. As a concrete application, this enables us to apply wavefunction constraints that control the fermion sign problem in the quantum-classical auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm (QC-AFQMC) [Nature 603, 416-420], without the exponential post-processing cost incurred by the original approach.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>