<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Exponentially tighter bounds on limitations of quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11505</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Daniel Stilck França, Sumeet Khatri, Johannes Jakob Meyer, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation has been proposed as a means to combat unavoidable errors in near-term quantum computing by classically post-processing outcomes of multiple quantum circuits. It does so in a fashion that requires no or few additional quantum resources, in contrast to fault-tolerant schemes that come along with heavy overheads. Error mitigation leads to noise reduction in small systems. In this work, however, we identify strong limitations to the degree to which quantum noise can be effectively `undone' for larger system sizes. We start out by presenting a formal framework that rigorously encapsulates large classes of meaningful and practically applied schemes for quantum error mitigation, including virtual distillation, Clifford data regression, zero-noise extrapolation and probabilistic error cancellation. With the framework in place, our technical contribution is to construct families of random circuits that are highly sensitive to noise, in the sense that even at log log(n) depth, a whisker beyond constant, quantum noise is seen to super-exponentially rapidly scramble their output into the maximally-mixed state. Our results exponentially tighten known arguments for error mitigation, but they go beyond that: Our arguments can be applied to kernel estimation or to compute the depth at which barren plateaus emerge, implying that the scrambling kicks in at exponentially smaller depths than previously thought. Our results also say that a noisy device must be sampled exponentially many times to estimate expectation values. There are classical algorithms that exhibit the same scaling in complexity. While improvements in quantum hardware will push noise levels down, if error mitigation is used, ultimately this can only lead to an exponential time quantum algorithm with a better exponent, putting up a strong obstruction to the hope for exponential quantum speedups in this setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Observation of non-Abelian exchange statistics on a superconducting processor</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10255</link>
    <author>Trond I. Andersen, Yuri D. Lensky, Kostyantyn Kechedzhi, Ilya Drozdov, Andreas Bengtsson, Sabrina Hong, Alexis Morvan, Xiao Mi, Alex Opremcak, Rajeev Acharya, Richard Allen, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Gina Bortoli, et al (149)</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Indistinguishability of particles is a fundamental principle of quantum mechanics. For all elementary and quasiparticles observed to date - including fermions, bosons, and Abelian anyons - this principle guarantees that the braiding of identical particles leaves the system unchanged. However, in two spatial dimensions, an intriguing possibility exists: braiding of non-Abelian anyons causes rotations in a space of topologically degenerate wavefunctions. Hence, it can change the observables of the system without violating the principle of indistinguishability. Despite the well developed mathematical description of non-Abelian anyons and numerous theoretical proposals, their experimental observation has remained elusive for decades. Using a superconducting quantum processor, we prepare the ground state of the surface code and manipulate it via unitary operations to form wavefunctions that are described by non-Abelian anyons. By implementing a unitary protocol to move the anyons, we experimentally verify the fusion rules of non-Abelian Ising anyons and braid them to realize their statistics. Building on our technique, we study the prospect of employing the anyons for quantum computation and utilize braiding to create an entangled state of anyons encoding three logical qubits. Our work represents a key step towards topological quantum computing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Classical simulation of short-time quantum dynamics</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11490</link>
    <author>Dominik S. Wild, Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Locality is a key simplifying feature of many physical systems. Cluster expansion techniques provide one particular way of exploiting it. They have historically appeared in statistical physics to prove the uniqueness of Gibbs states and the decay of correlations at high temperature, among many other results. Here, we apply these techniques to quantum many-body systems evolving under local Hamiltonians. We consider the evolution of both local observables and non-local quantities such as the Loschmidt echo. We show that for a product initial state, the cluster expansion enables efficient classical computation of the dynamics up to a fixed evolution time, independent of the system size. The computational cost scales polynomially with the system size and the inverse of the approximation error. In the case of local observables, we can extend the evolution time to any constant value using analytic continuation. In more than one dimension, the resulting algorithm has a better dependence on the approximation error than algorithms based on the Lieb-Robinson bound. Our algorithms rely on the convergence of the cluster expansion, which also has important physical consequences. In particular, we establish a novel quantum speed limit, a bound on dynamical phase transitions, and a concentration bound for product states evolved for short times.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Purification-based quantum error mitigation of pair-correlated electron simulations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10799</link>
    <author>T. E. O'Brien, G. Anselmetti, F. Gkritsis, V. E. Elfving, S. Polla, W. J. Huggins, O. Oumarou, K. Kechedzhi, D. Abanin, R. Acharya, I. Aleiner, R. Allen, T. I. Andersen, K. Anderson, M. Ansmann, F. Arute, K. Arya, A. Asfaw, J. Atalaya, D. Bacon, et al (156)</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>An important measure of the development of quantum computing platforms has been the simulation of increasingly complex physical systems. Prior to fault-tolerant quantum computing, robust error mitigation strategies are necessary to continue this growth. Here, we study physical simulation within the seniority-zero electron pairing subspace, which affords both a computational stepping stone to a fully correlated model, and an opportunity to validate recently introduced ``purification-based'' error-mitigation strategies. We compare the performance of error mitigation based on doubling quantum resources in time (echo verification) or in space (virtual distillation), on up to $20$ qubits of a superconducting qubit quantum processor. We observe a reduction of error by one to two orders of magnitude below less sophisticated techniques (e.g. post-selection); the gain from error mitigation is seen to increase with the system size. Employing these error mitigation strategies enables the implementation of the largest variational algorithm for a correlated chemistry system to-date. Extrapolating performance from these results allows us to estimate minimum requirements for a beyond-classical simulation of electronic structure. We find that, despite the impressive gains from purification-based error mitigation, significant hardware improvements will be required for classically intractable variational chemistry simulations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Doubling the order of approximation via the randomized product formula</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11281</link>
    <author>Chien Hung Cho, Dominic W. Berry, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Randomization has been applied to Hamiltonian simulation in a number of ways to improve the accuracy or efficiency of product formulas. Deterministic product formulas are often constructed in a symmetric way to provide accuracy of even order 2k. We show that by applying randomized corrections, it is possible to more than double the order to 4k + 1 (corresponding to a doubling of the order of the error). In practice, applying the corrections in a quantum algorithm requires some structure to the Hamiltonian, for example the Pauli strings as are used in the simulation of quantum chemistry.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Error Suppression for Arbitrary-Size Black Box Quantum Operations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10733</link>
    <author>Gideon Lee, Connor T. Hann, Shruti Puri, S. M. Girvin, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Efficient suppression of errors without full error correction is crucial for applications with NISQ devices. Error mitigation allows us to suppress errors in extracting expectation values without the need for any error correction code, but its applications are limited to estimating expectation values, and cannot provide us with high-fidelity quantum operations acting on arbitrary quantum states. To address this challenge, we propose to use error filtration (EF) for gate-based quantum computation, as a practical error suppression scheme without resorting to full quantum error correction. The result is a general-purpose error suppression protocol where the resources required to suppress errors scale independently of the size of the quantum operation. We further analyze the application of EF to quantum random access memory, where EF offers a hardware-efficient error suppression.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sequential Quantum Channel Discrimination</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11079</link>
    <author>Yonglong Li, Christoph Hirche, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the sequential quantum channel discrimination problem using adaptive and non-adaptive strategies. In this setting the number of uses of the underlying quantum channel is not fixed but a random variable that is either bounded in expectation or with high probability. We show that both types of error probabilities decrease to zero exponentially fast and, when using adaptive strategies, the rates are characterized by the measured relative entropy between two quantum channels, yielding a strictly larger region than that achievable by non-adaptive strategies. Allowing for quantum memory, we see that the optimal rates are given by the regularized channel relative entropy. Finally, we discuss achievable rates when allowing for repeated measurements via quantum instruments and conjecture that the achievable rate region is not larger than that achievable with POVMs by connecting the result to the strong converse for the quantum channel Stein's Lemma.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Zak transform: a framework for quantum computation with the Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.09494</link>
    <author>Giacomo Pantaleoni, Ben Q. Baragiola, Nicolas C. Menicucci</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) code encodes a qubit into a bosonic mode using periodic wavefunctions. This periodicity makes the GKP code a natural setting for the Zak transform, which is tailor-made to provide a simple description for periodic functions. We review the Zak transform and its connection to a Zak basis of states in Hilbert space, decompose the shift operators that underpin the stabilizers and the correctable errors, and we find that Zak transforms of the position wavefunction appear naturally in GKP error correction. We construct a new bosonic subsystem decomposition (SSD) -- the modular variable SSD -- by dividing a mode's Hilbert space, expressed in the Zak basis, into that of a virtual qubit and a virtual gauge mode. Tracing over the gauge mode gives a logical-qubit state, and preceding the trace with a particular logical-gauge interaction gives a different logical state -- that associated to GKP error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Theoretical Guarantees for Permutation-Equivariant Quantum Neural Networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.09974</link>
    <author>Louis Schatzki, Martin Larocca, Frederic Sauvage, M. Cerezo</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Despite the great promise of quantum machine learning models, there are several challenges one must overcome before unlocking their full potential. For instance, models based on quantum neural networks (QNNs) can suffer from excessive local minima and barren plateaus in their training landscapes. Recently, the nascent field of geometric quantum machine learning (GQML) has emerged as a potential solution to some of those issues. The key insight of GQML is that one should design architectures, such as equivariant QNNs, encoding the symmetries of the problem at hand. Here, we focus on problems with permutation symmetry (i.e., the group of symmetry $S_n$), and show how to build $S_n$-equivariant QNNs. We provide an analytical study of their performance, proving that they do not suffer from barren plateaus, quickly reach overparametrization, and can generalize well from small amounts of data. To verify our results, we perform numerical simulations for a graph state classification task. Our work provides the first theoretical guarantees for equivariant QNNs, thus indicating the extreme power and potential of GQML.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lattice-Based Quantum Advantage from Rotated Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.10143</link>
    <author>Yusuf Alnawakhtha, Atul Mantri, Carl A. Miller, Daochen Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Trapdoor claw-free functions (TCFs) are immensely valuable in cryptographic interactions between a classical client and a quantum server. Typically, a protocol has the quantum server prepare a superposition of two-bit strings of a claw and then measure it using Pauli-$X$ or $Z$ measurements. In this paper, we demonstrate a new technique that uses the entire range of qubit measurements from the $XY$-plane. We show the advantage of this approach in two applications. First, building on (Brakerski et al. 2018, Kalai et al. 2022), we show an optimized two-round proof of quantumness whose security can be expressed directly in terms of the hardness of the LWE (learning with errors) problem. Second, we construct a one-round protocol for blind remote preparation of an arbitrary state on the $XY$-plane up to a Pauli-$Z$ correction.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>