<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Learning quantum graph states with product measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06432</link>
    <author>Yingkai Ouyang, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>May 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of learning $N$ identical copies of an unknown $n$-qubit quantum graph state with product measurements. These graph states have corresponding graphs where every vertex has exactly $d$ neighboring vertices. Here, we detail an explicit algorithm that uses product measurements on multiple identical copies of such graph states to learn them. When $n \gg d$ and $N = O(d \log(1/\epsilon) + d^2 \log n ),$ this algorithm correctly learns the graph state with probability at least $1- \epsilon$. From channel coding theory, we find that for arbitrary joint measurements on graph states, any learning algorithm achieving this accuracy requires at least $\Omega(\log (1/\epsilon) + d \log n)$ copies when $d=o(\sqrt n)$. We also supply bounds on $N$ when every graph state encounters identical and independent depolarizing errors on each qubit.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Correlations in typicality and an affirmative solution to the exact catalytic entropy conjecture</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08915</link>
    <author>Henrik Wilming</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I show that if a finite-dimensional density matrix has strictly smaller von Neumann entropy than a second one of the same dimension (and the rank is not bigger), then sufficiently (but finitely) many tensor-copies of the first density matrix majorize a density matrix whose single-body marginals are all exactly equal to the second density matrix. This implies an affirmative solution of the exact catalytic entropy conjecture (CEC) introduced by Boes et al. [PRL 122, 210402 (2019)]. Both the Lemma and the solution to the CEC transfer to the classical setting of finite-dimensional probability vectors (with permutations of entries instead of unitary transformations for the CEC).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The QAOA with Slow Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06845</link>
    <author>Anthony Polloreno, Graeme Smith</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) was originally developed to solve combinatorial optimization problems, but has become a standard for assessing the performance of quantum computers. Fully descriptive benchmarking techniques are often prohibitively expensive for large numbers of qubits ($n \gtrsim 10$), so the QAOA often serves in practice as a computational benchmark. The QAOA involves a classical optimization subroutine that attempts to find optimal parameters for a quantum subroutine. Unfortunately, many optimizers used for the QAOA require many shots ($N \gtrsim 1000$) per point in parameter space to get a reliable estimate of the energy being minimized. However, some experimental quantum computing platforms such as neutral atom quantum computers have slow repetition rates, placing unique requirements on the classical optimization subroutine used in the QAOA in these systems. In this paper we investigate the performance of a gradient free classical optimizer for the QAOA - dual annealing - and demonstrate that optimization is possible even with $N=1$ and $n=16$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Optimising shadow tomography with generalised measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08990</link>
    <author>H. Chau Nguyen, Jan Lennart Bönsel, Jonathan Steinberg, Otfried Gühne</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Advances in quantum technology require scalable techniques to efficiently extract information from a quantum system, such as expectation values of observables or its entropy. Traditional tomography is limited to a handful of qubits and shadow tomography has been suggested as a scalable replacement for larger systems. Shadow tomography is conventionally analysed based on outcomes of ideal projective measurements on the system upon application of randomised unitaries. Here, we suggest that shadow tomography can be much more straightforwardly formulated for generalised measurements, or positive operator valued measures. Based on the idea of the least-square estimator, shadow tomography with generalised measurements is both more general and simpler than the traditional formulation with randomisation of unitaries. In particular, this formulation allows us to analyse theoretical aspects of shadow tomography in detail. For example, we provide a detailed study of the implication of symmetries in shadow tomography. Shadow tomography with generalised measurements is also indispensable in realistic implementation of quantum mechanical measurements, when noise is unavoidable. Moreover, we also demonstrate how the optimisation of measurements for shadow tomography tailored toward a particular set of observables can be carried out.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Hay from the haystack: explicit examples of exponential quantum circuit complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06977</link>
    <author>Yifan Jia, Michael M. Wolf</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The vast majority of quantum states and unitaries have circuit complexity exponential in the number of qubits. In a similar vein, most of them also have exponential minimum description length, which makes it difficult to pinpoint examples of exponential complexity. In this work, we construct examples of constant description length but exponential circuit complexity. We provide infinite families such that each element requires an exponential number of two-qubit gates to be generated exactly from a product and where the same is true for the approximate generation of the vast majority of elements in the family. The results are based on sets of large transcendence degree and discussed for tensor networks, diagonal unitaries, and maximally coherent states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Say NO to Optimization: A Non-Orthogonal Quantum Eigensolver</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09039</link>
    <author>Unpil Baek, Diptarka Hait, James Shee, Oskar Leimkuhler, William J. Huggins, Torin F. Stetina, Martin Head-Gordon, K. Birgitta Whaley</author>
    <pubDate>May 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A balanced description of both static and dynamic correlations in electronic systems with nearly degenerate low-lying states presents a challenge for multi-configurational methods on classical computers. We present here a quantum algorithm utilizing the action of correlating cluster operators to provide high-quality wavefunction ansätze employing a non-orthogonal multireference basis that captures a significant portion of the exact wavefunction in a highly compact manner, and that allows computation of the resulting energies and wavefunctions at polynomial cost with a quantum computer. This enables a significant improvement over the corresponding classical non-orthogonal solver, which incurs an exponential cost when evaluating off-diagonal matrix elements between the ansatz states, and is therefore intractable. We implement the non-orthogonal quantum eigensolver (NOQE) here with an efficient ansatz parameterization inspired by classical quantum chemistry methods that succeed in capturing significant amounts of electronic correlation accurately. By taking advantage of classical methods for chemistry, NOQE provides a flexible, compact, and rigorous description of both static and dynamic electronic correlation, making it an attractive method for the calculation of electronic states of a wide range of molecular systems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.08154</link>
    <author>Kerstin Beer</author>
    <pubDate>May 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This PhD thesis combines two of the most exciting research areas of the last decades: quantum computing and machine learning. We introduce dissipative quantum neural networks (DQNNs), which are designed for fully quantum learning tasks, are capable of universal quantum computation and have low memory requirements while training. These networks are optimised with training data pairs in form of input and desired output states and therefore can be used for characterising unknown or untrusted quantum devices. We not only demonstrate the generalisation behaviour of DQNNs using classical simulations, but also implement them successfully on actual quantum computers. To understand the ultimate limits for such quantum machine learning methods, we discuss the quantum no free lunch theorem, which describes a bound on the probability that a quantum device, which can be modelled as a unitary process and is optimised with quantum examples, gives an incorrect output for a random input. Moreover we expand the area of applications of DQNNs in two directions. In the first case, we include additional information beyond just the training data pairs: since quantum devices are always structured, the resulting data is always structured as well. We modify the DQNN's training algorithm such that knowledge about the graph-structure of the training data pairs is included in the training process and show that this can lead to better generalisation behaviour. Both the original DQNN and the DQNN including graph structure are trained with data pairs in order to characterise an underlying relation. However, in the second extension of the algorithm we aim to learn characteristics of a set of quantum states in order to extend it to quantum states which have similar properties. Therefore we build a generative adversarial model where two DQNNs, called the generator and discriminator, are trained in a competitive way.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Power and limitations of single-qubit native quantum neural networks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.07848</link>
    <author>Zhan Yu, Hongshun Yao, Mujin Li, Xin Wang</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum neural networks (QNNs) have emerged as a leading strategy to establish applications in machine learning, chemistry, and optimization. While the applications of QNN have been widely investigated, its theoretical foundation remains less understood. In this paper, we formulate a theoretical framework for the expressive ability of data re-uploading quantum neural networks that consist of interleaved encoding circuit blocks and trainable circuit blocks. First, we prove that single-qubit quantum neural networks can approximate any univariate function by mapping the model to a partial Fourier series. Beyond previous works' understanding of existence, we in particular establish the exact correlations between the parameters of the trainable gates and the working Fourier coefficients, by exploring connections to quantum signal processing. Second, we discuss the limitations of single-qubit native QNNs on approximating multivariate functions by analyzing the frequency spectrum and the flexibility of Fourier coefficients. We further demonstrate the expressivity and limitations of single-qubit native QNNs via numerical experiments. As applications, we introduce natural extensions to multi-qubit quantum neural networks, which exhibit the capability of classifying real-world multi-dimensional data. We believe these results would improve our understanding of QNNs and provide a helpful guideline for designing powerful QNNs for machine learning tasks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Variational learning algorithms for quantum query complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.07449</link>
    <author>Zipeng Wu, Shi-Yao Hou, Chao Zhang, Lvzhou Li, Bei Zeng</author>
    <pubDate>May 17 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum query complexity plays an important role in studying quantum algorithms, which captures the most known quantum algorithms, such as search and period finding. A query algorithm applies $U_tO_x\cdots U_1O_xU_0$ to some input state, where $O_x$ is the oracle dependent on some input variable $x$, and $U_i$s are unitary operations that are independent of $x$, followed by some measurements for readout. In this work, we develop variational learning algorithms to study quantum query complexity, by formulating $U_i$s as parameterized quantum circuits and introducing a loss function that is directly given by the error probability of the query algorithm. We apply our method to analyze various cases of quantum query complexity, including a new algorithm solving the Hamming modulo problem with $4$ queries for the case of $5$-bit modulo $5$, answering an open question raised in arXiv:2112.14682, and the result is further confirmed by a Semidefinite Programming (SDP) algorithm. Compared with the SDP algorithm, our method can be readily implemented on the near-term Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) devices and is more flexible to be adapted to other cases such as the fractional query models.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Barren plateaus from learning scramblers with local cost functions</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.06679</link>
    <author>Roy J. Garcia, Chen Zhao, Kaifeng Bu, Arthur Jaffe</author>
    <pubDate>May 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The existence of barren plateaus has recently revealed new training challenges in quantum machine learning (QML). Uncovering the mechanisms behind barren plateaus is essential in understanding the scope of problems that QML can efficiently tackle. Barren plateaus have recently been shown to exist when learning global properties of random unitaries. Establishing whether local cost functions can circumvent these barren plateaus is pertinent if we hope to apply QML to quantum many-body systems. We prove a no-go theorem showing that local cost functions encounter barren plateaus in learning random unitary properties.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>