<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum many-body systems in thermal equilibrium</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08349</link>
    <author>Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The thermal or equilibrium ensemble is one of the most ubiquitous states of matter. For models comprised of many locally interacting quantum particles, it describes a wide range of physical situations, relevant to condensed matter physics, high energy physics, quantum chemistry and quantum computing, among others. We give a pedagogical overview of some of the most important universal features about the physics and complexity of these states, which have the locality of the Hamiltonian at its core. We focus on mathematically rigorous statements, many of them inspired by ideas and tools from quantum information theory. These include bounds on their correlations, the form of the subsystems, various statistical properties, and the performance of classical and quantum algorithms. We also include a summary of a few of the most important technical tools, as well as some self-contained proofs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Clifford Circuits can be Properly PAC Learned if and only if $\textsf{RP}=\textsf{NP}$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06638</link>
    <author>Daniel Liang</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Given a dataset of input states, measurements, and probabilities, is it possible to efficiently predict the measurement probabilities associated with a quantum circuit? Recent work of Caro and Datta (2020) studied the problem of PAC learning quantum circuits in an information theoretic sense, leaving open questions of computational efficiency. In particular, one candidate class of circuits for which an efficient learner might have been possible was that of Clifford circuits, since the corresponding set of states generated by such circuits, called stabilizer states, are known to be efficiently PAC learnable (Rocchetto 2018). Here we provide a negative result, showing that proper learning of CNOT circuits is hard for classical learners unless $\textsf{RP} = \textsf{NP}$. As the classical analogue and subset of Clifford circuits, this naturally leads to a hardness result for Clifford circuits as well. Additionally, we show that if $\textsf{RP} = \textsf{NP}$ then there would exist efficient proper learning algorithms for CNOT and Clifford circuits. By similar arguments, we also find that an efficient proper quantum learner for such circuits exists if and only if $\textsf{NP} \subseteq \textsf{RQP}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Imaging stars with quantum error correction</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06044</link>
    <author>Zixin Huang, Gavin K. Brennen, Yingkai Ouyang</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The development of high-resolution, large-baseline optical interferometers would revolutionize astronomical imaging. However, classical techniques are hindered by physical limitations including loss, noise, and the fact that the received light is generally quantum in nature. We show how to overcome these issues using quantum communication techniques. We present a general framework for using quantum error correction codes for protecting and imaging starlight received at distant telescope sites. In our scheme, the quantum state of light is coherently captured into a non-radiative atomic state via Stimulated Raman Adiabatic Passage, which is then imprinted into a quantum error correction code. The code protects the signal during subsequent potentially noisy operations necessary to extract the image parameters. We show that even a small quantum error correction code can offer significant protection against noise. For large codes, we find noise thresholds below which the information can be preserved. Our scheme represents an application for near-term quantum devices that can increase imaging resolution beyond what is feasible using classical techniques.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Establishing trust in quantum computations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07568</link>
    <author>Timothy Proctor, Stefan Seritan, Erik Nielsen, Kenneth Rudinger, Kevin Young, Robin Blume-Kohout, Mohan Sarovar</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Real-world quantum computers have grown sufficiently complex that they can no longer be simulated by classical supercomputers, but their computational power remains limited by errors. These errors corrupt the results of quantum algorithms, and it is no longer always feasible to use classical simulations to directly check the correctness of quantum computations. Without practical methods for quantifying the accuracy with which a quantum algorithm has been executed, it is difficult to establish trust in the results of a quantum computation. Here we solve this problem, by introducing a simple and efficient technique for measuring the fidelity with which an as-built quantum computer can execute an algorithm. Our technique converts the algorithm's quantum circuits into a set of closely related circuits whose success rates can be efficiently measured. It enables measuring the fidelity of quantum algorithm executions both in the near-term, with algorithms run on hundreds or thousands of physical qubits, and into the future, with algorithms run on logical qubits protected by quantum error correction.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Tight Bounds for Quantum State Certification with Incoherent Measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07155</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Brice Huang, Jerry Li, Allen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the problem of quantum state certification, where we are given the description of a mixed state $\sigma \in \mathbb{C}^{d \times d}$, $n$ copies of a mixed state $\rho \in \mathbb{C}^{d \times d}$, and $\varepsilon > 0$, and we are asked to determine whether $\rho = \sigma$ or whether $\| \rho - \sigma \|_1 > \varepsilon$. When $\sigma$ is the maximally mixed state $\frac{1}{d} I_d$, this is known as mixedness testing. We focus on algorithms which use incoherent measurements, i.e. which only measure one copy of $\rho$ at a time. Unlike those that use entangled, multi-copy measurements, these can be implemented without persistent quantum memory and thus represent a large class of protocols that can be run on current or near-term devices. For mixedness testing, there is a folklore algorithm which uses incoherent measurements and only needs $O(d^{3/2} / \varepsilon^2)$ copies. The algorithm is non-adaptive, that is, its measurements are fixed ahead of time, and is known to be optimal for non-adaptive algorithms. However, when the algorithm can make arbitrary incoherent measurements, the best known lower bound is only $\Omega (d^{4/3} / \varepsilon^2)$ [Bubeck-Chen-Li '20], and it has been an outstanding open problem to close this polynomial gap. In this work, 1) we settle the copy complexity of mixedness testing with incoherent measurements and show that $\Omega (d^{3/2} / \varepsilon^2)$ copies are necessary, and 2) we show the instance-optimal bounds for state certification to general $\sigma$ first derived by [Chen-Li-O'Donnell '21] for non-adaptive measurements also hold for arbitrary incoherent measurements. Qualitatively, our results say that adaptivity does not help at all for these problems. Our results are based on new techniques that allow us to reduce the problem to understanding certain matrix martingales, which we believe may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Beyond i.i.d. in the Resource Theory of Asymmetry: An Information-Spectrum Approach for Quantum Fisher Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08439</link>
    <author>Koji Yamaguchi, Hiroyasu Tajima</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Energetic coherence is a valuable resource for various operations, including precise measurement of time and acceleration of quantum manipulations. Recently, it has been shown that the theory of energetic coherence, called the resource theory of asymmetry, has a thermodynamic structure, as do entanglement theory and quantum thermodynamics. In the so-called i.i.d. regime, where identical copies of a state are converted into identical copies of another state, the convertibility is entirely determined by the amount of energetic coherence measured by the quantum Fisher information (QFI). This fact means that QFI takes the place of entropy in thermodynamics and entanglement entropy in entanglement theory. So far, such a correspondence between energetic coherence and entropy is known only in the i.i.d. regime. In entanglement theory and quantum thermodynamics in the non-i.i.d. regime, entropy-related quantities based on the information-spectrum method reveal a non-equilibrium thermodynamics structure. Still, it has been an open question whether a similar structure exists for energetic coherence. In this Letter, we solve this problem by constructing an information-spectrum method applicable to the quantum Fisher information content. As a result, we establish a general theory of the pure-state convertibility in the non-i.i.d. regime of the resource theory of asymmetry. The given theory reveals a non-equilibrium thermodynamic structure of energetic coherence in the non-i.i.d. regime, based on QFI rather than entropy.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>ADAPT-VQE is insensitive to rough parameter landscapes and barren plateaus</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07179</link>
    <author>Harper R. Grimsley, George S. Barron, Edwin Barnes, Sophia E. Economou, Nicholas J. Mayhall</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum eigensolvers (VQEs) represent a powerful class of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms for computing molecular energies. Various numerical issues exist for these methods, however, including barren plateaus and large numbers of local minima. In this work, we consider Adaptive, Problem-Tailored (ADAPT)-VQE ansätze, and examine how they are impacted by these local minima. We find that while ADAPT-VQE does not remove local minima, the gradient-informed, one-operator-at-a-time circuit construction seems to accomplish two things: First, it provides an initialization strategy that is dramatically better than random initialization, and which is applicable in situations where chemical intuition cannot help with initialization, i.e., when Hartree-Fock is a poor approximation to the ground state. Second, even if an ADAPT-VQE iteration converges to a local trap at one step, it can still "burrow" toward the exact solution by adding more operators, which preferentially deepens the occupied trap. This same mechanism helps highlight a surprising feature of ADAPT-VQE: It should not suffer optimization problems due to "barren plateaus". Even if barren plateaus appear in the parameter landscape, our analysis and simulations reveal that ADAPT-VQE avoids such regions by design.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Matrix Product Operator Algebras II: Phases of Matter for 1D Mixed States</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06295</link>
    <author>Alberto Ruiz de Alarcón, José Garre-Rubio, András Molnár, David Pérez-García</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The classification of topological phases of matter is fundamental to understand and characterize the properties of quantum materials. In this paper we study phases of matter in one-dimensional open quantum systems. We define two mixed states to be in the same phase if both states can be transformed into the other by a shallow circuit of local quantum channels. We aim to understand the phase diagram of matrix product density operators that are renormalization fixed points. These states arise, for example, as boundaries of two-dimensional topologically ordered states. We first construct families of such states based on C*-weak Hopf algebras, the algebras whose representations form a fusion category. More concretely, we provide explicit local fine-graining and local coarse-graining quantum channels for the renormalization procedure of these states. Finally, we prove that those arising from C*-Hopf algebras are in the trivial phase.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Improving the efficiency of learning-based error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07109</link>
    <author>Piotr Czarnik, Michael McKerns, Andrew T. Sornborger, Lukasz Cincio</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Error mitigation will play an important role in practical applications of near-term noisy quantum computers. Current error mitigation methods typically concentrate on correction quality at the expense of frugality (as measured by the number of additional calls to quantum hardware). To fill the need for highly accurate, yet inexpensive techniques, we introduce an error mitigation scheme that builds on Clifford data regression (CDR). The scheme improves the frugality by carefully choosing the training data and exploiting the symmetries of the problem. We test our approach by correcting long range correlators of the ground state of XY Hamiltonian on IBM Toronto quantum computer. We find that our method is an order of magnitude cheaper while maintaining the same accuracy as the original CDR approach. The efficiency gain enables us to obtain a factor of $10$ improvement on the unmitigated results with the total budget as small as $2\cdot10^5$ shots.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Simplicial quantum contextuality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.06648</link>
    <author>Cihan Okay, Aziz Kharoof, Selman Ipek</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a new framework for contextuality based on simplicial sets, combinatorial models of topological spaces that play a prominent role in modern homotopy theory. Our approach extends measurement scenarios to consist of spaces (rather than sets) of measurements and outcomes, and thereby generalizes nonsignaling distributions to simplicial distributions, which are distributions on spaces modeled by simplicial sets. Using this formalism we present a topologically inspired new proof of Fine's theorem for characterizing noncontextuality in Bell scenarios. Strong contextuality is generalized suitably for simplicial distributions, allowing us to define cohomological witnesses that extend the earlier topological constructions restricted to algebraic relations among quantum observables to the level of probability distributions. Foundational theorems of quantum theory such as the Gleason's theorem and Kochen-Specker theorem can be expressed naturally within this new language.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>