<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>A mathematical framework for quantum Hamiltonian simulation and duality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11941</link>
    <author>Harriet Apel, Toby Cubitt</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Analogue Hamiltonian simulation is a promising near-term application of quantum computing and has recently been put on a theoretical footing. In Hamiltonian simulation, a physical Hamiltonian is engineered to have identical physics to another - often very different - Hamiltonian. This is qualitatively similar to the notion of duality in physics, whereby two superficially different theories are mathematically equivalent in some precise sense. However, existing characterisations of Hamiltonian simulations are not sufficiently general to extend to all dualities in physics. In particular, they cannot encompass the important cases of strong/weak and high-temperature/low-temperature dualities. In this work, we give three physically motivated axiomatisations of duality, formulated respectively in terms of observables, partition functions and entropies. We prove that these axiomatisations are equivalent, and characterise the mathematical form that any duality satisfying these axioms must take. A building block in one of our results is a strengthening of earlier results on entropy-preserving maps to maps that are entropy-preserving up to an additive constant, which we prove decompose as a direct sum of unitary and anti-unitary components, which may be of independent mathematical interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exponential concentration and untrainability in quantum kernel methods</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11060</link>
    <author>Supanut Thanasilp, Samson Wang, M. Cerezo, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Kernel methods in Quantum Machine Learning (QML) have recently gained significant attention as a potential candidate for achieving a quantum advantage in data analysis. Among other attractive properties, when training a kernel-based model one is guaranteed to find the optimal model's parameters due to the convexity of the training landscape. However, this is based on the assumption that the quantum kernel can be efficiently obtained from a quantum hardware. In this work we study the trainability of quantum kernels from the perspective of the resources needed to accurately estimate kernel values. We show that, under certain conditions, values of quantum kernels over different input data can be exponentially concentrated (in the number of qubits) towards some fixed value, leading to an exponential scaling of the number of measurements required for successful training. We identify four sources that can lead to concentration including: the expressibility of data embedding, global measurements, entanglement and noise. For each source, an associated concentration bound of quantum kernels is analytically derived. Lastly, we show that when dealing with classical data, training a parametrized data embedding with a kernel alignment method is also susceptible to exponential concentration. Our results are verified through numerical simulations for several QML tasks. Altogether, we provide guidelines indicating that certain features should be avoided to ensure the efficient evaluation and the trainability of quantum kernel methods.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Alternating Layered Variational Quantum Circuits Can Be Classically Optimized Efficiently Using Classical Shadows</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11623</link>
    <author>Afrad Basheer, Yuan Feng, Christopher Ferrie, Sanjiang Li</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Variational quantum algorithms (VQAs) are the quantum analog of classical neural networks (NNs). A VQA consists of a parameterized quantum circuit (PQC) which is composed of multiple layers of ansatzes (simpler PQCs, which are an analogy of NN layers) that differ only in selections of parameters. Previous work has identified the alternating layered ansatz as potentially a new standard ansatz in near-term quantum computing. Indeed, shallow alternating layered VQAs are easy to implement and have been shown to be both trainable and expressive. In this work, we introduce a training algorithm with an exponential reduction in training cost of such VQAs. Moreover, our algorithm uses classical shadows of quantum input data, and can hence be run on a classical computer with rigorous performance guarantees. We demonstrate 2--3 orders of magnitude improvement in the training cost using our algorithm for the example problems of finding state preparation circuits and the quantum autoencoder.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>No [[n, k, d < 86]] code can violate the quantum Hamming bound</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11800</link>
    <author>Emanuel Dallas, Faidon Andreadakis, Daniel Lidar</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>It is well-known that pure quantum error correcting codes (QECCs) are constrained by a quantum version of the Hamming bound. Whether impure codes also obey such a bound, however, remains a long-standing question with practical implications for the efficacy of QECCs. We employ a combination of previously derived bounds on QECCs to demonstrate that a subset of all codes must obey the quantum Hamming bound. Specifically, we combine an analytical bound due to Rains with a numerical bound due to Li and Xing to show that no [[n,k,d < 86]] code can violate the quantum Hamming bound.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A SAT Encoding for Optimal Clifford Circuit Synthesis</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11713</link>
    <author>Sarah Schneider, Lukas Burgholzer, Robert Wille</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Executing quantum algorithms on a quantum computer requires compilation to representations that conform to all restrictions imposed by the device. Due to device's limited coherence times and gate fidelities, the compilation process has to be optimized as much as possible. To this end, an algorithm's description first has to be synthesized using the device's gate library. In this paper, we consider the optimal synthesis of Clifford circuits -- an important subclass of quantum circuits, with various applications. Such techniques are essential to establish lower bounds for (heuristic) synthesis methods and gauging their performance. Due to the huge search space, existing optimal techniques are limited to a maximum of six qubits. The contribution of this work is twofold: First, we propose an optimal synthesis method for Clifford circuits based on encoding the task as a satisfiability (SAT) problem and solving it using a SAT solver in conjunction with a binary search scheme. The resulting tool is demonstrated to synthesize optimal circuits for up to $26$ qubits -- more than four times as many as the current state of the art. Second, we experimentally show that the overhead introduced by state-of-the-art heuristics exceeds the lower bound by $27\%$ on average. The resulting tool is publicly available at https://github.com/cda-tum/qmap.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Comparison of unknown unitary channels with multiple uses</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12519</link>
    <author>Yutaka Hashimoto, Akihito Soeda, Mio Murao</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Comparison of quantum objects is a task to determine whether two unknown quantum objects are the same or different. It is one of the most basic information processing tasks for learning property of quantum objects, and comparison of quantum states, quantum channels, and quantum measurements have been investigated. In general, repeated uses of quantum objects improve the success probability of comparison. The optimal strategy of pure-state comparison, the comparison of quantum states for the case of multiple copies of each unknown pure state, is known, but the optimal strategy of unitary comparison, the comparison of quantum channels for the case of multiple uses of each unknown unitary channel, was not known due to the complication of the varieties of causal order structures among the uses of each unitary channel. In this paper, we investigate unitary comparison with multiple uses of unitary channels based on the quantum tester formalism. We obtain the optimal minimum-error and the optimal unambiguous strategies of unitary comparison of two unknown $d$-dimensional unitary channels $U_1$ and $U_2$ when $U_1$ can be used $N_1$ times and $U_2$ can be used $N_2$ times for $N_2 \ge (d-1)N_1$. These optimal strategies are implemented by parallel uses of the unitary channels, even though all sequential and adaptive strategies implementable by the quantum circuit model are considered. When the number of the smaller uses of the unitary channels $N_1$ is fixed, the optimal averaged success probability cannot be improved by adding more uses of $U_2$ than $N_2 = (d-1) N_1$. This feature is in contrast to the case of pure-state comparison, where adding more copies of the unknown pure states always improves the optimal averaged success probability. It highlights the difference between corresponding tasks for states and channels, which has been previously shown for quantum discrimination tasks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>No graph states can be prepared in quantum networks with bipartite sources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.12099</link>
    <author>Owidiusz Makuta, Laurens T. Ligthart, Remigiusz Augusiak</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In research concerning quantum networks, it is often assumed that the parties can classically communicate with each other. However, classical communication might introduce substantial delay to the network, especially if it is large. As the latency of a network is one of its most important characteristics, it is interesting to consider quantum networks in which parties cannot communicate classically and ask what limitations this assumption imposes on the possibility of preparing multipartite states in such networks. We show that graph states of arbitrary prime local dimension known for their numerous applications in quantum information cannot be generated in a quantum network in which parties are connected via sources of bipartite quantum states and the classical communication is replaced by some pre-shared classical correlations. We then generalise our result to arbitrary quantum states that are sufficiently close to graph states.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Measurement-Prepared Quantum Criticality: from Ising model to gauge theory, and beyond</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11699</link>
    <author>Jong Yeon Lee, Wenjie Ji, Zhen Bi, Matthew P. A. Fisher</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Measurements allow efficient preparation of interesting quantum many-body states exhibiting long-range, topological, or fractonic orders. Here, we prove that the so-called conformal quantum critical points (CQCP) can be obtained by performing general single-site measurements in appropriate basis on the cluster states in $d\geq2$. The equal-time correlators of the said states are described by correlation functions of a certain $d$-dimensional classical model at the critical temperature, featuring spatial conformal invariance. This establishes an exact correspondence between the measurement-prepared critical states and conformal field theories of a range of critical spin models, including familiar Ising model and gauge theories among others. Furthermore, by mapping the correlations of the measured quantum state into the statistical mechanics problem, we establish the stability of long-range or topological orders with respect to measurements deviating from the ideal setting, without any post-selection. Therefore, our findings suggest a novel mechanism in which a quantum critical wavefunction emerges, providing new practical ways to study quantum phases and conformal quantum critical points.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Nishimori's cat: stable long-range entanglement from finite-depth unitaries and weak measurements</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11136</link>
    <author>Guo-Yi Zhu, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Ashvin Vishwanath, Simon Trebst, Ruben Verresen</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 25 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the field of monitored quantum circuits, it has remained an open question whether finite-time protocols for preparing long-range entangled (LRE) states lead to phases of matter which are stable to gate imperfections. Here we show that such gate imperfections effectively convert projective into weak measurements and that, in certain cases, long-range entanglement persists, even in the presence of weak measurements and gives rise to novel forms of quantum criticality. We demonstrate this explicitly for preparing the two-dimensional (2D) GHZ cat state and the three-dimensional (3D) toric code as minimal instances. In contrast to previous studies on measurement-induced phases and transitions, our circuit of gates and measurements is deterministic; the only randomness is in the measurement outcomes. We show how the randomness in these weak measurements allows us to track the solvable Nishimori line of the random-bond Ising model, rigorously establishing the stability of the glassy LRE states in two and three spatial dimensions. Away from this exactly solvable construction, we use hybrid tensor network and Monte Carlo simulations to obtain a non-zero Edwards-Anderson order parameter as an indicator of long-range entanglement in the 2D scenario. We argue that our protocol admits a natural implementation in existing quantum computing architectures, requiring only a depth-3 circuit on IBM's heavy-hexagon transmon chips.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Solvable model of deep thermalization with distinct design times</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.10542</link>
    <author>Matteo Ippoliti, Wen Wei Ho</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We study the emergence over time of a universal, uniform distribution of quantum states on a finite subsystem, induced by projectively measuring the rest of the system. Dubbed deep thermalization, this phenomenon represents a form of equilibration in quantum many-body systems stronger than regular thermalization, which only constrains the ensemble-averaged values of observables. While there exist quantum circuit models of dynamics in one dimension where this phenomenon can be shown to arise exactly, these are special in that deep thermalization occurs at precisely the same time as regular thermalization. Here, we present an exactly-solvable model of chaotic dynamics where the two processes can be shown to occur over different time scales. The model is composed of a finite subsystem coupled to an infinite random-matrix bath through a small constriction, and highlights the role of locality and imperfect thermalization in constraining the formation of such universal wavefunction distributions. We test our analytical predictions against exact numerical simulations, finding excellent agreement.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>