<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum supremacy in mechanical tasks: projectiles, rockets and quantum backflow</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00725</link>
    <author>David Trillo, Thinh P. Le, Miguel Navascues</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider a scenario where a non-relativistic one-dimensional quantum particle is prepared in some bounded region of space and left to propagate freely. After a certain amount of time, we check if the particle has reached some distant target region. We find that there exist "ultrafast" ("ultraslow") quantum states, whose probability of arrival is greater (smaller) than that of any classical system prepared in the same region with the same momentum distribution. We prove that the maximum possible difference between quantum and optimal classical arrival probabilities for projectiles, as well as for self-propelling particles or rockets, is limited by the Bracken-Melloy constant $c_{bm}$, introduced in $1969$ to characterize the maximum expression of the phenomenon known as quantum backflow. This mathematical correspondence extends to other examples of mechanical effects with a quantum advantage, whose study we advance by deriving the first rigorous upper bound $c_{bm} \leq 0.0725$. We also prove that the hard limit given by $c_{bm}$ can be overcome in a variant of the original projectile scenario: if the classical particle is required to possess, not just the same momentum distribution as the quantum particle, but also the same position distribution, then the difference between arrival probabilities can reach $0.1228$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Decomposition of Matrix Product States into Shallow Quantum Circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00595</link>
    <author>Manuel S. Rudolph, Jing Chen, Jacob Miller, Atithi Acharya, Alejandro Perdomo-Ortiz</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The rapid pace of recent advancements in numerical computation, notably the rise of GPU and TPU hardware accelerators, have allowed tensor network (TN) algorithms to scale to even larger quantum simulation problems, and to be employed more broadly for solving machine learning tasks. The "quantum-inspired" nature of TNs permits them to be mapped to parametrized quantum circuits (PQCs), a fact which has inspired recent proposals for enhancing the performance of TN algorithms using near-term quantum devices, as well as enabling joint quantum-classical training frameworks which benefit from the distinct strengths of TN and PQC models. However, the success of any such methods depends on efficient and accurate methods for approximating TN states using realistic quantum circuits, something which remains an unresolved question. In this work, we compare a range of novel and previously-developed algorithmic protocols for decomposing matrix product states (MPS) of arbitrary bond dimensions into low-depth quantum circuits consisting of stacked linear layers of two-qubit unitaries. These protocols are formed from different combinations of a preexisting analytical decomposition scheme with constrained optimization of circuit unitaries, and all possess efficient classical runtimes. Our experimental results reveal one particular protocol, involving sequential growth and optimization of the quantum circuit, to outperform all other methods, with even greater benefits seen in the setting of limited computational resources. Given these promising results, we expect our proposed decomposition protocol to form a useful ingredient within any joint application of TNs and PQCs, in turn further unlocking the rich and complementary benefits of classical and quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Software Tools for Decoding Quantum Low-Density Parity Check Codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01180</link>
    <author>Lucas Berent, Lukas Burgholzer, Robert Wille</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Error Correction (QEC) is an essential field of research towards the realization of large-scale quantum computers. On the theoretical side, a lot of effort is put into designing error-correcting codes that protect quantum data from errors, which inevitably happen due to the noisy nature of quantum hardware and quantum bits (qubits). Protecting data with an error-correcting code necessitates means to recover the original data, given a potentially corrupted data set-a task referred to as decoding. It is vital that decoding algorithms can recover error-free states in an efficient manner. While theoretical properties of recent QEC methods have been extensively studied, good techniques to analyze their performance in practically more relevant settings is still a widely unexplored area. In this work, we propose a set of software tools that allows to numerically experiment with so-called Quantum Low-Density Parity Check codes (QLDPC codes)-a broad class of codes, some of which have recently been shown to be asymptotically good. Based on that, we provide an implementation of a general decoder for QLDPC codes. On top of that, we propose an efficient heuristic decoder that tackles the runtime bottlenecks of the general QLDPC decoder while still maintaining comparable decoding performance. These tools eventually allow to confirm theoretical results around QLDPC codes in a more practical setting and showcase the value of software tools (in addition to theoretical considerations) for investigating codes for practical applications. The resulting tool, which is publicly available at https://github.com/lucasberent/qecc under the MIT license, is meant to provide a playground for the search for "practically good" quantum codes.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Sample optimal tomography of quantum Markov chains</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02240</link>
    <author>Li Gao, Nengkun Yu</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>A state on a tripartite quantum system $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C} $ forms a Markov chain, i.e., quantum conditional independence, if it can be reconstructed from its marginal on $\mathcal{H}_{A}\otimes \mathcal{H}_{B}$ by a quantum operation from $\mathcal{H}_{B}$ to $\mathcal{H}_{B}\otimes\mathcal{H}_{C}$ via the famous Petz map: a quantum Markov chain $\rho_{ABC}$ satisfies $\rho_{ABC}=\rho_{BC}^{1/2}(\rho_B^{-1/2}\rho_{AB}\rho_B^{-1/2}\otimes id_C)\rho_{BC}^{1/2}$. In this paper, we study the robustness of the Petz map for different metrics, i.e., the closeness of marginals implies the closeness of the Petz map outcomes. The robustness results are dimension-independent for infidelity $\delta$ and trace distance $\epsilon$. The applications of robustness results are The sample complexity of quantum Markov chain tomography, i.e., how many copies of an unknown quantum Markov chain are necessary and sufficient to determine the state, is $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\delta})$, and $\tilde{\Theta}(\frac{(d_A^2+d_C^2)d_B^2}{\epsilon^2}) $. The sample complexity of quantum Markov Chain certification, i.e., to certify whether a tripartite state equals a fixed given quantum Markov Chain $\sigma_{ABC}$ or at least $\delta$-far from $\sigma_{ABC}$, is ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\delta})$, and ${\Theta}(\frac{(d_A+d_C)d_B}{\epsilon^2})$. $\tilde{O}(\frac{\min\{d_Ad_B^3d_C^3,d_A^3d_B^3d_C\}}{\epsilon^2})$ copies to test whether $\rho_{ABC}$ is a quantum Markov Chain or $\epsilon$-far from its Petz recovery state. We generalized the tomography results into multipartite quantum system by showing $\tilde{O}(\frac{n^2\max_{i} \{d_i^2d_{i+1}^2\}}{\delta})$ copies for infidelity $\delta$ are enough for $n$-partite quantum Markov chain tomography with $d_i$ being the dimension of the $i$-th subsystem.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Barren plateaus in quantum tensor network optimization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00292</link>
    <author>Enrique Cervero Martín, Kirill Plekhanov, Michael Lubasch</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We analyze the barren plateau phenomenon in the variational optimization of quantum circuits inspired by matrix product states (qMPS), tree tensor networks (qTTN), and the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (qMERA). We consider as the cost function the expectation value of a Hamiltonian that is a sum of local terms. For randomly chosen variational parameters we show that the variance of the cost function gradient decreases exponentially with the distance of a Hamiltonian term from the canonical centre in the quantum tensor network. Therefore, as a function of qubit count, for qMPS most gradient variances decrease exponentially and for qTTN as well as qMERA they decrease polynomially. We also show that the calculation of these gradients is exponentially more efficient on a classical computer than on a quantum computer.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Transition states and greedy exploration of the QAOA optimization landscape</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.01159</link>
    <author>Stefan H. Sack, Raimel A. Medina, Richard Kueng, Maksym Serbyn</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 05 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The QAOA is a variational quantum algorithm, where a quantum computer implements a variational ansatz consisting of p layers of alternating unitary operators and a classical computer is used to optimize the variational parameters. For a random initialization the optimization typically leads to local minima with poor performance, motivating the search for initialization strategies of QAOA variational parameters. Although numerous heuristic intializations were shown to have a good numerical performance, an analytical understanding remains evasive. Inspired by the study of energy landscapes, in this work we focus on so-called transition states (TS) that are saddle points with a unique negative curvature direction that connects to local minima. Starting from a local minimum of QAOA with p layers, we analytically construct 2p + 1 TS for QAOA with p + 1 layers. These TS connect to new local minima, all of which are guaranteed to lower the energy compared to the minimum found for p layers. We introduce a Greedy procedure to effectively maneuver the exponentially increasing number of TS and corresponding local minima. The performance of our procedure matches the best available initialization strategy, and in addition provides a guarantee for the minimal energy to decrease with an increasing number of layers p. Generalization of analytic TS and the Greedy approach to other ansätze may provide a universal framework for initialization of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Some continuity properties of quantum Rényi divergences</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00646</link>
    <author>Milán Mosonyi</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In the problem of binary quantum channel discrimination with product inputs, the supremum of all type II error exponents for which the optimal type I errors go to zero is equal to the Umegaki channel relative entropy, while the infimum of all type II error exponents for which the optimal type I errors go to one is equal to the infimum of the sandwiched channel Rényi $\alpha$-divergences over all $\alpha>1$. Here we prove that these two threshold values coincide, thus proving, in particular, the strong converse property for this problem. Our proof method uses a minimax argument, which crucially relies on a newly established continuity property of the sandwiched Rényi $\alpha$-divergences for $\alpha\in(1,2]$. Motivated by this, we also prove various other continuity properties for quantum (channel) Rény divergences, which may be of independent interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Approximation Algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.02589</link>
    <author>Robbie King</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give an approximation algorithm for Quantum Max-Cut which works by rounding an SDP relaxation to an entangled quantum state. The SDP is used to choose the parameters of a variational quantum circuit. The entangled state is then represented as the quantum circuit applied to a product state. It achieves an approximation ratio of 0.582, significantly improving on the algorithms of Anshu, Gosset, Morenz, 0.531, and Parekh, Thompson, 0.533. In addition, we also study the EPR Hamiltonian, which we argue is a natural intermediate problem which isolates some key quantum features of local Hamiltonian problems. For the EPR Hamiltonian, we give an approximation algorithm with approximation ratio $\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Operational Interpretation of the Sandwiched Rényi Divergences of Order 1/2 to 1 as Strong Converse Exponents</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00554</link>
    <author>Ke Li, Yongsheng Yao</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide the sandwiched Rényi divergence of order $\alpha\in(\frac{1}{2},1)$, as well as its induced quantum information quantities, with an operational interpretation in the characterization of the exact strong converse exponents of quantum tasks. Specifically, we consider (a) smoothing of the max-relative entropy, (b) quantum privacy amplification, and (c) quantum information decoupling. We solve the problem of determining the exact strong converse exponents for these three tasks, with the performance being measured by the fidelity or purified distance. The results are given in terms of the sandwiched Rényi divergence of order $\alpha\in(\frac{1}{2},1)$, and its induced quantum Rényi conditional entropy and quantum Rényi mutual information. This is the first time to find the precise operational meaning for the sandwiched Rényi divergence with Rényi parameter in the interval $\alpha\in(\frac{1}{2},1)$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Mixed State Compiling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.00528</link>
    <author>Nic Ezzell, Elliott M. Ball, Aliza U. Siddiqui, Mark M. Wilde, Andrew T. Sornborger, Patrick J. Coles, Zoë Holmes</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 02 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The task of learning a quantum circuit to prepare a given mixed state is a fundamental quantum subroutine. We present a variational quantum algorithm (VQA) to learn mixed states which is suitable for near-term hardware. Our algorithm represents a generalization of previous VQAs that aimed at learning preparation circuits for pure states. We consider two different ansätze for compiling the target state; the first is based on learning a purification of the state and the second on representing it as a convex combination of pure states. In both cases, the resources required to store and manipulate the compiled state grow with the rank of the approximation. Thus, by learning a lower rank approximation of the target state, our algorithm provides a means of compressing a state for more efficient processing. As a byproduct of our algorithm, one effectively learns the principal components of the target state, and hence our algorithm further provides a new method for principal component analysis. We investigate the efficacy of our algorithm through extensive numerical implementations, showing that typical random states and thermal states of many body systems may be learnt this way. Additionally, we demonstrate on quantum hardware how our algorithm can be used to study hardware noise-induced states.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>