<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">

<channel>
  <title>Top Scirate Papers</title>
  <link>https://www.scirate.com</link>
  <description>The feed lists the top "scited" papers on the scirate website, often featuring the most widely appreciated quantum physics (quant-ph) preprints.</description>

  <item>
    <title>NLTS Hamiltonians from good quantum codes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13228</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas P. Breuckmann, Chinmay Nirkhe</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of non-trivial complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). We prove this conjecture by showing that the recently discovered families of constant-rate and linear-distance QLDPC codes correspond to NLTS local Hamiltonians.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The randomized measurement toolbox</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.11374</link>
    <author>Andreas Elben, Steven T. Flammia, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, John Preskill, Benoît Vermersch, Peter Zoller</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Increasingly sophisticated programmable quantum simulators and quantum computers are opening unprecedented opportunities for exploring and exploiting the properties of highly entangled complex quantum systems. The complexity of large quantum systems is the source of their power, but also makes them difficult to control precisely or characterize accurately using measured classical data. We review recently developed protocols for probing the properties of complex many-qubit systems using measurement schemes that are practical using today's quantum platforms. In all these protocols, a quantum state is repeatedly prepared and measured in a randomly chosen basis; then a classical computer processes the measurement outcomes to estimate the desired property. The randomization of the measurement procedure has distinct advantages; for example, a single data set can be employed multiple times to pursue a variety of applications, and imperfections in the measurements are mapped to a simplified noise model that can more easily be mitigated. We discuss a range of use cases that have already been realized in quantum devices, including Hamiltonian simulation tasks, probes of quantum chaos, measurements of nonlocal order parameters, and comparison of quantum states produced in distantly separated laboratories. By providing a workable method for translating a complex quantum state into a succinct classical representation that preserves a rich variety of relevant physical properties, the randomized measurement toolbox strengthens our ability to grasp and control the quantum world.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Complexity of NISQ</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.07234</link>
    <author>Sitan Chen, Jordan Cotler, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Jerry Li</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The recent proliferation of NISQ devices has made it imperative to understand their computational power. In this work, we define and study the complexity class $\textsf{NISQ} $, which is intended to encapsulate problems that can be efficiently solved by a classical computer with access to a NISQ device. To model existing devices, we assume the device can (1) noisily initialize all qubits, (2) apply many noisy quantum gates, and (3) perform a noisy measurement on all qubits. We first give evidence that $\textsf{BPP}\subsetneq \textsf{NISQ}\subsetneq \textsf{BQP}$, by demonstrating super-polynomial oracle separations among the three classes, based on modifications of Simon's problem. We then consider the power of $\textsf{NISQ}$ for three well-studied problems. For unstructured search, we prove that $\textsf{NISQ}$ cannot achieve a Grover-like quadratic speedup over $\textsf{BPP}$. For the Bernstein-Vazirani problem, we show that $\textsf{NISQ}$ only needs a number of queries logarithmic in what is required for $\textsf{BPP}$. Finally, for a quantum state learning problem, we prove that $\textsf{NISQ}$ is exponentially weaker than classical computation with access to noiseless constant-depth quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>How Much Structure Is Needed for Huge Quantum Speedups?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.06930</link>
    <author>Scott Aaronson</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I survey, for a general scientific audience, three decades of research into which sorts of problems admit exponential speedups via quantum computers -- from the classics (like the algorithms of Simon and Shor), to the breakthrough of Yamakawa and Zhandry from April 2022. I discuss both the quantum circuit model, which is what we ultimately care about in practice but where our knowledge is radically incomplete, and the so-called oracle or black-box or query complexity model, where we've managed to achieve a much more thorough understanding that then informs our conjectures about the circuit model. I discuss the strengths and weaknesses of switching attention to sampling tasks, as was done in the recent quantum supremacy experiments. I make some skeptical remarks about widely-repeated claims of exponential quantum speedups for practical machine learning and optimization problems. Through many examples, I try to convey the "law of conservation of weirdness," according to which every problem admitting an exponential quantum speedup must have some unusual property to allow the amplitude to be concentrated on the unknown right answer(s).</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum advantage in learning from experiments</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.00778</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Michael Broughton, Jordan Cotler, Sitan Chen, Jerry Li, Masoud Mohseni, Hartmut Neven, Ryan Babbush, Richard Kueng, John Preskill, Jarrod R. McClean</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 03 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum technology has the potential to revolutionize how we acquire and process experimental data to learn about the physical world. An experimental setup that transduces data from a physical system to a stable quantum memory, and processes that data using a quantum computer, could have significant advantages over conventional experiments in which the physical system is measured and the outcomes are processed using a classical computer. We prove that, in various tasks, quantum machines can learn from exponentially fewer experiments than those required in conventional experiments. The exponential advantage holds in predicting properties of physical systems, performing quantum principal component analysis on noisy states, and learning approximate models of physical dynamics. In some tasks, the quantum processing needed to achieve the exponential advantage can be modest; for example, one can simultaneously learn about many noncommuting observables by processing only two copies of the system. Conducting experiments with up to 40 superconducting qubits and 1300 quantum gates, we demonstrate that a substantial quantum advantage can be realized using today's relatively noisy quantum processors. Our results highlight how quantum technology can enable powerful new strategies to learn about nature.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A polynomial-time classical algorithm for noisy random circuit sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.03999</link>
    <author>Dorit Aharonov, Xun Gao, Zeph Landau, Yunchao Liu, Umesh Vazirani</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 09 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We give a polynomial time classical algorithm for sampling from the output distribution of a noisy random quantum circuit in the regime of anti-concentration to within inverse polynomial total variation distance. This gives strong evidence that, in the presence of a constant rate of noise per gate, random circuit sampling (RCS) cannot be the basis of a scalable experimental violation of the extended Church-Turing thesis. Our algorithm is not practical in its current form, and does not address finite-size RCS based quantum supremacy experiments.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Early Days of Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.09964</link>
    <author>Peter W. Shor</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I recount some of my memories of the early development of quantum computation, including the discovery of the factoring algorithm, of error correcting codes, and of fault tolerance.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Quantum Fourier Transform Has Small Entanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.08468</link>
    <author>Jielun Chen, E.M. Stoudenmire, Steven R. White</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The Quantum Fourier Transform (QFT) is a key component of many important quantum algorithms, most famously as being the essential ingredient in Shor's algorithm for factoring products of primes. Given its remarkable capability, one would think it can introduce large entanglement to qubit systems and would be difficult to simulate classically. While early results showed QFT indeed has maximal operator entanglement, we show that this is entirely due to the bit reversal in the QFT. The core part of the QFT has Schmidt coefficients decaying exponentially quickly, and thus it can only generate a constant amount of entanglement regardless of the number of qubits. In addition, we show the entangling power of the QFT is the same as the time evolution of a Hamiltonian with exponentially decaying interactions, and thus a variant of the area law for dynamics can be used to understand the low entanglement intuitively. Using the low entanglement property of the QFT, we show that classical simulations of the QFT on a matrix product state with low bond dimension only take time linear in the number of qubits, providing a potential speedup over the classical fast Fourier transform (FFT) on many classes of functions. We demonstrate this speedup in test calculations on some simple functions. For data vectors of length $10^6$ to $10^8$, the speedup can be a few orders of magnitude.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Computational advantage of quantum random sampling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.04079</link>
    <author>Dominik Hangleiter, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 10 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum random sampling is the leading proposal for demonstrating a computational advantage of quantum computers over classical computers. Recently, first large-scale implementations of quantum random sampling have arguably surpassed the boundary of what can be simulated on existing classical hardware. In this article, we comprehensively review the theoretical underpinning of quantum random sampling in terms of computational complexity and verifiability, as well as the practical aspects of its experimental implementation using superconducting and photonic devices and its classical simulation. We discuss in detail open questions in the field and provide perspectives for the road ahead, including potential applications of quantum random sampling.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Exponentially tighter bounds on limitations of quantum error mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.11505</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Daniel Stilck França, Sumeet Khatri, Johannes Jakob Meyer, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 24 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum error mitigation has been proposed as a means to combat unavoidable errors in near-term quantum computing by classically post-processing outcomes of multiple quantum circuits. It does so in a fashion that requires no or few additional quantum resources, in contrast to fault-tolerant schemes that come along with heavy overheads. Error mitigation leads to noise reduction in small systems. In this work, however, we identify strong limitations to the degree to which quantum noise can be effectively `undone' for larger system sizes. We start out by presenting a formal framework that rigorously encapsulates large classes of meaningful and practically applied schemes for quantum error mitigation, including virtual distillation, Clifford data regression, zero-noise extrapolation and probabilistic error cancellation. With the framework in place, our technical contribution is to construct families of random circuits that are highly sensitive to noise, in the sense that even at log log(n) depth, a whisker beyond constant, quantum noise is seen to super-exponentially rapidly scramble their output into the maximally-mixed state. Our results exponentially tighten known arguments for error mitigation, but they go beyond that: Our arguments can be applied to kernel estimation or to compute the depth at which barren plateaus emerge, implying that the scrambling kicks in at exponentially smaller depths than previously thought. Our results also say that a noisy device must be sampled exponentially many times to estimate expectation values. There are classical algorithms that exhibit the same scaling in complexity. While improvements in quantum hardware will push noise levels down, if error mitigation is used, ultimately this can only lead to an exponential time quantum algorithm with a better exponent, putting up a strong obstruction to the hope for exponential quantum speedups in this setting.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>How to simulate quantum measurement without computing marginals</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.08499</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, David Gosset, Yinchen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 17 2021</pubDate>
    <description>We describe and analyze algorithms for classically simulating measurement of an $n$-qubit quantum state $\psi$ in the standard basis, that is, sampling a bit string $x$ from the probability distribution $|\langle x|\psi\rangle|^2$. Our algorithms reduce the sampling task to computing poly$(n)$ amplitudes of $n$-qubit states; unlike previously known techniques they do not require computation of marginal probabilities. First we consider the case where $|\psi\rangle=U|0^n\rangle$ is the output state of an $m$-gate quantum circuit $U$. We propose an exact sampling algorithm which involves computing $O(m)$ amplitudes of $n$-qubit states generated by subcircuits of $U$ spanned by the first $t=1,2,\ldots,m$ gates. We show that our algorithm can significantly accelerate quantum circuit simulations based on tensor network contraction methods or low-rank stabilizer decompositions. As another striking consequence we obtain an efficient classical simulation algorithm for measurement-based quantum computation with the surface code resource state on any planar graph, generalizing a previous algorithm which was known to be efficient only under restrictive topological constraints on the ordering of single-qubit measurements. Second, we consider the case in which $\psi$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian with a spectral gap that is lower bounded by an inverse polynomial function of $n$. We prove that a simple Metropolis-Hastings Markov Chain mixes rapidly to the desired probability distribution provided that $\psi$ obeys a certain technical condition, which we show is satisfied for all sign-problem free Hamiltonians. This gives a sampling algorithm which involves computing $\mathrm{poly}(n)$ amplitudes of $\psi$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Opportunities and Challenges in Fault-Tolerant Quantum Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.15844</link>
    <author>Daniel Gottesman</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>I will give an overview of what I see as some of the most important future directions in the theory of fault-tolerant quantum computation. In particular, I will give a brief summary of the major problems that need to be solved in fault tolerance based on low-density parity check codes and in hardware-specific fault tolerance. I will then conclude with a discussion of a possible new paradigm for designing fault-tolerant protocols based on a space-time picture of quantum circuits.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Suppressing quantum errors by scaling a surface code logical qubit</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.06431</link>
    <author>Rajeev Acharya, Igor Aleiner, Richard Allen, Trond I. Andersen, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Abraham Asfaw, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Dave Bacon, Joseph C. Bardin, Joao Basso, Andreas Bengtsson, Sergio Boixo, Gina Bortoli, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, Leon Brill, Michael Broughton, et al (137)</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Practical quantum computing will require error rates that are well below what is achievable with physical qubits. Quantum error correction offers a path to algorithmically-relevant error rates by encoding logical qubits within many physical qubits, where increasing the number of physical qubits enhances protection against physical errors. However, introducing more qubits also increases the number of error sources, so the density of errors must be sufficiently low in order for logical performance to improve with increasing code size. Here, we report the measurement of logical qubit performance scaling across multiple code sizes, and demonstrate that our system of superconducting qubits has sufficient performance to overcome the additional errors from increasing qubit number. We find our distance-5 surface code logical qubit modestly outperforms an ensemble of distance-3 logical qubits on average, both in terms of logical error probability over 25 cycles and logical error per cycle ($2.914\%\pm 0.016\%$ compared to $3.028\%\pm 0.023\%$). To investigate damaging, low-probability error sources, we run a distance-25 repetition code and observe a $1.7\times10^{-6}$ logical error per round floor set by a single high-energy event ($1.6\times10^{-7}$ when excluding this event). We are able to accurately model our experiment, and from this model we can extract error budgets that highlight the biggest challenges for future systems. These results mark the first experimental demonstration where quantum error correction begins to improve performance with increasing qubit number, illuminating the path to reaching the logical error rates required for computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning to predict arbitrary quantum processes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.14894</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Sitan Chen, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We present an efficient machine learning (ML) algorithm for predicting any unknown quantum process $\mathcal{E}$ over $n$ qubits. For a wide range of distributions $\mathcal{D}$ on arbitrary $n$-qubit states, we show that this ML algorithm can learn to predict any local property of the output from the unknown process $\mathcal{E}$, with a small average error over input states drawn from $\mathcal{D}$. The ML algorithm is computationally efficient even when the unknown process is a quantum circuit with exponentially many gates. Our algorithm combines efficient procedures for learning properties of an unknown state and for learning a low-degree approximation to an unknown observable. The analysis hinges on proving new norm inequalities, including a quantum analogue of the classical Bohnenblust-Hille inequality, which we derive by giving an improved algorithm for optimizing local Hamiltonians. Overall, our results highlight the potential for ML models to predict the output of complex quantum dynamics much faster than the time needed to run the process itself.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Foundations for learning from noisy quantum experiments</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.13691</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Steven T. Flammia, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Understanding what can be learned from experiments is central to scientific progress. In this work, we use a learning-theoretic perspective to study the task of learning physical operations in a quantum machine when all operations (state preparation, dynamics, and measurement) are a priori unknown. We prove that, without any prior knowledge, if one can explore the full quantum state space by composing the operations, then every operation can be learned. When one cannot explore the full state space but all operations are approximately known and noise in Clifford gates is gate-independent, we find an efficient algorithm for learning all operations up to a single unlearnable parameter characterizing the fidelity of the initial state. For learning a noise channel on Clifford gates to a fixed accuracy, our algorithm uses quadratically fewer experiments than previously known protocols. Under more general conditions, the true description of the noise can be unlearnable; for example, we prove that no benchmarking protocol can learn gate-dependent Pauli noise on Clifford+T gates even under perfect state preparation and measurement. Despite not being able to learn the noise, we show that a noisy quantum computer that performs entangled measurements on multiple copies of an unknown state can yield a large advantage in learning properties of the state compared to a noiseless device that measures individual copies and then processes the measurement data using a classical computer. Concretely, we prove that noisy quantum computers with two-qubit gate error rate $\epsilon$ can achieve a learning task using $N$ copies of the state, while $N^{\Omega(1/\epsilon)}$ copies are required classically.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Physics of Quantum Information</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.08064</link>
    <author>John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 18 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Rapid ongoing progress in quantum information science makes this an apt time for a Solvay Conference focused on The Physics of Quantum Information. Here I review four intertwined themes encompassed by this topic: Quantum computer science, quantum hardware, quantum matter, and quantum gravity. Though the time scale for broad practical impact of quantum computation is still uncertain, in the near future we can expect noteworthy progress toward scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing, and discoveries enabled by programmable quantum simulators. In the longer term, controlling highly complex quantum matter will open the door to profound scientific advances and powerful new technologies.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Lecture Notes on Quantum Algorithms for Scientific Computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08309</link>
    <author>Lin Lin</author>
    <pubDate>Jan 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>This is a set of lecture notes used in a graduate topic class in applied mathematics called ``Quantum Algorithms for Scientific Computation'' at the Department of Mathematics, UC Berkeley during the fall semester of 2021. These lecture notes focus only on quantum algorithms closely related to scientific computation, and in particular, matrix computation. The main purpose of the lecture notes is to introduce quantum phase estimation (QPE) and ``post-QPE'' methods such as block encoding, quantum signal processing, and quantum singular value transformation, and to demonstrate their applications in solving eigenvalue problems, linear systems of equations, and differential equations. The intended audience is the broad computational science and engineering (CSE) community interested in using fault-tolerant quantum computers to solve challenging scientific computing problems.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Shallow shadows: Expectation estimation using low-depth random Clifford circuits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.12924</link>
    <author>Christian Bertoni, Jonas Haferkamp, Marcel Hinsche, Marios Ioannou, Jens Eisert, Hakop Pashayan</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 28 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We provide practical and powerful schemes for learning many properties of an unknown n-qubit quantum state using a sparing number of copies of the state. Specifically, we present a depth-modulated randomized measurement scheme that interpolates between two known classical shadows schemes based on random Pauli measurements and random Clifford measurements. These can be seen within our scheme as the special cases of zero and infinite depth, respectively. We focus on the regime where depth scales logarithmically in n and provide evidence that this retains the desirable properties of both extremal schemes whilst, in contrast to the random Clifford scheme, also being experimentally feasible. We present methods for two key tasks; estimating expectation values of certain observables from generated classical shadows and, computing upper bounds on the depth-modulated shadow norm, thus providing rigorous guarantees on the accuracy of the output estimates. We consider observables that can be written as a linear combination of poly(n) Paulis and observables that can be written as a low bond dimension matrix product operator. For the former class of observables both tasks are solved efficiently in n. For the latter class, we do not guarantee efficiency but present a method that works in practice; by variationally computing a heralded approximate inverses of a tensor network that can then be used for efficiently executing both these tasks.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Efficient Universal Quantum Compilation: An Inverse-free Solovay-Kitaev Algorithm</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.02040</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Tudor Giurgica-Tiron</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 06 2021</pubDate>
    <description>The Solovay-Kitaev algorithm is a fundamental result in quantum computation. It gives an algorithm for efficiently compiling arbitrary unitaries using universal gate sets: any unitary can be approximated by short gates sequences, whose length scales merely poly-logarithmically with accuracy. As a consequence, the choice of gate set is typically unimportant in quantum computing. However, the Solovay-Kitaev algorithm requires the gate set to be inverse-closed. It has been a longstanding open question if efficient algorithmic compilation is possible without this condition. In this work, we provide the first inverse-free Solovay-Kitaev algorithm, which makes no assumption on the structure within a gate set beyond universality, answering this problem in the affirmative, and providing an efficient compilation algorithm in the absence of inverses for both $\text{SU}(d)$ and $\text{SL}(d, \mathbb{C})$. The algorithm works by showing that approximate gate implementations of the generalized Pauli group can self-correct their errors.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A single $T$-gate makes distribution learning hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.03140</link>
    <author>Marcel Hinsche, Marios Ioannou, Alexander Nietner, Jonas Haferkamp, Yihui Quek, Dominik Hangleiter, Jean-Pierre Seifert, Jens Eisert, Ryan Sweke</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The task of learning a probability distribution from samples is ubiquitous across the natural sciences. The output distributions of local quantum circuits form a particularly interesting class of distributions, of key importance both to quantum advantage proposals and a variety of quantum machine learning algorithms. In this work, we provide an extensive characterization of the learnability of the output distributions of local quantum circuits. Our first result yields insight into the relationship between the efficient learnability and the efficient simulatability of these distributions. Specifically, we prove that the density modelling problem associated with Clifford circuits can be efficiently solved, while for depth $d=n^{\Omega(1)}$ circuits the injection of a single $T$-gate into the circuit renders this problem hard. This result shows that efficient simulatability does not imply efficient learnability. Our second set of results provides insight into the potential and limitations of quantum generative modelling algorithms. We first show that the generative modelling problem associated with depth $d=n^{\Omega(1)}$ local quantum circuits is hard for any learning algorithm, classical or quantum. As a consequence, one cannot use a quantum algorithm to gain a practical advantage for this task. We then show that, for a wide variety of the most practically relevant learning algorithms -- including hybrid-quantum classical algorithms -- even the generative modelling problem associated with depth $d=\omega(\log(n))$ Clifford circuits is hard. This result places limitations on the applicability of near-term hybrid quantum-classical generative modelling algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Short Proofs of Linear Growth of Quantum Circuit Complexity</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.05668</link>
    <author>Zhi Li</author>
    <pubDate>May 12 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The complexity of a quantum gate, defined as the minimal number of elementary gates to build it, is an important concept in quantum information and computation. It is shown recently that the complexity of quantum gates built from random quantum circuits almost surely grows linearly with the number of building blocks. In this article, we provide two short proofs of this fact. We also discuss a discrete version of quantum circuit complexity growth.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Demonstration of fault-tolerant universal quantum gate operations</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.12654</link>
    <author>Lukas Postler, Sascha Heußen, Ivan Pogorelov, Manuel Rispler, Thomas Feldker, Michael Meth, Christian D. Marciniak, Roman Stricker, Martin Ringbauer, Rainer Blatt, Philipp Schindler, Markus Müller, Thomas Monz</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 25 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers can be protected from noise by encoding the logical quantum information redundantly into multiple qubits using error correcting codes. When manipulating the logical quantum states, it is imperative that errors caused by imperfect operations do not spread uncontrollably through the quantum register. This requires that all operations on the quantum register obey a fault-tolerant circuit design which, in general, increases the complexity of the implementation. Here, we demonstrate a fault-tolerant universal set of gates on two logical qubits in a trapped-ion quantum computer. In particular, we make use of the recently introduced paradigm of flag fault tolerance, where the absence or presence of dangerous errors is heralded by usage of few ancillary 'flag' qubits. We perform a logical two-qubit CNOT-gate between two instances of the seven qubit color code, and we also fault-tolerantly prepare a logical magic state. We then realize a fault-tolerant logical T-gate by injecting the magic state via teleportation from one logical qubit onto the other. We observe the hallmark feature of fault tolerance, a superior performance compared to a non-fault-tolerant implementation. In combination with recently demonstrated repeated quantum error correction cycles these results open the door to error-corrected universal quantum computation.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Error Mitigation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.00921</link>
    <author>Zhenyu Cai, Ryan Babbush, Simon C. Benjamin, Suguru Endo, William J. Huggins, Ying Li, Jarrod R. McClean, Thomas E. O'Brien</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For quantum computers to successfully solve real-world problems, it is necessary to tackle the challenge of noise: the errors which occur in elementary physical components due to unwanted or imperfect interactions. The theory of quantum fault tolerance can provide an answer in the long term, but in the coming era of `NISQ' machines we must seek to mitigate errors rather than completely remove them. This review surveys the diverse methods that have been proposed for quantum error mitigation, assesses their in-principle efficacy, and then describes the hardware demonstrations achieved to date. We identify the commonalities and limitations among the methods, noting how mitigation methods can be chosen according to the primary type of noise present, including algorithmic errors. Open problems in the field are identified and we discuss the prospects for realising mitigation-based devices that can deliver quantum advantage with an impact on science and business.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Revisiting dequantization and quantum advantage in learning tasks</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.00811</link>
    <author>Jordan Cotler, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Jarrod R. McClean</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 03 2021</pubDate>
    <description>It has been shown that the apparent advantage of some quantum machine learning algorithms may be efficiently replicated using classical algorithms with suitable data access -- a process known as dequantization. Existing works on dequantization compare quantum algorithms which take copies of an n-qubit quantum state $|x\rangle = \sum_{i} x_i |i\rangle$ as input to classical algorithms which have sample and query (SQ) access to the vector $x$. In this note, we prove that classical algorithms with SQ access can accomplish some learning tasks exponentially faster than quantum algorithms with quantum state inputs. Because classical algorithms are a subset of quantum algorithms, this demonstrates that SQ access can sometimes be significantly more powerful than quantum state inputs. Our findings suggest that the absence of exponential quantum advantage in some learning tasks may be due to SQ access being too powerful relative to quantum state inputs. If we compare quantum algorithms with quantum state inputs to classical algorithms with access to measurement data on quantum states, the landscape of quantum advantage can be dramatically different. We remark that when the quantum states are constructed from exponential-size classical data, comparing SQ access and quantum state inputs is appropriate since both require exponential time to prepare.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Parallel window decoding enables scalable fault tolerant quantum computation</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.08552</link>
    <author>Luka Skoric, Dan E. Browne, Kenton M. Barnes, Neil I. Gillespie, Earl T. Campbell</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 20 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum Error Correction (QEC) continuously generates a stream of syndrome data that contains information about the errors in the system. Useful fault-tolerant quantum computation requires online decoders that are capable of processing this syndrome data at the rate it is received. Otherwise, a data backlog is created that grows exponentially with the $T$-gate depth of the computation. Superconducting quantum devices can perform QEC rounds in sub-1 $\mu$s time, setting a stringent requirement on the speed of the decoders. All current decoder proposals have a maximum code size beyond which the processing of syndromes becomes too slow to keep up with the data acquisition, thereby making the fault-tolerant computation not scalable. Here, we will present a methodology that parallelizes the decoding problem and achieves almost arbitrary syndrome processing speed. Our parallelization requires some classical feedback decisions to be delayed, leading to a slow-down of the logical clock speed. However, the slow-down is now polynomial in code size and so an exponential backlog is averted. Furthermore, using known auto-teleportation gadgets the slow-down can be eliminated altogether in exchange for increased qubit overhead, all polynomially scaling. We demonstrate our parallelization speed-up using a Python implementation, combining it with both union-find and minimum weight perfect matching. Furthermore, we show that the algorithm imposes no noticeable reduction in logical fidelity compared to the original global decoder. Finally, we discuss how the same methodology can be implemented in online hardware decoders.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random quantum circuits transform local noise into global white noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.14907</link>
    <author>Alexander M. Dalzell, Nicholas Hunter-Jones, Fernando G. S. L. Brandão</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 01 2021</pubDate>
    <description>We study the distribution over measurement outcomes of noisy random quantum circuits in the low-fidelity regime. We show that, for local noise that is sufficiently weak and unital, correlations (measured by the linear cross-entropy benchmark) between the output distribution $p_{\text{noisy}}$ of a generic noisy circuit instance and the output distribution $p_{\text{ideal}}$ of the corresponding noiseless instance shrink exponentially with the expected number of gate-level errors, as $F=\text{exp}(-2s\epsilon \pm O(s\epsilon^2))$, where $\epsilon$ is the probability of error per circuit location and $s$ is the number of two-qubit gates. Furthermore, if the noise is incoherent, the output distribution approaches the uniform distribution $p_{\text{unif}}$ at precisely the same rate and can be approximated as $p_{\text{noisy}} \approx Fp_{\text{ideal}} + (1-F)p_{\text{unif}}$, that is, local errors are scrambled by the random quantum circuit and contribute only white noise (uniform output). Importantly, we upper bound the total variation error (averaged over random circuit instance) in this approximation as $O(F\epsilon \sqrt{s})$, so the "white-noise approximation" is meaningful when $\epsilon \sqrt{s} \ll 1$, a quadratically weaker condition than the $\epsilon s\ll 1$ requirement to maintain high fidelity. The bound applies when the circuit size satisfies $s \geq \Omega(n\log(n))$ and the inverse error rate satisfies $\epsilon^{-1} \geq \tilde{\Omega}(n)$. The white-noise approximation is useful for salvaging the signal from a noisy quantum computation; it was an underlying assumption in complexity-theoretic arguments that low-fidelity random quantum circuits cannot be efficiently sampled classically. Our method is based on a map from second-moment quantities in random quantum circuits to expectation values of certain stochastic processes for which we compute upper and lower bounds.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A construction of Combinatorial NLTS</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.02741</link>
    <author>Anurag Anshu, Nikolas P. Breuckmann</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The NLTS (No Low-Energy Trivial State) conjecture of Freedman and Hastings [2014] posits that there exist families of Hamiltonians with all low energy states of high complexity (with complexity measured by the quantum circuit depth preparing the state). Here, we prove a weaker version called the combinatorial NLTS, where a quantum circuit lower bound is shown against states that violate a (small) constant fraction of local terms. This generalizes the prior NLETS results (Eldar and Harrow [2017]; Nirkhe, Vazirani and Yuen [2018]). Our construction is obtained by combining tensor networks with expander codes (Sipser and Spielman [1996]). The Hamiltonian is the parent Hamiltonian of a perturbed tensor network, inspired by the `uncle Hamiltonian' of Fernandez-Gonzalez et. al. [2015]. Thus, we deviate from the quantum CSS code Hamiltonians considered in most prior works.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>An Improved Sample Complexity Lower Bound for Quantum State Tomography</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.11185</link>
    <author>Henry Yuen</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 23 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that $\Omega(rd/\epsilon)$ copies of an unknown rank-$r$, dimension-$d$ quantum mixed state are necessary in order to learn a classical description with $1 - \epsilon$ fidelity. This improves upon the tomography lower bounds obtained by Haah, et al. and Wright.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Towards near-term quantum simulation of materials</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.15256</link>
    <author>Laura Clinton, Toby Cubitt, Brian Flynn, Filippo Maria Gambetta, Joel Klassen, Ashley Montanaro, Stephen Piddock, Raul A. Santos, Evan Sheridan</author>
    <pubDate>May 31 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Simulation of materials is one of the most promising applications of quantum computers. On near-term hardware the crucial constraint on these simulations is circuit depth. Many quantum simulation algorithms rely on a layer of unitary evolutions generated by each term in a Hamiltonian. This appears in time-dynamics as a single Trotter step, and in variational quantum eigensolvers under the Hamiltonian variational ansatz as a single ansatz layer. We present a new quantum algorithm design for materials modelling where the depth of a layer is independent of the system size. This design takes advantage of the locality of materials in the Wannier basis and employs a tailored fermionic encoding that preserves locality. We analyse the circuit costs of this approach and present a compiler that transforms density functional theory data into quantum circuit instructions -- connecting the physics of the material to the simulation circuit. The compiler automatically optimises circuits at multiple levels, from the base gate level to optimisations derived from the physics of the specific target material. We present numerical results for materials spanning a wide structural and technological range. Our results demonstrate a reduction of many orders of magnitude in circuit depth over standard prior methods that do not consider the structure of the Hamiltonian. For example our results improve resource requirements for Strontium Vanadate (SrVO$_3$) from 864 to 180 qubits for a $3\times3\times3$ lattice, and the circuit depth of a single Trotter or variational layer from $7.5\times 10^8$ to depth $884$. Although this is still beyond current hardware, our results show that materials simulation may be feasible on quantum computers without necessarily requiring scalable, fault-tolerant quantum computers, provided quantum algorithm design incorporates understanding of the materials and applications.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Time-energy uncertainty relation for noisy quantum metrology</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.13707</link>
    <author>Philippe Faist, Mischa P. Woods, Victor V. Albert, Joseph M. Renes, Jens Eisert, John Preskill</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 29 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Detection of weak forces and precise measurement of time are two of the many applications of quantum metrology to science and technology. We consider a quantum system initialized in a pure state and whose evolution is goverened by a Hamiltonian $H$; a measurement can later estimate the time $t$ for which the system has evolved. In this work, we introduce and study a fundamental trade-off which relates the amount by which noise reduces the accuracy of a quantum clock to the amount of information about the energy of the clock that leaks to the environment. Specifically, we consider an idealized scenario in which Alice prepares an initial pure state of the clock, allows the clock to evolve for a time $t$ that is not precisely known, and then transmits the clock through a noisy channel to Bob. The environment (Eve) receives any information that is lost. We prove that Bob's loss of quantum Fisher information (QFI) about $t$ is equal to Eve's gain of QFI about a complementary energy parameter. We also prove a more general trade-off that applies when Bob and Eve wish to estimate the values of parameters associated with two non-commuting observables. We derive the necessary and sufficient conditions for the accuracy of the clock to be unaffected by the noise. These are a subset of the Knill-Laflamme error-correction conditions; states satisfying these conditions are said to form a metrological code. We provide a scheme to construct metrological codes in the stabilizer formalism. We show that there are metrological codes that cannot be written as a quantum error-correcting code with similar distance in which the Hamiltonian acts as a logical operator, potentially offering new schemes for constructing states that do not lose any sensitivity upon application of a noisy channel. We discuss applications of our results to sensing using a many-body state subject to erasure or amplitude-damping noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Noise can be helpful for variational quantum algorithms</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06723</link>
    <author>Junyu Liu, Frederik Wilde, Antonio Anna Mele, Liang Jiang, Jens Eisert</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Saddle points constitute a crucial challenge for first-order gradient descent algorithms. In notions of classical machine learning, they are avoided for example by means of stochastic gradient descent methods. In this work, we provide evidence that the saddle points problem can be naturally avoided in variational quantum algorithms by exploiting the presence of stochasticity. We prove convergence guarantees of the approach and its practical functioning at hand of examples. We argue that the natural stochasticity of variational algorithms can be beneficial for avoiding strict saddle points, i.e., those saddle points with at least one negative Hessian eigenvalue. This insight that some noise levels could help in this perspective is expected to add a new perspective to notions of near-term variational quantum algorithms.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The Future of Quantum Computing with Superconducting Qubits</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.06841</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Oliver Dial, Jay M. Gambetta, Dario Gil, Zaira Nazario</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 16 2022</pubDate>
    <description>For the first time in history, we are seeing a branching point in computing paradigms with the emergence of quantum processing units (QPUs). Extracting the full potential of computation and realizing quantum algorithms with a super-polynomial speedup will most likely require major advances in quantum error correction technology. Meanwhile, achieving a computational advantage in the near term may be possible by combining multiple QPUs through circuit knitting techniques, improving the quality of solutions through error suppression and mitigation, and focusing on heuristic versions of quantum algorithms with asymptotic speedups. For this to happen, the performance of quantum computing hardware needs to improve and software needs to seamlessly integrate quantum and classical processors together to form a new architecture that we are calling quantum-centric supercomputing. Long term, we see hardware that exploits qubit connectivity in higher than 2D topologies to realize more efficient quantum error correcting codes, modular architectures for scaling QPUs and parallelizing workloads, and software that evolves to make the intricacies of the technology invisible to the users and realize the goal of ubiquitous, frictionless quantum computing.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning Distributions over Quantum Measurement Outcomes</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.03007</link>
    <author>Weiyuan Gong, Scott Aaronson</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 08 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Shadow tomography for quantum states provides a sample efficient approach for predicting the properties of quantum systems when the properties are restricted to expectation values of $2$-outcome POVMs. However, these shadow tomography procedures yield poor bounds if there are more than 2 outcomes per measurement. In this paper, we consider a general problem of learning properties from unknown quantum states: given an unknown $d$-dimensional quantum state $\rho$ and $M$ unknown quantum measurements $\mathcal{M}_1,...,\mathcal{M}_M$ with $K\geq 2$ outcomes, estimating the probability distribution for applying $\mathcal{M}_i$ on $\rho$ to within total variation distance $\epsilon$. Compared to the special case when $K=2$, we need to learn unknown distributions instead of values. We develop an online shadow tomography procedure that solves this problem with high success probability requiring $\tilde{O}(K\log^2M\log d/\epsilon^4)$ copies of $\rho$. We further prove an information-theoretic lower bound that at least $\Omega(\min\{d^2,K+\log M\}/\epsilon^2)$ copies of $\rho$ are required to solve this problem with high success probability. Our shadow tomography procedure requires sample complexity with only logarithmic dependence on $M$ and $d$ and is sample-optimal for the dependence on $K$.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum many-body systems in thermal equilibrium</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.08349</link>
    <author>Álvaro M. Alhambra</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 19 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The thermal or equilibrium ensemble is one of the most ubiquitous states of matter. For models comprised of many locally interacting quantum particles, it describes a wide range of physical situations, relevant to condensed matter physics, high energy physics, quantum chemistry and quantum computing, among others. We give a pedagogical overview of some of the most important universal features about the physics and complexity of these states, which have the locality of the Hamiltonian at its core. We focus on mathematically rigorous statements, many of them inspired by ideas and tools from quantum information theory. These include bounds on their correlations, the form of the subsystems, various statistical properties, and the performance of classical and quantum algorithms. We also include a summary of a few of the most important technical tools, as well as some self-contained proofs.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Learning many-body Hamiltonians with Heisenberg-limited scaling</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.03030</link>
    <author>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Yu Tong, Di Fang, Yuan Su</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 07 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Learning a many-body Hamiltonian from its dynamics is a fundamental problem in physics. In this work, we propose the first algorithm to achieve the Heisenberg limit for learning an interacting $N$-qubit local Hamiltonian. After a total evolution time of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-1})$, the proposed algorithm can efficiently estimate any parameter in the $N$-qubit Hamiltonian to $\epsilon$-error with high probability. The proposed algorithm is robust against state preparation and measurement error, does not require eigenstates or thermal states, and only uses $\mathrm{polylog}(\epsilon^{-1})$ experiments. In contrast, the best previous algorithms, such as recent works using gradient-based optimization or polynomial interpolation, require a total evolution time of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ and $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-2})$ experiments. Our algorithm uses ideas from quantum simulation to decouple the unknown $N$-qubit Hamiltonian $H$ into noninteracting patches, and learns $H$ using a quantum-enhanced divide-and-conquer approach. We prove a matching lower bound to establish the asymptotic optimality of our algorithm.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Random quantum circuits are approximate unitary $t$-designs in depth $O\left(nt^{5+o(1)}\right)$</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.16571</link>
    <author>Jonas Haferkamp</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The applications of random quantum circuits range from quantum computing and quantum many-body systems to the physics of black holes. Many of these applications are related to the generation of quantum pseudorandomness: Random quantum circuits are known to approximate unitary $t$-designs. Unitary $t$-designs are probability distributions that mimic Haar randomness up to $t$th moments. In a seminal paper, Brandão, Harrow and Horodecki prove that random quantum circuits on qubits in a brickwork architecture of depth $O(n t^{10.5})$ are approximate unitary $t$-designs. In this work, we revisit this argument, which lower bounds the spectral gap of moment operators for local random quantum circuits by $\Omega(n^{-1}t^{-9.5})$. We improve this lower bound to $\Omega(n^{-1}t^{-4-o(1)})$, where the $o(1)$ term goes to $0$ as $t\to\infty$. A direct consequence of this scaling is that random quantum circuits generate approximate unitary $t$-designs in depth $O(nt^{5+o(1)})$. Our techniques involve Gao's quantum union bound and the unreasonable effectiveness of the Clifford group. As an auxiliary result, we prove fast convergence to the Haar measure for random Clifford unitaries interleaved with Haar random single qubit unitaries.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Limitations of Linear Cross-Entropy as a Measure for Quantum Advantage</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.01657</link>
    <author>Xun Gao, Marcin Kalinowski, Chi-Ning Chou, Mikhail D. Lukin, Boaz Barak, Soonwon Choi</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 06 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Demonstrating quantum advantage requires experimental implementation of a computational task that is hard to achieve using state-of-the-art classical systems. One approach is to perform sampling from a probability distribution associated with a class of highly entangled many-body wavefunctions. It has been suggested that this approach can be certified with the Linear Cross-Entropy Benchmark (XEB). We critically examine this notion. First, in a "benign" setting where an honest implementation of noisy quantum circuits is assumed, we characterize the conditions under which the XEB approximates the fidelity. Second, in an "adversarial" setting where all possible classical algorithms are considered for comparison, we show that achieving relatively high XEB values does not imply faithful simulation of quantum dynamics. We present an efficient classical algorithm that, with 1 GPU within 2s, yields high XEB values, namely 2-12% of those obtained in experiments. By identifying and exploiting several vulnerabilities of the XEB, we achieve high XEB values without full simulation of quantum circuits. Remarkably, our algorithm features better scaling with the system size than noisy quantum devices for commonly studied random circuit ensembles. To quantitatively explain the success of our algorithm and the limitations of the XEB, we use a theoretical framework in which the average XEB and fidelity are mapped to statistical models. We illustrate the relation between the XEB and the fidelity for quantum circuits in various architectures, with different gate choices, and in the presence of noise. Our results show that XEB's utility as a proxy for fidelity hinges on several conditions, which must be checked in the benign setting but cannot be assumed in the adversarial setting. Thus, the XEB alone has limited utility as a benchmark for quantum advantage. We discuss ways to overcome these limitations.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>The learnability of Pauli noise</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.06362</link>
    <author>Senrui Chen, Yunchao Liu, Matthew Otten, Alireza Seif, Bill Fefferman, Liang Jiang</author>
    <pubDate>Jun 14 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Recently, several noise benchmarking algorithms have been developed to characterize noisy quantum gates on today's quantum devices. A well-known issue in benchmarking is that not everything about quantum noise is learnable due to the existence of gauge freedom, leaving open the question of what information about noise is learnable and what is not, which has been unclear even for a single CNOT gate. Here we give a precise characterization of the learnability of Pauli noise channels attached to Clifford gates, showing that learnable information corresponds to the cycle space of the pattern transfer graph of the gate set, while unlearnable information corresponds to the cut space. This implies the optimality of cycle benchmarking, in the sense that it can learn all learnable information about Pauli noise. We experimentally demonstrate noise characterization of IBM's CNOT gate up to 2 unlearnable degrees of freedom, for which we obtain bounds using physical constraints. In addition, we give an attempt to characterize the unlearnable information by assuming perfect initial state preparation. However, based on the experimental data, we conclude that this assumption is inaccurate as it yields unphysical estimates, and we obtain a lower bound on state preparation noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Realizing Repeated Quantum Error Correction in a Distance-Three Surface Code</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.03708</link>
    <author>Sebastian Krinner, Nathan Lacroix, Ants Remm, Agustin Di Paolo, Elie Genois, Catherine Leroux, Christoph Hellings, Stefania Lazar, Francois Swiadek, Johannes Herrmann, Graham J. Norris, Christian Kraglund Andersen, Markus Müller, Alexandre Blais, Christopher Eichler, Andreas Wallraff</author>
    <pubDate>Dec 08 2021</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum computers hold the promise of solving computational problems which are intractable using conventional methods. For fault-tolerant operation quantum computers must correct errors occurring due to unavoidable decoherence and limited control accuracy. Here, we demonstrate quantum error correction using the surface code, which is known for its exceptionally high tolerance to errors. Using 17 physical qubits in a superconducting circuit we encode quantum information in a distance-three logical qubit building up on recent distance-two error detection experiments. In an error correction cycle taking only $1.1\,\mu$s, we demonstrate the preservation of four cardinal states of the logical qubit. Repeatedly executing the cycle, we measure and decode both bit- and phase-flip error syndromes using a minimum-weight perfect-matching algorithm in an error-model-free approach and apply corrections in postprocessing. We find a low error probability of $3\,\%$ per cycle when rejecting experimental runs in which leakage is detected. The measured characteristics of our device agree well with a numerical model. Our demonstration of repeated, fast and high-performance quantum error correction cycles, together with recent advances in ion traps, support our understanding that fault-tolerant quantum computation will be practically realizable.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A rapidly mixing Markov chain from any gapped quantum many-body system</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.07044</link>
    <author>Sergey Bravyi, Giuseppe Carleo, David Gosset, Yinchen Liu</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We consider the computational task of sampling a bit string $x$ from a distribution $\pi(x)=|\langle x|\psi\rangle|^2$, where $\psi$ is the unique ground state of a local Hamiltonian $H$. Our main result describes a direct link between the inverse spectral gap of $H$ and the mixing time of an associated continuous-time Markov Chain with steady state $\pi$. The Markov Chain can be implemented efficiently whenever ratios of ground state amplitudes $\langle y|\psi\rangle/\langle x|\psi\rangle$ are efficiently computable and the starting state of the chain satisfies a mild technical condition that can be efficiently checked. This extends a previously known relationship between sign-problem free Hamiltonians and Markov chains. The tool which enables this generalization is the so-called fixed-node Hamiltonian construction, previously used in Quantum Monte Carlo simulations to address the fermionic sign problem. We implement the proposed sampling algorithm numerically and use it to sample from the ground state of Haldane-Shastry Hamiltonian with up to 56 qubits. We observe empirically that our Markov chain based on the fixed-node Hamiltonian mixes more rapidly than the standard Metropolis-Hastings Markov chain.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum Pseudoentanglement</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.00747</link>
    <author>Adam Bouland, Bill Fefferman, Soumik Ghosh, Umesh Vazirani, Zixin Zhou</author>
    <pubDate>Nov 03 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Quantum pseudorandom states are efficiently constructable states which nevertheless masquerade as Haar-random states to poly-time observers. First defined by Ji, Liu and Song, such states have found a number of applications ranging from cryptography to the AdS/CFT correspondence. A fundamental question is exactly how much entanglement is required to create such states. Haar-random states, as well as $t$-designs for $t\geq 2$, exhibit near-maximal entanglement. Here we provide the first construction of pseudorandom states with only polylogarithmic entanglement entropy across an equipartition of the qubits, which is the minimum possible. Our construction can be based on any one-way function secure against quantum attack. We additionally show that the entanglement in our construction is fully "tunable", in the sense that one can have pseudorandom states with entanglement $\Theta(f(n))$ for any desired function $\omega(\log n) \leq f(n) \leq O(n)$. More fundamentally, our work calls into question to what extent entanglement is a "feelable" quantity of quantum systems. Inspired by recent work of Gheorghiu and Hoban, we define a new notion which we call "pseudoentanglement", which are ensembles of efficiently constructable quantum states which hide their entanglement entropy. We show such states exist in the strongest form possible while simultaneously being pseudorandom states. We also describe diverse applications of our result from entanglement distillation to property testing to quantum gravity.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On a gap in the proof of the generalised quantum Stein's lemma and its consequences for the reversibility of quantum resources</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.02813</link>
    <author>Mario Berta, Fernando G. S. L. Brandão, Gilad Gour, Ludovico Lami, Martin B. Plenio, Bartosz Regula, Marco Tomamichel</author>
    <pubDate>May 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show that the proof of the generalised quantum Stein's lemma [Brandão & Plenio, Commun. Math. Phys. 295, 791 (2010)] is not correct due to a gap in the argument leading to Lemma III.9. Hence, the main achievability result of Brandão & Plenio is not known to hold. This puts into question a number of established results in the literature, in particular the reversibility of quantum entanglement [Brandão & Plenio, Commun. Math. Phys. 295, 829 (2010); Nat. Phys. 4, 873 (2008)] and of general quantum resources [Brandão & Gour, Phys. Rev. Lett. 115, 070503 (2015)] under asymptotically resource non-generating operations. We discuss potential ways to recover variants of the newly unsettled results using other approaches.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Is quantum advantage the right goal for quantum machine learning?</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.01340</link>
    <author>Maria Schuld, Nathan Killoran</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 04 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Machine learning is frequently listed among the most promising applications for quantum computing. This is in fact a curious choice: Today's machine learning algorithms are notoriously powerful in practice, but remain theoretically difficult to study. Quantum computing, in contrast, does not offer practical benchmarks on realistic scales, and theory is the main tool we have to judge whether it could become relevant for a problem. In this perspective we explain why it is so difficult to say something about the practical power of quantum computers for machine learning with the tools we are currently using. We argue that these challenges call for a critical debate on whether quantum advantage and the narrative of "beating" classical machine learning should continue to dominate the literature the way it does, and provide a few examples for alternative research questions.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Quantum divide and conquer</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2210.06419</link>
    <author>Andrew M. Childs, Robin Kothari, Matt Kovacs-Deak, Aarthi Sundaram, Daochen Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Oct 13 2022</pubDate>
    <description>The divide-and-conquer framework, used extensively in classical algorithm design, recursively breaks a problem of size $n$ into smaller subproblems (say, $a$ copies of size $n/b$ each), along with some auxiliary work of cost $C^{\textrm{aux}}(n)$, to give a recurrence relation $$C(n) ≤a \,C(n/b) + C^\textrmaux(n)$$ for the classical complexity $C(n)$. We describe a quantum divide-and-conquer framework that, in certain cases, yields an analogous recurrence relation $$C_Q(n) ≤\sqrta \u2009C_Q(n/b) + O(C^\textrmaux_Q(n))$$ that characterizes the quantum query complexity. We apply this framework to obtain near-optimal quantum query complexities for various string problems, such as (i) recognizing regular languages; (ii) decision versions of String Rotation and String Suffix; and natural parameterized versions of (iii) Longest Increasing Subsequence and (iv) Longest Common Subsequence.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Clique Homology is QMA1-hard</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.11793</link>
    <author>Marcos Crichigno, Tamara Kohler</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 27 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We tackle the long-standing question of the computational complexity of determining homology groups of simplicial complexes, a fundamental task in computational topology, posed by Kaibel and Pfetsch 20 years ago. We show that this decision problem is QMA1-hard. Moreover, we show that a version of the problem satisfying a suitable promise and certain constraints is contained in QMA. This suggests that the seemingly classical problem may in fact be quantum mechanical. In fact, we are able to significantly strengthen this by showing that the problem remains QMA1-hard in the case of clique complexes, a family of simplicial complexes specified by a graph which is relevant to the problem of topological data analysis. The proof combines a number of techniques from Hamiltonian complexity and homological algebra. We discuss potential implications for the problem of quantum advantage in topological data analysis.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Logical shadow tomography: Efficient estimation of error-mitigated observables</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2203.07263</link>
    <author>Hong-Ye Hu, Ryan LaRose, Yi-Zhuang You, Eleanor Rieffel, Zhihui Wang</author>
    <pubDate>Mar 15 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We introduce a technique to estimate error-mitigated expectation values on noisy quantum computers. Our technique performs shadow tomography on a logical state to produce a memory-efficient classical reconstruction of the noisy density matrix. Using efficient classical post-processing, one can mitigate errors by projecting a general nonlinear function of the noisy density matrix into the codespace. The subspace expansion and virtual distillation can be viewed as special cases of the new framekwork. We show our method is favorable in the quantum and classical resources overhead. Relative to subspace expansion which requires $O\left(2^{N} \right)$ samples to estimate a logical Pauli observable with $[[N, k]]$ error correction code, our technique requires only $O\left(4^{k} \right)$ samples. Relative to virtual distillation, our technique can compute powers of the density matrix without additional copies of quantum states or quantum memory. We present numerical evidence using logical states encoded with up to sixty physical qubits and show fast convergence to error-free expectation values with only $10^5$ samples under 1% depolarizing noise.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Thermalization without eigenstate thermalization</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2209.09826</link>
    <author>Aram W. Harrow, Yichen Huang</author>
    <pubDate>Sep 21 2022</pubDate>
    <description>In an isolated quantum many-body system undergoing unitary evolution, we study the thermalization of a subsystem, treating the rest of the system as a bath. In this setting, the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis (ETH) was proposed to explain thermalization. Consider a nearly integrable Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model obtained by adding random all-to-all $4$-body interactions as a perturbation to a random free-fermion model. When the subsystem size is larger than the square root of but is still a vanishing fraction of the system size, we prove thermalization if the system is initialized in a random product state, while almost all eigenstates violate the ETH. In this sense, the ETH is not a necessary condition for thermalization.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>A mathematical framework for quantum Hamiltonian simulation and duality</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.11941</link>
    <author>Harriet Apel, Toby Cubitt</author>
    <pubDate>Aug 26 2022</pubDate>
    <description>Analogue Hamiltonian simulation is a promising near-term application of quantum computing and has recently been put on a theoretical footing. In Hamiltonian simulation, a physical Hamiltonian is engineered to have identical physics to another - often very different - Hamiltonian. This is qualitatively similar to the notion of duality in physics, whereby two superficially different theories are mathematically equivalent in some precise sense. However, existing characterisations of Hamiltonian simulations are not sufficiently general to extend to all dualities in physics. In particular, they cannot encompass the important cases of strong/weak and high-temperature/low-temperature dualities. In this work, we give three physically motivated axiomatisations of duality, formulated respectively in terms of observables, partition functions and entropies. We prove that these axiomatisations are equivalent, and characterise the mathematical form that any duality satisfying these axioms must take. A building block in one of our results is a strengthening of earlier results on entropy-preserving maps to maps that are entropy-preserving up to an additive constant, which we prove decompose as a direct sum of unitary and anti-unitary components, which may be of independent mathematical interest.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Verifiable Quantum Advantage without Structure</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.02063</link>
    <author>Takashi Yamakawa, Mark Zhandry</author>
    <pubDate>Apr 06 2022</pubDate>
    <description>We show the following hold, unconditionally unless otherwise stated, relative to a random oracle with probability 1: - There are NP search problems solvable by BQP machines but not BPP machines. - There exist functions that are one-way, and even collision resistant, against classical adversaries but are easily inverted quantumly. Similar separations hold for digital signatures and CPA-secure public key encryption (the latter requiring the assumption of a classically CPA-secure encryption scheme). Interestingly, the separation does not necessarily extend to the case of other cryptographic objects such as PRGs. - There are unconditional publicly verifiable proofs of quantumness with the minimal rounds of interaction: for uniform adversaries, the proofs are non-interactive, whereas for non-uniform adversaries the proofs are two message public coin. - Our results do not appear to contradict the Aaronson-Ambanis conjecture. Assuming this conjecture, there exist publicly verifiable certifiable randomness, again with the minimal rounds of interaction. By replacing the random oracle with a concrete cryptographic hash function such as SHA2, we obtain plausible Minicrypt instantiations of the above results. Previous analogous results all required substantial structure, either in terms of highly structured oracles and/or algebraic assumptions in Cryptomania and beyond.</description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Multivariate trace estimation in constant quantum depth</title>
    <link>http://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.15405</link>
    <author>Yihui Quek, Mark M. Wilde, Eneet Kaur</author>
    <pubDate>Jul 01 2022</pubDate>
    <description>There is a folkloric belief that a depth-$\Theta(m)$ quantum circuit is needed to estimate the trace of the product of $m$ density matrices (i.e., a multivariate trace). We prove that this belief is overly conservative by constructing a constant quantum-depth circuit for the task, inspired by the method of Shor error correction. Furthermore, our circuit demands only local gates in a two dimensional circuit -- we show how to implement it in a highly parallelized way on an architecture similar to that of Google's Sycamore processor. With these features, our algorithm brings the task of multivariate trace estimation, crucial to applications in condensed matter and estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states, closer to the capabilities of near-term quantum processors. We instantiate the latter application with a theorem on estimating nonlinear functions of quantum states with ``well-behaved" polynomial approximations.</description>
  </item>

</channel>

</rss>